<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000999">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Edward L. Rowny </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>LIEUTENANT GENERAL EDWARD L. ROWNY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 2, 2000</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: General, I understand that there is an extensive oral history that has been
                    done on your military career deposited at the Corps of Engineers Oral History
                    Program. Is that correct?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes. It's not only the military but it extends into some othe work I did
                    in the diplomatic field also.</p>
                <p>Q: All right. We'll skip right quickly to the diplomatic field. I wonder if you
                    can start out by telling me where and when you were born and something about
                    your family.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I was born in Baltimore, Maryland, on the 3rd of April 1917. My father was
                    an immigrant from Poland who had come to this country in 1895, and he lived to
                    be 97. He was quite a man. When he wanted to marry my mother, she wouldn't marry
                    a foreigner, so he had to get out and get his citizenship papers. He went to the
                    judge, and the judge said, “Tell me about the separation of powers.” He said,
                    “Well, there's the executive, the legislative, and the judiciary,” and the judge
                    said, “Oh, you know all that stuff. Tell me, what ship did you come over on?” My
                    father saw that he was pretty sleepy, so he said, “I came over on the
                    Mayflower.” So, we have this family story that my father came over on the
                    Mayflower.</p>
                <p>He worked his way up from a laborer to a carpenter to a contractor. He was hit
                    hard by the Depression and lost everything and then came back. He was a pretty
                    successful builder in and around Baltimore. You see a lot of those form stone
                    houses, the ugly things, and they were his. He didn't like them at all but he
                    said that's what the customers wanted. He built and remodeled a lot of houses
                    all around Baltimore and did a lot of building of small community shopping
                    centers but not the big things that they have today. He built the six and ten
                    little Mom and Pop stores in the neighborhood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's your mother's background?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>ROWNY: My mother was born to parents who came here from the Austrian part of
                    Poland. Her father had come from the part that was occupied by Russia. I lived a
                    lot of time with my grandmother because my mother became quite ill when I was
                    five. I lived with my grandmother from the time I was five until I was
                    seventeen. She had been a governess to a rich family, part of the Patocki
                    family, in Poland. She spoke four languages, was a very dynamic and intelligent
                    woman who raised five children and sent three to college even after she was
                    widowed. I had a lot of respect for my grandmother. My grandfather died when he
                    was 60, and she lived on to be 85. My mother was the youngest of that family of
                    five.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you live in a Polish neighborhood? I was thinking
                        thaBaltimore had a German neighborhood.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, we lived in the southeastern part of Baltimore, which is variously
                    known as Canton and Highland Town. It is quite fashionable now. It was a clean
                    but poor section, which had some nine ethnic groups in it. They were ranked in a
                    hierarchy: English were the top because they were old settlers; Germans were
                    next because they were efficient; I don't know how the others ranked but the
                    Poles were not at the bottom but they were not at the top either. There were
                    Italians and Ukrainians and Finns and a few Irish families. It was a very ethnic
                    neighborhood divided into small enclaves.</p>
                <p>Q: Of course, Baltimore, particularly in those days, was a major port and also a
                    fishing port. There was a lot of canning and things like that going on. I
                    realize that your father was a contractor but did the Poles or your father fit
                    into any of the sea-related businesses?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, my father, when he came to this country, landed at Fells Point, which
                    is now a more fashionable part of town, and he was indentured when he came over.
                    He promised $100 for his steerage passage, and he could pay it off at $10 a
                    month at 10 percent interest. He paid it off in three months. He wanted to enter
                    into the war but at that time he was a carpenter in the Sun shipbuilding
                    company, and the country needed shipbuilders as well as warriors. He always
                    regretted that he couldn't go into the war. After the war, he founded a small
                    company which remodeled stores. He became known as a saloon remodeler. Most of
                    the saloons around Baltimore were rebuilt by him.</p>
                <p>In 1929, when the Depression hit, he had his first big job. He was to do the
                    woodwork of a Fischer body plant, which was moving to Baltimore. It was a huge
                    job and much larger than his previous work but, unfortunately, several things
                    happened. First, the banks closed. Second, the factory caught fire and burned to
                    the ground. Third, the insurance company went bankrupt and didn't pay off. He
                    had to sell his car and house and move into a couple of rooms. At that time my
                    mother was quite ill, and I went to live with my grandmother. My mother with the
                    help of a sister-in-law took care of my younger brother.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>My father, after the Depression, picked himself up and very proudly paid off all
                    his debts, which he didn't have to do. He could have declared bankruptcy
                    himself. He got larger and larger remodeling jobs, including tearing down some
                    old rows of houses in Baltimore and replacing them with new houses, what they
                    call townhouses now.</p>
                <p>At the end of World War II, he wanted my brother and me to go into business with
                    him but I decided I wanted to stay in the army. My brother who was not a career
                    officer left the army and came back from Germany, and they started a small
                    company, which built shopping centers around Baltimore. My brother would pick
                    out the areas and do all the research on what was going to succeed, and they
                    would buy a piece of land and improve it. They had to take profits because in
                    Baltimore they have a ground rent situation. If you own a piece of ground, you
                    can charge 6 percent interest for 99 years. No one can buy the ground that you
                    own. As soon as a lot they bought, say for $1,000, was improved, they could
                    assess it at $10,000. They did not become enormously wealthy but quite well off.
                    They broke up the business when my father reached the age of 75.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Growing up, where did you go to school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I went to public school number three, P.S. 3, which was only a couple of
                    blocks away. From there I went to Baltimore Polytechnic Institute, a high school
                    in Baltimore, which I now have learned was one of the best high schools in the
                    country. It had highly motivated teachers and students. I still think my best
                    teachers were those I had in high school. From there I got a scholarship to
                    Johns Hopkins and went to university, starting at the age of 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had the same drive that your grandmother and father
                        showed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, I was always ambitious to get out of that economic situation,
                    especially since we were hit so hard by the Depression. I started selling papers
                    at nine and, then, I made root beer and bags of peanuts and take them to the
                    airport where people would come out and watch the airplanes coming and landing.
                    In those days, it was a curiosity. I worked summers in the years I went to
                    college, and I paid off the other half of my scholarship and board by working as
                    much as 40 hours per week. It was a pretty busy time.</p>
                <p>Q: While you were growing up and before you went to college, from your
                    perspective, were you aware of the race problem in Baltimore or was it something
                    that was over the horizon?</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>ROWNY: We had no consciousness of race. The Negroes were on the other side of
                    town, and we had no contact with them. There was some rivalry among ethnic
                    groups. The Poles looked up to the Germans, yet it was a hate-love relationship.
                    They completely respected the old British ancestors of the British people who
                    migrated there. There was friendly rivalry. There wasn't any real hatred among
                    ethnic groups.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Mencken a presence when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Oh, yes. He was quite a hero. I sold newspapers downtown, and I used to
                    love to go by the saloon where he wrote. I didn't meet him but he was quite
                    something that our teachers told us about and we learned about at an early age.
                    I would say probably as a freshman or a junior in high school I read Mencken's
                    books.</p>
                <p>Q: When you were in high school at Polytechnic and before you went to Johns
                    Hopkins, what were you pointed toward? Did you have something to point
                    towards?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I thought that I would follow in my father's footsteps and maybe join the
                    company. I followed the technical line. It was a technical school but not the
                    vocational school you usually hear about. It had vocation but a very high
                    standard of liberal arts. It wasn't right in our neighborhood but it was closer
                    than the other high school. There were two high schools, Baltimore Poly and City
                    High, so I just kind of naturally drifted toward geography into Baltimore
                    Poly.</p>
                <p>Q: At Baltimore Poly, you were facing things such as mechanical drawing and that
                    sort of thing, which would essentially lead later to the engineering side.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, they had mechanical drawing, some elementary architecture, and half a
                    dozen different shops that I attended: among them, a foundry and a woodworking
                    shop. I decided at an early age that those things would be blue collar, and I
                    tried to get into a white collar environment. I always had an idea then that if
                    I could ever have a chance to get into West Point, I'd like to go there,
                    especially since my grandmother glamorized it. She had married a corporal who
                    had been indentured into the Austrian army, and she sort of married beneath her
                    stage although she wasn't higher class: she was a governess. In those days, the
                    soldiers were lower class. If she had married an officer, that would have been
                    different. But, she looked up to the military as did my grandfather, who I
                    respected. He died when I was six. He was quite proud of his short military
                    service in Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, Johns Hopkins was the neighborhood school in a
                        way,wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>ROWNY: It was the natural place to go to from Poly, particularly, if you tried to
                    get a scholarship. Some of the people from Poly went to more prestigious places
                    like Princeton and Cornell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Princeton was the normal breeding ground of
                        Maryland. Thiis where the gentlemen of Baltimore went.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: That's right. If you did well at Poly and had some family connections
                    behind you, then you went to Princeton, especially if you could play
                    lacrosse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever play lacrosse?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, I didn't. The story of that is, when I finally got to West Point, they
                    stuck out a lacrosse stick, saying, “Here, you're on the team.” I said, “Look, I
                    have never played lacrosse, I'm from Poly and Maryland.” I finally got kicked
                    off the team and became the undergraduate manager of lacrosse to stay with the
                    crowd.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At Johns Hopkins, what courses were you taking?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I took the normal engineering courses. They were pretty heavy in math,
                    sciences, and civil engineering, constructing buildings and bridges, and the
                    rudimentary elements of those. I thought it was pretty high on the liberal arts
                    side. When I branched out, I found out they really slighted history and English
                    and favored engineering.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your reading, I assume there was probably a Carnegie
                        FreLibrary when you were there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Oh, yes. There was the Enoch Pratt Library, and I had a special
                    relationship with the librarian, a Mrs. Wrigley. Instead of the usual two books
                    that you could take out a week, she would let me take out six. She'd even
                    suggest books and lead me into new fields, mostly biographies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the most wonderful things that you can have is a
                        mentor whcan lead you into this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I was fortunate there. I had my grandmother who spoke four languages and
                    could recite long epic poems by heart in several languages, the librarian, and
                    the teachers. There were a few teachers in the P.S. number 3 in elementary
                    school but, particularly in high school, I still remember the teachers I had
                    there in French, English, history, math, and chemistry.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Q: Were you getting any feeling for foreign affairs while you were in high school
                    or from your family? Were they looking at events because we are talking about,
                    as you move up, both the Depression and the rise of Hitler?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I did a little but I had joined a Saturday night Polish student
                    association, or social club, wherein high school boys and girls would usually go
                    to the center of east Baltimore. It was through that association that I learned
                    something about foreign affairs and learned that there was such a thing as a
                    Kusciuszko Foundation where I applied and got a scholarship to Europe at the
                    Kusciuszko Institute in Krak_w, Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you go there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: It was in the summer and the first half of the third year of college when
                    I went to Krak_w. They had a very liberal attitude about studying. You could go
                    to class or not as you saw fit. They would give you a dollar a day for food.
                    They had a voucher system that allowed you to travel anywhere around Europe by
                    rail. I spent most of my time traveling. I went to Venice. I went to Rome. I
                    went to London. I went to Paris and, on one of my trips, I went to Berlin and
                    saw the Olympics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, this was 1936.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, it was the 1936 Olympics. I saw Jesse Owens win his four gold medals.
                    I became so impressed with the efficiency and the terror of the goose-stepping
                    Nazis that I decided there was going to be a war and I would get into the army
                    as quickly as I could.</p>
                <p>Q: While you were in Poland, had you been filled with the Polish movement, or did
                    your mother's and grandmother's coming from the Austrian part of Poland
                    influence you? What was your feeling towards Poland as a nation that you were
                    getting from family and your association?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, they were proud Poles, and there was a hierarchy among the Poles.
                    They were divided up. The Austrians, at least in my family, looked down on the
                    Germans, and looked way down on the Russian side so that the Russians were the
                    peasants, except for my father whom my grandmother thought was an exception.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was an honorary Austrian.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, he was an honorary Austrian, so she took him in. I'd had a fair
                    amount of coaching on what a bad thing it was that Poland was broken up so many
                    times, how much they loved freedom, and the fact that they had the second
                    constitution in the world right after the American constitution. Freedom really
                    was its undoing because they were so democratic under their liberum vito
                    idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had an explosion of one vote.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, you had to have one hundred percent. One vote could defeat any law
                    that was proposed. I've learned a lot about Polish history and Jan Sobieski.
                    When I was in Poland, a big monument was built in Krakow to Pilsudski and what
                    they call in Polish circles, the 21st great battle of the world when the Polish
                    stopped the Russians on the outside of Warsaw.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you must have absorbed it because this would come out
                        later ia certain amount of antipathy towards the Russians/Soviets.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I think deep back in my psyche there must have been a feeling that the
                    Poles were unjustly treated, particularly by the Russians. I would say that that
                    didn't manifest itself in any particular hatred or anything but I think that
                    deep down inside there must have been that. I must say there was an even greater
                    resentment against the Germans. The Germans marched into Poland on the 1st of
                    September 1939 and destroyed Poland. I would say the Germans were enemy number
                    one and the Russians were enemy number two.</p>
                <p>Q: What was your impression of Poland in 1936 and 1937 while you were there on
                    scholarship?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: They were poor, proud, and weak. I went to see where my father was born,
                    which was only about 40 kilometers north of Warsaw. It was primitive. There was
                    a dirt road leading to the place when I visited them in 1936. They still had the
                    oil lamps and outside privies. The farms were small. It was a poor establishment
                    but immediately on entering the hierarchy in places like the Jagielionian
                    Institute in Krakow, you got the feeling of great pride in their intellectual
                    and cultural prowess. They looked down on a lot of other countries from those
                    vantage points. There was a great divide between the upper class and the lower
                    class. It was definitely a Third World country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression particularly of Italy and
                        Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>ROWNY: I thought that they were somewhat higher in their energy and organization.
                    Of course, after I got to Rome and Florence, I found that they were the real
                    centers of Western civilization. As for Germany, I had a great feeling of
                    efficiency and authoritarianism. It was cleaner than some of the other
                    countries. They were more militaristic than others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this change your reading habits when you came back?
                        Were yomore interested in world affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Not immediately but I did begin to feel that I had chosen the wrong path
                    going into engineering. If I was going to do anything, it had to be something
                    more akin to foreign affairs, history, or literature. Since I spent so much time
                    overseas, I was somewhat behind, so my last year at Hopkins was a very busy
                    year. I had to work, so that took some time. Then, I became president of the
                    American Society of Civil Engineering junior chapter. That took some time. I
                    became president of the Scabbard and Blade, which is an ROTC unit. That took
                    some time. I got into a few other things, too. So, it was hard. I was constantly
                    running. I was constantly trying to catch a few hours sleep and lost quite a lot
                    of weight. I went down about 20 pounds. I was pretty thin at the time of
                    graduation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of work were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: In the summers, I worked at the Crosse and Blackwell factory, which is a
                    higher class British food chain establishment. I had various jobs there,
                    starting out as the weigh boy that would weigh in the tomato trucks. Later, I
                    was the spice boy that would weigh spices. That was the summer job. In winter, I
                    had various jobs for professors. Professor Medaugh wrote a book on hydraulic
                    engineering and had me put together the charts and the logarithm charts that
                    went in the back of the books. I worked for Professor Thompson who became the
                    first highway commissioner of the United States. He had me trace sketches of
                    highways and highway facilities. There was tremendous pay, you know; it was 50
                    cents an hour. When I worked at Crosse and Blackwell, I was so delighted that
                    the minimum wage was raised from 21 cents to 25 cents. This meant that I made
                    $25 a week, working 100 hours a week. There was a big difference. Money was
                    pretty hard to come by but adequate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated from high school at the age of 16, so you
                        would havbeen how old when you graduated from college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I entered Hopkins at 16 and graduated at 20. I was in the class of 1937,
                    so I was exactly 20 years old. When I finished Hopkins, I got my reserve
                    commission in the Corps of Engineers. I was in the engineering part of the ROTC
                    course. I resigned my commission in the reserves to go to West Point on the
                    first of July.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's quite unusual, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes. It was a godsend because I got to do what I wanted to do, read and
                    join the military. I coasted through all the science courses. I was able to
                    really loaf through those without much trouble and spent a lot of time reading.
                    I began the old Great Books program and really enjoyed the academic side of
                    it.</p>
                <p>Q: This would have been 1937 to 1941. From your instructors, was there a sense of
                    urgency, saying, “We really are going to have a big war?”</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Oh yes, very much so, particularly in the political science department. We
                    had a man who was head of that department who was quite an able and broad minded
                    individual, a Captain George Lincoln who, when the War broke out, came down to
                    the Pentagon and became General Marshall's planner. Lincoln had what you would
                    call his brigade, “his fair-haired boys,” that he liked in his political science
                    course who would be invited to his home. He guided our careers for the next 20
                    years. Lincoln at the end of World War II was promoted from brigadier general to
                    major general. But he said he would rather be reduced to colonel and go back to
                    West Point to teach again, which he did until he died. He was quite an
                    outstanding man. I owe a lot to him in more waysthan one.</p>
                <p>In my senior year at West Point, my eyes suddenly deteriorated from 20-20 to
                    20-200. West Point was tightening up on eye qualifications in those days. Ten of
                    us were put on probation. Lincoln, at his own expense, sent me to an
                    ophthalmologist in New York City who worked very hard with me on exercises. My
                    grades dropped sharply because I wasn't allowed to read except in Lincoln's
                    department. Even when I felt I made mistakes, I got perfect grades. Of the ten,
                    I was the only one to squeak through and get my commission. The others were
                    graduated but not commissioned. Then, after Pearl Harbor, all nine were called
                    back into the military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eyes are very important. As a kid, my brother was in the
                        class o1940 at the Naval Academy, and eyes were such an important item.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: They put them high on the list.</p>
                <p>Q: You look at it today, and one would be somewhat dubious about that. Of course,
                    this really wouldn't be appropriate for young cadets but were you thinking about
                    new forms of war, or was it pretty much looking at World War I?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: There were several instructors who were thinking of new forms of war. One
                    we liked particularly became a general in World War II, Gavin.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it James Gavin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, James Gavin. He introduced us to the idea of jumping out of
                    airplanes, which the United States had not done. He'd heard that the Russians
                    had done this. I was very impressed because Gavin would work 10 to 15 hours in
                    preparation for every hour of instruction that he gave the cadets. He clearly
                    researched everything he did and dramatized it and did everything so
                    beautifully. Also, Lincoln, although he was more on the political side, was very
                    much interested in the blitzkrieg and, somehow, got an early contact with
                    Colonel Wedemeyer who had been our military attach� to Germany. Wedemeyer sent
                    letters back to Lincoln at West Point about the coming new warfare blitzkrieg.
                    It stressed getting away from trench warfare by using armor and aircraft. These
                    instructors were not instructors in the regular class work. They were what we
                    call tactical officers. They looked after the discipline of the corps but had
                    school's courses on the side in military tactics. Another, Waters, became a
                    four-star general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you mean William Waters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, no. I knew him, by the way, but this was John K. Waters. He was a son-
                    in-law of Patton's. He and Lincoln on the academic side teamed up on the
                    blitzkrieg, and we followed the war pretty closely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, the War really hadn't started by the time you
                        graduated.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: It started September 1, 1939, as far as Europe was concerned.</p>
                <p>Q: Things were perking up but there was also a war going on in China at that
                    time. One has to think hard to think of any military innovations that came out
                    of that. I mean, were we looking at it?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, we were looking at it but not from any point of view of the military
                    innovations. It was part of Lincoln's course in teaching contemporary events. We
                    followed China and Japan, so we were exposed to a lot of Far Eastern history. I
                    would say much more, probably, than other contemporary schools in the country at
                    that time because of our interest in the military.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Q: As a kid, I lived in Annapolis. My brother was there, and I was 10 years oldI
                    was born in 1928 and I was 10 years younger than my brother - but, you know,
                    practically into chapel at the end of “God bless America,” they'd say, “Beat
                    Army.” I am sure you were given the same thing at West Point, yet we were
                    getting ready for a war that was going to require great cooperation. Did you see
                    any signs of people at West Point at that time saying, “Hey, you know there is
                    another branch?” At that time, there was the Army and the Navy.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, I did but only peripherally. Fortunately, there was a course where
                    they exchanged students. The cadets went on a midshipman cruise, and it was
                    highly competitive. I didn't make it but one of the people in Lincoln's brigade,
                    Andrew Goodpaster, a man two years ahead of me, did. He was quite impressed with
                    his 30 days on the cruise, which took him to Europe. Through him, more than
                    anybody else, I learned there should be more cooperation and we should break
                    down the barriers. The barriers weren't great where we were; they were just
                    rivalry in sports. But, we could sense that there was a great difference, almost
                    cultural background. Andy Goodpaster was one of the first men I met at West
                    Point, and he became a lifelong friend. We talked weekly and would see each
                    other quite frequently. He had a particular part to play in my career. When
                    Lincoln was the Army planner, I learned later that he'd asked for me to come
                    back and join the planning staff at the Pentagon. There was a small 12-man
                    establishment known as OPD in the War Department, the Operations Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: This was 1945. On D-Day, I had finished the War in Italy. My commanding
                    general went to the safe and brought out a letter dated a year earlier that said
                    that I should report to the Pentagon. But he had said that I was essential to
                    the war effort, so he kept me in Europe until the end of the War. Two days later
                    I was in the Pentagon, and I wanted very much to get into OPD, which was very
                    prestigious and had Dean Rusk in it, James Matthews, who later became president
                    of M.I.T., and Hank Byroade, who was the general who became ambassador to Egypt.
                    They had eleven people on that team pretty well established...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...entrenched...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: The 12th had rotated. A man would go in there and spend a couple of months
                    and then find himself assigned somewhere else. They put me on probation. After a
                    week or so, I was assigned to write a part of the final invasion of Japan, which
                    never took place.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>So I worked on this for about a week. When it was finished, I went to the fellow
                    on the desk next to me who was Andy Goodpaster. I said, “Andy, I want this job
                    pretty badly. What do you think of my plan?” He said, “Your idea's all right but
                    you surely don't know how to write to please General Marshall.” He stayed after
                    hours from five or six o'clock until midnight, re-dictated the plan, then the
                    girl had to type it out twice with four or five carbon copies and met the
                    deadline of eight o'clock the next morning. By ten o'clock, General Marshall
                    called me in and said, “Colonel Rowny, we have been trying for years to fill
                    this 12th place and,” he said, “The job is yours.” I said, “Well, General, the
                    ideas are mine but I've got to tell you that this plan was written by Colonel
                    Goodpaster.” He said, “Young man, I wasn't born yesterday. Of course, it was
                    written by Goodpaster but anybody who can get Goodpaster to work for him is good
                    enough for me.” So that's how I got into OPD.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to go back to the question of your eyes. When
                        yograduated from Hopkins in 1937, were your eyes a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, they were perfect. They were 20-20. They were 20-20 until the fall of
                    1940 when suddenly I got up one day and couldn't see the eye charts and couldn't
                    see the details anymore. My eyes had shifted to 20-200.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What branch of the service did you go into?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I went into the Corps of Engineers. I didn't go into it as high ranking as
                    I would have liked because my grades dropped quite precipitously after my eyes
                    went bad because I couldn't read. I was getting some poorer grades except in
                    economics, which was the course Abe Lincoln was teaching. You could choose by
                    order of rank, and the Corps of Engineers always went out first.</p>
                <p>Q: This is something I've always wondered about West Point. The Corps of
                    Engineers, particularly, has always been extremely controversial because there
                    are really two corps of engineers. Please correct me but, if I understand it,
                    there is the Civilian Corps of Engineers which does public works and then
                    there's the combat corps. So when you go into the Corps of Engineers, at that
                    point do they decide which one of those or does it remain the Corps of Engineers
                    and you switch back and forth?</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>ROWNY: It remains the Corps of Engineers, and you switch back and forth but early
                    on you get a leaning for one way or the other. Usually, it's a selection by the
                    civilian side into their highly prestigious branch. It was highly sought after
                    for two reasons: one, it is traditional for the Robert E. Lees and Douglas
                    MacArthurs. The second reason was the engineers got to build dams and bridges
                    and an officer could stay busy during peacetime. When I entered the engineering
                    career and thought I had done a pretty good job on the combat side, the chief of
                    the Corps of Engineers visited and said, “You've done such a good job, I want
                    you to know I'll give you a job in rivers and harbors.” It didn't sit too well
                    with me.</p>
                <p>Q: This is the thing that has always bothered me. It's prestigious and all that
                    but at the same time, it is sort of like graduating high in a medical school and
                    then being put into tonsillectomy or something like that.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, I followed Goodpaster, and when he transferred to thinfantry, I did,
                    too.</p>
                <p>Q: So, in 1937 you graduated. I was just a kid in Annapolis but the young
                    professional things talked about a war coming, and you're going to fight. Of
                    course, the Navy was looking at the Japanese and the Germans but where did you
                    want to go and where did you go?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, feeling was not high at Hopkins that there was a war coming. This
                    was a more personal feeling. When I decided to go to West Point, the feeling was
                    not high that there was going to be a war. Of course, we heard more and more
                    about the coming war at West Point, and I must say that up to the time we
                    graduated, the focus was all on Europe. We'd learn what was going on in the Far
                    East but we didn't get the feeling that we'd get involved there but that we
                    would in Europe. Everything pointed towards Europe, particularly after September
                    1939.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, in the Navy, we knew the Brits and the Germans
                        both had navies and would take care of each other. So the Navy was looking
                        at the Japanese. It was a much bigger ocean to play around in. What was your
                        first assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: My first assignment was to an engineer regiment in North Carolina, the
                    41st Engineers. The old cadre came from the 10th cavalry. It was a combat
                    engineering regiment, which had an unusual commander, eccentric almost, a
                    colonel who commanded the 41st engineers. We had black troopers and white
                    officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was your commanding officer eccentric?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>ROWNY: His name was John Wood, and he was very innovative and ahead of the times.
                    First, on the political side, his brother, Stewart Wood, had been a Japanese
                    language student and corresponded quite a bit with John Wood whose nickname was
                    Joe. In August 1941, I joined the 41st engineers. Joe was training his people
                    very hard, much harder than the other units, and talking a lot about the coming
                    war with Japan. He was known as very unusual. It was an unusually oddball outfit
                    because others did their job from reveille to recall, but we trained weekends on
                    maneuvers.</p>
                <p>Joe had a number of highly - even today - unusual ideas. For example, he thought
                    that soldiering was an honorary and elevated position and soldiers should not do
                    any policing up or any menial work. Regiments were allowed a training fund, and
                    he would use his training funds to hire women from the town to come do KP in the
                    kitchen and clean up the barracks so that the soldiers could spend some time
                    training. For Negro soldiers to have white women come in and do cooking and
                    cleaning for them was quite something. It was a very proud outfit. He was very
                    proud. That was one of the innovative ideas he had, which has still not really
                    caught on. The army still does a lot of menial and routine work. He considered
                    himself the best trainer in the army. Ordered to provide cadres for new units,
                    he would always send out his best and keep the worst. After about six or seven
                    cadres of sending out people to form new units, we had the usual number of
                    replacements but we were highly loaded with the lower end of the spectrum, the
                    class 5s. They had scores of AGCTs in the '50s and '60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You are talking about the draft at this time, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, I'm talking about the draft. He'd the take normal replacements on the
                    draft but, since he would send all the best people out, they would send out a
                    cross-section. This was very unpopular with his subordinates, his company
                    commanders. They'd say, “Why do we have to spend 90 percent of our time on these
                    duds and rejects?” So, on one occasion, they were complaining very loudly about
                    the sixth or seventh cadre, and he would trick them. He had his own way of
                    finding out who the better people were, and he would overrule the company
                    commanders and send all the best people out.</p>
                <p>They were complaining one Saturday morning at an officers' called meeting about
                    the terrible injustice he was doing to the unit and to them. He asked, “Do you
                    know who these people are?” They replied, “Oh, yes, we know who they are.” He
                    said, “I want each of you 12 company commanders to write the names of 10 of your
                    worst soldiers, the 10 people you hope never to see again.” Then, he turned
                    around to me, and I collected the names and put them in front of him. He said,
                    “No, no, they are yours. That's your company. On Monday morning, they will
                    assemble out in the field, and that will be J Company.”</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>There had been no “J” companies in the army since the Civil War. I commanded “J”
                    Company for the next two or three months. I followed a lot of Wood's techniques
                    and ideas, so that with this company of 120 of the worst people in the regiment,
                    we won a major share of competitions in the various competitive events. He
                    maneuvered it so that we would be the first unit to go overseas. He said that we
                    had trained harder and were ready, and he had friends and got us assigned to
                    Africa. We got on board ship with secret orders, and we had a letter of
                    instructions of about 10 to 12 pages and then reams and reams of blueprints and
                    papers and ideas and details of what we were supposed do in Africa. He again
                    turned to me and said, “Lieutenant Rowny, open up the portholes and throw away
                    all those plans. We'll make up our own plans. We know more about what we are
                    going to do than they do.” So, we spent our time going to Africa writing up our
                    own detailed plans of what to do. I could write a book about Joe. He was so
                    unusual.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk a bit about race relations. I think it is important to understand
                    about race relations at that time, particularly in North Carolina. You lived in
                    Baltimore but you said this hadn't been part of your society in a way. On both
                    sides, how did you and the other white officers relate and how were they
                    received by the army?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: This was the rosy side of the picture. Joe Wood who was from Virginia, a
                    Southerner, considered himself a northerner in many ways. He had a gentleman
                    farmer approach to things. He always told the blacks how good they were and how
                    they could be better than anyone else. He built up their pride.</p>
                <p>He was not a West Pointer but he managed to have more West Pointers assigned to
                    his unit than anyone else. Joe was very careful about the officers he accepted.
                    He had great friends and was able to get officers assigned. If he found that
                    someone had what he thought was a bias or had any difficulty, he'd quietly
                    transfer him out of the outfit.</p>
                <p>We had, I would say, an almost ideal relationship with the blacks and the white
                    officers. The blacks were drafted. Most of them came from the South, and were
                    now well above their financial and cultural station. Because they were treated
                    as proud people and, especially, with this cadre from the old black soldiers and
                    black army, the 41st was the elite outfit for blacks. On Sunday afternoons,
                    people would come from miles around to watch the parades where we not only did
                    the normal parading but the trick elaborate parading. Joe was quite a showman,
                    and the soldiers loved this. He was a great believer in competitions. He was
                    competitive, and everybody got a prize. Some were better than others but we had
                    good relations. Of course, we did not have the element of combat in it. Even
                    though they were combat engineers, they maneuvered like infantry. Joe insisted
                    that we do most of our training as infantry and, even in Africa, we got to know
                    combat. That made quite a difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the non-commissioned officers? You are
                        talkinabout a pretty technical thing, in terms of combat engineers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: They were splendid. Of course, we were fortunate in getting the cream of
                    the crop of the old 9th and 10th cavalry. When I had my “J” company, I was the
                    only officer, and I had four non-coms with a total of 100 years service, who
                    were very highly dedicated and professional. I remained friends with these
                    non-commissioned officers until they died. That completely changed later when we
                    were finishing up our work in Liberia. We were sent there for three reasons: (1)
                    to save the rubber; rubber is essential and Firestone had its rubber plantations
                    there; (2) to keep the Liberians neutral; in World War I, the Germans had
                    bombarded Liberia, and the Liberians were neutral and we wanted to keep them on
                    our side as a possible springing off point; and, (3) Liberia had both a port,
                    Fisherman's Lake near Monrovia, and an airfield so that planes could take off
                    from Liberia up to Khartoum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a very important link at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, it was for the whole African campaign. It was important for the
                    supply of the Russian lend-lease. The airlift part of it went up from Miami to
                    Belize to Monrovia to Khartoum and, then, on up to the Black Sea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go out there before the African landings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: We were there in February or March of 1942, before the Africalandings in
                    October 1942.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you weren't feeling that you were out of it because
                        there wacombat elsewhere in that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, of course, there wasn't any yet. There wasn't any combat that we were
                    in. I guess we'd had some combat in the Philippines, and I'm sure army units
                    were shipped overseas but I don't think they had gotten into combat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nothing started, I guess, until October of 1942.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: That was the North African campaign.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was talking about the European theater.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>ROWNY: You are right. By October of 1942, Joe Wood had made brigadier general and
                    was known for his reputation with Negro troops. He was sent back home to put
                    together the 92nd black division. The Army placed a major general over him:
                    Edward (Ned) Almond. I went back to organize and train the 92nd Division.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Liberia, how were these black troops received in
                        Liberia, whicalways had these close ties to the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: It was a very difficult relationship. There is a hierarchy in Liberia, a
                    small group, which is very imperialistic or authoritarian. The rest were slaves
                    and very poor. Our black troops saw the great injustice that was being done to
                    the Liberians and felt that they were much better off in the United States than
                    ordinary Liberians unless they happened to be in the ruling class. There were
                    very few of those at the top, so it was very repressive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It didn't arouse any ethnic ties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, no. Black soldiers had nothing to do with the natives there except
                    that the men paid for the sexual favors. Otherwise, there was no contact of any
                    kind. Our officers had some contact with the Firestone Rubber people and just
                    one or two members of the Liberian government. Even then the Liberian government
                    was highly corrupt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll pick it up when you were called back in October of
                        1942 ttrain the 92nd division.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I joined the headquarters at Fort McClellan, Alabama. They put the
                    headquarters, the artillery, and the special troops in Alabama. The Army put
                    each of the regiments in a different state. The fear was that, if they had the
                    entire 15,000 troops in one state, there'd be too much of a chance of race riots
                    and difficulties, so they broke this up into four states.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Q: This is the interview with General Rowny. I will put in here that I have just
                    finished reading an oral history that was done with General Rowny called
                    Engineer Memoirs, and it was done by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and
                    published in 1995. It covers many of the things that I would be asking, and I
                    thought that rather than duplicate, I will see if I can get the Memoir included
                    in this oral history with credit to the Army Corps of Engineers. I am going to
                    be asking some foreign affairs type questions of General Rowny, and we'll start
                    at that point.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Q: General, you were obviously not a straight line soldier. You started out as an
                    engineer, and you had a distinguished military career and combat with infantry.
                    How many silver stars did you get?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I believe it was three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the stars awarded in World War II, in the Korean War,
                        and ithe Vietnam War?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, in Vietnam I got the Distinguished Service Medal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Vietnam when you got shot down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, but I didn't get any combat awards.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, I mean you were there, and you were doing things. At the same time while
                    you were doing this, you were obviously somebody who was tapped as a planner and
                    a military thinker. I noted that you felt that your ideas of using helicopter
                    troops during the Vietnam War was a bit ahead of the game. What's your
                    impression of how this army handled people who were thinkers and advanced
                    planners?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I think they handled them very well. They looked for people and put them
                    in key positions. Of course, my number one star here is Colonel George A. (Abe)
                    Lincoln, who became the army planner. Also, I think that the plan section was
                    always put in one of the most prestigious spots, a staff job among the G-1
                    through 3 and 4, and I've been both a G-3 and a G-4. The G-3 always has a higher
                    prestige, and within the G-3, plans and operations sections had their hierarchy
                    with planners coming out on top.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Eisenhower came out through there at the beginning
                        of WorlWar II. Wasn't he brought back to the Philippines and put into
                        planes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: He later became the OPD.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there a conscious effort on the part of army leaders to take people they
                    thought would be planners, or forward-lookers, and move them through good
                    positions both with command and then staff positions to bring them up and to
                    give them a feeling that someone was looking out for them?</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>ROWNY: There definitely was a guardian angel looking out for me in the person of
                    George Lincoln. There were several others later along the way. Yes, I think that
                    personal contacts were promoted. I was the first in my class to become a
                    captain, the first major, the first lieutenant colonel, the first colonel, and
                    the first brigadier general. We got early promotions and, at least from my point
                    of view, choice assignments.</p>
                <p>Q: I am just picking up little bits and pieces but, when Truman announced the
                    integration of the armed forces, what was your experience? You had already been
                    with a black engineering unit. What was your impression of the attitude of the
                    professional soldiers on this integration?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I think that the majority of them were in favor of integration. A
                    minority, whom I supposed were mostly people born in the South, thought this
                    would not work, was not a good idea. A majority believed that this was the way
                    to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in it in that early period? What were
                        yodoing at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I was in Korea at the time that the integration took place, and there was
                    a battalion of Negroes, the second division, which then was later broken up and
                    the blacks were distributed among the white units. By the time I got my infantry
                    regiment in Korea, I inherited a regiment, which had blacks integrated along
                    with the whites. Before then when I was a corps engineer, the units under me
                    were white, and I didn't have much contact with the blacks. Later in Korea, I
                    got an infantry regiment, and that regiment was integrated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within the enlisted ranks, did that seem to work fairly
                        well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Oh, yes, I think that, as far as I could tell, it was far superior to what
                    we had experienced in World War II when we had the all-black units with some
                    white officers at the top.</p>
                <p>Q: In general terms, as the Cold War developed, you were with the staff officer
                    of the general staff from 1945 to 1947. Is it a natural thing for planners to
                    look around for a potential enemy? Was the Soviet Union coming out pretty
                    quickly as a possible enemy?</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>ROWNY: We didn't have to look too far. The evidence was coming in fast and
                    furious. First, General Lincoln had us read Kennan's cables and study those. We
                    had that background. Then, we had the cables coming in from Lucius Clay who was
                    the U.S. member of the High Commission in Berlin. He had a devastating set of
                    events to report, and he was trying to work things out. Also, at the time I
                    remember, the original thought was that Soviet Union would take part in
                    thoccupation of Japan. There were two groups that fought about that. Generally,
                    the Pentagon was saying, “No way,” and the State Department was saying, “Oh,
                    yes, you have to do this,” because the Soviet Union had declared war or at least
                    declared they were going to put troops into battle just about two days before
                    the atom bombs were dropped. Fortunately, the ideas were cabled out to MacArthur
                    who was very strong in saying that he opposed any idea of the Soviets having a
                    part in the occupation of Japan. He insisted that he would retire or resign. He
                    would not wish to be a member of that group. We had all these signals coming in
                    as to what was going to be the future of our relationship with the rest of the
                    world and, particularly, with the Soviet Union. There was the idea of the
                    Soviets allowing elections in Poland. However, they put in their own puppet so
                    that the Poles in London had a government in exile. That played into all this,
                    so the Soviet Union was very much a pariah.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you getting reports back from officers who had served in Moscow or
                    elsewhere during the war about the attitude of the Soviets towards America or
                    giving a great deal of aid and all that?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, I don't remember getting that kind of report. I did have some reports
                    from my next door neighbor in Alexandria who was a White House press
                    correspondent, Merriman Smith. He had gone over to Berlin, and he told us about
                    the pillage and raping that was going on in Berlin. I heard a lot more about all
                    this after I went to Yale in 1947.</p>
                <p>Q: Within the Foreign Service - certainly not at the top but within the Foreign
                    Service - we had people who served in Moscow and Vladivostok and all, and they
                    came away with a very jaundiced view of this. This was during the height of our
                    aid to them in the war, and the Americans were treated like the enemy.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Exactly, and we had the cables back from General Dean who was the head of
                    our Lend-Lease; he later put these into a book called Strange Alliance, which is
                    my number one book on negotiating with the Soviets. He told about how difficult
                    they were to deal with. Even though we were giving them Jeeps and ammunition and
                    all kinds of other equipment, they were making life difficult for us. For
                    example, when U.S. pilots were shot down over Poland or Eastern Europe, the
                    Soviets put these pilots into prison camps. They were only released after the
                    war. It was outrageous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was pretty easy to figure out what the future might
                        portend,wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, we formed our ideas early on that the Soviet Union was on the march
                    ideologically and was not going to cooperate with the West. They were more
                    interested in promoting their ideology than in moving on with the occupation
                    policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It must have been very difficult to be a planner during
                        the 1945 to 1947 period and to look at how we had taken this magnificent
                        fighting force we had and had broken it down. The Soviets had all these
                        divisions. Was there any plan, other than if they came with atom bombs, at
                        the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: There are two aspects of that. On the demobilization, as much as I admired
                    Marshall, I was part of a small group that felt that we demobilized too rapidly.
                    We had torn down our magnificent fighting force, and gutted it. That was one
                    side of the question, just our own doing. As far as the atom bomb was concerned,
                    you called it the major influence in Washington at that time. This came from
                    Morgenthau who was very much in favor of using the atom bomb in any tense
                    situation. It was later our plan to make a new war department, and Washington's
                    idea was to use the atom bomb only if our national survival was actually at
                    stake. A lot of this developed after I left the Pentagon and was developing
                    during the time I was at Yale. That's another chapter of this story.</p>
                <p>In the 1945 to 1947 period, we were occupied with working out plans and
                    implementing them for the occupation of Japan and Germany, and the restructuring
                    of the Army and the birth of the United States Air Force, which was a major
                    problem. We worked on the future structure of our armed forces.</p>
                <p>Q: Was the army, as a planner, concerned that the birth of the Air Force would
                    have Mike Norstad's Seventh Air Force? You knew that you would lose this very
                    strong supporting strategic air fighter to fighter, a ground support outfit, and
                    that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>ROWNY: There wasn't much thought then that the Air Force would give close air
                    support for ground troops. All the talk was about the strategic bombing. You
                    remember these were the days when a number of army air corps officers and others
                    were promoting the Douhet theory, that air power could win wars by itself. The
                    Navy was very much opposed. One of Eisenhower's astute moves was to go to Hap
                    Arnold, who was the number one man in the Army Air Corps, and ask that his best
                    younger officer, Lauris Norstad, be assigned to the War Department. He became
                    our new boss, the head of OPD, as a major general and, later, a lieutenant
                    general in the Army Air Corps. He promoted the idea of a separate air force.
                    This idea of a man within the War Department being in charge of War Department
                    plans and operations, being an Army Air Corps man, was really a brilliant move
                    and helped bring about the creation of the Army Air Force against the objection
                    of the Navy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later we had the Admirals' Revolt. That was in the 1950s
                        o1960s, I can't remember.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, I wasn't around then. I think it was fortunate that there was this
                    close affinity between George Lincoln and Norstad, Lincoln being the army
                    planner who stayed on. He and Norstad had very high respect for each other.</p>
                <p>Norstad replaced the Army general as our chief of OPD. Norsted, having great
                    prestige with his old Army Air Corps buddies, was able to sit on a lot of super
                    ambitious plans that the future Air Force officers had for the battle for
                    resources. They said, “We don't need all these armed ground troops anymore. We
                    don't need so much navy. We are going to do it all with air power.” Norstad was
                    able to dampen that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This keeps cropping up. It hasn't died yet. After Kosova,
                        it istill there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Also, Billy Mitchell's battle over whether an airplane could sink a
                    battleship or not entered into this argument. It was a very tense time. The
                    original plan that was submitted by the newly formed Air Force for what they
                    wanted was just outrageous, it was so high. They wanted about half of all the
                    resources and, then, the other half could be divided between the Navy and the
                    Army. Whittled down over the years, I guess it's roughly one-third, one-third,
                    for each service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at Yale from 1947 to 1949. How did you find the
                        intellectual range at Yale as far as the people who were looking at the
                        East-West confrontation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I was fortunate at Yale in terms of both civilian instructors and those
                    who were in the military field. The people on the civilian side were really
                    broad thinkers, like Arnold Wolfers; Heil Holborn, who had been the first
                    historian for the Weimar Republic; and, W. T. R. Fox, who was a broad-gauge
                    historian. We were getting a broad-gauge idea of how the future of international
                    relations would be conducted with a heavy academic overload of United Nations
                    and overall government. The other half of the instructors we had were the best
                    academic thinkers on military matters in the country. The leader of the group
                    was Bernard Brodie, who was backed by Klaus Knorr and Bill Kaufman. Bernard
                    Brodie began writing his seminal work, The Absolute Weapon. There were great
                    debates within the academic community at Yale about which way U.S. policy should
                    go on the atom bomb but Bernard Brodie won out in the end with his book.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the thrust of this book?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ROWNY: The thrust of this book was that we would not rely on atomic weapons in
                    ordinary situations, that it was the ultimate arbitrator and that it would prove
                    strategic bombing to be a success. There was some controversy about strategic
                    bombing and surveys were made about how much damage the regular bombing
                    campaigns had done. Now, this was the absolute weapon, and it was to be used
                    only in the extreme case of national survival being at stake. Brodie and Kaufman
                    made frequent trips back to the Pentagon and talked to Lincoln and Norstad.
                    While they were developing their theories, I think the U.S. followed the lead of
                    what had been developed there at Yale.</p>
                <p>Q: As a military planner and army officer, I would think right from the beginning
                    any look at this nuclear weapon that was called the atomic bomb in those days
                    would be just absolutely repugnant. I mean, one, it messed up the battlefield
                    and, two, it threatened, you know. At that time we weren't thinking about full
                    destruction of civilization but, I mean, it was almost an impossible weapon to
                    plan around, wasn't it?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: It was very difficult to deal with and especially in a charged atmosphere
                    of the newly formed Air Force, which would take over and control this weapon.
                    There was a great deal of anxiety about how all this would work out. I think
                    with this charged atmosphere in the Pentagon and preoccupation with redesigning
                    the new forces and with the occupation problems facing us, it took an outside
                    agency, like academia, to lead the way on thinking. A part of Lincoln's program
                    was to bring us back, the four of us that were sent to different universities to
                    study international relations. We sat in on the seminars we had with the
                    strategic planning section in the Pentagon. Some general said that he would
                    rather go back to West Point.</p>
                <p>Q: In the academic world in the planning, were we going on the assumption that
                    within a relatively short period of time the Soviet Union would probably have
                    the weapon, too?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: We thought that they would eventually, but that we were far ahead. We had
                    a monopoly for a long period of time. I don't think anybody predicted that the
                    Soviets would advance as rapidly as they did in this field. The one exception
                    was the Yale historian Fred Barghoorn, who wrote about the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, when you got out of Yale, you were sent as plans
                        officer tthe Far Eastern Command.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, I was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Far Eastern Command was based in Tokyo, wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, what was your impression and what was the reputation
                        that you'd gotten inside the military of Douglas MacArthur at this
                        point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Oh, he had a very high reputation. Of course, when I was in the Pentagon,
                    in addition to my other duties, I had been the MacArthur desk officer, so I got
                    to read his cables. Of course, MacArthur was a legend. He had been a division
                    commander in World War I and earned a Medal of Honor and had a distinguished
                    career throughout the years. Except for overzealous lobbying for more forces in
                    the Pacific, he conducted himself quite admirably during the war and with his
                    island hopping ideas avoided a large number of casualties. I was delighted to be
                    assigned out to his command.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, how did you find the atmosphere on his staff? One always thinks of this
                    “coterie,” a term that might be used to describe the people and atmosphere that
                    surrounded MacArthur. They were extreme loyalists, and I would think that, as a
                    plans officer, it'd be difficult. I'm talking about just before the Korean War.
                    How did you find this?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: It was a difficult situation. Sometimes we envied the civilian side, which
                    was redesigning the entire Japanese government. Their relations were quite
                    smooth. On the military side, we found that there was some tension among
                    officers and, generally, it was caused by the simple fact that you were either
                    an old friend of MacArthur's and part of his personal entourage or you weren't.
                    If you were, you could do no wrong. If you weren't, you'd have to fight for your
                    positions. We'd find that atmosphere in the staff. There wasn't an open revolt
                    or anything but it was there nevertheless.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived as plans officer, this was November
                        1949.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you view the potential military situation in your
                        part othe world? What were the threats and what would be our responses?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>ROWNY: We were really preoccupied with the Soviet Union and China and,
                    particularly, what would happen if the two combined forces against us. For the
                    first 30 days I was there, I traveled around Japan accompanied by one of the
                    members on the civilian staff, a professor, Edward Morrow, who was both a
                    Japanese historian and an anthropologist. I had a wonderful tour and first hand
                    look at what was going on in Japan. I wrote a trip report that we were wasting
                    our assets by having troops out in so many villages and provinces. That view was
                    not original with me. It was a view that was held principally by the people who
                    were not among MacArthur's selected few. This idea of withdrawing and pulling
                    back our troops into central training camps was opposed by people like
                    Willoughby, MacArthur's G-2.</p>
                <p>Q: In a way, it was still an occupation, which no longer needed to be an
                    occupation, wasn't it? Was it the idea of local uprisings, or was it just more
                    for comfort?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: The traditional view, or fear, was that there would be uprisings and,
                    perhaps, difficulty in these various places; therefore, we needed American
                    presence in large numbers but that proved not to be not the case. The emperor
                    had good control of the situation but we did need some armed forces because
                    there was no such thing as a Red Cross over there to handle disasters and fires
                    and maybe even riots. The building of a Japanese self-defense force was
                    essential to replace the U.S. Army, which was being pulled back. I wrote the
                    first outline plan for the self-defense forces for the Japanese army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While we are looking at this, did Korea fall within your
                        bailiwick?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes, but there wasn't a great deal of thought given to Korea. It was a
                    minor worry. We followed it and some of us were very much opposed to the idea of
                    holding back our military support to Syngman Rhee. If you remember, the Soviet
                    Union was backing Kim Il Song and giving him their weapons. We were withholding
                    weaponry from South Korea, believing, or at least the State Department did, that
                    Syngman Rhee would use these forces to attack the North. The North Koreans used
                    this as a propaganda ploy to say that they had to build up because the South was
                    going to attack and reoccupy the North.</p>
                <p>At Yale it was one of our courses under Gabriel Almond on decision making. There
                    were 10 of us in the class and the professor gave each of us some incident which
                    had gone wrong because of bad decisions. We selected 10 periodicals and
                    magazines. The object was to study what these magazines and periodicals had said
                    about the mistakes that had occurred. I recall that of all the periodicals, I
                    think the Sunday New York Times and the Herald Tribune each had one out of 10.
                    The Baltimore Sun and the Atlantic Constitution had two out of 10, and one
                    periodical had four out of 10. If you had read that periodical for a year
                    before, you would have been able to predict what would happen, and that was The
                    Economist.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I became an avid reader of the Economist and had it air mailed to me in Tokyo.
                    Sometime early in 1950, there was a report in the Economist, saying keep your
                    eye on North Korea; it might attack. I flagged this and sent it in to the chief
                    of staff for General MacArthur. Again, we got a blast from Willoughby, saying,
                    “Look, I'm the chief here and if any information is going to be given of an
                    intelligence nature, I'll forward it.” So, I gained somewhat of a reputation as
                    being a seer of what was to happen, which I wasn't. I was just reporting what I
                    read in the London Economist.</p>
                <p>Q: The initial attack came June 25, 1950, a date which I think all of us of a
                    certain generation or two will remember very well. How well did you respond at
                    that point?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I think MacArthur's response was rapid and correct. He immediately talked
                    to people in Washington and was directing attention to the need for troops and
                    also for an international group. MacArthur put his whole staff to work on how we
                    were going to cope with the situation in Korea. We were fortunate at that time
                    to have a wonderful ambassador to South Korea, John Muccio, who did a
                    first-class job in his cables and phone calls to MacArthur. It had a lot to do
                    with formulating MacArthur's ideas of what he sent back. The military was
                    preoccupied with fighting the onslaught of the North Koreans, and Muccio was a
                    very courageous and cool-headed ambassador deserving much credit for our initial
                    response to North Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had there been any talks between our military and what
                        passed fothe South Korean military before this happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: We had a training force in South Korea but it wasn't very strong or large.
                    We didn't equip the South Korean army very well. There was close talk and
                    integration between the two but it didn't amount to much because of the small
                    size of our military training force and its lack of resources to support
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a concern when this thing happened that, for
                        somreason, the Japanese might rise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, not at all. The Japanese were very much behind MacArthur's idea of
                    calling for an international force, which worked out very well because the
                    Soviet ambassador to the U.N. was absent. They had said they'd veto our plans. I
                    might mention one thing in passing. I think it's on the 5th of January 1950 that
                    Churchill met with Truman and we got a cable in which Churchill said that he had
                    held Truman in low regard until he had met him personally and that, now, he
                    regretted that and felt that Truman was a good president. I've never seen that
                    in print anywhere. I don't know if you've come across it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I haven't. I know obviously that Truman rose in many
                        people's estimation over the years. What about the attitude towards
                        Marshall, the chief of staff, and Truman and all? Was there a tendency on
                        MacArthur's staff to be somewhat dismissive, “We'll do this thing, and don't
                        tell us what to do?” I'm talking about prior to the actual attack and
                        shortly afterwards.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Well, it wasn't so much the staff. There was this tendency on the part of
                    MacArthur to, with the help of a few of these sycophants on his staff who had
                    been giving him bad advice, look down his nose at Truman as just an underling
                    who had only risen to be a captain in the Army. We were happy when the cable
                    came giving Churchill's high regard for Truman and circulated that among the
                    staff so that we would influence people around MacArthur and MacArthur himself
                    to have a higher regard for Truman. Truman was gaining in stature all through
                    that time.</p>
                <p>Q: You've already covered it thoroughly and very well. You were with the planning
                    of Inchon, but what was your impression after you became a field officer in
                    Korea of your Korean counterparts? Did you see them as having a long way to go
                    to learn how to be military officers?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: Yes. They had a very long way to go. They had not been trained well, and
                    there was not a professional officer corps. Some of the soldiers, individually,
                    were brave and fought well but, in general, it was not what we would consider a
                    first-class military force. It was second or third class. Particularly, one can
                    contrast it to the North Korean forces who were well trained and well equipped
                    and came down in force with great capabilities, much more than the South Koreans
                    then.</p>
                <p>I changed that idea later when I went back in 1967 and 1968 and commanded the
                    First Corps. I saw how the Koreans had built an academy modeled after West
                    Point. They had built a first-class officer corps. There originally were six
                    Korean divisions and two U.S. divisions under my command on the DMZ. It later
                    became seven Korean divisions and one U.S. division. Those divisions, I
                    considered, were as good as our U.S. division. To answer your question,
                    initially, we had a low opinion of their ability.</p>
                <p>Q: You were going to be more and more involved in working in solely-American
                    organizations. For you and maybe for others who were making the plans, let's say
                    we've got to start building up really professional armies on the part of Vietnam
                    and other places. Did the lesson get to some of your political masters?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: It's hard to say on the civilian side but I know that it was very much on
                    our mind when the Vietnam War began. In the early days of that war, the
                    Vietnamese followed our experience of building an officer corps, including the
                    establishment of a military academy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had - what was the term? - KATUSAs, the Korean
                        soldierintegrated into our divisions. Was that ever contemplated in
                        Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I wasn't in that element of the battle enough to know. In the time that I
                    used KATUSAs in the second year of the Korean War, I used them largely in my
                    engineer outfits. I don't remember integrating them into our fighting outfits
                    that early but maybe they did. We did use thousands of them as laborers and
                    truck drivers and, in some cases, equipment operators on our engineering
                    equipment. They did quite well.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's move ahead. When you were in NATO, this goes into the 1960s. In
                    particular when you were in the 24th division from 1965 to 1966, how did we view
                    the Soviet threat? We knew they had a lot of forces there but, one, did we see
                    war as being able to happen on a hair trigger and how effective did we think the
                    Soviets would be?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: It was always a great worry because the Soviets outnumbered our divisions
                    by at least two or three to one. The question was, could we hold them off if
                    they attacked without our resorting to use of the atomic bomb? How would we
                    contain the Soviets if they moved across Germany through the Fulda Gap against
                    our inferior forces? Twelve years earlier when I was secretary of the General
                    Staff at SHAPE, it was already apparent that we faced a threat from the Soviet
                    Union. As you may recall, in 1956, the Soviets moved into Hungary. The worry
                    was, who would be next? These concerns never faded. The original plans made in
                    the Pentagon for the number of troops the U.S. had to be pared back again and
                    again. The first plans called for 60 U.S. divisions. That was cut in half and
                    then in half again. Even with the buildup of the Allies, the question was
                    whether we would have time to mobilize or would have to resort to the nuclear
                    weapon.</p>
                <p>Q: I was in Germany in the middle fifties as an enlisted man in the Air Force at
                    Darmstadt near Lendenfels and, then, later as a vice counsel in Frankfurt. I
                    used to see this huge atomic cannon driving around, tactical weapons. Was this a
                    bluff as far as the use of this?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: No. It was not a bluff, nor was resorting to atomic weapons. Rather, it
                    was what we called a measured response. We would move by degrees. If we couldn't
                    contain the forces with our ground troops, we would use the 280 millimeter
                    atomic cannon to try to stop the onslaught. If that failed, we would resort to
                    strategic bombing from the air. We always had the feeling that we were very much
                    behind and we were in a vulnerable position all through the years.</p>
                <p>Q: In a way it is very dangerous to be involved in that, but also the fact that
                    if you are looking at it from the Soviet side, you don't want your opponent to
                    be so weak as to have the massive weapons used. They are almost automatically
                    going to have to use it. When you were with NATO, you got involved very much in
                    the logistics of the withdrawal of our forces from France. That was a very
                    difficult time. What was your impression of the French military reaction? Their
                    leader, General De Gaulle, had made the decision but how did the military
                    respond?</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>ROWNY: Our contacts with the French military were first rate and, while the
                    French were loyal to De Gaulle, a lot of them expressed privately their
                    unhappiness with what was going on. We had a good relationship with the French
                    military at our level, our opposite numbers, but at the top there was this great
                    division. De Gaulle said he would support NATO politically but not militarily
                    and gave the U.S. a year to move its troops and supplies out of France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this cause any rifts with the French military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I don't know what the internal politics were and what happened. I was not
                    in a position to see any higher traffic. I only saw people at my own level. They
                    were friendly and apologetic for what was going on. Whether there was a rift
                    with DeGaulle, I just don't know.</p>
                <p>Q: Back to Vietnam, early on you got involved with that from 1962 and variously
                    involved up to 1965. Were you getting reports back of disquiet about our
                    involvement there?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I didn't in the early days. There was what we considered a one-sided view
                    of the press. Halberstam and others were writing from Saigon that the Vietnamese
                    and Diem would never be able to succeed, and we shouldn't be backing him. After
                    the assassination of Diem in 1963, everything went downhill. We never recovered
                    from that. Once he was gone, there was no one to rally around.</p>
                <p>Some of us who had been in Korea thought it was similar to the events that
                    happened there. Syngman Rhee was unpopular in some circles in the U.S. but
                    America backed him. Our original thought in Vietnam was that we'd better work
                    with Diem. There was, even in those early days, what turned out later to be a
                    very great opposition to our involvement in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't felt very greatly in those early days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, it wasn't.</p>
                <p>Q: Getting back to Korea where you were serving in 1971, you were commanding
                    general of I CORPS. How did you see the military situation at that time?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: We were quite confident that, despite the larger North Korean forces, we
                    could hold them off. We believed we had trained our forces well enough so there
                    would be enough time to decide whether we had to resort to nuclear weapons.
                    There was a stockpile of nuclear weapons in Korea, which could be used by U.S.
                    Air Force. What we didn't know is what might happen if the Soviets moved in
                    Germany. That was another problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were commanding general of the I CORPS, did you
                        ever havany dealings with Park Chung Hee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: Not that I remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the embassy? Were you involved with the embassy
                        at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: I just made courtesy calls and social visits. I worked for the Eighth Army
                    commander who did all the liaison with the embassy and the Korean government. I
                    did keep contact with some of the younger officers that we had known,
                    particularly on the East Coast of Korea in the Korean War in 1950-51. They had
                    risen to high positions, including the defense minister.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's move on to the deputy chairman of the NATO Military
                        Committee in 1971 to 1973. What was your impression about the capabilities
                        of the French and the Germans and the Italians and the British?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: We had very high respect for the Germans as a military force, which we
                    felt was superbly trained and entirely reliable. We had close relations with our
                    British allies who were having economic troubles back home, and we always felt
                    they were doing the very best they could with the limited resources they had.
                    The French, we felt, would come back into NATO if there was a real attack, and
                    would reopen the line of communications back to the Atlantic. This would be
                    better than turning the line of communications north to the Baltic. We felt the
                    Italians would do a credible job but had limited resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the perennial Greek-Turkish problems affect you at
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROWNY: There were always problems occurring at the political level. My boss,
                    General Steinhof, chairman of the NATO Military Committee, made great efforts to
                    smooth relations at the military level between the Greeks and the Turks. He was
                    very successful at building mutual respect at the military level. It would never
                    happen at the political level. At the political meetings that I attended, there
                    was always animosity and almost open warfare between the Greeks and Turks.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Q: It's really sad that this continues. I think actually there have been real
                    efforts recently to do better but relations between the Greeks and the United
                    States aren't very good. You then became a representative of the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff to the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks from 1973 to 1979. What was the
                    thinking on the part of the Pentagon about nuclear war at this particular
                    time?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: The feeling was that we had to negotiate with the Soviets quite carefully.
                    We had to be careful because of their strong ground superiority. They were now
                    becoming superior in numbers of strategic weapons. As a result, we were quite
                    apprehensive. We always felt we would be able to absorb the first nuclear blow
                    and have enough weapons left to completely obliterate the Soviet Union. We were
                    quite confident that if they ever started a war we would be the ultimate
                    winners. Nevertheless, we didn't relish the idea of ever getting into a nuclear
                    war.</p>
                <p>I joined right after the SALT I and the ABM Treaty were signed. There was a great
                    deal of skepticism on the part of the chairman and the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                    about whether or not the Soviets would curtail their buildup. Their original
                    promise was that, if we signed the Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty, they would not
                    increase their forces over ours. That didn't happen. They built and built and
                    built until by the time SALT II was signed, they had twice our number of weapons
                    and about six times as much throw weight or total nuclear power. We thought this
                    might embolden them to feel they could make such a devastating attack on us that
                    we could not retaliate. We knew that that was not true because we always had the
                    submarines at sea. Even if they could neutralize our strategic bombers and our
                    Minute Men, the submarines would always save us. It was a tense time.</p>
                <p>Q: Around this time I heard about these irritants at the Pentagon who were
                    talking and saying, “If we lose 20 million or 40 million people and all this.”
                    As a military man dealing with this thing, did these people get in the way in
                    their theoretical basis, or were they helpful?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: I would say they were unhelpful because our feeling was that these
                    computations were not meaningful. If we lost a million or two at Washington and
                    New York, the question was, would we have the heart to continue to fight and
                    sacrifice even more people or would we sue for peace? Our thought was to try to
                    play down any of these calculations, “Well, we'll take 10 million casualties and
                    take 20 million casualties.” We all thought that was taking a negative approach.
                    Our objective was to be sure that a nuclear war would never occur. We could not
                    allow the Soviets to believe we would succumb to their threats without a fight
                    or, nor could we permit them to feel that in any situation they would employ
                    nuclear weapons. If it came to that, the game was over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your view of the Nixon-Kissinger approach to the
                        SALtalks in 1973?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>ROWNY: Kissinger was very much in charge, and we were disappointed that Nixon
                    didn't assert himself more strongly. Nixon was Kissinger's intellectual equal,
                    but he didn't harness or hold him in and allowed him to become both the Security
                    Advisor and the Secretary of State. We found that Kissinger was very much in
                    charge. Outwardly, when they went to meetings, Kissinger always deferred to
                    Nixon. For example, at Moscow summit meetings, Nixon was clearly in charge and
                    Kissinger never challenged him. However, back home we always felt that Kissinger
                    had the upper hand and dictated what was going on.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you concerned about Kissinger going for a treaty - this was before the
                    Ford Administration - rather than to be willing to walk away if we couldn't get
                    what we really needed?</p>
                <p>ROWNY: No, I didn't think Kissinger was trying to give away thstore, nor did
                    Nixon cave.</p>
                <p>Several months before Nixon resigned, there was a summit in Moscow, and the high-
                    level gossip was that Nixon might want to make a deal in order to save himself
                    from Watergate but that didn't happen. When the chips were down, Nixon didn't
                    give any indication that he was ready to succumb or give in.</p>
                <p>I think this is a pretty good time to stop. I'd like to have one more session,
                    and I'd like to pick it up talking about the arrival of the Carter
                    Administration and the SALT talks. On the SALT talks we need to talk about the
                    issues that particularly concerned you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
