<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000166">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ellsworth Bunker </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Service, Lyndon Baines Johnson
                    Library</p>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR ELLSWORTH BUNKER</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Michael L. Gillette, LBJ Library</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: December 9, 1980</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Let's start with your appointment, Ambassador Bunker. Do
                        you recall the circumstances under which you were chosen ambassador to
                        Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, I remember how it occurred. I had been asked by Secretary Dean Rusk
                    to go to Buenos Aires to head our mission to the OAS [Organization of American
                    States] meeting. He had to leave, asked me to come there and take his place. I
                    was then in Nepal. On the way back from Buenos Aires to Washington, I had a
                    message from him which I received in Sao Paulo saying he would like to see me on
                    my return. I got back on a Saturday, went to see him, and they said, “The
                    President is in Texas, but he would like to see you Tuesday morning on his
                    return. But I forewarn you, he wants you to go to Vietnam.”</p>
                <p>So I went to see the President on Tuesday morning, and he said he wanted me to go
                    to Vietnam. Well, I at first said, “Well, you know, Mr. President, you've just
                    appointed me ambassador-at-large and I was married last month in Kathmandu. I
                    really have to consult Carol [Laise].” He said, “That's right, you do. I'll give
                    you a plane. You go out to Kathmandu and consult Carol, and then meet me in
                    Guam.” He said, “I want you to go because it's the most important issue facing
                    us today in our foreign affairs. I think it's very important that you should go
                    out there and take over.” So I did go out. I cabled my wife that I would be
                    there probably for only a few days. And as I got off the plane she said, “Well,
                    I know the answer.”</p>
                <p>But the President said to me, “I'm going to give you a plane. I want you to go
                    see Carol every month.” I did get the plane, of course. I didn't get up every
                    month either. But when I couldn't go I would send the plane up to Kathmandu and
                    she would come to Saigon. It became a very popular flight because there were
                    extra seats—I think some thirty extra seats in the plane—and we had a long line
                    waiting for R-and-R in Kathmandu. So it was always full, whether I sent it up
                    for her or whether I went up myself. It was a feature that added greatly to my
                    satisfaction and situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I recall reading that Congressman H. R. Gross, who opposed
                        so many expenditures, opposed the use of that plane.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, he did I think, but he didn't get much support, fortunately from my
                    point of view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did President Johnson elaborate the reasons that he was
                        naming you or wanted you to go in particular? Did he enumerate the
                        particular talents that he hoped you would bring to the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, he did remark on my role in the Dominican Crisis and did say that
                    he admired the way I had handled the Dominican situation, and that we were
                    facing even tougher problems in Vietnam and he wanted me to go out there and see
                    what I could do with the situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any aspect of your job that he emphasized at
                        that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: My recollection is, and I have written to Walt Rostow also to see whether
                    my recollection is correct, because I saw the President alone. There was no note
                    taker there. I have no record; I made no record of our talks either when I came
                    away from it. My recollection is that the President emphasized the fact that he
                    wanted to see the training of the Vietnamese accelerated and speeded up to
                    enable us to more quickly turn the war over to them, which was our main
                    objective, of course, to enable the Vietnamese to defend themselves. As a matter
                    of fact, a month after I arrived General Creighton Abrams came out in May, 1967
                    as deputy to [General William] Westmoreland. About his chief function then when
                    he first came was to speed up the training of the Vietnamese armed forces. He
                    did a splendid job, of course, and succeeded Westmoreland and was outstanding as
                    commander there. So that—and I've asked Walt to check his
                    recollections—certainly was my objective when I went there, and I think that was
                    the beginning of what later was known as Vietnamization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there intended any departure from the procedures under
                        Ambassador [Henry Cabot] Lodge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I don't know, because I really don't know what the procedures
                    were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But did the President say, “I want you to do this
                        differently than Lodge?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, no. I don't recollect that he did that. But he did want me to arrive
                    as soon as Lodge left, which was quite unusual for a new ambassador to arrive
                    the day his predecessor left. Lodge left in the morning and I arrived in the
                    afternoon. Usually there's a gap of some weeks or even months. But the President
                    was very anxious apparently to see the post covered, so that I arranged to get
                    there just as Lodge almost stepped on the plane to take off.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any doubts in your own mind about accepting
                        this post, aside from the one that you've already mentioned, consulting your
                        wife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I realized it was going to be a difficult post, but my feeling was
                    that since the President had placed a great emphasis and importance on it, that
                    it was something that one had to undertake.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now given the broad authority of General Westmoreland, was
                        there any notion that possibly you might be in a secondary role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that spelled out in advance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, it was understood that the ambassador was in charge. I simply acted
                    on that premise. I never had any problem with Westmoreland or Abrams or anyone
                    else. Westmoreland and Abrams never took any major step without consulting me
                    first. I simply assumed that was the way it was going to be and proceeded on
                    that basis. And I must say I had splendid cooperation from both of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the Guam Conference. Do you recall
                        specifics of the President's activities there at Guam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, first you had a general review of the situation. Lodge summarized
                    the situation as he saw it from the political aspect; Westmoreland. the military
                    aspect. [Nguyen Van] Thieu and [Nguyen Cao] Ky were both there: both spoke, Ky
                    at greater length than Thieu because Ky was acting as prime minister. Thieu was
                    head of the council then and Ky was the more active and more articulate in some
                    ways. But they both gave a report from their own view of it, aspect of it. The
                    atmosphere I would say was generally rather upbeat. There were reports of
                    progress both from our people, from Lodge, Westmoreland and also from the
                    Vietnamese, so that my reaction to the Guam Conference was that the feeling in
                    Vietnam was fairly optimistic as to the progress that had already been
                    achieved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this your first meeting with Thieu and Ky?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, the first time I had seen them.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your first impressions of them, do you
                        recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Thieu was quite reserved, I felt, rather enigmatic, rather more difficult
                    perhaps to get at, to get to. Ky was more articulate, rather flamboyant, and
                    much more voluble. But Thieu had a certain solidity about him which I think Ky
                    lacked. Ky gave the impression of being, I say, more flamboyant, more
                    articulate, but not as profound as Thieu, as deep.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the President seem to have a greater rapport with one
                        as opposed to the other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't think so. I don't recollect that he did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand from the messages that there was some problem
                        or some pledge that Thieu and Ky gave to President Johnson that you would
                        later remind them of again and again. Do you recall the circumstances of
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't specifically recall that. Well, one thing that I did—and this may
                    be it-was to impress on them fairly continuously the importance of their working
                    together and in harmony, not only at the time of the council but after the
                    elections, also in 1967 where Ky became vice president and took a secondary
                    role. You see, there was considerable rivalry between Thieu and Ky for the top
                    spot. There was even a threat that this might divide the military, and I
                    remember calling in the military and making it very clear to them that we
                    couldn't go along with any division in military ranks at the time of war, that
                    they would have to come to some decision themselves. I wasn't going to tell them
                    what it ought to be, but nevertheless they'd have to come to a decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On one candidate or the other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: On one candidate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a decision that was reached at the level of Ky and
                        Thieu or was it something that their principal military backers decided on,
                        do you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, it came about through a meeting of the military council at which
                    both Thieu and Ky were present, is my recollection. Ky finally agreed that he
                    would accept the vice presidential spot.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to ask a lot of questions on that, but before we
                        get there I want to ask one more on the Guam Conference, and that is, what
                        was the primary purpose of that conference, do you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I think the primary purpose was to review the situation as it
                    stood, to get some feeling for what was possible, not only from the military
                    point of view, but the political point of view. the development of democratic
                    institutions and how rapidly that might progress. The question came up about the
                    elections which took place in September—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Third, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: 1967, and the preparations for that, for the drafting of a constitution.
                    and the more or less tentative timetable worked out for that. Then one other
                    decision that came out of the Guam Conference was to put the pacification
                    program under Westmoreland. And Bob Komer was appointed to head up the
                    pacification program under Westmoreland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a decision that President Johnson made? Do you
                        recall the process here?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't think so. I don't think he made it himself, but he agreed to
                    it. I think it was suggested because the pacification program required a
                    preponderance of military personnel out in the provinces. Numerically I think
                    the military outnumbered the civilians about three to one, about that.
                    Therefore, it seemed logical to put it under Westmoreland with a civilian
                    head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [William] Porter I suppose had resisted previous attempts
                        to do this, and his argument had been that the soldiers would not give a top
                        priority to community development projects. Do you recall the rebuttal to
                        this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't recall that. As a matter of fact, at Guam I had not been
                    aware of Porter's opposition to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a belief at Guam that pacification was not
                        working properly? That it needed to be overhauled?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I think there was a feeling that it needed to be invigorated and
                    speeded up, and that more emphasis should be put on it. That it was an essential
                    part of our whole program.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My notes indicate that the conference in Guam ended on
                        March 22 and you arrived in Saigon on April 25, so I've got a month here
                        that I can't account for. Do you recall the circumstances of the intervening
                        month?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, you say the Guam Conference ended when?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: March 22.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. And I arrived... right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go back to Kathmandu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I went back to Kathmandu, but I'm trying to think whether I went first to
                    Washington and then Kathmandu. But I did have some time in Kathmandu, to give
                    Lodge time to arrange for his departure and say his farewells and so forth. So
                    that I waited there in Kathmandu and when I got word about Lodge's departure
                    time, then I arranged my arrival time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have an opportunity at some point, either at Guam
                        or in the intervening month, to get Lodge's impressions of the situation
                        there in Saigon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. I never saw Lodge from the time I left Guam, and of course didn't see
                    him when he departed. So the last talk I had with him was in Guam itself, and
                    there of course we had a chance to talk. Lodge, I'm not certain, but I have the
                    impression that he rather felt that Ky was the more dynamic of the two. I
                    remember his saying that Ky was a learner, could grasp things. But as the
                    situation turned out, I think that Thieu was the abler in most ways.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you your first impressions of the mission in
                        Saigon? I suppose the new Chancellery was under construction by this
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: It was under construction. I opened it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It opened the following month I gather. No, it would be in
                        the fall I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I arrived in the spring. I think it was in the fall, yes. Yes. we were in
                    the old building when I first went there.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The embassy personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Embassy personnel, yes. I think was very good. First-rate. In fact in
                    recalling my talk with the President when he asked me to go out there. He said,
                    'You can have anybody you want. If there's anybody there that you don't want,
                    he'll be on his way home in twenty-four hours.” I think in the whole six years I
                    was there I only asked for one change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall that one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I've forgotten who it was now. I think it was our economic counselor at
                    the time that I thought wasn't quite up to the job. But by and large we had a
                    first-rate embassy. This was especially true of the younger people in the
                    Foreign Service who were out there and out in the provinces, out on their own,
                    of course in very hazardous posts, and did a magnificent job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Bob Komer coming out to work on
                        pacification. Was this part of your decision or was he already scheduled to
                        go out there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. He was scheduled to go out, yes. And Bob was a very able fellow, but
                    not always easy to control, I remember shortly after he got out there he sent
                    through the back channel a message recommending that the head of our AID program
                    be changed, without saying anything to me about it. I found out about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you become aware of this, do you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, what I did was, I had all the back channel messages come to me. Bob
                    found out this, discovered this, and said, “I understand that all the back
                    channel messages are routed through you.” I said. “That's correct, Bob.” I never
                    had any more trouble with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Barry Zorthian and Edward Lansdale apparently were
                        scheduled to leave Vietnam, but it was decided that they would stay after
                        your arrival. Do you recall that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, they did stay for a period, yes. And they were both very useful.
                    very able.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about Ambassador [Eugene] Locke, what was his role
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: He was my deputy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you delegate a certain area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes, I delegated particularly pacification to Locke. But he didn't
                    stay very long, as you recall. He came out with me. He left I think in January,
                    1968 to go back to Texas to run for governor. So that he left I think in
                    January.</p>
                <p>Ambassador [Samuel] Berger didn't get out there until March, so there was that
                    interim period which included Tet when I didn't have a deputy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the fact that Ambassador Locke was an old acquaintance
                        of President Johnson cause any chain of commands problem at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the atmosphere in Saigon at the time
                        you took over. How would you describe the city and the mentality of the city
                        in the spring and summer of 1967?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I think the city was quiet when I got there. People were going about
                    their business. There was not an air of great apprehension. I think people were
                    confident that progress was being made. The city gave the appearance of going
                    about its business. And of course it was Tet which upset that whole situation
                    there. But I think there was some feeling of euphoria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Others have given the impression of Saigon as being sort
                        of very removed from the war and very different from the provinces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I think that's true in certain ways, until Tet came along when that
                    changed rather rapidly. But I think that was true at the time I arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about U.S.-Vietnamese relations. I gather that
                        one of your principal functions as ambassador was to deal with Thieu and Ky
                        and to apprise them of our positions, to use, as Bob Komer would say,
                        leverage on them to get them to do the things that we hoped they would do
                        and things of this nature. Would that have constituted a major part of your
                        role there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather at the time of your arrival there was a
                        considerable conflict between them.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>BUNKER: There was rivalry between them. Certainly rivalry, particularly until the
                    decision was made as to the ticket for the elections in September.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any one individual who was the key to this
                        decision?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not one military man on the council?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you yourself favor Thieu over Ky?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I did, yes. Yes, I was pleased when they finally did decide on Thieu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this primarily based on the difference between the two
                        men or was this at all relating to different policies that one might
                        espouse?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Not different policies, but the difference between the two individuals. I
                    thought Thieu was a wiser, more solid person. Ky was too unpredictable, too
                    emotional, too flamboyant. Thieu more solid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you use your influence before the unified military
                        ticket, before they resolved the two candidacies? Ky was censoring some of
                        Thieu's campaign statements and General [Nguyen Ngoc] Loan apparently was
                        using some public officials and one thing and another. I gather you may have
                        used some influence to get them to control some of the political activities
                        that you regarded as excessive. Do you recall that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, yes. Loan, this chief of police, was a very difficult—well, I had
                    little use for him. I made it very clear to Ky and Thieu that I didn't think he
                    was the right person in that job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he stayed for a good while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: He stayed for quite a while.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he primarily a Ky supporter rather than Thieu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Yes, he was. No, he was bad medicine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you exert any other influence on Ky before he agreed
                        to assume the vice presidential position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I didn't. No, I didn't exert any influence on either one of them. I
                    simply said to them and to the military, General Cao Van Vien, who was chairman
                    of the joint chiefs, and two or three others whom I called in. I said, “I'm not
                    interfering in this, but you've got to make up your minds. There can't be a
                    division at a time of war among the military. It's not possible.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you fear that it would go beyond a political division,
                        that it might also involve a coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Not necessarily a coup but I just thought it would divide the military
                    into Factions which was not acceptable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why do you think Ky agreed to step aside?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yell. I think that Thieu had the larger measure of support from the
                    military actually.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was some notion at first that Thieu would actually
                        be merely a figurehead and Ky would have the authority to name the cabinet
                        and to head the armed services. Do you recall the dispute over a formula of
                        who would actually do what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. As far as I can remember, I don't think Ky had any veto over
                    individuals. I don't recollect any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the civilian candidates, the others.
                        There was quite an array. Was it important to the U.S. and to public opinion
                        to keep those candidates in the race?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I think it was important, yes. Because I think it was a demonstration
                    that the elections were free, as they were. Thieu and Ky were elected with a
                    plurality, not with a majority. I think they got about 35 per cent of the vote.
                    As it turned out, it was of course a more democratic election than the one in
                    1971 where there was no opposition. If the civilian candidates could have agreed
                    on one they might have given Thieu and Ky a good run.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any civilian candidate that we favored
                        informally as an alternative?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would it be fair to say that we expected and hoped the
                        Thieu-Ky ticket to win?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, I think so. I think it's fair to say that we thought that would be
                    the most effective in carrying on the war and carrying the country along.
                    Because there are too many factions among the civilians, as evidence by the fact
                    that there were eleven civilian tickets I think. So that it was very difficult
                    to find a civilian who could bring the country together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather they were united only in their opposition to
                        Thieu and Ky.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: That's right. Yes, sure. And of course all those countries are more
                    accustomed to authoritarian rule than we are. I mean, after all, they adopted
                    our presidential system. As one senator said, “We've got a democratic system now
                    though we have a history of four thousand years with no tradition in it of that
                    kind.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the election a maturing experience for them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, I think it was, yes. Because it was carried out, I think, really
                    quite well. We had a great many observers there, as you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think that as the process continued during that
                        campaign that there was less censorship, more freedom of the press? Did you
                        see an emerging democracy in terms of the practices?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, there was more freedom, freedom of the press. One of the problems of
                    the whole war we had to contend with was the fact that there was no press
                    censorship, which raises the issue or the question whether a democracy can wage
                    war successfully without censorship and with the war now being shown on
                    television, which never happened before. This is the first time it happened, the
                    first time that the war came into everybody's living room. No question in my
                    mind that it had a very important effect on public opinion in this country,
                    whereas the other side didn't wage war under those handicaps. They had complete
                    censorship.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the prospect of “Big” Minh [General
                        Duong Van Minh] returning from Bangkok to run as a candidate. Do you recall
                        how this was prevented?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I should, but the details escape me at the moment. I must try to refresh
                    my memory on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall I think it's the Dongha incident where the
                        other candidates were assembled and supposedly prepared to debate and Thieu
                        did not join them? They all got mad about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, they got mad about it. I remember that, too. Yes. But I do remember
                    they got mad about it. My recollection is, too, that I've forgotten now why
                    Thieu and Ky didn't show up. I think it's because they didn't want to give
                    importance to the other side, lend that much credibility to their opponents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you urge Thieu to appear with the other
                        candidates?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Subsequently I did. I told him I thought ....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on the campaign that you feel is
                        important?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't think so. I think I did report this to the President in one
                    of my messages. We did have a chance to observe the elections over a wide area
                    of the country, and the reports from the observers came in that they were fairly
                    conducted, without pressure, and with everybody given a chance to vote, and that
                    we were really quite pleased with the way the government had organized the
                    elections and carried them out. I guess [Hubert] Humphrey came out for the
                    inauguration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In one of these wires you referred to your persistent
                        persuasion and patient prodding. Can you recall any particular examples of
                        using your influence to get Thieu and Ky to adopt a policy during the
                        campaign that has more in keeping with public opinion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: During the campaign?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I can't recollect any particular instance.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a crisis I suppose at the end when the national
                        assembly appeared to want to invalidate the election. Do you recall this
                        crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I do recall the crisis, but I don't recall the circumstances
                    particularly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I gather some of these assemblymen were defeated
                        senate candidates.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, that's right, some of them were defeated and wanted to—because of
                    that reason, I think, but I just don't recollect the details.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could it be that some of them were also Ky partisans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Might have been so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But I think the record indicates that you met with a group
                        of them and brought them to a different frame of mind.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, but I don't recollect what the reason for the... I think it was
                    because, as you say, some of them were defeated. It's hard for an Oriental to
                    accept loss of face.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In addition to the observers, did the embassy make any
                        other efforts to ensure an acceptable level of honesty and voter
                        participation in the elections?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, we made it very clear to the government, Thieu and Ky and the rest
                    of them, that we placed great importance on fair elections and that there should
                    be no coercion or attempts of coercion of the voters. I made it very clear to
                    both of them that the question of support. Degree of support they would receive
                    from here would depend very largely on how the elections were carried out and
                    how they were seen here and not only seen here and reported by the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your pressures, do you think, generate
                        anti-Americanism?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I don't think so really. Maybe at times. Well, there were times, of
                    course, later on when they generated anti-Americanism, when I tried to get them
                    to go to Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was President Johnson's reaction to the election, do
                        you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I think he was very pleased, of course, with the way it was carried
                    out, and I think he expected certainly that the military would be returned to
                    power and probably felt that that was the best thing for the country, given the
                    situation that existed at the time. And he was concerned that the election
                    should be seen here as being open and free.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand that there was an invitation to the UN to
                        send observers as well. Do you recall your role in that invitation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't recall specifically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now General Loan arrested a former economics minister, [Au
                        Troung] Thanh. Do you recall that incident?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't recall that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have a note here that you filed a stiff protest after
                        that happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I probably did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a problem of regionalism that affected the
                        government in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, regionalism in the sense that you had, for example, the Cao Dai
                    religious sect, which is very strong in the South, very anti-communist and
                    therefore pro-government. There's still also an element which was rather
                    insistent on its prerogatives as such. and of course there were the Buddhists
                    and what we call the radical Buddhists. who were often anti-government. And
                    there was the Catholic element, which had come from the North, which was a minor
                    but substantial element in the country, Thieu himself being a Catholic. So that
                    you had this sense of rivalry between the Catholics, the Buddhists, the other
                    elements like the Cao Dai. On the other hand, while that led to rivalries
                    domestically, politically, still they were united I think in their opposition to
                    the communists. So it was an element that could and did occasionally cause some
                    disturbance, unsettlement. Before I got there they had the Buddhist uprising in
                    the North, you know, at Danang.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems that the Buddhists were never really brought into
                        the process, that they were always a force of resistance.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, particularly what was known as the An Quang Buddhists, the more
                    radical element. There was another element which was much more cooperative with
                    the government, but it was the An Quang Buddhist faction that got the publicity,
                    of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you yourself have any formula for muting their
                        opposition?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. I didn't have any formula. I can't say that I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In retrospect, as you look back, could anything have been
                        done to further unify the country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't know. The Thieu-Ky rivalry was at times unsettling and it's
                    something that I kept working on constantly, pointing out to both of them it was
                    absolutely essential that they work together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How responsive were they overall in these meetings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: They were responsive in the meetings, but they didn't always follow
                    through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did persistence help here? Were you eventually able to
                        bring them around in some cases?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Yes. I think so, until the elections of 1971, and then they had the
                    split between Thieu and Ky. But then Ky pulled out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of your advice to Thieu seems to have been more along
                        the lines of political advice: to get out more among the people, to use
                        television, to become essentially a more aggressive leader in attempting to
                        unify the people. Can you elaborate on this sort of advice and the success
                        of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, Thieu, as a military man and being himself rather austere, and I
                    think because of perhaps the secretive characteristics about him, was not used
                    to using the press, the television. He was used to command as a military man,
                    not used to persuasion, to giving orders but not used to persuasion. And he had
                    to go through really an educational process. This is what I was trying to help
                    him with and urging him to do, to expose himself more to the people. And he did
                    progress a great deal I think. I went with him on a good many trips where he did
                    get out among the people and talk to them, and I think improved very much in the
                    course of time on his public relations aspect.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think he ever achieved the status in the minds of
                        the Vietnamese as a national leader?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I think he did, but not necessarily—as a leader, but not as a national
                    hero.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there anyone in South Vietnam at the time that you
                        felt would have been the natural leader to unify the country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. No, I didn't see anyone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about some more of your pressures. One,
                        dismissing corrupt officials. I gather this was something else you were very
                        interested in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How far did you get with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, we made some progress with it. Thieu did replace quite a number of
                    province chiefs who were guilty of corruption. Some of the military were, some
                    not. One of the problems we had occasionally was with the military wives, the
                    wives engaged in corruption instead of their husbands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now another thing I understand that you were interested in
                        was the~ matter of higher military and civilian pay scales. Do you recall
                        your efforts there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Yes, I know I did try. I did urge Thieu to improve their pay scales,
                    because they really were getting very poorly paid, which as I said to him, leads
                    to corruption. The attitude in the Orient towards corruption is somewhat
                    different than it is here. In most of those countries there are no social
                    security laws. The extended family, the family is the social security unit, and
                    your first duty is to take care of your family, provide for your family. If you
                    do engage or feel that you have to engage in corruption in order to do that,
                    there are extenuating circumstances which you don't have here in the Western
                    civilization. So people look at it with more tolerance as being done to take
                    care of the family situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the salaries increased?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Yes, they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did the government have the funds to do this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Well, we of course were giving economic support to the government
                    right along, but also the country was making progress economically in spite of
                    the war, particularly in the later years of the war when I was there, not only
                    in the industrial sector, but particularly in the agricultural sector where
                    farmers were really more prosperous than they'd ever been. I can remember going
                    down to the Delta, which is the great agricultural area there, and seeing
                    farmers who used to ride bicycles riding motorcycles, and seeing television
                    aerials or radio aerials in houses. And they were buying tractors, sometimes
                    pooling on their tractors, but getting into machinery operations. There was a
                    very large land distribution program effected, which became effective in 1970,
                    1972.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have a policy of advocating land reform?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know President Johnson was interested in that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes. He did have a very great interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How effective were you at advancing that policy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I think we were quite effective in advancing it and had good cooperation
                    from Thieu and the government. They did a very substantial, really very
                    creditable piece of work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you also favor giving more authority to the province
                        chiefs rather than the military commanders? Do you recall this
                        question?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Well. we recommended or advocated more authority to the Province chiefs
                    because their concern was with the local government rather than with the
                    military effort, except from the point of view of the village and hamlet
                    security aspect. But they were closer to the people than the military were and
                    were permanently stationed in the provinces. Consequently they had a greater
                    interest in the progress of their own provinces, an interest, of course, in
                    security, too, but also in the economic situation and the political situation.
                    So that we felt that if people had problems or grievances or things of that
                    kind, that the province chief was the more suitable person to whom they could
                    address themselves and look for relief or redress or whatever it might be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The question of prisoners of war and repatriation of
                        prisoners, were there questions here that were addressed to the Thieu
                        Administrations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I'm not quite clear on your question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, for example, did our concern over the safety of our
                        POWs in North Vietnam cause us to advance a particular policy of how Viet
                        Cong prisoners should be treated or repatriation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. We were, of course, interested in seeing that these prisoners, our
                    prisoners, were treated according to the rules of warfare and that they were
                    properly treated, and saw to it. And I think they were. The Con Son Island
                    incident, where there was a great fuss about—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, the tiger cages?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Tiger cages, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever attempt to improve the conditions of Viet
                        Cong prisoners or to step up repatriation in order to aid our own prisoners
                        of war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I'd have to refresh my memory on what we did on repatriation, I just
                    don't recall at this point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cambodia must have presented a dilemma at this point. It
                        was clear that the enemy was using Cambodia as a sanctuary.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, absolutely. In fact, I sent a message back in June—June 9, June 19,
                    I've forgotten the exact date—recommending that we go into Laos and cut the
                    trail on the ground, that the war was kept alive, of course, in the South by the
                    infiltration of men and supplies and materiel and equipment, reasoning that if
                    we could cut the trail that the Viet Cong in the South would wither on the vine.
                    Well, obviously I was turned down; they never did it, on several grounds. One,
                    it would be a violation of the Laotian treaty of 1962 to which we were
                    signatories. My response to that was that it was quite true it would be a
                    violation, but the other side violated it from the day they signed it, and the
                    Laotians would be delighted to have us go in.</p>
                <p>Secondly, it would take two or three more divisions, which again was true, but we
                    put in that many more before we got through.</p>
                <p>The third point was that there was fear it might provoke the Chinese. but my
                    observation on that was that while we have no relations with the Chinese, had
                    none, our friends did. The British had embassies in Peking, the French, Dutch,
                    and we could make it very clear to the Chinese we had no designs on China or on
                    North Vietnam. North Vietnamese could have any kind of government they wanted as
                    far as we were concerned, but they weren't going to take over the South.</p>
                <p>Well, we didn't do it. If we had done it, of course it would have helped to close
                    sanctuaries, not only in Laos but in Cambodia, too. But we didn't do it, and
                    then finally did go into Cambodia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course you had a problem with Prince [Norodom]
                        Sihanouk, I suppose.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, Sihanouk tacitly let it be understood that as long as we didn't
                    bomb civilian areas and kept our bombing to the sanctuaries that he didn't
                    really object to it, although he wasn't going to say so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you understood that this was his position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There seems to have been some rivalry between South
                        Vietnam and Cambodia here. One example, the halting of shipping on the
                        Mekong River that impaired the Cambodian economy. Do you recall your efforts
                        to free up the shipping on the Mekong River, keep Sihanouk in a friendlier
                        posture?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BUNKER: I'm not very clear on it. I think we did, and did arrange to let shipping
                    go up the Mekong. It's my recollection it went up pretty freely, even though the
                    other side were bringing in supplies through Sihanoukville and bringing them up
                    into the sanctuaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the post-election situation. Was
                        there an effort made to broaden the base of the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, yes, I think there was. I think in the appointments to the cabinet,
                    and Thieu did make several changes as time went on. I'll have to look. I'm
                    certain I reported that in my messages, but I'd have to check it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this period, before Tet and after the inauguration,
                        were there overtures made to the other side to discuss settlement terms or
                        cease-fires or peace conferences?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: 1967. When was the San Antonio formula, which has been referred to in
                    some of these?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have September 29, 1967 on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: September 29. The President made a proposal there. I've forgotten just
                    what the terms were. September, 1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe there was a normal flow of men and materiel
                        continuing from the North during the bombing pause, but no stepped up
                        activity. Wasn't it something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, I must look it up to refresh my memory on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For example, didn't President Thieu write a letter to Ho
                        Chi Minh?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: He did write a letter. The question came up of how it was to be
                    delivered, I remember. I'm not sure whether we ever reached a solution, or that
                    he ever did, on the ways to get it to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather there was some consideration of having the Pope
                        deliver it, and even some speculation that perhaps President Johnson in his
                        visit had taken the letter with him to Rome when he saw the Pope at
                        Christmas?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, but my recollection is that it never was worked out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems a shame that there's no basis for communication.
                        Another intriguing event was the Buttercup affair, where an NLF emissary
                        supposedly was on his way to meet with you and was arrested. Do you recall
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I recall it, yes, but I don't recall the details.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was some speculation that this was merely a hoax on
                        the Viet Cong's part.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I must really refresh myself on that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But do you yourself recall any talks, informal talks, that
                        you had with emissaries of the other side on the basis of settlements or
                        ceasefires?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. No, I never had any talks. No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there neutralists that you could talk with that could
                        get word indirectly to the other side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Not that I could talk with, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about foreign nationals, say British or French or
                        other individuals that had contacts with North Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, we never made any approach to the North Vietnamese through other
                    nationals in South Vietnam. Now, anything of that sort was done in Washington,
                    but outside of Vietnam itself. I never got involved in any negotiating proposals
                    or peace proposals in Vietnam with other nationals, or with emissaries from the
                    other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on the negotiations before Tet?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>BUNKER: No, no. I don't recall anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about pacification. How would you define
                        the pacification program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, the pacification program had two sides at least to it. One was the
                    question of the hamlet and village security. That was the primary objective. The
                    second objective, also equally important, was the economic aspect. And third,
                    the political. So that pacification was, you see, a well-rounded program in
                    which the rural self-defense forces were involved, training civilians in
                    defense. Economic development was equally important. And you remember the
                    village elections, council elections, were held all over the country also
                    beginning in 1967. So that it was the development of a conscious part in the
                    government of the people at the local level that really was involved in the
                    pacification program, self-help program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about the CORDS program, Civil Operations
                        and Revolutionary Development Support, as part of pacification. Do you
                        recall that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Oh, yes, very well. That was the principal part of pacification as
                    far as Komer was concerned and his duties. That was really a very essential part
                    of our whole program in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What specifically did this involve?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Self-government at the local level. Revolutionary development is really a
                    misnomer; rural development would be the better name for it. We called it
                    revolutionary development, but I think we got changing it as it went along. We
                    called it revolutionary development because in the beginning it was developing
                    local political self-consciousness and self-government at the local level. But
                    the reason I say it was rural development in this other sense was it involved
                    agriculture, too, fisheries, agriculture, all of the economic activities
                    involved at the village level, at the local level. So that it was a
                    comprehensive program and a very important one.</p>
                <p>It involved, as I say, security first, the training of the local citizenry. One
                    indication of the confidence the government had in support of the citizenry was
                    the fact that they distributed, if I remember correctly, six hundred thousand
                    weapons at large in the countryside. Well, if you felt uncertain about the
                    loyalty of the people, you wouldn't give them arms they could use against you. I
                    mean, I think it was a mark of confidence by the government that they had the
                    support of the citizenry. Anyhow, that was an important part. Training both men
                    and women, too, in this hamlet and village self-defense.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feedback on the extent or evaluation to
                        determine if, in fact, the arms were falling into friendly hands rather than
                        potential Viet Cong?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes. Oh, yes. Except where the Viet Cong could come in and capture
                    them, we never had any indication they were ever turned over to the Viet
                    Cong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the Phoenix program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: The Phoenix program, I think, was an important program in unearthing the
                    underground. It was criticized, I know here, saying it was an assassination
                    program. It was not an assassination program. People were killed when they
                    resisted arrest, yes, of course. But the great majority of those people were
                    imprisoned and were not executed. There were casualties, of course, because
                    there was resistance, but it was an important program. You see, what happened at
                    Tet was because Tet was a military defeat, a very significant military defeat
                    for the other side, but a psychological victory for them here in the United
                    States because of the press reaction and the way it was reported. And that I
                    think is brought out by Peter Braestrup in his books. But what happened was that
                    the communist side was so confident that the Viet Cong surfaced for the first
                    time. The underground all came up and were identified, many of them killed. I
                    mean, they virtually suffered such severe losses at Tet they never recovered
                    from it. But it made them more vulnerable. More identifiable, and hence the
                    Phoenix program became more effective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it tied into the Chieu Hoi program at all, the
                        returnee program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Well, yes it was, where ralliers would come in. In my earlier
                    messages to the President, I think every week I reported about the Chieu
                    Hoi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think that these people who came over and were
                        evidently reimbursed for doing so and joining the South Vietnamese army, do
                        you think they ever slipped back into the jungles and rejoined the Viet
                        Cong?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Not many so. Maybe a few, but not many.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really? Our intelligence indicated that—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: That's right, they didn't go back.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you talk to many of these people and determine why
                        they were changing sides?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I never talked to them personally, no. Our people did, of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, lots of stories came in about the hardships and the
                        North and the difficulty there, and the hardships of fighting in the South,
                        this kind of warfare they were carrying on. Most of these Chieu Hoi people
                        were guerrillas you know, not many of them were the regular military who
                        were living hand-to-mouth and fighting in the jungles. What was Edward
                        Lansdale's role in the pacification program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, principally as an adviser, based on his long experience there in
                    that part of the world: principally as an adviser on the local scene—which he
                    knew. I suppose, perhaps better than most of us, most of the people who were
                    there: he'd been there longer—aha, I think the native culture, psychology, so
                    forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he controversial in official circles?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Not with me or there at the time. I think he had been at some time. But I
                    had no problem with him. I thought he was quite effective really.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he critical at all of pacification, the implementation
                        of it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't think he was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather this was one of the ARVN's weakest areas,
                        pacification.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, it may have been. Yes, I suppose perhaps so. They were more
                    concerned really about fighting the war and the enemy. However, I think they
                    cooperated pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: William Corson, who was over there, made the criticism
                        that the pacification project should not have to be cleared through the
                        Vietnamese officials. Do you recall this issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Corson? Now, when was this, do you remember?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have been, I think, in the 1967-68 period.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't even remember, was Corson stationed there?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was with the marines. He was a ....</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes, marines. In the North. That's interesting, shouldn't have to be
                    cleared with the Vietnamese? I'd forgotten that. That's interesting. Do you
                    remember how that came out?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He wrote a book called The Betrayal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: That's right, that's right. I haven't read it. Have you read it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. I have some notes on it here though.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: What was the thrust of it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I'm not going to elaborate, since I haven't read it,
                        but I gather he was critical of Komer's performance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Komer's handling of it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also another issue that seems to have been raised was the
                        method of evaluation of various hamlets.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Hamlet evaluation security, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The A-B-C-D rating system..</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: A-B-C-D, yes. A-B-C-D and the communists. Yes, well, like all evaluations
                    it's inexact, of course. It's an approximation, really. But it was an
                    approximation and gave a pretty good idea, I think, of the general situation. I
                    say, like all evaluations based on judgments, it was not exact, but it did by
                    1972, end of 1972, you could travel anywhere in the country you wanted to go
                    without any security protection or anything at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The press argued at the time that the C category, which
                        was the designation of hamlets under government control, were really sort of
                        a toss-up and would thereby in the evaluation total reduce the government
                        control to less than 50 per cent of the population.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, depending on, I think, what year you took the evaluation, because
                    the situation kept changing steadily for the better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a direct result of pacification, do you think,
                        rather than just military advances?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: It was a combination of both. No question, a combination of both. The
                    military situation improved and the pacification situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did we learn from that pacification experience that
                        you would apply in other situations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I think we did learn the importance of getting the local population
                    people involved in their own situation, not only their own protection, their own
                    economic development, their own political development. This was the whole thrust
                    of the pacification program. It was government at the local level involving
                    defense, involving the political situation, involving the local councils, hamlet
                    chiefs, and the local economic development programs. So it was a rounded
                    approach. I think it applies not only to Vietnam but to other situations in the
                    less developed world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It seems that apathy was a great problem, that so many of
                        the Vietnamese people were not interested in the Viet Cong or the other
                        side, but on the other hand they seemed apathetic about the Thieu-Ky
                        government.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: A great bulk would prefer to be left alone, obviously. I mean, prefer not
                    to be involved in the war on one side or the other. But I think this is true
                    anywhere in the world you go. I mean, many of them just wished the war would go
                    away. Sure, no question.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another area that you seemed to have some concerns about
                        was intelligence. In fact in November, 1967, when you came back to the White
                        House and met with President Johnson, I gather that there were some
                        proposals to revamp our intelligence system to get better intelligence.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. I don't remember the specifics of that particular talk at the White
                    House, but certainly the intelligence was a matter of concern, a matter of great
                    concern to us. The question of attempting to improve the intelligence was also a
                    matter of concern. Now, I felt that the agency, the CIA there was well run. We
                    had good people, I thought, there. Ted Shackley, for example, was first-rate.
                    His successor who was there a briefer time, Lou Lapham was good. Tom Polgar was
                    the last one. He was only there about—well, he stayed on with [Ambassador
                    Graham] Martin, but only the last year I was there. They were all, I thought,
                    good, able. I thought they were doing a pretty good job for us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about military intelligence? Did you feel that you
                        were getting adequate military intelligence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I wasn't so sure about the military intelligence. Of course, I had
                    a briefing every week from the military, a general roundup, of the situation
                    each week. But it was more difficult for me to judge about the quality of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Enemy troop levels. There have been indications, or
                        certainly at least contentions, that we drastically underestimated the size
                        of the enemy force in the field.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't know. I don't know about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall this being a source of concern at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No, I don't, really. Where did that develop, do you remember? Estimates
                    of enemy force level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about some of the visitors that you had out
                        there. I gather there was almost a constant flow of congressional and
                        diplomatic visitors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, absolutely. I think the Christmas-New Year's season, 1967-68. I've
                    forgotten how many congressmen, senators I had. I think I remember a hundred and
                    forty-six or something like that, fantastic. Just descended on us in swarms.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any sort of official policy of how you treated
                        these people and what sort of procedures to follow with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, well, in this sense, that they all got briefings, of course, from
                    the military aspect and also from us on the political aspect, the economic
                    situation. And where they expressed a wish to do so, we would take them out into
                    the country in areas we thought it was safe for them to go. I remember Senator
                    [Charles] Percy and his wife came out. I think he got out in a place where he
                    got pretty close to getting under fire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand that he injured his hand or something when he
                        jumped for cover.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Something like that, yes. But we had some amusing experiences, too, I
                    remember. The first helicopter ride I ever took in Vietnam, I had a forced
                    landing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Crash landing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes. Have I described that to you?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Please do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: General [Bruce] Palmer was out there as deputy to Westmoreland, and he
                    was out at Bien Hoa base. He had been with me in the Dominican situation, where
                    he was deputy commander to the Brazilians. I was going out to see him and we
                    were flying along over the highway, and we started to come down. I looked out
                    and I didn't see anything that looked like the base, and I thought maybe we were
                    going to be met by a jeep or something. Well, then the traffic began to swerve
                    off. And we came down and we skidded along. I got out of the chopper, thanked
                    the pilot. He said. “Oh, we're not there yet. We've had a forced landing; I had
                    to come down. My power shut off. Fortunately we were over fifteen hundred feet,
                    or we couldn't have made it.” Well, it was a very amusing incident in a way, but
                    what happened was there was a photographer aboard. He got the strap of his
                    camera afoul of the fuel valve, shut off the fuel. We came down and we were
                    rescued by the Jolly Green Giant. [HH-53, special operations helicopter].</p>
                <p>So I was quite amused by it. I described this to General Palmer. He said,
                    “Anyhow, another chopper should have been following you anyway. Somebody will
                    catch hell for that.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any other close calls while you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes. Tet. We were under fire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we'll deal with that in detail. But in your travels
                        around the country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No. At the same time I went out to the First Division fire base. The
                    commander there asked me if I'd like to go around the base. I said, “Yes, I
                    would.” So he assigned an officer to take me out, show me the base. He took me
                    around outside the base. So I came back and he said, “Where did he take you?” I
                    said, “He took me around outside of the base.” He said, “Well, we're supposed to
                    be protecting you, you're not supposed to be protecting us.” So I reported this
                    to Bruce Palmer. too. “Oh.” he said, “Somebody will catch hell for that.” I got
                    back. I thought it had been a very amusing day. I told Westmoreland about it.
                    And he said. “A lot of people have already caught hell.” (Laughter) But no,
                    except for Tet, I don't think there were any very close situations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did official visitors from Washington ever tend to want to
                        go beyond the areas that were safe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about George Romney's visit. This is the
                        one where he was brainwashed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, but I think that was before my time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He came back then I guess in December of 1967.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, he did come back in December. We didn't try to brainwash him then.
                    (Laughter) As I remember, his visit was a very brief one. It really didn't make
                    much of an impression on me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hubert Humphrey attended the inaugural ceremonies, I
                        believe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Yes, he did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you recall the occasion?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Oh, yes. He headed the delegation, our delegation. Hubert, as usual, got
                    along extremely well wherever he went. He was really great. But, as you know,
                    Hubert didn't have many terminal facilities, and I said to him, I'd like to have
                    him address the embassy staff. We had a very large embassy, you know, the
                    biggest in the world. I said, “Now, Hubert, they'll all be out in the compound
                    in the yard in the sun, and it's hot. So only talk ten or fifteen minutes.” He
                    said, “Oh, sure, Ellsworth, that's fine.” Well, Hubert made a rattling good
                    fifteen-minute speech. Then he made a second fifteen-minute speech. I thought,
                    well this is going to be all. Then he made a third fifteen-minute speech. I
                    think we timed him at fifty-two minutes. But he got a good hand, of course. Oh,
                    he was great.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he have any proposals or advice or any suggestions for
                        President Thieu that you recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I don't recall any in particular, but he got along very well with Thieu.
                    They were very appreciative of his coming out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the Maxwell Taylor-Clark Clifford mission in
                        July, 1967? Do you recall that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, that was to our allies, not to Vietnam. They went to our allies, I
                    think, in the interest of seeing whether they could get further troop
                    reinforcements. But they didn't come to Vietnam at that time. Clark Clifford
                    came out later after Tet in 1968 again and wanted to start withdrawing troops
                    then, and I objected to that because I thought it would have a very demoralizing
                    effect. And I was upheld. We subsequently met in Honolulu, and the President
                    agreed that we would not begin to pull out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else on visitors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: Well, I remember that Governor [Ronald] Reagan and his wife came out,
                    just what date I can't quite remember. He was a strong supporter of what we were
                    doing, and I was very happy to see them because he really backed us up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get many visitors who were opposed to the war or
                        opposed to the conduct of the war, the way it was being conducted?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>BUNKER: Some. Yes, we did. Well, Townsend Hoopes came out when he was Secretary
                    of the Air Force I think. He later became opposed to the war, as you know.
                    Congressman [Lester] Wolfe—in fact, I think Wolfe at one time said he thought I
                    ought to be recalled, if I'm not mistaken. We had a visit from Senator [Edward]
                    Kennedy, who was critical of the way we were handling the refugees, but
                    unfortunately came out to make a case. He had his mind made up when he came
                    apparently, because he avoided the embassy largely and brought some staff with
                    him. They went to a refugee camp which was being abandoned because we had built
                    a new one and a better one, but made their report based on what they'd seen at
                    the old one, which didn't go very well with me. I didn't feel it was really a
                    straightforward report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet with him while he was out there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: I saw him just briefly, that's all. He stayed away from us largely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the refugee situation some more. I gather
                        there were a tremendous number of displaced people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: There were, yes, a great many. If you add them all up, they weren't all
                    displaced at one time, but the total, I think, came to some five million. But
                    that was spread over a span of years; it didn't all happen at once. I mean, they
                    came out and went back again. But the point is that, as I guess Bob [Sir Robert]
                    Thompson put it, or someone, they voted with their feet. They never went over to
                    the other side. They always ran away from the other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there anything that could have been done in your
                        opinion to improve the refugee situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BUNKER: My feeling is, given the fact that the country was at war, given the fact
                    of limited resources, I think it was handled remarkably well. Obviously
                    hardships existed, but the fact is, as I say, nobody went over to the enemy.
                    They did vote with their feet, and went back as soon as they had a chance to go
                    back. Naturally they were attached to their own villages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I certainly do thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
