<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001541">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mr. Jose Perez "Pepe" Del Rio </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>Information Series</p>
                <p>JOSE PEREZ (PEPE) DEL RIO</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Cliff Groce</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 9, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 2009 ADST</p>
                <p>Editor's Note: Jose Perez (Pepe) Del Rio was for nearly 25 years the MC of VOA's
                    Spanish Version of the Breakfast show. In Spanish, it was “Buenos Dias,
                    America.” The interview presents a fascinating and often heart warming picture
                    of the mechanics of producing such a show, and the responses it can draw from
                    the listening audiences.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get to be a broadcaster for the Voice of
                        America in the first place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Del Rio Initially Resists Offer to Go to VOA</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: In 1960, in San Antonio, Texas, Pete Moraga and another guy whose name I
                    can't remember came on a recruiting trip, looking for American citizens with
                    radio experience. They listened to me on the radio, a local Spanish-language
                    station in San Antonio, and I was one of the guys that they approached. They
                    came to see me at KUKA, the radio station where I was working as program
                    director, and offered me a job with the Voice of America. Of course I had to
                    pass the test. And when we talked about money, there's where we had a little
                    disagreement. They talked to me in terms of GS-9, and to me, a perfect stranger
                    to the federal lingo, I didn't know what that meant. I asked Moraga, in terms of
                    money, how much that was. He told me, and I immediately said that I was not
                    interested, that I couldn't sacrifice what I was making, not only from radio,
                    but working in the theater as MC of big shows that came from Mexico with big
                    movie starts. And also I was working on TV, Channel 5, CBS in San Antonio at
                    that time, and also working on weekends in a very plush night club in San
                    Antonio as MC. So all together I was making a very nice figure, and a GS-9
                    wouldn't make even close to that figure. So he understood. I didn't play
                    difficult to catch or anything like that. I just went to facts: I could not take
                    a job because of the difference in payment.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>So he asked if I would like to be a stringer for the Voice of America, and I
                    jumped at it right away, and said I would be honored and delighted. So I worked
                    for a about a year as a stringer for the Voice in San Antonio. Sometimes I went
                    to Laredo, I went to Galveston, places where news for the Latin American
                    division was developing. Then in 1961 came the Bay of Pigs invasion, and the
                    Voice went on the air 24 hours a day, as you well remember, and they called me.
                    This time it was Fred Galvan who called, and said, “Look, we have this
                    tremendous problem. We're on the air 24 hours, and we are ready to give you a
                    GS-11 without any exams or anything, just come. We have known your work for a
                    year.” Again I asked what that meant in terms of money. I sound like a very
                    money-minded person, but I had to ask, because I had a lot of personal
                    responsibilities with my children. They were small at that time, and I needed
                    the money. I don't want to just sound money-minded; no, I had my reasons for it.
                    Anyway, he offered me the GS-11 without exams, and again I could not take it
                    because of the money. That's April, '61.</p>
                <p>Then I had some problems in my private life, and I wanted to leave San Antonio. I
                    had a chance to go to Los Angeles or Washington, but I thought Washington
                    wouldn't take me after turning them down twice. But I was not very enthusiastic
                    about going to Los Angeles. I know the radio stations in Los Angeles are very
                    competitive, and I'm going to try Washington and see what they say. So I called
                    Washington and talked to Mr. Galvan and he said, “Yes, we are willing to take
                    you in, but now the Cuban crisis is over so you'll have to pass the exam.” So in
                    a few days they sent a package to the post office in San Antonio, and I went and
                    spent three hours a day for three days on the exams, which consisted of
                    translations and writing and voicing, but they were timing me. The examiner
                    there in the post office never had given an exam like that, and he was curious
                    about it. He said, “I've never seen anything like this in civil service. What
                    are you applying for?” And I told him, and he said, “Oh, well that's very
                    interesting. This is the first time in my life that I've seen anything like
                    this.” The exam was not difficult. It was not easy, but it was okay. I finished
                    it in three days, and I remember vividly that the day I finished, coming out of
                    the building, the San Antonio Light had on the front page that Trujillo had been
                    assassinated in the Dominican Republic — that very same day that I finished my
                    exam. Well, anyway, two or three days later I got a call from Fred Galvan,
                    saying that I had passed the exam and that any time I was ready they were ready
                    for me. I said, “Just give me a couple of weeks to shut down my business
                    here.”</p>
                <p>Acceptance of VOA Offer</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got the GS-11 level?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: GS-11. I don't remember the money. I think it was something like $9,000
                    at that time. But as I said, I didn't want to go to Los Angeles. Probably I
                    could have done very well there; I don't know. But the thing is, I considered
                    that I had enough of commercial radio. I have great respect for commercial
                    radio, for commercial announcers, but on the other hand I was eager to get
                    involved in something different, in something really meaningful, like the Voice
                    of America. I wanted to be a part of that organization because I thought then
                    your profession becomes worthwhile. If that explains my feeling. Commercial
                    radio was fine; it paid for many things in my life, for every thing in my life.
                    But I wanted to go into something different, something more worthwhile, and that
                    was radio journalism. And I said, this is my opportunity; go with the Voice of
                    America. So I came in August, 1961.</p>
                <p>It was not easy. The first months, from August till December, I didn't go on the
                    air. At that time the programs were planned, and they had the staff already for
                    those programs — writers, voices and everything. So what I did was edit tapes
                    and things like that, and I was very, very frustrated, because I wanted to do
                    more. I talked to Galvan and said, “Look, I don't think I want to stay. I came
                    to do something here and apparently I'm not. It's not that you don't want me,
                    but the system that we have, already established, is for certain voices and
                    certain programs, and there is nothing for me.” The only thing I can do is read
                    news — and they also had their newscasters appointed for that. I read a newscast
                    once in a while. They put me in the morning show. I told Galvan that I wanted to
                    quit. I said, “Look, I'm going back to commercial radio.” He said, “No, I think
                    your place is here. The only thing is that you need time, a little time.
                    Probably you miss your family. Why don't you take a couple of weeks off and go
                    to San Antonio and see your family, and come back, and I'm sure you will feel
                    different.” I did that. I went to San Antonio, and talked to my agent, Joe
                    Harry. I said, “Joe, I'm ready to come back to commercial radio,” and I
                    explained why. He said, “Don't be a fool. I think you are in the right place,
                    the best place in the world. Go back, and do what you do; just be a little
                    patient.” So I came back. At that time the morning show was an hour or 45
                    minutes and consisted of the news, live, and then a girl would come with music
                    and announce the orchestra and the singer, the composer or whatever, and just
                    play music, back to back. Then again at the half-hour, a news summary, and then
                    go back to music and close the hour. While at night we had beautiful programs of
                    15 minutes or half an hour. I think the reason they didn't use them in the
                    morning was because of the timing. If you have one hour of programming, and you
                    use a half-hour program, there goes most of your time. So then this girl got
                    married in December '61, and they wanted me to do the morning show.</p>
                <p>Events Lead to Putting Del Rio On Spanish Language Morning Show With His Own New
                    Format</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that was the beginning of “Buenos Dias, America.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: The program already had the title of “Buenos Dias, America.” The title
                    was there. Hoyt Ware was the division chief at that time, and Henry Loomis was
                    the VOA director. I told Mr. Ware that I had in mind something different for the
                    morning —a live show. At that time the English program of the Voice had the
                    “Breakfast Show.” Al Johnson was running it at the time. I wanted something like
                    that, something in which you can project a human being through the radio with a
                    message, not just a voice in a piece of plastic. I said, “Look, we can do many
                    things with this show. I can talk to the people, I can inject a little humor.
                    Something different.” And Hoyt went for it a hundred percent, but of course he
                    had to go on and sell it to the front office. Alex Klieforth was program
                    manager. Hoyt Ware and Fred Galvan went to the front office and proposed this
                    show. We were then still in the Cold War and everything at the Voice, as you
                    remember, was scripted. Even the break, “This is the Voice of America,” had to
                    be recorded — except the news. So I thought the timing was very bad. Here we are
                    following a policy of everything written down, and I want to go live, ad lib. Of
                    course I was not going to talk about anything political or anything like that.
                    That can be prerecorded. I just wanted to be a little more human in the
                    broadcast.</p>
                <p>Show Becomes Great Success: Fan Mail Heavy</p>
                <p>So Hoyt Ware and Fred Galvan talked to Alex Klieforth and Henry Loomis, and they
                    gave the okay, and we went on the air with the new “Good Morning, America” show.
                    I remember that I used to ask my colleagues from the night shift to write little
                    stories to fit the time we had, because everything from the night program was
                    too long. And everyone cooperated willingly. I had little short stories, and
                    that way I put the program together with my newscaster.</p>
                <p>We didn't ask for mail, but the letters started pouring in — hundreds of letters
                    from people all over the hemisphere. Why? Probably they were surprised to hear a
                    show like that. One of the first things I got was a letter from the President of
                    El Salvador, Julio Adalberto Rivera. He wrote me a beautiful letter, and sent me
                    a five-pound package of coffee from El Salvador. I had mentioned, ad libitum, I
                    said, “Well this morning I'm having a cup of coffee with you.” I didn't plan to
                    say that; it just came out. So he sent me a five-pound package of coffee. And of
                    course I acknowledged it on the air, and immediately I started getting coffee
                    from Costa Rica, Guatemala, and every place where they have coffee. And people
                    wrote, “Now we spend every morning with you, having a cup of coffee and
                    listening to the Voice of America.” So you see, I think we established a bond, a
                    rapport, between the audience and the Voice. So that's the way the program
                    started. One hour, little features, news, music, chit-chat. But through the
                    years the program has changed a lot.</p>
                <p>Format Changes Over Years; More Direct Live Reports From Correspondents
                    Abroad</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At what point did you start bringing in reports from
                        correspondents around the hemisphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: Oh, that was several years afterwards. I can't give you a precise year,
                    but I used to have that prerecorded. I used to have in the morning repeats of
                    what the correspondents had sent in the night before. But then I asked for
                    fresher reports in the morning, and they used to call to Central Recording. They
                    would take them there, and I would send somebody to pick them up, edit them and
                    put them on a reel and take them to the studio. I thought this was fine. At
                    least we have something fresher in the morning. But through a long chain, you
                    know— Central Recording, editing, put it on the reel, come back to studio.</p>
                <p>Why don't we have a telephone and get the spots from the correspondents directly
                    on the air?</p>
                <p>Why don't we have a telephone and get the spots from the correspondents directly
                    on the air?</p>
                <p>That was another battle. What is he going to send? I said, “Well, the same thing
                    he's going to send to Central Re cording. The piece is already written, has been
                    okayed, so I don't think there is any problem.” So we started doing that. And it
                    had its impact, because we started getting live reports from the correspondents
                    in Latin America.</p>
                <p>Example of Live Report of Cuban Refugees Arriving By Plan In Costa Rica</p>
                <p>One example of the effectiveness of this is when a group of Cuban refugees
                    arrived in Costa Rica, in San Jose. Our stringer was there at the airport, and
                    the only way to get in touch with us was through a public telephone. But he was
                    lucky enough to get to the telephone and get through to the studio, live. He
                    told me, “Look — this is off the air — the plane is already in the area, he will
                    land in a few minutes, and from where I'm standing I can see where the refugees
                    will be coming in, and I'm going to use the telephone, if you don't mind.” I
                    said, “I can hear you perfectly. Don't worry. If this is the quality you'll give
                    in the report, I'll take it.” He said, “Okay, then, don't hang up, because to
                    get the line again is going to be difficult. Stay there.” We stayed about 20
                    minutes, but I couldn't take the chance to cut off the line. Of course,
                    afterwards they called my attention to, you know, “How come you stayed so long
                    on the phone,” and I said, “Well, it was a scoop.” And it really was, because
                    this man picked up with the telephone the songs that the Cubans that were
                    waiting for the refugees were signing there, and the excitement of the moment.
                    He talked to some of them, and he talked also to the President of the republic
                    who was there. I don't know whether he excused himself, saying, “Look, I don't
                    have a microphone, only a telephone,” but he used the telephone, and the
                    president spoke through the telephone, and you could hear the excitement and the
                    happiness of the atmosphere at that moment at the airport.</p>
                <p>That's why I said this is an example of what I want to catch, what I want to put
                    in the morning show. That's the only way we can compete with TV — and with less
                    equipment. Can you imagine a TV station being there? They need a lot of cameras
                    and crew and cables and all that. Radio is the most powerful thing for
                    communications, I think.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>1961: Effect of Bay of Pigs On VOA Latin American Programming</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You talked about the Bay of Pigs. What about the Cuban
                        Missile crisis? How did that affect the program, and the whole Spanish
                        operation of the Voice of America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think it affected the whole house. I remember I saw many colleagues
                    that used to have the same schedule that I had in the morning, working at night.
                    First of all, in the Latin American Division, all the regular programs were
                    suspended, and we had a gigantic, 24-hour continuous broadcast, with news on the
                    hour and the half-hour, and interviews. Everything was interrupted. It was a
                    rough time, but I think everybody that was there pitched in very well. I used to
                    work from midnight till 8 o'clock in the morning. That was the shift that they
                    gave me. Gene Karst was the division chief at that time, but I remember that
                    Hoyt Ware, who had gone to Brazil in the foreign service, came back to help
                    during that period. It was a strenuous time for everybody in the Latin American
                    Division. You know, lots of people came from New York and other places to work
                    there temporarily, because the staffers were not enough to cover that. We took
                    everything from the Central Services. It was very touchy. Of course, our people
                    in Miami got a lot of interviews which came through the central operations
                    system. Those interviews in Miami and other places were exclusive for us. They
                    were checked by policy, though they were recorded originally in Spanish. They
                    were translated into English, and the news center would use them for other
                    languages. But we had many original pieces during the crisis.</p>
                <p>1983: Morning Show (BDA, i.e. Buenos Dias. America)Goes On The Road -
                    Broadcasting From Various Countries</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You talked about the growth of popularity, the response
                        through the mail, and so on. At what point did you begin to go on trips to
                        Latin America in order to project BDA into the hemisphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think it was in the beginning of the seventies, when Lem Graves was
                    the division chief. He sent me on the first trip to Latin America. I was not
                    sending any materials for the program. I was sent on this trip exclusively to be
                    interviewed on radio, TV and newspapers, and to make contacts with the local
                    media. I was so busy doing that that I didn't have time to do anything for the
                    program. Through the years that changed, because in 1983 we did the first
                    on-the-road show, broadcasting BDA from various places. First, we went to
                    Central America in 1983. And then we went to Ecuador, Colombia and Venezuela in
                    '84. We were originating the program from the capitals of these countries.</p>
                <p>Del Rio Becomes Personality In Latin AmericaDel Rio: Invited to Barbecue By El
                    Salvador President</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In looking through some old files, I ran across a note
                        from the past that said, and I quote: “Dividends are beginning to show up in
                        our Spanish breakfast show programs as a result of the goodwill tour of 17
                        Central and South American countries recently completed by breakfast show
                        host Jose “Pepe” Del Rio. While in Venezuela, Pepe arranged for a future
                        live telephone interview with Sr. Diego Arria, Governor of the Federal
                        District of Caracas. On May 6, with Pepe in our Washington studio and Sr.
                        Arria in his office in Caracas, the Governor talked about a beautification
                        program which he started in Caracas as a clean-up project, and a national
                        environmental improvement program he heads. Carried live by two top
                        commercial stations in Caracas and by the national radio network, other
                        stations also taped the interview and relayed it later in the day. The
                        Venezuelan Minister of Education heard the broadcast, contacted USIS, and
                        requested a similar interview with Pepe. The Minister, Sr. Pinalva, said he
                        would like to talk about education in Venezuela and Latin America.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Give me some more examples of people with whom you talked and the receptions you
                    received. I've heard of one case in which you were greeted by the car of the
                    President and whisked away to his hacienda, or something like that. Can you
                    refresh our memory on that, Pepe?</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: There were so many things. Cliff. I can tell you, for instance, that in
                    El Salvador I was invited by the then President, Arturo Armando Molina, for a
                    barbecue. The invitation was for me only. It came through the local employees in
                    Salvador, who told the PAO (Public Affairs Officer), “There is an invitation for
                    Pepe Del Rio from the President for a barbecue tomorrow. The only thing is that
                    nobody else is invited.” I was embarrassed for him. He said, “What do you mean,
                    nobody else is invited?” “ No, the invitation is for him.” Well, you can
                    imagine, this stirred up a little commotion. “Why?” “I don't know. The President
                    wants to meet Pepe Del Rio on a one-on-one basis.” So he said, “Okay, we are
                    going to give you a briefing. You have to know what's going on here.” So they
                    gave me a big briefing, which I think is correct because if a subject came up
                    that I couldn't deal with it could be embarrassing to the post and to VOA and
                    the United States. So I think they were correct in trying to put as much
                    information in my head as they could. But overnight? That's difficult.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>The next day at noon came a big limousine, parked right in front of the USIA
                    office, and a lieutenant came out. I was wearing a suit, and had my tape
                    recorder hanging on my shoulder. I think the PAO or the IO (Information Officer)
                    there at the time was Bill Mateer. Bill was very nervous about it. “Are you sure
                    you have everything?” “Yes, Bill, don't worry, I'll do my best.” “Okay. You will
                    be debriefed afterwards.” So the lieutenant came in and said, “Mr. Del Rio?”
                    “Yes.” “Please.” He opened the door of the limousine, and I got in. It was
                    air-conditioned, beautiful. And we drove about 15 miles out of San Salvador. As
                    we were approaching the place, I could hear mariachi music. Very nice, you know.
                    Lots of people there. So we stopped, and they opened the door for me. I didn't
                    know President Molina personally; I couldn't recognize him. But one of the
                    helpers there came and took me directly to President Molina, who was wearing a
                    khaki shirt, no tie, and he immediately threw his arms around me and said, “It's
                    very nice to meet you. You don't know how much we like you here in El Salvador.”
                    I was sweating, with the heat and the humidity, and he said, “Take off that coat
                    and your tie,” and the tape recorder he gave to a sergeant, and he said, “You
                    just relax.” They had so many things there. They had a deer roasting, and lots
                    of ribs and chicken — it was a big barbecue — wonderful. And the mariachi music.
                    Then one of the sergeants came with a small plate and two big shots of tequila,
                    one for the President and one for me, and of course with a slice of lemon and
                    salt, which is the way to drink it. President Molina took one and I took the
                    other one. “To our friendship.” We drank the tequila, one shot all the way down.
                    Then he said, “Now I want you to meet members of my cabinet.” And would you
                    believe that with each of them I had to drink a shot of tequila!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't see how you were still standing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I don't know. Probably I had practice. But you can't turn down a thing
                    like that. You would be rude. That's one of the things that you, as a U.S.
                    Government representative, sometimes have to do. They were delighted. After the
                    luncheon, President Molina said that he wanted to show me the stadium they were
                    building, and we were flown there by his son in a French helicopter they had
                    just bought. We went to the stadium, and then we flew to the President palace,
                    and I had an interview with him on tape. The next day I turned it in to Bill
                    Mateer, and said, “Here is the interview.” He said, “Okay, now we want the
                    debriefing.” I said “We didn't talk about politics or anything.” It was fun,
                    what we had, very nice. I think they were pleased. I was pleased. The interview
                    is there, and you can see all the questions I asked him and the answers he gave
                    me. The tape speaks for itself; I don't have to say anything else. It was quite
                    an experience, and I think Bill Mateer and the rest of the officers there were
                    very pleased with the results of the interview.</p>
                <p>Another Personal Presidential Meeting (Breakfast)With President Stroessner of
                    Paraguay</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about another visit to a chief of state, in
                        Paraguay.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: That was another unforgettable experience. I was staying at the Guarani
                    Hotel, and in Paraguay, because of the geography, the sun rises very early. I
                    got a call about six o'clock in the morning, or before six, from the President's
                    press secretary, Alejandro Caceres Almada. He said, “Pepe, the President read in
                    the paper this morning that you are in town, and he just called me to see if we
                    can arrange that you have breakfast with him.” I said, “Well, I'll be delighted,
                    but Alejandro, I have to get the approval of my superiors here, the Public
                    Affairs Officer.” At that time, it was Mr. Wooten, I think. I called him at
                    home, that early, and of course he was very surprised. He said, “Well, you are
                    not prepared to go to an interview like that.” I said, “Well, if you don't want
                    me to, I won't go. I don't think it's an interview. He invited me to have
                    breakfast.” “Yes, but you have to be briefed.” I said, “Yes, I understand what
                    you mean, and if you say no, I will call Mr. Almada right now and tell him,
                    'Sorry.'" “No, we can't do that; it's an invitation from the President. I think
                    you should go, but be very careful.” I said, “Yes, sir, I will”. So far in my
                    career with the government I haven't made any big mistakes. Besides, there was
                    no time. They were supposed to pick me up at 7 o'clock. So I called back to
                    Alejandro, and said, “Yes, they gave me the okay.” He said, “Somebody will pick
                    you up in the lobby of the hotel, and you're supposed to be with the President
                    at 7:30. They'll bring you here to the presidential palace.” So I shaved and
                    dressed, and went down to the lobby. There were about 150 Americans on a tourist
                    trip, going to the Iguazu Falls. The lobby was bubbling with American tourists.
                    I quietly sat down, and at seven o'clock sharp I saw a jeep coming up to the
                    door; of course, a military jeep. All the Americans looked at it, and
                    immediately sensed that something was going on. I saw this lieutenant step out
                    of the jeep, and I knew he was looking for me, but I just stayed there, thinking
                    I'm going to wait.</p>
                <p>So he went to the desk, and they paged me. “Mr. Del Rio, please come to the
                    desk.” And of course all the Americans saw me walking over. The lieutenant was
                    very nice, and took me to the jeep. Everybody was silent. He put me in the jeep,
                    and we drove to the presidential palace. There were a lot of people there.
                    Apparently the President used to receive people in the morning, personally. At
                    7:30 sharp, Alejandro Caceres Almada said, “Okay, let's go in” He and a
                    photographer and I entered the President's office, and I still have the picture
                    of President Stroessner and me shaking hands, taken by the photographer that
                    entered with the press secretary and myself. Once they took the picture, they
                    left, and I was alone with the President. To tell you the truth, I was a little
                    nervous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Understandably.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think anyone in my shoes could be nervous. You don't know what the
                    President is going to ask you to talk about. It turned out that President
                    Stroessner was very interested in the space program. He had heard many of my
                    broadcasts from Cape Kennedy, and he was very interested in learning the
                    technicalities of the broadcasts, and about the aims of the program, and how you
                    do this and how you do that. The conversation went around the space program. We
                    had coffee. The maid came in, served coffee, and left. I was supposed to be
                    there for 15 minutes, but it was close to half an hour. He asked about some of
                    my colleagues at the Voice, whom he obviously knew personally, among them
                    Mauricio Goldchain. The President asked me, “How is Mr. Goldchain?” They seemed
                    to be friends. I said, “Fine.” It was a very nice conversation. Purely social,
                    and space.</p>
                <p>At the end of the conversation, Mr. Caceres Almada came in and I sensed that they
                    wanted to wrap it up, so I got up, ready to get out of there. President
                    Stroessner pointed out an article that was published locally, based on an item
                    from USIA World, the Agency organ, about my son and me in Vietnam, accompanied
                    by a picture of us. Apparently the news media got hold of this story, as they
                    seemed to pick up others occasionally from USIA World. They got interested,
                    asked for the material, and apparently he saw the picture and the local article.
                    He said, “I've seen the picture of you and your son in Vietnam, and I think this
                    picture is an editorial. You can see here a father and a son, two generations,
                    fighting against communism with different weapons; your son has a rifle, and you
                    have a tape recorder. And I want you to know that here in Paraguay, we also
                    fight communism.” That was the only political reference we had in the whole
                    conversation. I said, “Mr. President, thank you. I appreciate the honor of being
                    invited for breakfast.” He asked me if I had been to the Iguazu Falls. I said,
                    “No, Mr. President, when I have come to your country I have not had time to get
                    out of Asuncion.” He said, “Well, the next time you are here Almada will see
                    that you go to the Iguazu Falls to see that wonderful thing that we have in our
                    country.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever get back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, I went back, on a private trip, and I went to the Iguazu Falls. But
                    I didn't see President Stroessner again, never again since that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: President Stroessner's reference to the picture of you and
                        your son in Vietnam brings us to the period of your career which you spent
                        in Vietnam. Tell me how you got assigned to Vietnam, what the circumstances
                        were, how you were able to leave your program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Temporary Duty In Vietnam</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: It was 1968, right after Tet — the big Tet. My boss at the Voice was Lem
                    Graves. Before me, my colleague Fred Schiele had been in Vietnam for two
                    temporary duty tours (TDY's). This time they wanted to send somebody else. At
                    that time, one of my sons — the one that's in the picture — was there with the
                    Marine Corps, stationed in Danang. I had a personal reason to go there. Of
                    course, the assignment was voluntary. They cannot force you to go. They asked,
                    “Do you want to go?” And I grabbed it immediately, and said, “Yes, I'll go.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a reporter.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, as a reporter. I want to mention something that probably is not
                    fitting for the interview. But, at that time, my wife Beatrice and I had a boy a
                    year old, and we didn't have any relatives or close friends here in Washington.
                    We were living in an apartment. She knew that I was going to be away for six
                    months, and it was hard on her to stay all by herself with a one-year-old boy,
                    in case anything should happen. So I think it is fair on my part to recognize
                    the courage of my wife. She told me afterwards, “If I had said I don't want to
                    go, you wouldn't have gone. But if I had said something like that, you would
                    tell me afterwards, 'You didn't let me go where I wanted to go.'" So I just want
                    to mention that. She agreed, and she stayed here by herself with the little
                    boy.</p>
                <p>Del Rio Sees The Successful Side of The Chu Hoi Program In Vietnamand Other Human
                    Interest Incidents</p>
                <p>So I went to Nam as a Spanish-language reporter for the Voice of America. What
                    they asked me to do was to report on the other side of the war — the positive
                    side, of things happening despite the war. Like What? you may ask. Well, there
                    was the Chu Hoi program — the open arms program to bring those that went to the
                    other side back, and give them tools to build a hut, and give them medical
                    attention, bring them back to the South Vietnamese society. It was very
                    interesting, very interesting, because I saw so many cases of how the people
                    came back disenchanted with what the other side had offered them. They wanted to
                    start building their own huts and their own communities. It was a very exciting,
                    a very humanized story. Also, the construction of roads, and the help that the
                    Koreans were giving in building orphanages and places for the elderly. All that
                    is not front-page news, and I was told to dig on that.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>One of the most interesting stories that I did was on the Spanish medical team
                    that was in Vietnam. Nobody knew about it. There were about ten people —
                    doctors, technicians — that came on a rotating basis to Vietnam, and they were
                    in a hospital in Go Cong province, in the south. Go Cong was VC-infested and
                    they were right in the middle. I remember vividly the three flags: the Spanish
                    flag, the South Vietnamese flag, and the American flag. But the operation, the
                    hospital, was run exclusively by the Spaniards, sponsored by the Spanish
                    government. They would take in any patient — no questions asked. They didn't
                    care if they were VC or North Vietnamese army. They were taking care of a lot of
                    eye diseases, like conjunctivitis. I saw cases there with no eyes, just two
                    balls of puss — horrible! And also skin diseases. These guys were working 24
                    hours a day, and taking in anyone. You had a woman expecting a baby — you are
                    welcome. You had a problem with your skin, they would take you. I was planning
                    to stay there for two or three days, and I spent a whole week. I couldn't leave.
                    Every day they would have new things to do.</p>
                <p>The way I was delivered to that place I will never forget. I left Saigon early in
                    the morning by helicopter, and the flight was not too long, so it was still
                    early in the morning when we arrived at the place where I was to be dropped out
                    of the helicopter. I didn't know I was going to be dropped. I thought we would
                    land. Apparently we were shot at by the enemy, and the pilot had to maneuver
                    around and ask for help. We couldn't land where we were supposed to land, so we
                    stayed around for about half an hour, and then came back to the same place.
                    Apparently the pilot got instructions to go back to the same place, that it was
                    safe. Instead of landing, the helicopter didn't touch the ground, it was about a
                    couple of yards off the ground, and the gunner told me, “jump!”. So I jumped
                    with my tape recorder, and the helicopter took off. Just took off. Here I am in
                    the middle of nowhere, in hostile territory, obviously, and I could hear the
                    mosquitoes humming around me, and I said, “What am I doing here?” In two or
                    three minutes a jeep with military pulled up. Can you imagine? Just imagine
                    yourself in that situation. I was scared. But I heard this jeep approaching,
                    with army people — U.S. army... That's something I want to stress: every time I
                    required services like transportation or lodging in Vietnam, the armed forces
                    were number one. A hundred percent. They would go out of their way in order to
                    give you what you wanted.</p>
                <p>So they came, and picked me up. I didn't even mention to them anything about the
                    incident; I didn't want to sound chicken. But I had gone through quite an
                    experience. They took me to the hospital where the Spanish doctors were. And I
                    did a series that was used by our Spanish Service to Spain, by Julian Fernandez,
                    and he told me when I came back that the stories were used very much in Spain.
                    It was a very human story.</p>
                <p>Del Rio Meets His Marine Son In Saigon</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you in Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: I was there from August to December of '68. My son didn't see me till
                    December. He found me. I went to Danang several times looking for him, but he
                    was always out in the boondocks, patrolling. His officers told me if I wanted to
                    go to those places where he was, I was welcome. But I don't think I was prepared
                    to do that; I was not a Marine. Anyway, Joe somehow got a permit to go to
                    Saigon, flying as a gunner on a helicopter from Danang to Saigon, and he got
                    there on a Sunday, of all days. He didn't know where I was staying, so he went
                    immediately to the American embassy. But JUSPAO was separate from the embassy,
                    in a separate building by the Saigon River. But Joe didn't know that, so he went
                    to the American embassy and the guard told him that he didn't know anything
                    about me. He knew that the JUSPAO offices were down by the river. So my son went
                    to the JUSPAO offices. Again, the Marine guard said, “I'm sorry, but they change
                    us; I don't know anybody here personally.” So Joe was talking to him about me
                    when a girl who had been working overtime that Sunday came out. She had to sign
                    the book to leave the building, and she overheard the conversation between my
                    son and the Marine guard, and she said, “Are you talking about Pepe Del Rio, the
                    VOA man?” “Yes, he's my father.” She said, “Well, I know that he lives in the
                    Central Palace Hotel, but that's the only thing I can tell you.” So he went to
                    the Central Palace Hotel, and I wasn't there. Usually on Sundays I used to go to
                    a place called the Club Esportif, and my son was referred to the club because
                    the desk clerk knew me and knew that I was there. He went there, but he couldn't
                    get in because he was an enlisted man. So he sat on a bench in a small park that
                    was near the entrance of the club until 11 o'clock or so when I left the place
                    to go to my hotel. When he saw me coming out of the building, he didn't say
                    anything. He let me start walking in the semi-dark streets. Just a few steps
                    behind me, he said, “Dad.” I heard that voice, and it struck my heart so
                    strongly. Without looking at him, I knew that it was my son. I turned around and
                    just saw his silhouette, a big tall guy, and I cried. I couldn't help it. It was
                    a very wonderful thing for me to see him — alive. But then he told me — he was
                    supposed to come home that December — he said that he had extended his tour for
                    another six months. At that moment, I didn't understand why he did it. He was
                    very honest with me. He said, “Dad, politically I don't know what we're doing
                    here. I came because I'm an American and they asked me to fight for my country.
                    I don't think we are going to win this war. We are fighting it with one hand
                    tied behind our back. But I am staying because I lost many friends, many
                    buddies, and I feel like I owe them something, and the only way to pay this debt
                    that I feel to them is to stay here for another six months.” Now, what can you
                    tell a man — not a boy, a man —in those circumstances? Come home, I don't want
                    you to stay? No, that was his decision. So he stayed. But he was wounded in
                    February. He didn't last the six months. He was evacuated to Okinawa. It was not
                    even in combat. One night a rocket landed in the barracks and killed several
                    guys there, and my son was lucky enough just to get a shrapnel wound in one of
                    his shoulders. Now he's okay, after two operations. He's got only limited
                    movement in one of his arms, but he's okay. He has three wonderful girls, a
                    wonderful wife, and he's working fine.</p>
                <p>Does Feeds Both For VOA (Buenos Dias) and Latin American Stations</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in Vietnam, did you feed material
                        specifically designed for “Buenos Dias, America,” as well as the rest of the
                        programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, I was trying to feed, taking into consideration the difference in
                    time. Unfortunately I could not go live on the show because of the time element
                    and also because of the communications system. I had to go through the Pentagon
                    in order to get to the Voice. Anyway, it was very difficult for me to get</p>
                <p>live on the show. But I could send material to Central Recording of the Voice,
                    and they would pass it to the show. So every day, I was on the show from
                    Vietnam, not live but on tape, but with only one or two hours of difference. I
                    was also sending material for the Feed Service for stations in Latin America,
                    and that was a very successful idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In which we do correspondent reports for broadcast on the
                        local stations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Right. I used to close, “This is Jose Perez Del Rio, for this station,
                    in Vietnam” — without mentioning any station. And Cliff, I remember Dan Garcia,
                    who was the deputy chief, told me, “You know, we are selling these like hot
                    biscuits. Every- body in Latin America is using this material.” I used to send
                    three or four stories, without closes, so the stations were getting information
                    from Vietnam free of charge. I don't know whose idea it was, but it worked out
                    very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So when you returned and resumed “Buenos Dias, America,”
                        what changes did you put into effect?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Well, first let me tell you that Ramon Levy, who was my back-up man and
                    took over the show as MC when I went to Nam, when I came back we started again
                    trying to inject new ideas or whatever. I was glad to be back, in the sense that
                    I was doing more radio. Being in the field is nice. It's a good experience, but
                    it's not the kind of human broadcasting we were talking about. It's not the
                    projection that you do in the studio. I went back to Vietnam in 1970, and
                    noticed a big difference in Vietnam from '68 to '70. This assignment was less
                    than six months. I was there in March, April and May, and I came back in June —
                    about four months more. But I could notice the difference in the smallest hut of
                    the Vietnamese people the South Vietnamese flag. Also in Saigon, the fountains
                    had water again. The people went to the zoo on Sundays, and they had music in
                    the zoo, and colored balloons, and the children playing. No more shellings in
                    '70. No more bombardments. But I remember, one piece I wrote described how you
                    could walk the streets of Saigon, not feeling threatened at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to go back and talk a little more about the space
                        program, which President Stroessner talked about. You said you reported from
                        Cape Kennedy, now Cape Canaveral again. How did you get out of “Buenos Dias,
                        America,” to go on this kind of trip? Was it the same as when you went to
                        Vietnam? Sort of a leave of absence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Broadcasting Space programs From Cape Canaveral</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: No, it's not a leave. Let's go back. At the beginning, the pioneers of
                    the space broadcasts in Spanish were Ivo Luis Alonso and Herb Morales. Morales
                    covered the Glenn sub-orbital flight and Ivo covered Alan Shepard's first
                    flight. So I went there after these two guys. My first assignment was with
                    Walter Schirra, and from then on I covered the rest of Mercury, Gemini, and
                    Apollo until the moon landing. I was assigned there to cover the space flights,
                    but that didn't mean I was quitting the breakfast show. I had my reports every
                    morning in the show, live. We didn't have the time problem the way we had in
                    Vietnam. This was very easy to do. Communications were very easy. Besides
                    reporting the live action, I used to give reports every morning to “Buenos Dias,
                    America.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you utilize a good deal of Laszlo Dosa's and other
                        correspondents' materials?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, by all means. I think — and this is something that I believe the
                    rest of my colleagues in the language services would agree to — Laszlo Dosa's
                    pieces were the base for the languages. He was the guy who provided us with the
                    insight, the basic information, the technical information. I think that Laszlo
                    Dosa did — and will do any time — a superb job. He's a wonderful writer, and he
                    has the gift of explaining the most complicated technical situations in a
                    layman's style” which is what you need in radio. I know he's retired, but I want
                    to express my admiration for Laszlo Dosa for the wonderful job he did, and the
                    scripts that he wrote on the space program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What special memories do you have of your many years on
                        “Buenos Dias, America”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think in our type of work you go with a happy heart. If you don't go
                    with a happy heart, you are not going to project, my friend; you are just going
                    to do a job that you have to do. But if you really want to tell the audience
                    that you believe in what you are doing, you have to be with a happy heart. So
                    every day, regardless — and you have to get up at 2 o'clock in the morning to do
                    “Buenos Dias, America,” and shovel snow off your car in order to move — but I
                    knew that every day was a different challenge. Even though we knew what we had
                    prepared for the next day, every day was a challenge for me and the rest of the
                    crew. We enjoyed every day, every day, and we kidded among ourselves. We had a
                    spirit.</p>
                <p>Mechanics of Putting “Buenos Dias” Together</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me a little bit about the mechanics of putting the
                        program together. You talked about your crew. How many people were involved
                        in the program? What time did you get to the studio? What time did you start
                        getting your material together? Did you use material from the night
                        before?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Okay. The news editor and the news translators got there first, about 2
                    or 2:30 in the morning. By that time the newsroom has sent already the items we
                    are supposed to pick up from the ticker. So that's the first thing that starts
                    working — the news. I used to get there at 3 o'clock. Then I went to the ticker
                    to see all the CR's (correspondent reports) that we had — the latest ones.
                    Select whatever is the high priority, wherever it has anything to do with a news
                    item, so it could be an extension of the news item. That was my first priority,
                    to see what we have in CR's related to the news items, and distribute them to
                    the translators. Then see the log from the night before, and see what you can
                    still use in the morning, that's not outdated. Then check with the man in charge
                    of the (Spanish-language) correspondents (around the hemisphere), the calls that
                    he has already set for you. He had talked to these people the night before or
                    the day before, and told them, “Tomorrow morning you call at this hour on this
                    subject.” So I had that information on my desk — say, “The correspondent in
                    Bogota is going to call you at 8 o'clock on this subject.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These correspondents were employees of the USIS
                        posts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, or free-lancers that worked as stringers. So that information has
                    to be combined with whatever CR's I have, you see; if not, they will go by
                    themselves. Once you have all that, you start writing down the themes of the
                    day. By that time it's almost six o'clock. We go on the air, and some of the
                    material has not been translated, so we will do that during the show. I would
                    have two or three calls that would come during the show, so it was not precut:
                    “This is the way it's going to be.” No, you have to be flexible. And then
                    suppose there is a hurricane in the Gulf of Mexico. George Wehby, our excellent
                    correspondent in Miami, will call me about five o'clock in the morning and say,
                    “Look, I'm planning to listen to the six o'clock weather report, and I'll give
                    you a live report about 6:35. Is that okay with you?” Let me write it down. So
                    we communicate, and I'll get that report live from Miami. So every day is the
                    same structure, but different insides. And that's beauty of the show. And
                    everybody pitched in beautifully. We were a team.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did you run this program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Twenty-five years. Twenty-five years.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you retire?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Wisdom of Assigning Foreign Service Officers to VOA Jobs</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: 1986. And now, if you'll allow me, I'd like to say something about the
                    presence of our colleagues from the Foreign Service. I'll ask you a question.
                    How do you feel about having new people come to the Voice every two or four
                    years. Foreign Service Officers, and they change what their predecessors did,
                    and they have their own ideas. Do you think that's good for the operation of the
                    Voice of America?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think there's a better way. But I'm supposed to be
                        asking the questions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think there's a better way, yeah. And I think these gentlemen, they
                    bring their baggage of knowledge of the regions that they come from. I'm talking
                    about the Latin American program, but it applies to the whole operation. So they
                    go there and spend two or three or four years — obviously they have a deeper
                    knowledge than we do in Washington of the countries where they've served. So now
                    these guys are put in a very difficult situation, because all of a sudden, next
                    assignment: Washington, Voice of America. They might ask themselves, “What do I
                    know about radio?”. But they have to come and perform. I can't blame them. They
                    are in a hot spot. I guess they are in a hot spot. So they come and try to run
                    things the way they used to do it in their own offices abroad. And it's quite
                    different. They discover that — afterwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some do and some don't. Some are excellent and some are
                        lousy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Well, as I said, you cannot blame them, because most of them, I know,
                    don't want to come to Washington. For many reasons. They'd rather go on another
                    assignment abroad. But they are required to come to Washington and jobs have to
                    be found for them. But I think the Voice and the government would be better
                    served if these gentlemen were sort of advisers, but let somebody else run the
                    day-to-day operation, dealing with the personnel — the announcers, the writers,
                    and others — and just have their wonderful knowledge help us to direct the
                    content of our broadcasts. I should also note that a number of these Foreign
                    Service Officers have journalistic backgrounds, and have been able to contribute
                    to better programming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of the Foreign Service people we've had in senior
                        positions at VOA started at the Voice before going into the Foreign Service,
                        like Bill Haratunian and Vallimarescu, but these are very exceptional
                        cases.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: They are exceptional cases. But they are two different capacities.
                    Absolutely. The capacity of running a radio station, and the capacity of
                    advising in policy. I think it would be fair to them, also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before you left the organization, Pepe, you received one
                        of the greatest honors that could be bestowed on you by the organization.
                        You were named Outstanding Employee of the Year. What year was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: It was 1984; February 1984.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had also received Superior Service awards in the
                        past.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes, I received some citations for my work in Vietnam and my work in
                    Latin America, for my trips. But this Outstanding Employee of the Year award in
                    1984 was the first award of this kind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “For extraordinary commitment and dedication in making a
                        personal contribution to the goals of the Voice of America.” That's very
                        impressive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Comments on Success of Program - and Some Criticisms</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: And then in 1986, On October 31, when I retired, I got this: “Presented
                    to Jose Pepe Del Rio upon retirement in grateful recognition of 25 years of
                    service in the government of the United States of America.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I do think it is very ironic that, because of the
                        way the law is written, and we're not supposed to publicize ourselves — the
                        USIA is not supposed to publicize its activities — you are practically
                        unknown in terms of publicity in the United States — except through the
                        network operations that you've now been able to engage in commercially, and
                        yet through your travels in Latin America, you've gotten so much ink, as
                        it's put, in terms of newspaper stories wherever you've been. I've seen your
                        albums, and I know of these hundreds of stories that have been written about
                        your visits to the various parts of the hemisphere. As in the case of Willis
                        Conover, who's hardly known in the United States at all but overseas is well
                        known.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: I think you were involved in a very successful project that I took part
                    in. Bill Reynolds made some contacts on the West Coast, and this project was
                    sort of a tourist visit to San Diego, Las Vegas, Palm Springs. They approached
                    Bill Reynolds, who came to you because you were the deputy program director. You
                    had to give the okay for that project, and it worked beautifully. It consisted
                    of me going to those places and doing reportages with sound, interviews, and
                    then broadcast that as Americana themes in our programming in Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Bill Reynolds' material in English Breakfast Show to
                        the rest of the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: The way to determine the success of these programs were the letters that
                    we got. The Voice told these people that we weren't going to answer the letters
                    we might get, so we'd give their address. We gave the address of these tourists
                    departments so people could write there to get maps and brochures of Disneyland,
                    Las Vegas, the San Diego Zoo and the other places — a beautiful package for the
                    audience. They got thousands and thousands of letters from Latin American,
                    flooded with requests for the package. And the only way they knew about it was
                    through “Buenos Dias, America.” It was very successful. I don't see anything
                    wrong with that. We're trying to project our country and our society to other
                    societies, and this is a beautiful way to do it. The Voice should be able to do
                    that more often.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course now they've got this big bus that they go around
                        in. Only they've cut the budget so they can't travel much. Have there been
                        any criticisms through the years of your approach to broadcasting — of the
                        human side as opposed to the straight, deadpan, objective reporting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yes. Within the Voice there have been criticisms of me, saying that I
                    don't have enough “freight,” they my program didn't carry enough freight, that I
                    was too trivial on the air. That's within the Voice, at different levels. That's
                    all I can say. I cannot pinpoint or determine who said what, but I know because
                    I was told several times that there had been criticism about me, that I didn't
                    go in depth with my interviews, that I was too light, didn't carry enough
                    weight. I don't know if I personally did that, you know. I don't think I was a
                    commentator. I never even tried to pretended to be a commentator. My job I think
                    consisted of delivering the policies of the country, and I tried to make it
                    palatable for the audience. I worked for radio, and I know it's very easy for
                    anyone, if they think you are too hard or harsh, just to move the dial a little
                    bit and you are gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some people used to say that we're not in the
                        entertainment business, and I agreed we were in the information business,
                        but it had to be information presented entertainingly.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: Those are exactly the words that I heard from some people at the Voice.
                    We are not in the entertainment business, and Pepe Del Rio is trying to do an
                    entertainment program. Nothing is father from the truth than that. I was trying
                    to put as much freight as we could in the morning show, that now is three hours
                    long, with the best flavor for the people that listen to it. That was my only
                    sin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since you left, has the program retained its format and
                        its shape and style and content?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: From what I have heard, yes, it has retained the same format. I've heard
                    in general terms that it's still the same, with an emcee, and they still do the
                    show on the same basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I'd consider that a high compliment to you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: At the beginning, I understand that they were trying to make drastic
                    changes in the show. There was a phrase that said something like, the Voice of
                    America is not going to cultivate personalities. Now, I don't know what they
                    mean by that. Cult of personalities. In my case, I think it was a very big
                    injustice, saying that I was trying to sell myself in the show, that I was
                    pushing Pepe Del Rio. I don't know who said that, but people at the Voice said
                    that, that I was pushing for me, and that's the biggest injustice and the
                    biggest lie, because the only thing I was thinking of on the air, when that red
                    light went on, and I knew that I was on the air with three hours to fill, the
                    only thought I had in my mind was to do a good show and tell what we have to
                    tell.</p>
                <p>I also have letters from Latin America in which they said that I was another guy
                    sold to the American imperialism — which is a favorite phrase in Latin America.
                    I remember once — I don't have to mention the country — one newspaper, the guy
                    who interviewed me asked, “Are you an American citizen?”. I said, “Yes, I am.”
                    He asked me, “Why?”. I said, “Because I believe in the American ideology and my
                    life has taken place in the United States and I want to be 100 percent a part of
                    the American people.” That's what I told him. But what he published in the
                    newspaper was a different story. The article came out saying something like, “I
                    have betrayed my country of birth, that I have become an American citizen
                    because of convenience.” Absolutely nothing of what I told the guy.
                    Unfortunately we didn't record it; we were just talking. That's an experience I
                    will never forget.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What politically motivated kind of paper was it? Left,
                        right, center?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: I don't remember. That was the way it came out. It was embarrassing to
                    me. As a matter of fact, the USIS office, when they saw that the next day, asked
                    me, “How come you gave this kind of statement?” And I said, “I didn't give this
                    kind of statement. What they say there is not true.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did anybody protest?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I don't know. I left the country; I was only there for two or three
                    days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Considering all the good press you've gotten, that one you
                        can live with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Yeah, I guess. But that's unfair. Another criticism, again, this one
                    from some Latin American listeners, is that I was trying to sell myself, to
                    promote myself. But what you really are doing is trying to project an image of
                    complete control, or something like that, about the show.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you can't please everybody, Pepe, but you've pleased
                        an awful lot over a long time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Heart Warming Experiences That Offset Bitter Moments</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: But it's not roses all the way. Cliff. You have beautiful experiences.
                    Like once I was in Bogota and an old friend of mine whom I hadn't seen for ages,
                    the signer, Leo Marini, all of a sudden I saw his picture in the lobby of the
                    hotel. I said, “My God, I thought he was dead.” He was performing that night in
                    the penthouse of the Tequendama Hotel in Bogota. So I called the operator and
                    said, “May I have the room of Mr. Leo Marini?” I called him up on the phone and
                    he said, “Hello?” I said, “This is Pepe Del Rio, you remember me?” “Yes, my God,
                    I haven't heard from you in ages.” “Well, same here. I saw your picture
                    downstairs.” He said, “Listen, I'm performing tonight, as you know, in the Roof
                    Garden here in the hotel. Are you coming?” I said, “I'm by myself.” “Okay, you
                    will have a table.” I went up there, about 11 o'clock. (The night club shows
                    there are late.) I told the maitre d' who I was, and he showed me to my table.
                    And there is Leo Marini in the spotlight. The guy is a master. He sang more than
                    an hour by himself, with his old songs, and the public was delighted with him.
                    At the end of his performance, he said, “Tonight, I have a wonderful guest, a
                    dear guest of mine here, came all the way from Washington — giving the
                    impression that I came there for his performance — Mr. Pepe Del Rio from the
                    Voice of America.” They put the spotlight on me, and here I am all by myself.
                    That was beautiful. And then Leo went to sign autographs. A young Colombian
                    couple came to my table and the boy said, “Mr. Del Rio, are you really Pepe Del
                    Rio from the Voice of America? “Yes, I am.” “You know, if my father could be
                    here instead of me, he would be the happiest man in the world. I am 23 years old
                    now, but since I was a little boy, your name has been a household word in my
                    home, because my dad listened to you every morning and you are just like one of
                    the family. I am here on my honeymoon. I am from Santa Marta. And this is the
                    best present that I ever had. I can't believe I'll go home and tell my father
                    that I met you.” He introduced his wife, and I asked if they would care to have
                    a drink with me and he said, “No, no, I just want to say that you are like an
                    uncle to me. I never thought I was going to meet you on my wedding trip.” His
                    wife was very nice. That's a moment. That's beautiful</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's gratifying. That made it all worthwhile.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: And then in Costa Rica. Did I tell you this story? I was there, and the
                    guys in the (USIS) office said, “We've got to go to Alajuela, because there is
                    an old farmer who keeps asking us about you. He's always writing letters. He
                    cannot afford the postage to send a letter to the States, so he brings the
                    letters here to us for us to mail.” And I'm sure that I got some of his letters,
                    but I couldn't remember the name. So we went to Alajuela, and we went to this
                    little hacienda, and the old man came out, all wrinkled by the sun, an old man.
                    He was crying. Cliff, with emotion. He embraced me, and I embraced him —
                    wonderful! Meeting somebody that he knew just on the air. He said, “Listen, I
                    want to share you with Oscar.” Who's Oscar, I asked myself. Sure, let's share
                    this moment with Oscar. So we went back in the field, and Oscar was an ox! An ox
                    that he uses to plow the land. He hangs on his horns a transistor radio, and
                    that was how he was listening to the Voice of America, and the morning
                    broadcast. While he was plowing the land, he was listening. And Oscar was
                    listening too! My God, those are things. Cliff that — how can you forget them? I
                    think that pays for every bitter moment.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>Twenty-five years. And I still miss the Voice. I miss it. I miss the exciting
                    moment, you know, preparing the show. I used to shout, close to airtime, to
                    everybody: “It's showtime!” (Laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What are some of the oddball memories you have of events
                        that occurred while you were out covering a story?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A Birth Aboard An Eastern Airline Plane Out of Puerto Rico</p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Well, I cannot precisely tell you the odds, but something happened to me
                    that I don't think could happen ever again in my life. I might go back to cover
                    a war or I might interview presidents or what have you, but I don't think
                    something like this would happen to me over again. I think the odds are very
                    high; I don't know how many millions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I went to San Juan, Puerto Rico to cover a music festival — with my
                    wife, Bea — and we had a nice time. We were coming back, flying toward Miami. I
                    always carry my tape recorder, and I had it in my seat, next to me. I was having
                    a drink, enjoying the flight, and all of a sudden I hear this commotion in the
                    back of the plane, people talking, and I asked, “what's going on?”. Somebody
                    said, “A lady is about to give birth.” (Laughter) That's what I mean about the
                    odds being so high. I went back to my seat and picked up my tape recorder and
                    went toward the back of the plane. The crew put a big blanket up to separate the
                    last back seats from the rest of the cabin, and that was where this lady
                    was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a doctor on board?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Fortunately. The captain announced the event over the speakers, saying,
                    “We are in a rare position” — something like that — “a baby is going to be born.
                    If there is a doctor on board, we would appreciate his help.” I couldn't believe
                    my ears. Fortunately, a doctor from Argentina was aboard the plane, and went
                    behind the blanket. The crew was kind of rude with me, because I wanted to see
                    the lady. I didn't know how old she was, where she was from — on those flights,
                    lots of people come from Puerto Rico, but maybe they are from Colombia or
                    Venezuela or where have you. So I didn't know the nationality of this lady, or
                    how old she was, or her name. The flight attendants refused to give the name or
                    let me see this lady. By the time I got my tape recorder, they had the blanket
                    there. I got close to the blanket but didn't see anything that was going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think the woman deserved some privacy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Of course. But you know I was always looking for news. Anyway, I had my
                    tape recorder on, I was taping everything, including the discussion I had with
                    the flight crew, and all of a sudden there was the cry of a baby, and you could
                    hear it in the recording. Unfortunately we were talking at that moment; I was
                    arguing with these people when we heard the cry of the baby, and everybody
                    started applauding and cheering and what have you. I said something like, “Maybe
                    you hear the cry of the baby.” Once I edited the whole thing, I said, “I want to
                    repeat that particular moment. Please pay attention, and you will hear the cry
                    of the baby.” And I repeated the same part.</p>
                <p>A few minutes later, the doctor came out from behind the blanket. He gave me his
                    name but he didn't know the name of the girl. The only thing he could tell me
                    was that she was from Puerto Rico, about 18 or 20 years old, and that she had
                    given birth to a baby girl. That was all the information he had. The
                    stewardesses sent me back to my seat because we were approaching the airport
                    already. We were supposed to change planes in Miami and continue to Washington,
                    but I said I had to follow this story. I made arrangements to pick up our
                    luggage, and went to the hotel. (When we landed), an ambulance was waiting, and
                    before anyone left the plane they took this lady on a stretcher into the
                    ambulance and took off. I talked to the captain of the plane. I was interested
                    in knowing the nationality of the baby, born in the air, and he told me that
                    when a baby is born in a plane that flies under the flag of the United States,
                    wherever it's flying, that baby is an American.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't just take on the nationality of the mother
                        then. As a Puerto Rican, this mother was an American citizen, but if she'd
                        been Venezuelan, the baby would still have been an American.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: This was a first time for the captain, too, he'd never flown a flight
                    when a baby was born on board. Anyway, we went to the hotel, and I immediately
                    called the Eastern (airlines) PR people. They already knew, because the guy on
                    the phone said, “Oh, you were the reporter aboard the plane that was asking
                    questions.” He said, “I'm sorry, I want to apologize, but these are company
                    rules, that they cannot give you this kind of information.” I said, “I stayed
                    because I want to follow the story.” He said, “I will be very glad to pick you
                    up at the hotel and take you to the hospital so you can see the lady.” I said,
                    “Wonderful!” So he came and drove my wife and me to the hospital. And there she
                    was, in a room by herself, very young and very tiny. In the interview, she told
                    me that she was on her way to Chicago to join her husband. I asked, “How come
                    you boarded a plane being so close to giving birth?” She said, “Well, it was not
                    very noticeable to begin with, and second, I didn't expect to have the baby for
                    another four or five weeks. She was very nice. Then they put one of those green
                    hospital gowns on me and a mask on my face and we went to the nursery, this lady
                    with me. She was walking already. They took a picture of the mother and
                    baby.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>During the interview, I asked her, “Is this your first baby?” She said, “No, this
                    is my third baby.” I said, “My God, you married very young,” and she said, “Yes”
                    and gave me a special smile. She said, “You want to know something? My first
                    baby was born on a train.” I couldn't believe my ears. I said, “I beg your
                    pardon. Your first baby was born on a train?” “Yes. I was traveling from New
                    Jersey to New York, and I just had the baby right there on the train.” I said,
                    “My God, this is unbelievable! How about the second one?” She laughed, and said,
                    “Well, the second one was born at the airport in St. Thomas, while I was waiting
                    for a flight to go to Puerto Rico.” I said, “You mean you gave birth, the first
                    time on a train, the second one at the airport, and the third one on a plane?”
                    And she said, “Yes sir, this is the truth.” Well, that's the story. Then I had
                    to do a lot of editing, and put it on the air at the Voice.</p>
                <p>I understand that Eastern Airlines took care of the hospital bill, and somebody
                    told me that that girl was going to get a lifetime pass on Eastern so she could
                    fly free. They flew her, with the baby, to Chicago. I gave her my address, and
                    she sent me a clipping from a Chicago newspaper — a big story, with the baby and
                    the husband and she and the whole story — and I have it somewhere in my
                    scrapbooks. So I think that's something that's extraordinary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not going to ask you for another one, because nothing
                        could top that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: I don't think anything could top that. As I said, you can go and cover
                    one war or another one, you can interview one president and another one, but
                    something like this I don't think will ever happen again in my life. It was
                    unbelievable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It certainly is. But I have to believe you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Let me tell you who else was on that flight, who could be a witness:
                    Guillermo Portuondo, our (VOA Spanish) sportscaster, who had been covering some
                    sports events in Puerto Rico.</p>
                <p>Importance of Complimenting the “Troops” — “Little Things Mean A Lot!”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Changing the subject drastically — what would you suggest
                        as a means of helping to improve the morale or working conditions at
                        VOA?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>DEL RIO: I'd like to see something like incentives for the people that work at
                    the Voice. I will use the word troops, and by that I mean simple announcers,
                    writers. Incentives. When you work at the Voice, or in a private organization,
                    you don't expect a pat on your shoulder every day; that's overdoing things. But
                    I think that in the Voice, due to the work that we do, the people should be
                    reminded more often by the supervisors, by the chiefs — the higher the better —
                    that they are doing a good job. I think that's a wonderful incentive that
                    promotes the creativity in the people. We don't have that at the Voice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in recent years, Pepe, there has been a significant
                        increase in the awards program, honoring every quarter programs put out by
                        the Persian Service or the Latin American Division or the whoever.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: All right, you might have that kind of awards, that go only to one or
                    two are dealing with human beings, with people, and in this kind of work many of
                    us, you know, have big egos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's also the tendency because there's so much to be
                        done by so few people. People are too busy to acknowledge what other people
                        are doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: That's another good example, you know. Sometimes when we have these
                    blizzards in Washington, and you're supposed to operate with seven or eight
                    people and all of a sudden you have only three. Well, the next day, buy a cup of
                    coffee for these people, tell them, “Hey, you were great, only three people
                    handled the job of ten.” Little things like that I think are important. It
                    boosts the morale of people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What else do you want to talk about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: (JPDR muses about retirement, his own and others, and about his new
                    career as Washington correspondent of a Spanish-language U. S. network)</p>
                <p>I wanted to stay longer at the Voice. I retired because of my health; I couldn't
                    cope with the pressures of a daily program like that. That would take a lot out
                    of anyone, especially if he does it with his heart. My doctors advised me not to
                    go farther, and I decided to retire. Sometimes I listen to the Voice in the
                    morning and at night, and I listen to many other international short-wave
                    stations. That's something that everybody that works at the Voice of America — I
                    don't care what language — should do, so that they know what the competition,
                    the other side is doing. It'll give you a more realistic perspective on what
                    you're facing. I think that a guy that writes a story or translates a story and
                    gets it edited and goes to the studio and records it, and that's it — but in
                    order to analyze where that story is going to and what it's supposed to do —
                    it's not just punching a clock and I'm through. I think that's very
                    important.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They need to know the context into which they are
                        broadcasting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Right. You have to listen to what the other people are doing — the
                    sound, to begin with, what kind of voices they have, their delivery, their
                    content. Then compare with what you're doing. I listen — in Spanish — to BBC, I
                    listen to Radio Moscow, I listen to Radio Havana, Radio Peking, Radio Praga in
                    Czechoslovakia, Radio Vaticano, La Voz de los Andes, Radio Canada, Radio
                    Nacional de Espana, Radio Israel. That gives you a different dimension of what's
                    going on. And I'm sure that if I went back to international radio I might make
                    some changes in order to compete. I have more time now to listen. Sometimes it's
                    two o'clock in the morning and I'm listening to short-wave radio.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what else is on your mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>DEL RIO: Well, I know that somewhere here in the States, and somewhere in Latin
                    America, there are a lot of professionals that are dreaming of coming up and
                    working for the Voice of America. That's a fact. Why? Because the Voice of
                    America is an institution, a respected institution. My only advice to these guys
                    is, if they come to work at the Voice of America, try to do it with all their
                    hearts. Not just try to fulfill the agreement, the job description, but try to
                    put their hearts in it and I'm sure they will find very satisfactory
                    results.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you, Pepe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
