<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000475">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Paul D. Harkins </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project, Lyndon Baines Johnson Library</p>
                <p>PAUL D. HARKINS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Ted Gittinger</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: November 10, 1981</p>
                <p>Q: General Harkins, will you begin by giving us a brief sketch of your military
                    career before your assignment to Vietnam in 1962?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, my goodness, that starts back in 1922 when I joined the Boston
                    National Guard just to learn how to ride a horse because I figured only soldiers
                    and millionaires could ride horses on the weekends. And I ended up forty-two
                    years later in Vietnam without a horse, but I went to West Point from the
                    National Guard. Then I joined the horse cavalry at Fort Bliss and then went to
                    the cavalry school in 1933. I stayed there for six years; I was an instructor
                    after two years in courses there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that at Leavenworth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, this was at the cavalry school at Fort Riley.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And I took the advanced equitation course. Then I stayed on there as an
                    instructor in riding for four years. Then I went to Fort Myer. While at Riley, I
                    served with General [George] Patton for a while; he was the director of
                    instruction for a short term. And I went to Fort Myer and he was the commanding
                    officer of the regiment at Myer, the Third Cavalry, and I had F Troop with the
                    Third Cavalry. From there I was on maneuvers with the Second Armored. I joined
                    the Armored Division because that was the thing to do for horse cavalrymen in
                    those days. I was on maneuvers in Louisiana and got a telephone call. General
                    Gay had called, Colonel Gay at that time. He was with General Patton. He asked
                    me if I wanted to go with them, and I said, “Where are you going?” And he said,
                    “I can't tell you.” And I said, “Sure.” (Laughter) So I went as deputy chief of
                    staff for the Western Task Force, and we landed in Africa just about thirty-nine
                    years ago yesterday, as a matter of fact, the eighth..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Operation Torch.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, Operation Torch. After that, we went into Sicily, which I hada lot
                    to do with the writing of the invasion of Sicily. We had a bet, General
                    [Geoffrey] Keyes, who was General Patton's deputy commander, General Gay, myself
                    and General Patton all bet how long it would take to do Sicily. General Patton
                    said ninety days, General Keyes said eighty-five, General Gay said ninety-five,
                    and I said forty-five. We did it in thirty-eight, so I won thirty dollars.
                    (Laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thirty dollars. Which was more then than it is now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Then from there we went up to Europe and had the Third Army. General
                    Patton had the Third Army, and as you know, we went through [Europe]. I wrote a
                    book as a matter of fact, When the Third Cracked Europe. It's a short book; I
                    did it in conjunction with the Army Times.</p>
                <p>From Europe I came back and went to West Point where I was assistant commandant
                    for two years, and then I was commandant for three. In 1951 I went to the
                    Pentagon with General [Maxwell] Taylor who had sort of adopted me after General
                    Patton - I was with him for several years. I ran into General Taylor. He was the
                    G-3 of the army at that time, and I was made chief of plans. He went to Korea
                    and he had me ordered over to Korea. He was the commander in Korea and I was his
                    chief of staff in the Eighth Army. Then I commanded the Forty-fifth Division
                    Infantry, and that was sent home, so they gave me the Twenty-fourth Division. I
                    stayed in Korea for another six months.</p>
                <p>I came back to the Pentagon and I was in the international branch which ran the
                    MAAGS and the missions all over the world We had missions and MAAGS in forty-two
                    different countries, so I got to see the world going out and seeing them. Then
                    General Taylorcame back and was chief of staff and he Sent me to Izmir, Turkey,
                    where I commanded the Greek and Turkish Armies in the NATO chain. I was there
                    for three years in Izmir. From Izmir I went to Hawaii where I was deputy army
                    commander to General I. D. White.</p>
                <p>From there I was sent to Vietnam, stayed there two and a half years,and I retired
                    from Vietnam in 1964.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had a misapprehension. I thought you were Commander U.S.
                        ArmPacific.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I was deputy. General White was the commander.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. I see. Had you been able to monitor developments
                        iVietnam while you were in Hawaii?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, yes. We had a little task force there. As a matter of fact we had a
                    task force that was going into Laos if anything happened in Laos, and I was the
                    commander. I had a marine brigade and an air wing and we were in the Philippines
                    already. All the planes were lined up on the runway, but nobody ever knew about
                    it, and we had five thousand men there. I'd go to the club at night and play
                    bridge in civilian clothes, of course, and nobody knew that I was lieutenant
                    general and sitting there ready to invade Laos. But they made a deal with Laos,
                    and we were called back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. What was your general impression of the situation
                        iVietnam before you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, you could see after the French left it was deteriorating because
                    that's when they asked us for help. And that's when we decided to go ahead and
                    help them. They were trying to stop the communist inroads through the Viet Cong,
                    land they just weren't qualified to do it at that time. They didn't have the
                    know-how, and their army wasn't - you see, the French wouldn't let them command
                    anything. There was only one general in the whole Vietnamese Army under the
                    French, and he was a sort of a figurehead. And they'd never let them go and see
                    the Montagnards. That was taboo as far as the French were concerned.</p>
                <p>So they learned a lot after the French took out. The Montagnards, of course,
                    wanted to have their own government and that was difficult. Then there were two
                    or three sort of private armies; they were the Cao Dais and the Hoa Haos and
                    they were all fighting each other. Finally they had to put the regular army
                    against them and disarm all these religious groups. It was sort of a mixed-up
                    affair for a while.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, General Maxwell Taylor visited Vietnam in order to report to President
                    Kennedy just a few months before you were assigned to Saigon. Did you have a
                    chance to talk to him on his way back?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, yes, we had him out to dinner, as a matter of fact, and he didn't
                    do too much discussing. That was on the way out. On the way back, he stopped and
                    he called me from the airport, I think.' He said, “Get ready to put your finger
                    in the dike.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were those his words?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Those were his words, and I said, “Thank you very much.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>HARKINS: So he went back and reported. I guess that was in December or it was in
                    late fall, and on New Year's Eve, I got a call. He said, “Be prepared to go to
                    Washington on the day after New Year's.” I said, “For what?” He said, “Well,
                    never mind. You're going to Washington.” So I flew back to Washington and went
                    down to see the President, President Kennedy, down in his Florida home - Palm
                    Beach - and he told me I was going to be the commander in Vietnam and that I was
                    then made a four-Star general as of that date. He said it would probably be a
                    month before I went out there but be ready to go. I went out in February.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the President, would you say, concerned
                        especially?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, he didn't seem to be at that time. He said, “I want you to go out
                    and help President [Ngo Dinh] Diem do everything he can to stop these communist
                    inroads and build up his army. There are about eight hundred advisers there now,
                    and if you need more let us know and we'll do everything we can to help.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the usual tour for an officer commanding the
                        MAAG?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I think at that time it was about a year</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About a year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was pretty - I think General [Samuel] Williams
                        wathere four.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, that's true, and then I think General [Lionel] McGarwas there for a
                    couple of years, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just about a year and a half. That's why I was curious.
                        Was theranything special about the circumstances of his leaving?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, apparently when General Taylor talked to McGarr, he wasn't too
                    impressed. But I think McGarr was more or less right, because General Taylor
                    said he should prevent all the infiltration. Well, you know when you have nine
                    hundred miles of jungle and then a few soldiers and just tiger paths and
                    elephant paths, it's pretty hard to defend a whole front like that. He said,
                    “Well, it's an almost impossible thing to do.” Which it was. Particularly the
                    infiltration from Laos.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your impression was that General Taylor was not happy
                        witGeneral McGarr's performance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That's right. And then as soon as I went out there, McGarwas
                    relieved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a chance to talk to him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, yes. I visited him two or three times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did he have to say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, he said it was just impossible to guard the border like that, and
                    he told me that when the war was over, [when] the French gave up, the North
                    Vietnamese took about thirty thousand youngsters up North and trained them, and
                    after they had trained them, sent them back to rejoin their villages. They were
                    sort of indoctrinated - they were brainwashed, really - and they became
                    believers in the communist cause. They formed little cells throughout the
                    villages and all over Vietnam and when they got them formed, they were told to
                    stay still and keep undercover until they were told to rise up. And they were
                    told to rise up about, I guess, 1959, 1960. That's when the war started in
                    forty-three different provinces, and they had forty-three wars going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard that quote several times.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, that's true. Every province was different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your initial impressions when you arrived in
                        Vietnam? mean, the sorts of things you notice when you step off the
                        plane.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: The first thing I noticed was the security; I mean, you couldn't do
                    anything. All the windows had steel blinds on them, and all the curtains were
                    pulled down. I said, “Let's open this up and get some daylight in here.” That's
                    the first thing. Even the house I lived in had steel shutters closed tight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were those left over from the French war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, they were left over from McGarr's doing.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I said, “Let's put some light on the subject so we can see out.” And we
                    did. I was always - I guess I was born an optimist - a little more optimistic
                    than the people there who had been there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Saigon like when you [were there]?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Saigon was just a good old French city, the Pearl of the Orient.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the security situation in the countryside?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Very loose, because what they did, the Vietnamese had built forts, and
                    they had about sixteen thousand forts at different crossroads and canals and
                    things like that. They'd man those forts at night and they'd patrol all day.
                    Well, when the Viet Cong found that out, they just did all their night work, and
                    nobody was patrolling. They had to live there with their families, the
                    Vietnamese did, and that wasn't too good, too, because they had to protect their
                    families. So I finally got them to get rid of most of these outposts or forts,
                    and I think they were down to about six thousand after -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's still a pretty considerable number.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, yes. They kept them on where canals would cross down in the Delta
                    area, on roads, important roads, but it just pinned them down. You knew where
                    they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the advisory effort going when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: It was coming along, just very, very slowly. They were still having
                    siestas in the afternoon, which I stopped. I mean, you couldn't fight a war and
                    go to sleep from twelve to three and then not expect the enemy to do
                    something.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a five or six-day week as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, at that time. We changed that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Vietnamese government making much progress with
                        itvarious reform programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think that's what caused the people in the North to tell the people in
                    the South to rise up, the ones they'd sent back. Because when we took over in
                    1954, we initiated what was called a five-year program, and that would build
                    more canals, build more roads, build airfields, build up the army. And it was
                    going very, very well. As a matter of fact, the Vietnamese were exporting about
                    three hundred thousand tons of rice a year. Well, when you could do that and
                    still feed all the people in Vietnam, you can see the programs are going well.
                    They were going so well, that's when they were told to rise up. That's when the
                    little cells in the different villages started raising hell. They'd go
                    immediately to the head guys and knock them off: the province chiefs, the
                    village chiefs, the schoolteachers, the people in the government. If a village
                    chief could sleep in the same bed twice in a row, he knew his place was all
                    right. But if he couldn't, it was not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The strategic hamlet program was getting a lot of
                        publicity abouthis time. How was that going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, that didn't start really until -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hadn't started yet?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, no, it hadn't started until 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That was more or less under Mr. [Ngo Dinh] Nhu, Diem's brother, and the
                    British helped with it, because they had done it in Malaya, I think it was
                    pretty good as a matter of fact. We had goals of getting at least 75 to 80 per
                    cent of the people in the hamlets. And the trouble was that these little cells
                    went right in with them, because they were part of the village, so that you were
                    putting the VC in the hamlets as well as the people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you deal with a problem like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, that's the trouble, you couldn't. Because they were so
                    indoctrinated that they told the people there, and they'd persuade many of the
                    peasants because the peasants weren't the most brilliant people in the world,
                    you know. They'd believe what they hear.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Q: There was a lot of speculation - I'm not sure when it begins, but from very
                    early times - about advisers engaging in combat. We were constantly, I
                    understand, having to reassure the press that this was not the case.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, that was one of the things. They did go on patrols with them, but
                    they had instructions not to shoot back or shoot unless they were shot at first.
                    So they actually - I know there was a big to-do when one of the advisers got
                    killed, and that was just north of Saigon. He was the son of an army officer
                    whom I knew, and I got all sorts of chit-chat on that because they didn't think
                    the advisers should go out to combat. But you couldn't teach them how to Patrol
                    or anything else unless you went along with them.</p>
                <p>Q: That's a very fine, I suppose. What about the air element? There was a lot of
                    speculation that U.S. pilots were flying missions, for example.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: They were flying with the Vietnamese, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that the Farmgate program, I think it was called?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, and of course they didn't have many planes. I think they only had
                    forty- five planes in the whole country at that time, and when they put them
                    between Danang and Hue and Dalat, the South in Saigon, you had about three or
                    four planes in each place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. How serious was the infiltration problem? HARKINS:
                        It was bad when I got there, and it got worse and worse.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How good was our intelligence about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Not too good in the beginning, and that's why we increased
                    theintelligence effort. The first thing we did, I guess we brought in, oh, eight
                    or nine hundred intelligence people to see if they could improve. Because the
                    Vietnamese didn't know what to do with intelligence. I mean, if they captured a
                    Viet Cong lieutenant or something, they'd immediately leave their post and bring
                    them all the way into Saigon and present him to Mr. Diem. That's the way they
                    did their intelligence, without talking to them and asking them where they came
                    from and how big the outfit was and things like that. They didn't use that. They
                    didn't know much about intelligence.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there some disagreement about this? Because I recall reading a National
                    Intelligence Estimate of about 1961 which was prepared by the CIA which said
                    that they estimated that 80 to 90 per cent of the Viet Cong main force units
                    were local recruits, and they tended to play down the infiltration problem. Was
                    this an item of controversy?</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I think in the beginning there weren't very many big Viet Cong
                    units. I think most of them were about platoon size or squad size that would do
                    all the infiltrating. I think the first time we noticed a Viet Cong battalion in
                    action was at the Battle of Ap Bac - I used to call it My Aching Back - but
                    that's when they did use a battalion. And we flew a parachute regiment down to
                    drop into the fields and surround them. But when they get down, the whole
                    battalion would disappear. They'd just disappear in the jungle and the swamps
                    and they weren't a battalion anymore, but they were available.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We suffered some heavy losses in that engagement, I
                        believe,didn't we?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, not too bad. I mean, the Viet Cong took Ap Bac, but we took it back,
                    the Vietnamese took it back the next day. So I mean it was just like going
                    through France, you'd lose a city and then take it the next day. Yes, we did
                    suffer some casualties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The press got hold of that in a big way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that why you called it My Aching Back?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: My Aching Back.</p>
                <p>Q: There are some things that lead off of that I want to come back to later, but
                    were you still pretty worried about the possibility of an invasion from the
                    North at that time? How big a factor was that in our thinking?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: It was pretty big, because we had a lot of stuff up there on the front
                    line, I mean, the Vietnamese. But the main thing was the infiltration from Laos
                    and Cambodia. That was the thing that was-bothersome.</p>
                <p>Q: How much of your military resources did you have to devote to guarding against
                    the possibility that they might cross the DMZ, as they had done in Korea, for
                    example?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, I can't remember the exact figures, but I think thaprobably five or
                    six divisions were up there in that First Corps area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pretty considerable. What we called I Corps?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>HARKINS: I Corps, yes. Then there were a couple of the Second Corps and then
                    there were more around Saigon and then the Delta area had the rest of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You mentioned the British in Malaya and so on. Were they active in Saigon in
                    offering advice and designing programs and so on to cope with the insurgency
                    problem?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I had close contact with their adviser who had also beeresponsible for
                    the strategic hamlet program of the British in Malaya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that General [Robert] Thompson, I believe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, I think his name was Thompson. And he was very fine,very helpful as
                    a matter of fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were our relations with the British, would you call them
                        cordial?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, yes, very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Diem? You can find all sorts of opinion about
                        Diem.What were his ideas on combating the insurgency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, to me he was fine. He knew more about that part of the world and
                    the different people in it than anybody I ever knew. He was a stubborn
                    individual, but I got along very well with him and I saw him two or three times
                    a week probably. He was always very gracious to me. As a matter of fact, I'm the
                    only one he spoke English to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I didn't know he spoke English.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought he always spoke French.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He did. Except to me.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I'll be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He lived in America, you know, for two or three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. At Maryknoll Seminary, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And we got along fine. I had quite an admiration for him, because he
                    wasn't storing wealth away. He wasn't cheating any. He only had two suits, one
                    white to greet visitors and one brown one when he went in the field, and every
                    time we went in the field, he'd take some money along and give it to the honor
                    guard or the province chief or the village chief. He'd go out and he knew
                    agriculture; he'd teach them how to sow seeds and how to transplant rice and
                    things like that. And he was really - he had appointed all the generals. There
                    were I think nineteen generals in the whole Vietnamese army, so he knew them all
                    personally. Yet some of them were opposed to him, and I couldn't understand
                    that. Because the first time I met General Don, he said, “We're not going to get
                    anyplace until we get rid of Diem.” And he was a major general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Tran Van Don?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. And I couldn't believe that, because everybody thought Don was one
                    of the finest generals there. Well, he was, but he was a sort of political
                    general. He wasn't a combat general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was very senior, I think, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, he was senior. And [General Duong Van] Big Minh, who had really
                    helped Diem put down the Hoa Haos and the Cao Dais, he was given a desk job in
                    Saigon as a security adviser to the President, and he saw him once a week on a
                    Saturday morning. But I couldn't ever get Big Minh to go out with me and see
                    what the war was, I don't know why. But I'd go in and report to Diem as to what
                    was going on in the different villages and provinces, because I was out every
                    day. I don't think there was a place in Vietnam I didn't visit. I'd come back
                    and tell Diem what was going on, and Big Minh would usually go with me to see
                    the President, and he said, “Why don't you go out like General Harkins?” Well,
                    he didn't have the plane, he didn't have the personnel. I took him out once or
                    twice, but it was hard to get him to go out. As a military adviser, I don't know
                    what he did, as a matter of fact, because he didn't know what was going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard it rumored that Diem kept Minh in Saigon
                        because hwas afraid of Minh's political clout because Minh was so
                        popular.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, he was. That could have been true. Yes, I guess he waunder the
                    gun.</p>
                <p>Q: In February, as I recall, of 1962, I believe it was, two pilots - renegade
                    pilots I suppose you would call them - bombed the presidential palace. Do you
                    recall that incident?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Indeed I do. I had just got there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That was the first attempted coup, and I heard the bombing about seven
                    o'clock in the morning. I looked out and there from my hotel room I could see
                    the palace was burning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my. What were your thoughts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I thought, “What do I do now?” I still hadn't shaved yet. So I got over
                    to the office and I drove up to see that the palace was still burning and
                    finally I found out that Diem was fine and was in his office and I went down to
                    see him. And he said, “Well, we captured one of them. I shouldn't have put him
                    in the air force, because I had put his father in jail years ago.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember the name by any chance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I don't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I haven't heard it mentioned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He said, “If I'd realized what I'd done to his father, wouldn't have
                    made him a pilot.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they capture him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think one of them got shot down. There were two planes.One escaped, I
                    think, into Cambodia, and the other got shot down.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Q: I'd heard a story that ever after that, Diem required his personal approval
                    for anybody to take off with five hundred pound bombs aboard. Is there any truth
                    in that?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't know about that, but I wouldn't be surprised.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any aftereffects of this? Diem, naturally, I suppose this had an
                    impact on him.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: That was the second attempt at a coup and when I visited him shortly
                    after that, he said, “Well, that's the second one.” And he said, “Sometime I'm
                    going to get shot right in the back of the neck.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He told you that himself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. He said, “Sometime they'll get me that way.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My goodness. Well, not too far from the truth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That's what happened, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me get you to talk about Laos for a minute. How did
                        thLaotian situation affect the Vietnamese situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, it was just a camp for the Viet Cong. And the trouble was, we
                    could send Vietnamese patrols across the border, but then they put a stop to
                    that - and I think the State Department put a stop to that - that you couldn't
                    go into [Laos].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did they do that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't know. So we still sent the patrols, and where there was the
                    border along South Vietnam and Laos, [it] wasn't marked at all. It was just
                    watershed, really, at the top of the hills. There are two or three roads that
                    go, and they'd pick up the road sign and take it with them and put it back when
                    they came back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're carrying the border along.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: But they wouldn't allow the Americans to go. And the planecouldn't fly
                    within a mile or two of the border.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: So it was an impossible thing. If the Viet Cong came over and made a
                    raid, say up around Pleiku and places like that, and you got the division to
                    chase them back, you couldn't follow them. You weren't allowed to. So it was a
                    sanctuary for them. Remember President Nixon ordered a raid into Laos and got
                    very severely criticized about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course that was a very large-scale operation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, it was. But they broke up a big training camp dowthere.</p>
                <p>Q: It was rumored - not rumored, it was reported pretty reliably, I think, that
                    many South Vietnamese were alarmed at the compromise settlement that was made
                    finally in Laos.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, absolutely. Particularly Diem. That's when the battle cry went up
                    “We've got to get rid of Diem.” He told [Averell] Harriman - Mr. Harriman, he
                    made the deal and said they were going to put anon-communist government in Laos.
                    Three guys, two of them were communist and one wasn't. And Mr. Diem told him
                    point blank, he said,”If you put that government in Laos, and put a communist
                    government next to my borders, I'm going to withdraw my ambassador from
                    Vientiane.” And Harriman put the government in, I think that was May of
                    1962,probably, and he did pull his ambassador out of Vientiane. Well, here we
                    are trying to run a foreign country, and he said,”Okay. We'll start the cry,
                    'We've got to make some changes. We've got to get rid of [Diem].'”</p>
                <p>Q: Was Diem afraid that we might do the same thing in Vietnam someday?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: What do you mean?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sell him out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't think so, as far as I know. He might have to some of the other
                    people but not to me, I never felt that way. But it could have been.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I mentioned the phrase to you, the Averell Harriman
                        MemoriaHighway, does that bring up any memories?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's what certain people I know called the Ho Chi Minh
                        Trail.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh. That's a new one. I hadn't beard that before.(Laughter) It's a good
                    name for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think it's a good name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. He and [Roger] Hilsman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, Hilsman. Well, we'll come to him I hope. How did you
                        regarthat settlement in Laos at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I sort of felt that they were making it more difficult for us, because
                    here was a communist country on the border of one we didn't want to be
                    communist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, they were not saying it was communist. They
                        said iwas -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No but it was run by two communists, one who didn't have much to say. He
                    was sort of a figurehead. I think there were two brothers. I think they were
                    cousins, but they were related, yes.</p>
                <p>Q: Let me ask you to talk about the relations within the American country team in
                    Saigon. How were your relations with Ambassador [Frederick] Nolting, for
                    example?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Absolutely perfect. He was one of the best I've ever seeand ever dealt
                    with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, he's just my type of man. He is a very fine ambassador. He went
                    out with me on most of my trips. He got around the country. He was entirely
                    different from [Henry Cabot] Lodge. Nolting would get out and see what was going
                    on throughout the country, and when Lodge came over, he said everything that
                    happens in Vietnam happens in Saigon, so he never left. When we'd go on trips,
                    Nolting and I and Diem would probably go together in a helicopter or a plane,
                    and when Lodge got there, I was always with Diem and he was in the second plane,
                    and he didn't like that at all. And he didn't like going around one bit. He was
                    a loner. Well, I can't say all I want to say about him.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we'll come back to it. Under Ambassador Nolting,
                        werthere ever disagreements between you and Nolting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No. Never. We just got along just hand-glove, reallfine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He was something like Ambassador [Ellis O.] Briggs, who was in South
                    America when I went down to visit and also he was in Greece, and to me he was
                    fine.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, you were in a position to have had some experience with relations between
                    MAAG chiefs and ambassadors, I suppose, from your previous Pentagon experience.
                    Was it common for a MAAG Chief to have difficulties with his ambassador?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I never noticed it particularly. I visited them all ovethe world and
                    they never complained about it.</p>
                <p>Q: I've heard it said that sometimes there was tension because the ambassador is
                    always bringing the bad news and the MAAG chief is the guy with the goodies, and
                    the head of state tends to try to play one off against the other if he can get
                    away with it.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I wouldn't be surprised at that. I know when I would report on the
                    up side, people would say, “Well, it isn't that way at all.” At least you had to
                    make them feel that way, and I think it was, everything was going fine. But I
                    knew that if anything happened to Diem the thing would collapse, and it did. And
                    I tried my very best not to let that happen, but I was sort of overruled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's another thing I want to come back to. How did
                        AmbassadoNolting get along with Diem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you [say] more or less like you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. Every time he went he asked me to go with him, and every time I
                    went I'd ask him to go with me. But sometimes we could get together and go or
                    sometimes we'd just go alone. But we always reported to each other what the
                    conversation was and what we were going to talk about with Diem.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Diem speak English to Nolting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No. French.</p>
                <p>Q: For some reason that really intrigues me. I had never heard anybody say that
                    Diem spoke English to them before, and I just assumed that he couldn't speak
                    English.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, he wasn't really articulate, but we understood each other. And we
                    were walking along one day and speaking, [he said], “You know, you're the only
                    one I speak English to.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you speak French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, I've studied it, but I couldn't do the technical business. I could
                    listen to the conversation and know what they were talking about. But when I get
                    into technical discussions or anything like that, I wouldn't know the words to
                    use.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you, in general, characterize the quality of
                        thcountry team in Saigon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: When [John] Richardson and Nolting were there, they were fine, it was
                    great. When Lodge came over, and [William] Trueheart was there, it was not
                    good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now Trueheart preceded Lodge, though. He was there under
                        Nolting,wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He was there as deputy of Nolting, and he was on the otheside of the
                    fence. He wanted to get rid of Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: You see, Nolting was away when things happened here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That summer of 1963.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. He had a month's leave; he hadn't had a leave since he'd been
                    there. And Trueheart took over then. When Nolting came back he asked me what on
                    earth had happened, and Diem told Nolting that if he had been there it wouldn't
                    have happened, but under Trueheart things just started to go wrong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When we talk about the coup, I want to come back to that a
                        littlbit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: You mean in August.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, sir. Well, beginning in August right. Were there problems, dissensions
                    between agencies in Saigon that you know of? I'm thinking of nothing in
                    particular, but I'm picking the CIA and AID, for example.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I think that under Nolting there weren't anproblems, under Lodge
                    there were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does this have anything to do with the timing of the
                        thing? Odo you think Lodge caused the problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Lodge caused the problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Now, in his book, which I didn't read all of it except for what involved
                    me, he said that he had a secret channel that he couldn't show to me. He had a
                    secret channel with the President, President Johnson, and he was very sorry,
                    that I was his close friend, but I wasn't in on it. Well, I'm not sure that's
                    the truth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That you were his close friend or that was the reason -
                        ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I had known him ever since 1925. We were both from Boston.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't you both go to Boston Latin I heard somewhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>HARKINS: I went to Boston Latin, I don't know whether he did or not. But he used
                    to be a very close friend of General Crittenberger's, and he used to come down
                    to Fort Bliss on maneuvers, and I got to know him very, very well. But when the
                    reports came in in Washington, General Taylor and Mr. [Robert] McNamara would
                    get them and go up and see the President, and the President would say, “Well,
                    what does Harkins think about that?” And they'd say, “Well, he doesn't think
                    anything because he hasn't seen the messages.” He said, “Well, I want him to see
                    the messages.” I'm not sure that there was a secret channel, because I'm sure
                    Taylor would have known about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did Diem's problems begin in your opinion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: In the Laos -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the spring of 1962?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. When they put the communist government into Laos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you be more specific? How did this begin Diem's
                        long, slodecline?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, that's when Harriman told him he couldn't pull the ambassador out
                    of Vientiane, but he did. And then the State Department just didn't like
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: From then on they weren't very favored toward Diem.</p>
                <p>Q: Some people who have written on this subject could make a good deal of State
                    Department versus Defense Department attitude. Is that a good way to put it?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. I think that's true. We were trying to save Diem and build up their
                    army, and they were trying to get rid of Diem and that's what caused the
                    attempted coup in August.</p>
                <p>Q: I see. Of course, the problem as it was reported begins with the troubles
                    between Diem and the Buddhists, as they were called, although of course they
                    weren't all Buddhists. What were the sources of discontent in the country with
                    Diem?</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, it's hard to say, because actually in the five-year plan, not only
                    in building canals and roads and airfields, Diem, who was a Catholic of course -
                    there were seventeen people in his cabinet and there were only three Catholics
                    in the cabinet; Vice President [Nguyen Ngoc] Tho was a Buddhist and all the
                    others were Buddhists -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the cabinet have much power, however?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: -and he built as many pagodas as he did churches, but they were also
                    infiltrated from the North. I mean, at least they were brainwashed, and they
                    started these things about raiding pagodas and things like that. Then the press
                    got on it, particularly led by this guy [David] Halberstam from the New York
                    Times. If you ever look up the press reports in those days, you'll find
                    Halberstam would write them and then hand out the circulars to all the other
                    press guys and they'd actually put in the same thing, change a few words here
                    and there. But Halberstam was a Jew, and he didn't like Diem. He was on the side
                    to get rid of Diem and they wrote about “Thirty bonzes killed in a raid on a
                    pagoda.” Well, there were no bonzes killed in any raid on any pagoda all the
                    time I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that a fact?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And they talked about Buddhist battalions fighting Catholic battalions.
                    Well, there weren't any Buddhist battalions, as such, to fight Catholic
                    battalions as such. And those are the reports you get back here.</p>
                <p>Q: Still, there seems to have been a lot of popular unrest in Hue, for example,
                    in that summer, led by people like Thich Tri Quang, I believe.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: He was a Buddhist, and his brother was a communist up in North Vietnam.
                    I think he was a press man, as a matter of fact. And again, it's a matter of
                    brainwashing and causing this upset and another plot to get rid of Diem. And the
                    Buddhists - they just blow everything way out of importance, as far as I'm
                    concerned. As a matter of fact, I guess when I talked with General [Le Van] Ty
                    who was there - he died as a matter of fact while I was there; he was the head
                    guy of the Vietnamese Army, T-Y-I asked him about the Buddhist things. He said,
                    “Well, when the French took a census when they first came over there, they'd go
                    into the religious [question] and ask the people what they were. Well, actually,
                    they were ancestor worshipers. They worshiped their ancestors. They lived and
                    died in the same place their ancestors did. Well, that wasn't a religion to the
                    French, so they said, 'Okay, you're a Buddhist.'” So they named 90 percent of
                    the people Buddhists, and they weren't really, truly Buddhists.</p>
                <p>Q: How many practicing Buddhists do you think there were, perhaps, in the
                    country? Is there any way to tell?</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Ty said there's probably about - I forget the population, but it was I
                    think seventeen million in the whole country. And he said probably about 30 per
                    cent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how many Catholics?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: About 10 per cent.</p>
                <p>Q: About l0 per cent. Now, in the summer of 1963, things began to come apart, it
                    seems. Can you tell me what was your view of how that happened, what the
                    progression of events was?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, this is the Harriman-Hilsman thing. They sent a telegram. The CIA
                    had been working with the generals, led by Big Minh, for the overthrow of
                    Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that Richardson's boys?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think he had gone with Nolting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Richardson left about October, I think, early
                        October o1963.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I guess it was still him then. But his people had been working
                    with the State Department and the CIA to get the generals, telling them that if
                    they overthrew Diem, we'd back them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought Richardson was pro-Diem. Or is that a
                        mistake?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He was.</p>
                <p>Q: He was? HARKINS: But he went along with the new regime of Harriman-Hilsman to
                    get rid of Diem. So they sent a telegram to have somebody contact the generals
                    and tell them what they would do if they overthrew Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the famous August 24 [1963] telegram?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. Twenty-third or -fourth. So they nominated this guy named [Lucien]
                    Conein - CIA man - and Conein went up to see Big Minh, and through [Tran Thien]
                    Khiem, K-H-I-E-M, who I think was chief of staff at that time, Big Minh said,
                    “No, I don't want to see him. I want to see somebody in authority.” So Mr.
                    Lodge, who found out that Big Minh wouldn't see Conein, immediately sent back
                    word to the State Department and in a flash message, I think. So the message
                    came back and said, “Well, have General Harkins see him.” So I was dragged into
                    it and told what was going on. I got hold of Khiem and asked him to come down to
                    my office. I didn't want to go out to see him at his place, because he had been
                    G3 and we had worked on different things before. So he came down to the office
                    and I just saw him all by myself and told him what I was going to propose. And
                    he said, “Well, I'll let you know.” I said, “If Big Minh is ready, let me know.”
                    Well, he got the word back from Big Minh, he said, “They're not ready. The
                    generals weren't ready.” So when I had to report that to Lodge, that ended that
                    right there. Big Minh said the generals weren't ready. Well, as a matter of
                    fact, they weren't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was holding them up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, they didn't have everything organized. There were about twelve of
                    them that would go along with the generals, and the others were on the fence,
                    particularly [General Nguyen] Khanh, who headed the First Corps up in the north.
                    He was not in on it at all. Then when they finally took over in November when
                    they killed Diem, there were thirteen generals on the committee, and you just
                    can't run a country by a committee. It doesn't work. And it didn't work. I mean,
                    the strategic hamlet program collapsed, the officers in the field, the corps
                    commanders, didn't know whether they were going to stay on, whether they were
                    going to hold their jobs or whether the generals would change them. Some of them
                    came running in to me to see what should they do. Like [General Van Thanh] Cao
                    down in My Tho came up to see me. He was not put in house arrest or anything, he
                    wasn't in on the thing. He was one of the generals, but he didn't go along with
                    it. He said, “What'll I do?” I said, “You better hold your job as long as you
                    can.” And Khanh didn't come in at all until the twenty-eighth of January when he
                    sent word to me that he was growing a beard and he wasn't going to shave it off
                    until he took over.</p>
                <p>Q: That's another thing I want to come back to. To back up for just a second, as
                    I recall there were of course many fact-finding visits by various people in
                    Washington. I had two hundred and fifty a month. One of the things I was going
                    to ask was how you ever got any work done, but -</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I'd just go out.</p>
                <p>Q: One in particular that sticks in my mind was made by General [Victor] Krulak
                    and Mr. [Joseph A.] Mendenhall. Do you remember that one specifically?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, very well. Krulak went all over the country. I gave him a plane and
                    he went every place. He talked to advisers. Mendenhall stayed in Saigon.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who did he talk to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He talked to the Ambassador, the staff there in the embassy. That's when
                    they went back and reportedly the President asked if they had visited the same
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a famous story. I suppose General Krulak talked to
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, yes, very much so.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, later, just a few weeks after that visit, General Taylor and Secretary
                    McNamara visited. This may have been the third time they came in tandem, I lose
                    count. This was the visit, as I recall, that resulted in a selective suspension
                    of aid to Diem.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: That's right. Unless he did certain things.</p>
                <p>Q: Right. Certain reforms were carried out and so on. Hadn't we told the generals
                    earlier that a suspension of aid should be regarded as a signal?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Not that I know of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd read that, I think, in the Pentagon Papers, that we
                        had tolthe generals that this was our signal that we were ready.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: It could have fit in very well, because soon after they made that
                    announcement General Don came to see me and said; “We'll have a'- new president
                    - “ This is on the twenty-eighth of October, I think. He said, “We'll have a new
                    president by Saturday.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you believe him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I sent the message back to Washington, and I said, “This is what Don
                    says.” And they had the coup. Admiral [Harry D.] Felt was there - was it the
                    first or the second?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had just left, I think, when the coup took place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, because the coup was on when he was there. Q: Oh, it was? I see.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>HARKINS: And they kept the airfield open until his plane took off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And I got a message to him in the air. I said, “The airfield's closed.
                    Don't try to come back because they're having a coup.” That was a Saturday and I
                    was home for lunch, and all hell broke out because I lived near the palace. The
                    soldiers had gone through my place, the people on the roof of the palace were
                    shooting down at the soldiers in the streets and several of the bullets coming
                    into my house, in the front yard, particularly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Mrs. Nolting still there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, Nolting wasn't there. Lodge was there, though. I came home to see if
                    Mrs. Harkins was all right. I called her first, and we had big concrete archways
                    downstairs, and I said, “Just get under one of those archways and stay there
                    until I get there.” And I had a hard time getting home, because the troops were
                    going to attack the palace, which is right close to where I lived. I got back
                    and then I went to the office and found out that Diem had escaped. He and his
                    brother Nhu had gone out through, I don't know, some tunnel and ended up in
                    Cholon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard that that tunnel story was not true, that they
                        simplwalked out. Do you know for sure?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think they had a secret passage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You think so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. To get away. Now, where it came out, I don't know. But when Khanh
                    had taken over and I went through the palace with him and he took me to a
                    stairway that led down, he said, “This is how Diem and Nhu got out.” And it was
                    so far down, I didn't want to go down to walk up the thing. It really went down
                    to the depths.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to keep track very well of what was going on
                        durinthe coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>HARKINS: At that time, yes. Well, yes, I saw Big Minh all the time, and I saw
                    Don. I saw Khiem, and when we went out to visit the country, I mean, I always
                    rode with Big Minh. And there was Khiem and Don usually in the same helicopter
                    with me. It was a French helicopter, one of their own. So I kept right alongside
                    them all the time. But the Buddhists rose up again and the VC took advantage.
                    They'd been trying to get rid of Diem ever since 1954, and it took about one day
                    to do what the Viet Cong had been trying to do for six years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard it speculated by some fairly knowledgeable
                        people thathe-coup caught the VC by surprise -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: By surprise, Absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: -and stole a lot of their thunder for a time. They weren't
                        quitsure how to handle that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That's right. But then when they realized what had happened, they rose
                    up in the villages and said, “Tear these hamlets down and pull down the fences,”
                    because we had put barbed wire around most of the strategic hamlets. They cut
                    all the wire up, filled in the ditches and everything else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you know why Richardson was sent home?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I don't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard it speculated that this was supposed to be a
                        signal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I imagine he wasn't getting along with Lodge. They didn't see
                    eye-to-eye. He was a very close friend of Nhu's, Richardson. I didn't know Nhu
                    too well. I had met with him once or twice. I met with him with General Taylor
                    one day. I had a French interpreter, a young colonel, with me and we went along
                    together. Nhu was talking French and General Taylor was an expert in French, you
                    know, and in order to get out he turned to the interpreter and said,”What is he
                    talking about?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And he said, “That French is something I haven't heard before.” And the
                    interpreter said, “Well, I didn't understand part of it either.” And I don't
                    know what it could have been, because I couldn't understand it.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You don't know the explanation for that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At one time the State Department was pushing the line, I
                        think,that if Diem would get rid of Nhu, that they would settle for
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think so. I think that was the beginning. When Madame Nhu left the
                    country, they probably - blood is thicker than water, you know, and Nhu and Diem
                    were brothers and Diem wouldn't get rid of him. Now, what they could have done
                    easily, and I think for probably all intents and purposes was to put Diem in
                    house confinement with his brother in Dalat. But it didn't work out that way,
                    because this young captain who finally captured them out at Cholon shot
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask you if you knew who pulled the trigger
                        and whgave the order.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't think anybody gave the order. I don't think he was supposed to,
                    but he had them and had their hands tied behind their back in this half-track
                    and just put a bullet right through their heads.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've heard a lot of speculation - have you read Tran Van
                        Don'book? It's not very old, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No.</p>
                <p>Q: He says Xuan gave the order, Mai Huu Xuan was the hatchet man on that job. Mai
                    Huu Xuan. He was, I think, chief of security for Minh. But he thinks Minh gave
                    the order and Xuan had them executed.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't know. I hadn't heard about Xuan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it's just one of many versions, because I think
                        -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't think that Minh would have them shot. I really feein my own
                    heart that I don't think he would.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reaction of Americans in Saigon to the coup?
                        I guesit was mixed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Mixed. I think the embassy and the CIA now - that's another thing. When
                    everything settled after the twenty-third of August attempt, they took off
                    military law and things were going along pretty well again for a while. Then in
                    Lodge's book, now, I was supposed to be very close working with the Ambassador,
                    and I did with Nolting. But he said that he worked with CIA, and this guy Conein
                    again contacted the generals without informing me. That's true, because I didn't
                    know it, but he'd been working with CIA and this man Conein, other generals had,
                    until the twenty-eighth of October when Don came in and told me that they were
                    going to change the government. Later on I found out that they had been working
                    behind my back, which is not a very good way to run the country team.</p>
                <p>Q: I've seen you quoted - I don't know whether it was accurately or not - on
                    October 30 making a very optimistic prognosis for the war and the general
                    situation in Vietnam, or maybe it was October 31. It was very close to the coup,
                    a day or two before. Were you quoted accurately?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't think so. I don't remember the quote.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I have a copy of it here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I felt that way, and I so reported to Taylor and McNamara and as a
                    matter of fact, Mr. McNamara said, “Well, get ready to bring a thousand American
                    troops home.” And we started working on that right away.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, what I would like you to comment on is if you knew that there was a coup
                    in the offing, didn't that affect your optimism in any way?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, not particularly, because I think things in the country, all over
                    the country, were going in our favor at that time. The army was taking over and
                    we had built up the CIDG, the Civil Defense [Civilian Irregular Defense Group],
                    and the province troops, and they had things pretty well under control as a
                    matter of fact at that time.</p>
                <p>Q: Now Lodge, I think, reported a couple of months after the coup when things
                    began to slide downhill, when it became obvious that the military situation was
                    turning around, that in fact the security situation had been deteriorating since
                    the previous spring or some such.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: He didn't know anything about it. He never left Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he wasn't taking your advice on this kind of
                        thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>HARKINS: No, no. We didn't see eye-to-eye at all. I think if Nolting had stayed
                    there, things would have been much different. But every time Lodge would stab me
                    in the back he'd tell Mrs. Harkins how pretty she was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much time did Ambassador Lodge spend at the Cercle
                        Sportif?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Do you mean playing tennis?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: -And swimming. I've heard that he spent a lot of time
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, I think he probably went over in the afternoon every day. I don't
                    know. I never went there, as a matter of fact. I wasn't a tennis player at the
                    time. I didn't have time to, in the first place.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, Diem's other brother, [Ngo Dinh Can], who was up in Hue, I think, that
                    made quite a story, how he was handled. He was arrested and executed, I think,
                    well after the coup, sometime after the coup. Did this case pose some special
                    problems for you?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No. No, I don't remember the Can incident too well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was mainly a political thing. HARKINS: There were
                        so many people being done away with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe how all of this affected the military
                        situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, as I say, the commanders didn't know who to turn to, and they
                    didn't know whether they were going to keep their own jobs or whether they'd be
                    colonels tomorrow, or the generals didn't know if they would be reduced in rank
                    or if they'd be the next ones to go. And they were looking back towards Saigon
                    for guidance, and guidance wasn't coming out of Saigon, because as I say, you
                    can't get guidance from twelve guys who don't see eye-to-eye all the time. So
                    that really they were looking for their own jobs and staying close to home and
                    not getting out with the troops and seeing that the war was carried to the
                    VC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why didn't Minh assert himself and give direction to all
                        of this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't think he was that strong. I think he was a popular man, but I
                    don't think his decisions were very good, and as a matter of fact, that's when
                    General Khanh said, “We're not getting any guidance from Saigon and I'm just
                    going to take over.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to establish a good relationship with the
                        neregime, the Minh regime?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. I got along fine with them, because I knew them all, except one
                    named Thien, I think. He had been out of the country, and I didn't know him at
                    all. But he was a pretty important guy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give me some assessments of character of some of
                        thesguys? What was your assessment of Big Minh? That he was popular?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: That he was popular, but as I say, he was not a decision-maker as far as
                    knowing what to do in the country. Khiem was probably the strongest of them all.
                    He was sort of the one that held them together as chief of staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was Tran Thien Khiem, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: K-H-I-E-M.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And Don, as I say, he wasn't a good military commander. I think he would
                    have been a good ambassador someplace. He was a very polite, nice, easy-going
                    type of man, but not the type that would carry on military thing and go out and
                    see that things were done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did none of Minh's regime impress you particularly as
                        take-charge sort of type?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I don't think there was anyone who showed the leadership, and that's
                    probably why he didn't get any decisions out of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, a couple of weeks after the coup there was one of
                        manHonolulu conferences.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: One a month.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Q: The country team was there, Secretary [Dean] Rusk was there, Secretary
                    McNamara was there, General Taylor, McGeorge Bundy was there, I know that you
                    were there. I don't know what transpired. Did you give a briefing on the
                    military situation? Can you recall?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I usually did. At all those briefings I was asked to give my - Q: Can
                    you recall anything special that transpired then?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Not particularly, that one, no, because I told them what the truth was
                    then, that the whole strategic hamlet program - well, I'm not sure now whether
                    this is after Khanh took over or-</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, this is before Khanh.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Before Khanh took over.</p>
                <p>Q: This would have been probably November, still, of 1963. My information is that
                    you gave a fairly optimistic report and that McNamara expressed a good deal of
                    skepticism, but I don't know if that's true.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't recall. I mean, we had so many different conferences. As a
                    matter of fact, somebody from the Joint Chiefs of Staff was to visit me every
                    month I was there, and of course, Admiral Felt would visit me frequently. Then
                    if they didn't visit, I would have to go back to Hawaii. So it was really a
                    monthly trip. I don't know how many times I've flown the Pacific Ocean, coming
                    and going. You could leave Honolulu, say, at twelve noon and fly in daylight all
                    the way to Saigon and get in to Saigon at 7:00 p.m. the next day. But it would
                    still be daylight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of thing did that do to your biological
                        clock?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I had a couple of bunks on the plane.</p>
                <p>Q: I see. I know that one thing resulted from this conference, at least I have
                    seen a document that says that there was a directive put out that planning
                    begin, I gather contingency planning, for clandestine operations against the
                    North, what later became the 34-A operation. Do you remember the origins of that
                    at all?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No. No. I don't. Sorry.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Q: That's fine. Now, McNamara came again, I think in December of 1963, to Saigon
                    and visited, and I have some indications that he carried back a recommendation
                    that contingency planning begin for bombing the North. Do you remember anything
                    about that visit? I'm sorry I don't have the documents for that period, but I
                    just don't have them.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I don't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: You see, I didn't have any control over the bombing outhere. That would
                    come from CINCPAC, probably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And although I was probably in on it, I don't recall that was in on any
                    of the planning.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, it would fit that CINCPAC would have made the recommendation. My records
                    show that Mr. Trueheart went home in December. Do you remember that?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: You mean to stay home?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. What I'm curious about is the background for that.
                        Was thia routine change or in line with a policy change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think probably a policy - no, I'm not sure because Trueheart was more
                    or less of the opinion that it was good for Diem to be gone, and so was Lodge.
                    He'd been there quite a while, I think.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, I'll tell you. Frankly, I've heard that he was sent home because he d
                    made you his enemy. And I thought I'd just ask you if there was anything to
                    that.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Enemy?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't know in what sense you'd mean an enemy.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in the sense that he'd been anti-Diem and you were
                        pro-Diem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, that's true. Yes, that's true. Yes, he was anti-Diem.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, my source said that he had crossed you, and that deputy chiefs of
                    mission don't cross chiefs of MAAG and get away with it. Is that true?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I had nothing to do with his relief.</p>
                <p>Q: Okay. Now, this is curious, because as I understand it, Mr. Trueheart was
                    replaced by David Nes, and Nes only lasted about six months before he was sent
                    home. Do you know anything of that story?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, because after the Khanh - I knew Nes, but I'm not sure of the reason
                    why [he was relieved]. Lodge had so many likes and dislikes. As I say, he was a
                    loner. He liked to do everything by himself and if his deputy would do
                    something, and he might be away or have a different interpretation, it was up to
                    Lodge to tell them, “'I can't work with this man. Have him relieved'.”</p>
                <p>But after - well, [William] Westmoreland came out as my deputy in January and
                    he'd been there two days or three days when Khanh took over and said, “What do
                    we do now?” I said, “Nothing. You just sit and wait and see what happens.” Then
                    I knew Khanh very well, and Lodge had to call me and say, “Who is General
                    Khanh?” He had never met him, and yet he was a corps commander up in Hue. I told
                    him he was probably the best general in the Vietnamese Army, I mean as far as
                    the military was concerned. So when he took over, Lodge didn't know him very
                    well, and when we went out on trips, Khanh would take me along with him and, as
                    I say, Lodge would be in the second seat of the second helicopter.</p>
                <p>The first Sunday after he took over, we met him at the airport at six o'clock in
                    the morning for breakfast, and then we went out and got some helicopters and
                    flew about fifteen miles north over Saigon and landed, and there was an
                    artillery battery there, four guns. He went up and I said, “What are you going
                    to do?” They were all pointing north, and he said, “I'm going to shoot to the
                    North.” So he went up and I stayed in back because it was his day, and he had
                    the whole press corps there; there must have been about thirty of them,
                    photographers and all taking pictures of him. And he'd turn around and say,
                    “Where's General Harkins?” The press looked around, and I said, “I'm right here.
                    I'm back here.” He said, “Come up here.” And Khanh put his arm around me and
                    turned to the press and said, “I just want to tell you that General Harkins is
                    not my boss, but he's the best friend Vietnam has, and I just want you to
                    publish that.” And they never did.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They never did? What did Lodge make of a statement like
                        that, dyou suppose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He wasn't there. He wasn't asked to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you say that you knew that Khanh was going to make a
                        coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, he told me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does this put you in a kind of predicament?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He put it this way, when I went up to see him and he had this beard
                    which is a funny little goatee - they don't grow [them] very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think they grow [them] but only when they're old and
                        respected,don't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He said, “I'm not going to shave this off until I've taken over.” And I
                    just told him, I said, “Oh, General Khanh, we don't want another coup.” So about
                    two days [later] he sent his American adviser, who was a Colonel Wilson - I
                    think his name was Wilson - down to see me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jasper Wilson.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Jasper. And he said that Khanh was going to come down to this corps
                    commanders' meeting in Saigon, but he wasn't going to stay in the house with the
                    other generals. He was going to stay with me in my quarters, Wilson's quarters.
                    And he says he has a friend, a parachute battalion commander in Saigon, and I
                    think they had five companies in the battalion, and he put a company around each
                    of the five leading generals - Minh's house, Don's house, [Le Van] Kim's house,
                    and [Ton That] Dinh's house, or whoever they were then, Din's, I think. And when
                    they found the troops there, they said, “What's this?'' They said, “We
                    understand there's going to be a coup and we're to protect you.” So at four
                    o'clock in the morning they went in and arrested the generals.</p>
                <p>Q: These are the generals that became known as the Dalat generals, I think.
                    HARKINS: Yes, they took them out to the airport and met Khanh, and he said, “I'm
                    the commander now.” And then they were sent to Dalat, I think.</p>
                <p>Q: Does this put you in a rather peculiar position when you know a coup is coming
                    and you're supposed to be the adviser to the senior military man? I told them
                    back in Washington that it was coming up, and I said, “I've already got this
                    word.” And they didn't do anything about it.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>HARKINS: They didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. They took over.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, as the adviser to the head of government, and you know that he's
                    about to get knocked out of that chair, doesn't that put you rather in a
                    compromised position if you know that this is coming? Well, it's hard to figure
                    those things out, because I knew that Don had told me that they were going to
                    get rid of Diem, but I didn't go up and tell Diem, and I knew that Khanh was
                    going to do something. I wasn't quite sure how he was going to do it, and I
                    didn't go up and tell Big Minh. They weren't getting along anyway - the generals
                    - so maybe it was a change for the better. I thought it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You thought it was a change for the better with
                        Khanh?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, I did. Because one man was running things then, and hwas strong
                    enough to make decisions.</p>
                <p>But I left and they had a meeting in June in Hawaii and I wasn't invited to go,
                    so I knew something was up. Well, I was sixty then, anyway, and I had to retire
                    that year, and that was a good way to get me out, to say that I was going to
                    retire. Westmoreland went with Lodge. I didn't go. So I don't know what
                    happened. But I was sort of depressed at that, and I knew my days were short,
                    that Westy was going to take over. I made arrangements to come home by a slow
                    boat and I was told that I had to fly home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about a couple of things -</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: The President wanted to see me.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, I think I sent you a copy of that document. Now, McNamara visited again
                    in March and made a very well-publicized trip, I think, around the country with
                    Khanh, with his arm around Khanh and saying -</p>
                <p>HARKINS: And Taylor, too. They said the President told them to havtheir hands
                    holding his hand up in the air, that we are behind him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he was chanting a slogan, too, as I recall, and he got
                        iwrong. Do you remember that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>HARKINS: What?</p>
                <p>Q: He was chanting a slogan in Vietnamese, as I recall, and he got the inflection
                    wrong, and everybody laughed at him. I've heard this story. Tran Van Don tells
                    this story. He said the phrase was “Vietnam Muon Nam,” but he got the inflection
                    wrong. It's supposed to mean “Vietnam a thousand years,” but the way he
                    inflected it, it came out “Vietnam go to sleep.” (Laughter)</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, you had to be careful in Vietnamese. I know my wife started to take
                    it up and studied Vietnamese, and we went to dinner one night with [Nguyen Dinh]
                    Thuan, who was the secretary of defense at that time. He turned to her and said,
                    “I understand you're taking Vietnamese.” And she said, “Oh, I've only had three
                    lessons. I find it very hard.” And he said, “Well, say something.” And she said
                    something that she thought was “How do you do” and he laughed like hell. She
                    said, “Why are you laughing?” And he said, “Would you say that again?” So she
                    did, and he said, “Well, what are you saying?” She said, “How do you do?” And he
                    said, “No, you're saying 'Hello, dearie.'” So she quit. (Laughter) She decided
                    she wasn't going to get in trouble anymore.</p>
                <p>Q: How often during that spring when obviously the military situation was
                    beginning to get bad, you said that the Viet Cong battalions were beginning to
                    be encountered pretty regularly, and they were beginning to chew up some South
                    Vietnamese battalions. Was the subject of introducing American troops beginning
                    to be discussed at this time?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, not while I was there. No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not yet. Not even as a contingency?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No.</p>
                <p>Q: At some point, and I haven't determined exactly when, Khanh began to talk - at
                    least privately, later publicly, but at least privately - about extending the
                    war in some way or other, marching north or moving north. Did he talk to you
                    about this?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, but I think that was his line of chatter when I went out that Sunday
                    after he'd taken over, and he said, “We're going to carry the war to the North.”
                    Well, shooting four guns off fifteen miles north of Saigon wasn't going to carry
                    the -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not very far north, was it? Well, what did he mean, do
                        yosuppose? What did he have in mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>HARKINS: I think he probably wanted to go up and I think he probably had an idea
                    that he'd probably take his army and move right north across the Seventeenth
                    Parallel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you give him any advice on that score?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I didn't, because we weren't for it, I don't think, at that time and
                    it would take a lot of backing, a lot of supplies and a lot of things we didn't
                    have.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, the media have come up a couple of times. Some reporters' names have come
                    up, and I wanted to ask you a few questions on that score. Can you describe how
                    your relations with the media evolved during your tour? How did they start out?
                    How did they end up?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, they started out fine, and they ended up very poorly. I think
                    because of the way they reported things like Halberstam reporting things that
                    just weren't true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give me examples of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I think that his reporting that the bonzes were killed and the
                    raids on the pagodas, that wasn't true. I think the Catholic battalions fighting
                    Buddhist battalions, I don't think that was true. I mean, within the Vietnamese
                    Army. Of course they were fighting Buddhist battalions, but there weren't
                    Catholic battalions fighting Buddhist battalions within the [Vietnamese Army].
                    And then four or five other little things that he took up to the press. As I
                    say, he handed out mimeographs and sort of had the press eating out of his hand.
                    And I was walking along with him one day and I said, “What's the matter? I know
                    you're Jewish, I know Diem is Catholic,” and I said, “Are you letting that
                    bother your reporting?” And he turned to me and said, “How do you know I'm a
                    Jew?” Well, I wasn't sure of it at the time, but then after he left and was
                    relieved from that - as a matter of fact, the New York Times people came over
                    and they relieved Halberstam. They sent him over to Poland, and he tried to do
                    the same thing in Poland, and Poland kicked him out within thirty days. He
                    should have been kicked out of Vietnam in the beginning, but the Times, I don't
                    know -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know one of the big stories that he broke was one that
                        you'vmentioned about the story of Ap Bac, the battle of Ap Bac.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: How we got slaughtered there. Well, they said, “What's happened down at
                    Ap Bac?” And I said, “Well, nothing. They got defeated, the village troops got
                    defeated, but we sent this parachute battalion down. We lost the city for a day
                    and then we took it back.”I said, “That's war. We went in and took the whole
                    thing right back.” So I said, “There's nothing wrong with that. I mean, they had
                    the courage to go in there, and win it back.”</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course he reported it as a defeat for government
                        forces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: It was in the beginning, I mean, they were just driven out of town. But
                    they were the province forces; they weren't the regular army at that time. I
                    think there were the village forces and the province forces.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, he cites as one of his principal sources on this story, an American
                    adviser who was down there, I think with the Seventh Division under General Van
                    Thanh Cao. Did you have a lot of trouble with that sort of thing, with advisers
                    talking to the press?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Just one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Just that particular one. He was always outspoken. And when he was down
                    there when I wanted Cao to go out and see what was going on, he said, “Well, I
                    can't. Your adviser has taken my plane and he's flying around.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, boy. This was John Paul Vann we're talking about,
                        right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. Then he went back there and got killed over there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, as a civilian, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. I don't know what happened to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was killed in a helicopter crash.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Was he?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Now, Halberstam plays up Colonel Vann as a superb
                        fieladviser and so on and so on. What is your version of that story?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I told him one time I didn't know whether to promote him or demote
                    him. I said, “Sometimes you're so fine and sometimes you're just too outspoken.”
                    And I said, “That doesn't help me in my job when you're.. .” And I think he did
                    talk to Halberstam quite a bit. But he was a very opinionated sort of a man.
                    Quick-tempered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he good?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think in advising the military, yes, he did very well. But then some
                    of them tried to be province chief and you couldn't do that. You had to let the
                    Vietnamese be the province chiefs.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, his boss, Vann's immediate boss, as my information has it, was a man
                    named Daniel Boone Porter, who was the adviser to the IV Corps colander, I
                    guess. He was a full colonel. Do you remember a Colonel Porter? Daniel Boone
                    Porter was his full name. He lives down the road down at Belton, I believe. A
                    Texas A&amp;M graduate.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I probably knew him but I don't pin the name down.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well it's not that important. How was Ambassador
                        Lodge'relations with the press?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, I think he got along fine with them. He had them to his house for
                    breakfast and things like that. I'd invite the press - not all of them at a time
                    - but if we had some dignitary there and we'd give a dinner party, I'd invite
                    one or two of the press to be there. I got along with them very well until they
                    started reporting things that weren't true. I know one Saturday they had a
                    report come out over the wire and somebody had said, “'Have you seen this report
                    by this reporter just sent'" - and I forget which one it was, AP or UP or
                    something - “that ten thousand troops have invaded Pleiku? What do you know
                    about that?'" And I said, “Well, I don't know anything about it. I can't believe
                    ten thousand troops are going to invade without me knowing it.” So I immediately
                    got on the phone to Pleiku and I put out a refutation of that that afternoon
                    because I talked to not only the province chief, I mean my adviser in that
                    province, the corps, and he said, “No, that isn't true at all. We're still here
                    and have our patrols out at the border.” So I denied it, and the press room
                    called me up and said, “Why did you deny that?” I said, “Because it isn't
                    true.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would have been a little unusual for the VC to put
                        tethousand troops together, wouldn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I guess they were North Vietnamese coming in. I think we'vpretty well
                    covered the waterfront.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, we've mentioned a couple of reporters. We've
                        mentioneHalberstam several times, Neil Sheehan I suppose was there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, he was there. I don't remember their names.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember any good ones? Any that struck you as
                        particularlwell-versed, objective, good reporters.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: What was the girl's name?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Marguerite Higgins, perhaps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: ...Marguerite Higgins. She was very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was [Jim] Lucas there when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes, Lucas was there. I've seen him on TV many times, and I've met him
                    someplace out in the West Coast, I believe, he was out there. He was a
                    go-getter, I mean, he was down there at the palace running along the walls as
                    soon as - when they overthrew Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, I believe you said you did not attend that last
                        Honolulconference in June, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, I did not.</p>
                <p>Q: Now, you were presented the Distinguished Service Medal later that month, June
                    24, I think. Can you give me any of the details of that? Anything that stands
                    out in your mind about that visit?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: To Washington?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Oh, I was told that the President wanted to see me, and he wanted to
                    present me with this medal, the Distinguished Service Medal. And I said, “That's
                    very fine.” Then they wanted to have a review for me at Fort Myer. And I said,
                    “Oh, tell them I don't need the review. ____________ the troops.” But they
                    insisted, so I said, “All right.” So I made a farewell, short talk there. And
                    Mr. McNamara had a dinner for me and the President was there. I talked to him
                    and he said, “I want to see you in the office,” and I said, “Let me know.” So
                    the next day I called to make an appointment with him to see him, and they said,
                    “Well, he's busy. He's out of town now for the next three weeks and getting
                    ready to run his campaign.” Well, I found he'd gone down to Texas for a while,
                    and I never did get to see him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You never did get to see him then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Never did see him. They didn't want me to see him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: General Harkins, did you have a debriefing to go through
                        when yocame back to the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: They called it a debriefing, but I did the briefing, it seems to me. I
                    went up to see Congress. I talked to Mr. [Clement J.] Zablocki, is it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And I talked to his committee, and I never did get to see the President,
                    and talk to him. And of course I talked to Mr. McNamara and Secretary Rusk, but
                    it was me doing the talking rather than a debriefing, as such. I don't know what
                    they would call a debriefing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a sort of end-of-tour summary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you recall the kind of picture you tried to present to
                        Mr.Rusk and Mr. McNamara?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, at that time, I thought Khanh was doing pretty well and I thought
                    he'd bring the whole thing together, but apparently when General Taylor went out
                    there as ambassador -</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was just about this time, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. As a matter of fact, I had an office in the Pentagon, which was
                    just in case I wanted to do anything or see anybody. I didn't. I wasn't going to
                    write a book about it then but I did have some notes and they told me I was
                    going to have this review and I wrote a little speech for that, that was just a
                    one-page affair. But Mr. - the press man for Mr. McNamara - I can't think of his
                    name right now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Arthur] Sylvester?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Sylvester. He came over to see me, and when I left Saigon, I said, “You
                    know it's a funny thing.” Khanh had a dinner for me and invited Ambassador
                    Lodge, and that was in 1964. And I'd get up and thank Khanh and made a few
                    remarks. I said, “It's an odd thing to me that here we are in the middle of a
                    war over here, and the commander's being sent home when here we are in the
                    middle of an election back in the United States and, Mr. Ambassador, you're
                    staying here. You should be running for president.” He looked at me, sort of
                    shocked, and I got home, was in this office [when] Mr. Sylvester came [and he
                    said], “You know, Mr. Lodge is home now.” I said, “No.” He said, “Yes, he only
                    stayed a week after you did.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And he said, “We're going to send a new ambassador.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had no intimation that Lodge was leaving
                        whatsoever?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No, not at all. Not at all. I was surprised. He said, “We're going to
                    send a new ambassador,” and he said, “Do you know who he is?” I said, “Yes, I
                    can guess.” He said, “Who? Nobody knows.”I said, “General Taylor.” He looked at
                    me, and he said, “How did you know that?” I said, “It was just logical.”
                    (Laughter) So then they said, well, he's the one. So he went out there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you think it was Taylor, and what was your
                        reaction? Hodid you feel about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I don't know. I thought he'd probably do fine, because he knew so much
                    about Vietnam. But then he and Khanh didn't hit it off at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any insight into why that was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>HARKINS: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have you talked to General Taylor since that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Yes. I've talked to him, but he just didn't get along with Khanh. I
                    don't recall what he said, but he said, no, he wasn't the man as far as he was
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any occasion to consult or advise about
                        Vietnam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: No. No. When I came back, and as I say I met myself coming home giving
                    talks around town to the Rotary and the Kiwanis and the schools and the churches
                    and things like that, women's clubs, engineering clubs. I really was on the
                    soapbox four or five times a week. Then everything turned around [against]
                    Vietnam, I mean the attitude of the country here turned against it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When would you time that more or less? Was there a
                        specifitime? Would you say that it was at Tet in 1968 or was it before
                        then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think it was right before then, because all the things yoget from the
                    press and the TV and everything were horror stories.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And the bloody war. It was really gruesome as a matter of fact, and that
                    turned the attitude of the people and in particular the youth who didn't wan tot
                    go over there and get into that mess. Then people stopped asking me to speak
                    because the war - because we went over there to help a country stop communism
                    and we were asked to go over there. We didn't go over there on our own. We were
                    just asked as defense if we would help, and we did. Like we've done for so many
                    other countries. But it didn't sit right with the American people, and I just
                    stopped talking about Vietnam because I only had the one story.</p>
                <p>Q: Looking back now - and I'm sure you have many times - what seemed to you to be
                    the significant personalities, the significant turning points or changes in
                    policy? Were there any crucial points when the thing could have turned around
                    and wasn't?</p>
                <p>HARKINS: I think the first upsetting thing was a visit by Senato[Mike] Mansfield
                    around Christmas in - what was it, 1962?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He came over, and he didn't leave Saigon. I was there, so - and he had
                    been there once before in 1954 or 1955, and he talked to Diem. Now, when you
                    talk to Diem you've got to listen an awful lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's my information, too, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: And Mansfield liked to talk, and this first visit he had was for about
                    four hours. And he couldn't get a word in edgewise, I mean, Diem did all the
                    talking. Well, on this visit, the second one, he came back and he didn't leave
                    Saigon. He went to see the President, Diem, and there was a six-hour meeting. I
                    wasn't with him. I don't think the Ambassador was with him. So he came back and
                    reported to the President there had been no change in seven years from his visit
                    in 1954 to this visit he made then. And I don't think he meant it the way it
                    sounded. I think he meant it that he didn't get a word in edgewise. But the
                    changes that had gone on in Vietnam were really terrific: the schools, the
                    villages, the roads, the airfields. Oh, there were tremendous changes, the
                    harvest, the crops, and all those things. Really, the five-year plan was really
                    going, but the way Mansfield put it, there'd been no change in six years. And it
                    really was the beginning of “we've got to have new leadership.”</p>
                <p>Of course, then the Harriman-Hilsman thing [happened] in August and trying to
                    overthrow the government when the message came to Lodge, and Lodge showed it to
                    me and he sent Conein over and Big Minh wouldn't see Conein. Then Lodge went
                    back to Harriman and Hilsman with this message saying that they wouldn't accept
                    it unless there was somebody in authority. Then the word came for me to do it.
                    Well, I had got nothing from the Defense Department; these were all State
                    Department messages. So I put a flash on the wire for General Taylor saying, “I
                    have been told to go to see the generals to overthrow Diem.” I said, “This is
                    from the State Department. I have no advice from the military, Defense.” Taylor
                    was playing tennis at the country club, McNamara was out of town, the President
                    was down in Hyannis Port, and none of them knew the telegram had come. President
                    Kennedy said, “Who is running this country?” And he had a meeting at nine
                    o'clock from them on Vietnam and what was going on out there, and that was
                    another very upsetting thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, I've heard versions of that story which say
                        thaHilsman did get the telegram cleared before it went out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: He did not. He got it cleared by [Michael] Forrestal, and he had it
                    cleared by Harriman. But Hilsman didn't last long after that, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think he left in February of 1964.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I think it was sooner than that, wasn't it?</p>
                <p>Q: No, he stayed on for the first couple of months of the Johnson Administration
                    and left in February of 1964, although I think the decision was made before that
                    time.</p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, he was a West Pointer - class of 1941, I think - and when he first
                    came out to visit me, he said he knew all about guerrilla warfare. He had been
                    in Burma, I think, during his career. And he said, “The only one I have to see -
                    Mr. Kennedy, the President, said, 'I want you to see Harkins and talk to
                    Harkins, and see how things are going.'” So that's really the only time I met
                    him personally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your impressions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>HARKINS: Well, I didn't know his background, but I don't think he wathe expert he
                    said he was on guerrilla warfare.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
