<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000988">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Stephen H. Rogers </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR STEPHEN H. ROGERS</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Raymond C. Ewing </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 27, 1994</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This interview with Ambassador Stephen H. Rogers is being
                        conducted on behalf of the Foreign Affairs Oral History Program of the
                        Association of Diplomatic Studies and Training and I am Raymond C. Ewing.
                        This session of the interview is taking place on Wednesday, July 27, 1994.
                        Steve, I am glad to have the chance to talk with you today. It would be
                        helpful if we could start the interview by talking a little bit about your
                        early life and how you came to be interested in foreign affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Thanks, Ray. I am pleased to participate in this program. That question
                    comes up often about what got me into the Foreign Service. What interested me in
                    joining the Foreign Service? I wonder if a lot of us didn't have sort of the
                    same experience of growing up as teenagers in World War II when so much of our
                    attention was on the world, a rather unhappy state for much of that time, until
                    the middle of the forties. But I remember getting the maps of the Pacific and
                    the Eastern Front in Europe and putting pins in the maps and doing all that sort
                    of thing. I really think that contributed to an international focus for a
                    generation of us, or a partial generation of us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was an exciting time. Major events were taking place
                        during the war, and of course right after the war too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That is the next point. From 1944-45, when there was planning for the
                    post-war period and the building of the new institutions that have served us
                    tremendously well the last fifty years on balance I think caught my imagination
                    like many other people. The end of the war itself, the technological elements
                    involved in the war, the building of the UN system, the GATT, NATO, the coming
                    of the Cold War, all of these things, I found very interesting. I remember being
                    quite interested in the United World Federalists. That was quite a movement in
                    those days. It sounded very good to me, very idealistic obviously.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One world.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>ROGERS: One world, yes, that kind of thing. I should say also that I think my
                    mother, in particular, had this kind of outlook, feeling sort of responsibility
                    for being involved and trying to help, or at least understand global issues,
                    etc. She got involved in the League of Women Voters and other groups with an
                    international outlook.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you living during that period when you were in
                        high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: In 1940, when I was nine, we moved to Long Island, to Port Washington.
                    So, we were east coast, near New York, and that contributed I am sure to a
                    broader outlook.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not too far from Lake Success.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Not far at all from Lake Success, which is an interesting point. That is
                    the area where I went to high school and graduated in 1948, Port Washington High
                    School.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you went up to Princeton University.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. By the time I was applying for colleges, in 1947-48, I was really
                    pretty sure that I wanted to go into the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is unusual to have that clear a commitment at that
                        age.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I had begun to develop ideas about the Foreign Service without knowing
                    anything about it, really. But that broad perspective was the kind of thing that
                    I wanted to do. I remember hearing about George Kennan...he wrote his X article
                    in 1947, I think. Whenever it was I remember being very impressed by that and by
                    the fact that he was a Foreign Service career officer and he was having that
                    kind of impact on the evolving international situation. That encouraged me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went to Princeton with the intention of preparing
                        for the Foreign Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. I applied to four or five different colleges, I guess. I don't even
                    remember which ones. The way I got to Princeton was that I also applied for the
                    Naval ROTC scholarship and got it for Princeton specifically. So that sort of
                    ended any debate there might have been as to where I would go. I really didn't
                    know much about Princeton then, but I did know it had a School of Public and
                    International Affairs, the Woodrow Wilson School, so I was very pleased to go
                    there. I did, in fact, graduate from the Woodrow Wilson School.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a BA in public and international affairs. Then, of
                        course, with the Navy ROTC scholarship, you were committed to go immediately
                        into the Navy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was your Navy service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: We had training sessions for six to seven weeks each summer and the first
                    and third of those were at sea, but the second one was four weeks at Pensacola
                    and two weeks at Little Creek so we could learn about Naval Air and then about
                    Marines and amphibious operations. We had just arrived in Pensacola a couple of
                    days before the Korean War broke out on June 25, 1950. That, of course, tended
                    to focus our minds considerably because all of a sudden our expectation of
                    graduating into a peacetime Navy changed somewhat, it became less certain. That
                    changed the terms of our arrangements with the Navy. For instance, at that point
                    the Navy decided I was committed to three years of active duty instead of two
                    years of active duty. But I didn't object to that. It was a very good
                    arrangement for me financially making it possible for me to go to Princeton.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you served three years on active duty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, three years on active duty on a destroyer in the Pacific. I got to
                    see parts of the world I had never seen before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Korean War was still going on but was tending to wind
                        down by that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. We sailed to the western Pacific and I think it was October, 1952,
                    and participated in the Korean War in November, December and early 1953. We had
                    missions to fire at North Korean bunkers, escort duty, etc., the kinds of things
                    that destroyers do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You weren't tempted to make the Navy a career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I thought about it at one point, but only in terms of intelligence. I
                    thought it might be interesting to be in naval intelligence. But I didn't try to
                    go in that direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you take the Foreign Service examination?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, when I got out of the Navy, I needed a year or so to become a
                    civilian again and figure out how I was going to pursue my goals. For those
                    reasons, as much as anything, I went to Columbia for a year and studied
                    economics. I had had courses at Princeton in economics and they quite fascinated
                    me, so I was quite interested in studying more economics and that is what I did
                    for a year. I took the Foreign Service exam at the end of 1955, during my first
                    term at Columbia, and took the oral in March or April, 1956. During that year I
                    also found my bride and we were married, June 23, 1956 and went off on our
                    honeymoon. The Foreign Service got a hold of me while we were on our honeymoon
                    and said, “Will you accept as of a certain date?” I said, “Yes, sure. I will be
                    there.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you meet your wife in New York?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: At Columbia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the oral exam you took in 1956 the old style?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Just an interview, as far as I remember, for an hour or hour and a half.
                    There was a panel of three people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In New York or in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I think it was in New York, but I couldn't swear to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think that was the so-called old style of exam
                        that went on for several days. It was what I took also in 1957, a year
                        later. I think it was considerably easier for us than for our
                        predecessors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: And successors. I think it was about an hour and a half. Was that about
                    what you had?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think closer to an hour.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, something like that. I remember it was actually a lot of fun. I read
                    a short history of the United States the night before being pretty sure there
                    would be emphasis on that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One thing I remember doing for mine was carefully reading
                        the Los Angeles Times the morning of the exam. That was discussing the
                        situation in Jordan, as I recall. So, when did you actually enter into the
                        Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was in July, 1956.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very soon after your honeymoon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That is right. Our honeymoon was a week; that was all we could afford. We
                    were anxious to get to Washington. My wife had by that time gotten a job
                    teaching in Fairfax County. It was very quick, so much quicker than for so many
                    people since who wait around for a year or two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you entered on duty in the Department of State you
                        had the usual initial training course at the Foreign Service Institute and
                        your first assignment was in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. When I got there it was just too late for one class so I spent a
                    month in Personnel, as often happened, and then started in August, 1956 the
                    first six weeks of the A-100 course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the junior officer-training course at the Foreign
                        Service Institute?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. It is still the A-100 course all this time later. And then I was
                    assigned...I really wasn't asked, they found out I had studied economics and
                    they said, “Okay, that is what we need at this point.” You will remember that
                    when you entered that this was a time of the expansion of the economic
                    activities of the Foreign Service and this was closely connected with
                    Wristonization and saw a whole change in the career structure of the State
                    Department and the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your assignment to the Bureau of Economic Affairs was
                        to take advantage of your economic training and experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't because your wife had a teaching job in the
                        area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were given no choice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: You will also recall that we pretty much were told what we did and we did
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What part of the Economic Bureau did you work in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: In what was then called the trade agreements division, in the commercial
                    policy branch, which later became a division, itself, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of work responsibilities did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, it was trade issues. It was GATT work. I attended the 12th session
                    of the contracting parties of GATT in 1957 in Geneva. So it was that kind of
                    thing. Specific trade issues, often with Canada. The role of GATT, our
                    participation in the GATT. I did position papers for GATT sessions, and all that
                    kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And, at that time the Department of State played a very
                        lead role in trade negotiations. It was before the creation of the Office of
                        the Special Representative for Trade—STR.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. As I mentioned, it was Wristonization time, so I was put into an
                    office which traditionally had been largely civil service. In fact, the director
                    of the office, Carl Corse, and the deputy director, Len Weiss, were both civil
                    service people. Under pressure of Wristonization, Len became a Foreign Service
                    officer, but Carl did not. I worked for Herm Barger and then Joe Greenwald in
                    the commercial policy branch.</p>
                <p>That was, I think, a fairly tough introduction to the Foreign Service. These old
                    timers, Corse and Weiss, had pretty high standards for both substance and
                    presentation. I was told early on it is best not to have a whole lot of pride of
                    authorship because I wasn't going to recognize what came out at the other end.
                    They did redraft a great deal, probably too much. But they had very high
                    standards and that was good preparation for my career.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they had high standards and expected a lot from
                        their staff. It was a difficult time for them too, because some of them were
                        being forced into the Foreign Service fairly late in their working careers.
                        You stayed there for two years and then went to your first Foreign Service
                        assignment where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I had to go back and finish the A-100 course. Remember at that time they
                    sometimes split it. So I went back to the second six-week portion and learned
                    about consular matters, which I had absolutely nothing to do with anytime
                    since.</p>
                <p>As I remember I told the Foreign Service that I didn't mind where they sent me,
                    but I would rather not go to India because it was hot, sticky, crowded and there
                    was disease, etc. So in April, 1959, we left for New Delhi and spent a little
                    over two years in the embassy there in the economic section. We enjoyed it
                    immensely. It was a very exciting experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador there at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was Ellsworth Bunker. I always think about him when we talk about the
                    difference between career and non-career ambassadors. He was as close to a
                    career ambassador as you can come without being one. He had five or six
                    different missions in his time with the State Department. I had tremendous
                    respect for him. I had a certain amount of contact with him, not a great deal of
                    contact, but enough to see him in action and develop respect for his integrity,
                    his sensitivity to the Indian scene, etc. It was a little bit difficult for us
                    at that point in India for various reasons.</p>
                <p>Then John Kenneth Galbraith replaced him about two months before we left New
                    Delhi, so I got to know him a little bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was at the beginning of the Kennedy administration in
                        1961. You were the junior officer in the economic section and did a range of
                        reporting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And commercial work also?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>ROGERS: No, not as such. It was economic issues and economic reporting, a certain
                    amount of contacts, a certain amount of travel to see how the economy was
                    coming. It was the time when Nehru was the prime minister and he believed very
                    firmly in building a base of heavy industry. Of course, we had some problem with
                    that approach, but it went ahead without our assistance. He got his assistance
                    from the Russians and to some extent the British and the French and others. But
                    we pretty much stayed out of these major heavy industry projects because we
                    disagreed in principle to the approach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had some assistance programs of our own at the time,
                        didn't we?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Oh, we had very substantial programs. We had a very large mission, TCM,
                    Technical Cooperation Mission. My recollection is it was agriculture, education
                    and that kind of thing. But I don't remember it in great detail. But, a very
                    important part of our program was PL 480. While we were there we signed a very
                    large agreement for PL 480 grains for India with the expectation that this would
                    cover the time until India could be self-sufficient. Well, it took far longer, I
                    take it. I haven't been back to India since 1961. It took far longer than we had
                    anticipated, but finally it seems to have happened, and that is good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a period not long after partition and independence
                        for India and Pakistan, but before the next major war between them in 1965.
                        Did you travel to Pakistan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No. We were certainly aware of the tensions and the history and all, but
                    we could not, as I recall, we certainly did not, cross the border on land.
                    Flying in we flew from Karachi, so there was that link at least.</p>
                <p>While I was there the main focus of concern was on China. There was an incursion
                    by the Chinese into Ladakh in the north and there was a certain amount of
                    fighting there, which I take it sounded far worse back here than it did to us
                    sitting in New Delhi. But still, it was a matter of concern. The Chinese were
                    building their embassy very close to ours in the new diplomatic enclave,
                    Chanakyapuri, and they stopped work on it. Things became quite tense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had our new embassy been completed during the time you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: The chancery, yes, but the residence not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The architect for the chancery was Edward Durell
                        Stone.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. I liked that building. It had been opened for just three months
                    when we got there. I thought it was beautiful and enjoyed it. A lot of people
                    didn't care for it because it was an open rectangle and you had to walk around
                    the courtyard to get somebody from the economic section over to the political
                    section or other parts of the embassy. I thought it was a magnificent building
                    and was very pleased with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your wife teach in New Delhi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: She did. There was an American school. She taught about half time because
                    we had a little girl by that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Born in New Delhi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, she was five or six months old when we went to New Delhi. So Kent
                    could teach...she wasn't really asked, she was sort of told that they needed
                    her. She taught in what was called the old Taj Barracks, which had very high
                    ceiling and pretty surroundings. But she loved it because she could do anything
                    she wanted in her room. There was lots of wall space way up if she wanted to put
                    things on and nobody cared about whether there was going to be a little sticky
                    stuff left over and that kind of thing. So she enjoyed teaching there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there in New Delhi for two years and where did
                        you go next? This would have been what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: We left in June or July, 1961. Again as part of beefing up the economic
                    function in the State Department I was given the opportunity to study economics
                    for a further year and went to Harvard for that purpose. I spent the year
                    1961-62 at the Graduate School of Public Administration, which later became the
                    Kennedy School. I got a masters in public administration. That isn't why the
                    Department sent us there—to get a degree—and they weren't all that enthusiastic
                    about it, but it came easily with the work I was supposed to do. Essentially all
                    of my course work was in economics. It was the toughest economics I have ever
                    done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a very rigorous program. I went a few years later.
                        In 1961-62 I would have thought that quite a few of the Harvard economic
                        professors were in Washington in the Kennedy administration or serving
                        somewhere else, like Galbraith.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Kissinger was there and I sat in on a few sessions of his seminar in
                    national security, with Mort Halperin, incidentally, his assistant. But there
                    were some outstanding figures in economics who were still there. Quite enough to
                    keep me occupied very thoroughly for that year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you finished at Harvard with your masters degree in
                        1962 and then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Then I went to the embassy in Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you already have French or did you go to French
                        language training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I had French in high school and at Columbia. In fact Kent and I met at
                    the French House at Columbia, so we had that link also to French. But I had
                    studied French at the Foreign Service Institute, I don't recall for how long,
                    during our first tour in Washington. It was a very good program, as you know.
                    FSI always has had very good language programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is always much better when you can start with a good
                        foundation, which it sounds like you had than starting totally from scratch
                        because often the length of training is not as long as it should be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: The important part was conversation at FSI. I had the grammar and a
                    certain amount of vocabulary. Conversation was not part of high school French in
                    those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Unfortunately that is still the case in many schools. But
                        the FSI does give you a chance to develop your ability to use the language
                        in everyday settings.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Paris you were again an economic officer. What sort of
                        responsibilities did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, I worked in the part of the economic section that was headed by the
                    Treasury Attach�, Don McGrew, a person who is still remembered who was there in
                    the embassy maybe 20 years. He had been there 12 or 13 when I got there and he
                    stayed many years later. Don knew French and knew the French and knew France
                    very well. He never lost his Toledo accent in French, but he was very effective,
                    had good contacts, very skeptical of what the French were doing a good deal of
                    the time. He never became Frenchified, never lost his sense of US interests and
                    the objectivity of dealing with the French. But that also was a good experience,
                    working on financial matters, economic analysis and some specific issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Treasury Attach�'s office was part of the economic
                        section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And particularly responsible for macro economic reporting,
                        financial analysis, monetary matters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. And for AID. For the first year I was there a large part of my
                    responsibility was for our liaison with the French Ministry of Cooperation and
                    others on aid matters in Africa, which was quite interesting. It got me to
                    Africa on one occasion for a conference of the ambassadors and AID mission
                    directors from the French speaking countries in Africa. There was an interesting
                    issue there that might be worth discussing. It was a question...You know, we all
                    know, that France has maintained very close official and commercial relations
                    with most of its former colonies in Africa, and the question that we had and
                    seemed relevant to how we treated the French on aid matters in Africa was
                    whether these programs were essentially for the benefit of France or essentially
                    for the benefit of the African countries. There were some in our missions in
                    Africa who felt that much of French aid, or most of it, was self-serving and
                    should not be recognized as aid in the same, more objective sense, that our aid
                    was thought of anyway. Now we all know that all aid programs are self-interest
                    as well as in the interest of the recipients at their best. But this became
                    quite a debate and I wrote quite a long telegram on the subject making the point
                    that whatever the motivations were, whatever the returns to France were, these
                    programs certainly seemed from my vantage point to be providing resources in
                    teachers, in administrative help, in trade credits and in all sorts of ways that
                    had to be beneficial to the receiving countries. It was paternalistic, there was
                    no question it was and I would guess still is. But I argued that these were real
                    aid programs in that sense. And that telegram became something of a subject of
                    discussion at this conference I went to in 1963 which was held in Lagos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that was still quite early in the independence of the
                        former French colonies. Many became independent in 1960-61.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>ROGERS: That is true. From this perspective, it seems as if it was immediately
                    after. At that time I wasn't thinking of it in terms of it being quite so new.
                    And the French relationship with those countries had been established...I think
                    Guinea had gone its own way, I think the others had fallen into line, with the
                    relationship that the French accepted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were getting the advantage of the flow and transfer
                        of technology as well as money, those countries that were continuing to
                        cooperate and have a good relationship with Paris.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. The French certainly sent hundreds, probably thousands, of
                    teachers, in particular, to these countries, or kept them there when they became
                    independent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, soldiers as well and businessmen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. I think the French had never denied that they feel that they have a
                    special relationship and occasionally special responsibilities and even
                    authorities in these countries. We have seen that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have seen that many times, not just in former French
                        colonies, but in...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They have expanded a little bit in recent months. Personally, I think we
                    can be rather pleased that they are willing to take on that responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They also have a great deal of expertise and knowledge of
                        the countries. They are not coming in as total neophytes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. So, that in any case, was a large part of my responsibilities in
                    the first year I was there. It became important enough that AID had decided it
                    had to have their own man there, so they sent Denis Baron, a fine AID officer,
                    out there to serve that purpose. So in my second year in Paris I was working on
                    other issues.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>One thing we, the Kennedy enthusiasm and energy had an impact on us, specifically
                    in the AID area. There was something called the Middle Level Manpower
                    Conference. The administration had decided that the problem in development was
                    very much focused on developing the capabilities of middle level managers. We
                    got instructions to press the French to send a high level delegate to this
                    conference, which was to be held, I think, in Puerto Rico. It was just the kind
                    of thing where cultures clash—the enthusiasm and idealism of this approach, “get
                    something done; do something dramatic, quickly at a high level”—and the French
                    resisted. They couldn't see sending a minister or anybody at that level to this
                    conference. We had phone calls from high level people in the White House on
                    weekends and everything to try to get the French to send someone. They finally
                    sent a Mr. Boisdevant. Mr. Boisdevant, I guess, was a good man, but he was not a
                    minister and did not serve the political purpose that we were looking for.</p>
                <p>So there were issues like that, that I got involved in that were interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did some of the reporting about the French
                        economy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. It was fairly routine. Whatever the Weekly Economic Reports were at
                    that time, that kind of thing. We did that all around the world, I guess, at
                    that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a fairly early period in the new Organization for
                        Economic Cooperation and Development, the OECD, and, of course, the European
                        Community was moving along. Were you involved with either of those
                        organizations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Not at that point. If I could go back a little. In TAD, the Trade
                    Agreement Division, we were very much involved in the GATT and how to absorb the
                    creation of the European Economic Community. And that was a major issue of the
                    12th session of the contracting parties that I went to. But in Paris, I don't
                    recall that I had very much to do with either of those organizations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, your next assignment brought you into contact with
                        both of them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You finished in Paris when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: In 1964 we returned to Washington and I went to RPE in the Bureau for
                    European Affairs—the Office of Regional Political Economic Affairs...what does
                    it say on the sheet?</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Office of OECD, European Community and Atlantic Political
                        Economic Affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, that is right. I guess there had been a single regional office and
                    it was broken into two parts and the people wanted to make sure that the
                    political element was in that one too, so it became Political-Economic...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The other office, RPM, was in the Bureau of
                        Economics...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, it was in the Bureau for European Affairs and was political military
                    as opposed to political economic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of responsibilities did you have in RPE? You
                        were there for quite a while, did your responsibilities changed during that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They did, I was there for five years. At first it was exclusively on OECD
                    matters and I worked for Ruth Phillips. She was the officer in charge of OECD
                    affairs. I was working on the trade committee, agriculture committee, and I
                    don't recall which other committees I was particularly working on. And then
                    there was a reorganization. Deane Hinton had been the director of the office,
                    and when he left he was succeeded by Abe Katz and Abe decided it was time to
                    reorganize things a bit. He created a small unit consisting of me and two other
                    officers to look at substantive matters across the board within RPE's
                    responsibilities, meaning the OECD side but also the European Community side and
                    the economic aspects of NATO. So we were concerned with all three of the
                    organizations and to a minor extent with the ECE (Economic Commission for Europe
                    at the UN) and things like that. Our responsibilities were substantive—trade and
                    agriculture and science.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of the trade side, this must have been about 1966-67, the
                        Kennedy administration was in process of negotiation, STR had been
                        established, the Economic Bureau where you had served before was very much
                        involved. How did you and the European Bureau interact with all of those
                        other actors in Washington, not to mention, Treasury and Commerce and
                        Agriculture Departments, etc.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That was tough bureaucracy at that point. You know about that from your
                    own experience. We sometimes saw things quite differently from the way people in
                    EB did and had some pretty difficult discussions with the people there. Julius
                    Katz was a tenacious battler and I had tremendous respect for him, but I wasn't
                    always able to get through to him issues that came up or with his people.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a time when a lot was going on in Europe.
                        Integration was well along with six countries in the European union at that
                        point. Expansion was not a major issue or was it? I guess British membership
                        was always an issue during that period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, it was a question as to whether, and I would have to review the
                    history of the thing, but certainly the idea of expansion was in the air. The
                    British had opted out and by that time they had been rebuffed on the European
                    defense community, I don't know exactly the year of that, but there was a lot of
                    tension across the channel. So we were dealing with a Community of six
                    countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in the European Bureau quite a while later when
                        Arthur Hartman was Assistant Secretary, and I know that RPE and the
                        political/economic dimension was of tremendous interest and importance to
                        him. That hasn't always been the case, I don't think, on the part of the EUR
                        Assistant Secretary. How was it at the time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: When I arrived in RPE, there was still an almost crusading philosophy in
                    favor of European integration. People were dedicated to the importance of it,
                    for good reason. People remembering the war and the importance of integrating
                    Germany into a new structure and make sure that things didn't go wrong in those
                    relationships. And it was ideological, or it came across as being ideological,
                    in favor of European integration. That changed over the five years I was in RPE
                    as people moved out and new people came in. People were looking at the downside
                    from our point of view in trade terms, etc. The common agricultural policy
                    became a very serious concern of ours for a very good reason. So, it became more
                    of a kind of pragmatic approach. Within RPE we still had people who had this
                    intense devotion to the idea of European unity. We all believed in it. The
                    question was to what extent you allow them leeway in meeting GATT requirements
                    and other norms of international economic behavior in the creation of this very
                    important EEC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was also a time when the Agriculture Department with
                        soybean exports and some of the other agencies became much more interested,
                        involved and concerned about the trade damaging potential effects of the
                        EEC.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were in RPE for five years. That must have been one
                        of your longer assignments.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, there were personal reasons why I was pleased to stay there for
                    those five years. We had come back from Paris with one child and a few months
                    later we had another and two years after that we had two more. So, we thought it
                    was a good time to let those kids grow up at least a little bit before we went
                    overseas again. So I was pleased to stay there for five years, and the work
                    changed, my responsibilities changed and the direction of the office
                    changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were certainly dealing with some very important
                        substantive issues, and different issues over that period of time. I often
                        have found that simply the movement from one assignment to another is
                        obviously a big transition, but an equally big and sometimes even more
                        difficult transition is when you have a new boss or other changes within
                        your unit. You don't need to move to have a major change.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: You are absolutely right about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So at the end of your time at RPE it looks like you took a
                        year off and went to the Industrial College of the Armed Forces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. I was offered senior training. I didn't particularly choose the
                    Industrial College, but that is where they sent me, and we were pleased to spend
                    another year in Washington instead of going somewhere else for a year. That was
                    a good experience. The substance of it was largely useful but far from all of it
                    was of direct interest to the Foreign Service. But the process of working in an
                    environment that was 75 percent military, or close to that, and watching this
                    being a joint Defense Department institution, watching the different services
                    getting to know each other, that also was very interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That period, 1969-70, of course, was also a period of
                        great stress at the national level with Vietnam, the invasion of Cambodia
                        taking place while you were at Ft. McNair. I don't know if that had much
                        reverberation among the student body?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: We certainly debated Vietnam and we found that people in the military
                    covered the spectrum in views about Vietnam. I mean there were people who were
                    not bomb throwing anti-war activists but who felt very strongly that we should
                    get out, that we should not be there. And there were many, of course, who
                    thought we had a job to do there and should continue it until we finished it. So
                    that was an issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the end of that training then you have what looks like
                        another good assignment. You went as counselor for economic affairs in
                        London?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. One other thing that was interesting about ICAF was the
                    international trip we took. I went with a group that spent a week in Argentina
                    and a week in Chile. That was quite an eye opening experience. Argentina was not
                    democratic, but was very neat, orderly and seemed secure. And then to spend a
                    week in Chile at the time of the campaigning for the election that resulted in
                    Mr. Allende's becoming president was really quite fascinating. Things were
                    disorderly with political slogans painted on walls and streets. You got a
                    feeling of great political, democratic vitality in Chile. A freshness in a
                    rather disorderly way that you didn't see in Argentina. It was my introduction
                    to Latin America and it served me well later.</p>
                <p>Then I went to London where I was the number two in the economic section. Stan
                    Cleveland was the minister for economic affairs, and I was his deputy and the
                    head of a section that included quite a wide variety of different economic
                    relationships of about ten or twelve people and different aspects including one
                    person who spent all of his time on commodity trade because of the commodity
                    institutions that were centered in London. We had a civil air attach�, a
                    maritime person, trade people, quite a variety.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All of those people were in the unit which you
                        headed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. They were responsible to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That included British relations with Common Market and
                        some of the other regional issues as well as the specific air and
                        commodities issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That's right. Several of the people in my section were from different
                    agencies in Washington. So I had only a couple of just plain Foreign Service
                    officers, generalists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things did you, yourself, specially work
                        on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: The question of British entry into the Common Market was an issue for
                    discussion in much of that period. We had trade issues, we had maritime issues,
                    we had civil air issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Meanwhile, you and your family now consisted of your wife
                        and four children and enjoyed living in London, I assume.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>ROGERS: We enjoyed London very much. We lived in a house built about 1815 on
                    Edwardes Square just off Kensington High Street, one of maybe 80 row houses
                    around this very pleasant two or three acre fenced in square for the residences.
                    A lot of charm. There was a certain amount of inconvenience associated with that
                    charm, but it was very nice. We enjoyed London very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was ambassador during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was Walter Annenberg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was during the Nixon administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was Jerry Greene (Joseph N. Greene, Jr.), who didn't stay very long.
                    He left and Earl Soames came and replaced him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your tour finished about 1972 and you went back to
                        Paris.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Back to Paris and the OECD mission this time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had the mission been there during your previous assignment
                        in Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. I had very little to do with it at that point. I can't say that I
                    was very enthusiastic about going to the OECD mission. Joe Greenwald was there
                    at the time I arrived but left about a month later to become Ambassador to the
                    European Communities. As a matter of fact we didn't have an ambassador for two
                    years and the acting chief of mission was the Treasury representative, Weir
                    Brown, who had been there for many years and knew the business. I acted as his
                    deputy for that time. At the end of two years the administration finally got
                    around to replacing Joe with a businessman from Arizona, named Bill Turner. He
                    was a very nice fellow, but was new to the business and it wasn't easy for him
                    to get a hold of this very technical organization, so they sent Abe Katz to be
                    his deputy. Weir Brown left at that point. So the third year I was under Bill
                    Turner and Abe Katz.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then Weir Brown, who had come from the Treasury was
                        replaced by another Treasury man?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, but not at as high a rank within the structure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was Ralph Korp wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I think it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He came from Rome.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. Jim Ammerman was there then too. We had two Treasury people all the
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were acting deputy, what other responsibilities
                        did you have or was it all coordination of the mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, it was partly that, partly personnel matters and coordination of
                    Mission activities, but with special responsibilities for the trade committee,
                    the energy committees, the manpower and social affairs committees. I did not
                    have responsibility for the financial side of the OECD, the Economic Policy
                    Committee and Working Party III, which were under the Treasury person there. But
                    much of the rest...agriculture for most of the time I was there was part of my
                    responsibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I spent part of that period in Bern and I was spending a
                        fair amount of time on something called the Executive Committee in Special
                        Session which was where high level trade economic policy officials come
                        together in fairly quiet ways periodically. Did you work with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. That was a limited group. It wasn't all countries. I was there at
                    the time that structure was set up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The OECD has been there a long time and still does good
                        macro economic research, studies, coordination of AID programs. How would
                        you assess the OECD, particularly looking at the period when you were there,
                        but more generally both before and later?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>ROGERS: I had had some background, of course, in my time in RPE, so I knew
                    something about it. I think anyone who has had experience with international
                    organizations knows enough not to jump at the chance of going back to such
                    environments because there is so much talk and so much paper. But I also feel
                    strongly that the OECD is a necessary organization. It serves to deal with some
                    pretty basic problems in international economic and scientific and other
                    relations. It isn't a very exciting place and that is probably an advantage in
                    dealing with these difficult subjects in a technically competent way. I can
                    think of two or three examples, perhaps.</p>
                <p>One is the issue that was brought up in Europe about US technological domination
                    of the world—the technological gap. This had become a major political issue for
                    some people. We were able to put that into the Committee on Science Policy in
                    the OECD and deal with it through a series of specific studies on different
                    areas to see what the situation was and to see whether in fact there was damage
                    to the Europeans of the sort that would require some kind of action which
                    presumably we would not like. I think that somewhat depoliticized the issue and
                    controlled it. That worked quite well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another aspect that I think is interesting about the OECD
                        is the inclusion of Japan at a fairly early time. I think the OECD was the
                        first regional grouping that Japan became a member of after the Second World
                        War. The willingness of the Europeans, I think with strong American
                        leadership, to have Japan be a part of the OECD was very much appreciated in
                        Tokyo. I don't know if you had any experience with the Japanese at OECD or
                        any reflections about the expansion of the OECD beyond Europe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, it certainly was an interesting development when the European
                    countries started expanding to Australia and New Zealand and then Japan. It made
                    it the premier organization of developed countries on economic matters. I think
                    the expansion was obviously necessary, to include Japan. Everything since then
                    has shown that it was absolutely right. I don't recall that the Japanese took
                    great leadership at my time there, but they did become active. They had people
                    in the Secretariat and wanted to be active in that fashion.</p>
                <p>There was another issue that I should mention that came up then, an issue with
                    which I also had quite a bit to do with in RPE, and that was energy, the oil
                    crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The oil crisis was about 1973.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>ROGERS: It was the end of 1973 when OPEC announced that prices would rise. We
                    thought it was a very big rise as of January 1, 1974. I say we thought it was a
                    very big rise, but it went up a good deal more in 1979. The OECD was well placed
                    to do a quick analysis of what the implications were of this great increase in
                    the price of oil. Much of the month of December, 1973 was focused on this. It
                    happened to be a time when Weir Brown was on a well-earned home leave so I was
                    sitting in the Council for the US and was the principal high-level contact on
                    these matters with the Secretariat and all. The Secretariat put out some
                    analyses and policy papers that certainly impressed me at the time and as far as
                    I can recall would still stand up well. They had to do with the implications for
                    capital movements. They foresaw the massive transfer of capital to OPEC
                    countries and the fact that this capital would have to be placed somewhere.
                    Something would have to happen with it. This led through the years to tremendous
                    lending through Western banking institutions during the critical times of the
                    late seventies and eighties in the international balance of payments
                    situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another thing that happened with strong OECD involvement
                        as a result of the OPEC price increases was the establishment of the
                        International Energy Agency.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, that's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. That happened in my third year there, or we were in the process of
                    creating it then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Steve, let's break for today and pick up at this point at
                        our next meeting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is Thursday, August 4, 1994 and this is the second
                        session of the interview with Ambassador Stephen H. Rogers which is being
                        conducted on behalf of the Foreign Affairs Oral History Program of the
                        Association for Diplomatic Studies. Steve, when we finished talking last
                        week, you were talking about your experiences as counselor of the US
                        delegation to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development
                        (OECD) in Paris where you worked in 1972-75. You were talking about how the
                        International Energy Agency got started. I wonder if there is anything else
                        that you particularly wanted to cover from that time in Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>ROGERS: The five years that I had in Europe, that is the two years in London and
                    three years at the OECD mission in Paris, occurred at a good time to be there in
                    the sense it was a time of economic change and a certain amount of crisis and
                    many major issues. To go back to the London time, in August, 1971 when President
                    Nixon took major economic steps to protect the US balance of payments including
                    cutting the tie to gold and putting a surcharge on US imports, it caused a good
                    deal of consternation in Europe and in Britain in particular. Then going through
                    the rise in the oil price on the first of January, 1974, that I think we
                    mentioned before. And, in this period also, the negotiations for Britain's entry
                    into the Common Market, which raised issues and heightened issues in our minds,
                    in particular about agriculture, but about other things too. So this was a time
                    of tension, uncertainty and change. In some senses it showed the importance of
                    the OECD, the fact that we had something like that in existence, well supported
                    with a secretariat that was excellent in some fields, including fields of most
                    importance here. I remember that following the announcement, late in 1973, by
                    the OPEC countries of the increase in the oil prices that would shortly go into
                    effect, there was this flurry of activity in the OECD and the Secretariat
                    through the Christmas period and all, to try and analyze what the significance
                    of this would be and the analysis, which I think I mentioned last time, seems to
                    have held up as having been quite valid.</p>
                <p>One concern that the Secretariat and the Organization expressed in particular was
                    that countries, especially the developed companies, the oil importing countries
                    that were most impacted by this rise in price of oil, would react in
                    protectionist ways. So, the organization developed a trade pledge, that is a
                    pledge that committed the countries not to take protectionist actions as a
                    reaction to the rise in the price of oil. And that was something we worked on
                    significantly, both in the development of the pledge and then in its renewal
                    later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it initially for one year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: My recollection is that it was for one year. I remember the discussions
                    of renewal while I was there too, so I suppose that means it was one year in
                    each case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have been reading a book called “The Cold War, A
                        History,” and one of the points it makes is that one of the good results, if
                        you will, of the Cold War was a number of economic measures that served to
                        strengthen and pull together the cohesion of the countries of the West. The
                        OECD, obviously, was one of the important organs or institutions that
                        brought together the industrial countries. Was that a theme or sentiment
                        that you thought much about at the time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ROGERS: I think it was more something that we took for granted. I don't think it
                    was explicit in our thinking. Rather the focus of our thinking tended to be
                    protecting the continuing movement, the overall trend towards liberalization and
                    opening up markets for goods and capital and all, against the rise in the price
                    of oil. This was a period of adjusting to or toward a new international
                    financial system, devaluation of the dollar in 1973, I guess it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think 1971 perhaps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, there was August 15, 1971, but then in February, 1973 there was
                    another action, and I can't remember just what it was, but it again disturbed
                    people and we had to explain and defend the action. I mention that because
                    looking through my notes I recall that I happened to be sitting in the Council
                    of the OECD at that point and defending the action by the United States to our
                    major trading partners.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose in retrospect one would have wished that when a
                        major action like that were taken that there had been prior consultation,
                        discussion in an organ like the OECD with our major trading partners. But in
                        some cases that wasn't feasible, wasn't possible, wasn't even thought of,
                        and then it became an important task of explaining, justifying, defending
                        what had already been done after the fact.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: All that is true and a little embarrassing on occasion, but the United
                    States was and remains a large economy and has perhaps different
                    responsibilities and requirements than other countries because of that
                    reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was also some disadvantage when you telegraphed your
                        intentions by consulting, by discussing because that has an impact,
                        obviously, for certain parties who are involved in the market.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It gives a field day to speculators, among other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1975 you returned once again to Washington to a
                        very different part of the world and different kind of assignment.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, as I remember that was at the time when a policy was established by
                    Secretary Kissinger (”GLOP”) came into affect. He had decided that people who
                    were well experienced and thoroughly familiar with one part of the world ought
                    to go to another part of the world. He wanted to break up certain groupings,
                    traditions, etc. to bring ideas and fresh light into various policies,
                    including, perhaps particularly, that of Latin America. So I left Paris in 1975
                    to become the director of office of regional economic policy (ECP) in the Bureau
                    of Inter-America Affairs, which was quite new to me. It wasn't entirely new in
                    the sense that another theme that certainly was important to us at the OECD (and
                    the OECD covers a tremendous range of interesting activities, very quietly for
                    the most part), was the relationship between developed and developing countries.
                    Of course, oil figured prominently in that context, but it was much broader than
                    that. The whole world trade structure was important and the developing
                    countries, of course, felt they were being disadvantaged by it. There were the
                    problems of the multi-national corporations that acted, the developing countries
                    thought, not necessarily in their interests and their connections abroad. So it
                    was an interesting time to become involved in Latin American affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were involved primarily in multilateral regional
                        issues or also bilateral economic issues between the United States and Latin
                        American countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: We got somewhat involved in the bilateral issues, but it was more
                    directed at those issues that extended to more than one country in Latin
                    America. I remember we spent a lot of time working with other agencies and other
                    parts of the department on the list of products that would be covered by the
                    generalized scheme of preferences to try to make it as beneficial as possible
                    within the context of US interests to Latin American countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't suppose at that time there begun to be any
                        consideration of what came after, much later, involving Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Right. To jump a head a little bit about that. That certainly came up in
                    my next assignment when I was in Mexico. That was at the time of the second big
                    oil price hike in 1979. Mexico didn't exactly discover it had oil at that point,
                    because it had been a major oil producer back in the 1930s which led up to the
                    nationalization of the oil industry, but rather there was new public recognition
                    that Mexico had huge reserves of oil that had not yet been exploited. That
                    hadn't been widely discussed publicly partly because they were of recent
                    discovery in their magnitude and partly as a matter of policy because of the
                    concern of what knowledge of such oil supplies would do in the domestic
                    political scene. But we can come back to the NAFTA business later.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, let's go back to your time in ARA. That was at the
                        end of the Ford administration and the beginning of the Carter
                        administration. Certainly the Carter administration in terms of Latin
                        American policy stood for human rights, democracy. I don't know how
                        important economic and trade issues were.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Human rights and democracy were not particularly our responsibility in
                    RPE. Of course, there was always fall out from things such as Deputy Secretary
                    Christopher's mission to Brazil on the nuclear question, and we had to take this
                    into account in looking at other policies. But basically it continued to be
                    matters of trade and development and trying to reconcile our interests. We had
                    issues of trade in meat that some of the Latin American countries were quite
                    concerned about.</p>
                <p>To go back again, continuing when Secretary Kissinger was running things, Latin
                    America wasn't very high on the list of his priorities, for understandable
                    reasons. That is not a criticism. But he did get involved, including I recall a
                    meeting of the OAS General Assembly in Santiago at one point when he wanted to
                    make a real statement showing our interest in Latin America. I recall working on
                    the speech that he gave there, at length in Washington and then rewriting and
                    adding to it up to the last minute in Santiago a kind of agenda of policies to
                    assist Latin America and respond to their concerns.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Secretary Kissinger give that speech?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: He certainly did. He insisted on strengthening it and beefing it up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were part of the delegation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. That was a function of ECP, to help backstop the delegation to the
                    OAS, as well as to the Economic Commission for Latin America. At an earlier time
                    I headed the US technical delegation to an ECLA conference in Guatemala. So I
                    had a fair amount of contact of that sort with Latin Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How large a staff did you have in ECP?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Six or seven people or so. It was not a huge staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you work closely with the Economic Bureau of the State
                        Department as well as other agencies?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Sometimes in conflict, but we did our best to work with them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then after that, in 1978 you went to Mexico City as
                        counselor for economic affairs. We talked briefly about what later became
                        the North Atlantic Free Trade Area. I assume that you were primarily
                        involved with trade issues in Mexico, or other issues as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was trade, energy, environment, transport, communications, a whole
                    range of different aspects of the relationship. You know the expression “Pobre
                    Mexico. Tan lejos del Dios, tan cerca de Los Estades Unidos,” “So far from God
                    and so close to the United States.” That attitude was completely understandable.
                    Mexico is so vulnerable to the United States if it chooses to see it that way,
                    and if we choose to act in that way. Like Canada, it is in the position of
                    sometimes being forgotten when we make our policy decisions and forget to
                    realize to what a huge extent these two countries are economically dependent on
                    the United States. So, I found a kind of understandable defensiveness on the
                    part of the Mexicans on issues of all sorts where many of them felt we were
                    taking advantage of them.</p>
                <p>I guess the extreme case was when one of the prominent papers, I think it was
                    Excelsior, at a time of drought in Mexico published a theoretically serious
                    story about how they had discovered that this was the result of a US plot—that
                    we by seeding clouds had made sure that the rain fell elsewhere and not in
                    Mexico. But, as I say, this was understandable.</p>
                <p>At the time that oil became such a factor, in the Mexican economy and in its
                    political consciousness, the Mexicans both felt pride and hope and became
                    protective of this wealth that they had. And when there were proposals in the US
                    Congress at that point for a North American Free Trade Area, the Mexicans
                    naturally reacted that this was an attempt by the United States to get a hold of
                    Mexico's oil reserves. I don't know what the motivation of the proposers was,
                    but one can assume that that was a factor in their thinking, that it would make
                    it easier for the United States to buy oil from Mexico, also giving Mexico an
                    assured market in the United States, and that became a factor later. But the
                    Mexicans saw this kind of proposal as another attack on their sovereignty, or
                    some Mexicans did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the feeling that perhaps the United States
                        paid more attention, took more into account, its other neighbor Canada,
                        perhaps because of its higher standard of living, more developed economy,
                        perhaps even greater integration than Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>ROGERS: One would think that Canada and Mexico might have found common interests
                    in trying to deal with the United States and I seem to recall one or two
                    occasions when there were contacts between the two governments of that sort. My
                    impression is that the Mexicans consider themselves in such a different
                    situation from Canada's that it was just hard to find any comparability there. I
                    don't recall that there was any jealousy or resentment of our policy toward
                    Canada. I don't think that was the situation. I think Mexico felt it was not
                    relevant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the period that you were in Mexico City, 1978-82, a lot
                        of American investment was taking place, especially in the border
                        region...assembling plants, etc. Was that a particular issue for you? Did
                        you spend quite a bit of time up along the border?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, I can't say that I spent a lot of time up there, but certainly we
                    were very conscious of this, and the Mexicans were very conscious of the
                    positive aspects of the maquiladora phenomenon. The industry grew very fast and
                    I take it it has continued to grow very fast since. I suppose NAFTA put it into
                    a different context which decreases the value of the maquiladoras except the
                    geographical location is still important. Maquiladoras could be in other parts
                    of Mexico, but the great bulk of them were near the US border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One other aspect perhaps of US-Mexican relations that I
                        would like to touch on briefly. I know from my experience in dealing with
                        Canada on a couple of different occasions, the issues are extremely concrete
                        and specific and also involved domestic agencies of government which were
                        perhaps not otherwise involved in international affairs...in environment and
                        various aspects on the economic side. Did you find that was the case in
                        Mexico too, and did other agencies try to interact directly with their
                        counterparts in Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Fortunately, or unfortunately, the Mexicans speak Spanish and not
                    English. But for other reasons too, there was much less of that with Mexico than
                    with Canada. In fact, my recollection is that we tried to encourage this kind of
                    contact on environmental matters for instance, to get the EPA involved with
                    their counterparts in Mexico. We have so many problems that affect both
                    countries along the border and the oceans on both sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went to Mexico City it was still the Carter
                        Administration and you stayed under 1982, which was the first two years of
                        the Reagan Administration. Who was the ambassador when you first went
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>ROGERS: It was Governor Pat Lucey. This is an interesting matter. Governor Lucey
                    was former Governor of Wisconsin and was a very, very pleasant man. He was a man
                    not of Foreign Service experience, but still he did well. Then President Carter
                    decided to appoint Julian Nava as ambassador. Ambassador Nava was from Los
                    Angeles and had been on the school board there. He was the first American
                    Ambassador of Hispanic, Latino descent to be sent to Mexico. I don't recall that
                    the Mexicans were all that excited about having the first Latino American sent
                    there. In any case his tour was cut quite short by the arrival of Mr. Reagan in
                    the White House. President Reagan sent John Gavin down there, another Latino
                    American, in that his mother was born and raised in Mexico. Ambassador Gavin was
                    an interesting person who made quite an impact, quite quickly in the press. He
                    had no fear of the press. Apparently he had had a lot of experience with it. I
                    think he perhaps succeeded, whether immediately or not, President Reagan in the
                    Screen Actors Guild. So he had a lot of experience with the press. He took on
                    the press quite cleverly, sometimes against the advice of his counselors, and
                    held his own very well. The press was tough on the United States there. But he
                    had good humor, his Spanish was a very nice and fluent. I served under him for a
                    year or so, or more. He was quite impressive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is a very large American community, of course, in
                        Mexico. I assume there is a large chamber of commerce. Did you interact to a
                        certain extent with that or with the American business community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. I was an honorary member of the board of the American Chamber and
                    saw American businessmen often. There were issues, certainly, that we tried to
                    help on. It is a very large community spread over a good deal of Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were the relations during that period between the
                        embassy in Mexico City and the State Department in Washington, especially in
                        the economic area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Through most of the time I was there, they went quite well. The last year
                    or so, things got a little tense. There were differences. The fact that
                    Ambassador Gavin was close to President Reagan probably was a factor in that,
                    but I wouldn't want to speculate just how that impacted. But it was the classic
                    case of an ambassador with access that backstoppers in Washington didn't have in
                    the same way. This had an impact on our relations with the Office of Mexican
                    Affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>One other thing about Mexico. Mexico was fascinating for a variety of reasons. I
                    won't go into the historical and cultural reasons, but they are deep. It is a
                    far more interesting country than I think most Americans give it credit for
                    being. But during that period from 1978-82 that I was there as economic
                    counselor—I take neither pride or responsibility in the fact—it was a time of
                    the rise and fall of the Mexican economy. When I got there in 1978 it was coming
                    out of a serious depression. President Lopez Portillo was considered as having
                    the right kinds of attitudes toward business, the economy, inflation, etc. Then
                    the whole oil matter impacted on the economy, so Mexico had a period of growth
                    and prosperity for a couple of years which seemed quite impressive. But in that
                    time, oil rapidly became too dominant a factor. It was a sad thing to watch
                    because the Mexicans knew what was happening, or many did. They had seen what
                    happened in Venezuela, where the ability to export oil crowded out so much
                    economic activity, including feeding themselves. This same sort of thing
                    happened in Mexico, where oil became the great majority of Mexico's exports to
                    the detriment of other parts of its own economy. And then the price of oil
                    declined in the early eighties and by 1982 there was an oil glut. This had
                    tremendous impact. A few months before I left the first crisis devaluation of
                    the Mexican peso took place, and then things just got worse and fell apart. This
                    became a sort of sparkplug for tremendous attention given to the problems of
                    developing countries and their balance of payments in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Mexico a member of OPEC?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Mexico is not a member of OPEC, but coordinated with OPEC and, of course,
                    took advantage of OPEC's decisions to some extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You weren't there later on, but as the Mexican economy
                        became less dependent on its reliance on oil, it industrialized towards an
                        almost developed country economy. I believe only recently Mexico has joined
                        the OECD.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, to someone with my background in Mexico fifteen years ago, the
                    recent events there are hard to believe. From the time that Mexico had this
                    resentment towards the United States and defensiveness, for it to have agreed to
                    the North American Free Trade arrangement, is just astounding and I think a very
                    positive development. And I am not thinking just of the economic side, but as a
                    reflection of a kind of maturity in the political relationship between Mexico
                    and the United States. From my background in the Economic Bureau and my European
                    experience, I am a little bit concerned about the development of regional
                    economic blocs, unless there is some overwhelming economic, or more likely
                    political, reason for it. But I think in this case the political reason was
                    obvious. And the importance of Mexico's economic development to the United
                    States is also obvious in terms of our illegal immigration problem and all. And
                    now, as you mentioned, Mexico has joined the OECD and that is extraordinary.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There have been some very significant developments in the
                        last twelve years since you left.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That is right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is certainly a very dynamic country, both on the
                        economic and political side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: One other thing I would like to mention. By 1982 there was concern by the
                    United States about what was happening to Mexico and also in other developing
                    countries, but especially in Mexico. I give credit to the Reagan administration
                    for trying to develop a set of measures that could help Mexico out of this.
                    Ironically one of those measures was to contract with Mexico for a certain
                    amount of oil to be put into our strategic petroleum reserve. So in a very brief
                    time, say 1980-82, there had been a kind of ironic flip-flop in the oil
                    relationship where we were using oil to help Mexico instead of being a threat to
                    Mexico.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, so in 1982 you completed your assignment in Mexico
                        City and came back to Washington again and I believe you were an instructor
                        in economic matters at the Industrial College of the Armed Forces where you
                        had been a student a few years earlier. We talked a bit before about ICAF
                        and its role. Do you have anything particularly to say about the second
                        experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was interesting to be able to observe the Industrial College from the
                    point of view of the faculty and staff. I took a delight in the title of
                    professor which I must admit was granted, as far as I could tell, without
                    tremendous thought, but I accepted it for what it was worth and enjoyed it.</p>
                <p>There were several aspects of this tour. It took me back to the roots of
                    economics. I was teaching basic economics, which, of course, required that I go
                    back and review a good deal of basic economics and find out how the academics
                    had developed their views on basic macro and micro economics. And that was a lot
                    of fun. I found teaching is not easy. After a couple of classes I was really
                    quite drained. But it was exciting and the students were a good, serious bunch.
                    But teaching 40 year old colonels basic economics was not the easiest job. But
                    also it was the matter of interacting with the State Department students. We
                    always had three or four there.</p>
                <p>I did quite a bit in ICAF's foreign programs, that is, overseas travel, and
                    interaction with the Inter-American Defense College, which is also on the same
                    campus. We set up something called Operacion Amistad to try to get students
                    between the two organizations to interact.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The last year you were there you held the title of
                        International Affairs Advisor, so I assume you were kind of the senior State
                        Department representative on the administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you continue to teach?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I taught some. I taught a course in economic development. I succeeded
                    Bill Wolle in that job and continued more so in being involved in the
                    international aspects of ICAF.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume in both capacity, as professor and international
                        affairs advisor, you did counseling for the State Department students, but
                        also for those from the Defense Department and other agencies.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, then after that you spent a year as senior policy
                        advisor with the Bureau of Oceans and Environmental and Scientific Affairs.
                        That certainly ranks right up there with titles.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, again...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me what you did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I was without an assignment when I left ICAF and didn't feel I should
                    stay there a fourth year, so I went over to the Department to see where I could
                    be useful. It happened to be at a time when then Rep. Manuel Lujan, had inserted
                    with the Congress' permission a clause in legislation that required a serious
                    study of scientific and technological cooperation between the United States and
                    Latin America. OES took me on for the purpose of preparing that report. That
                    took me about six or seven months to write with a lot of help from other people
                    and a certain amount of travel and consultation in Latin America, as well as
                    some discussion with Rep. Lujan as to just what he was looking for. The report
                    was submitted and published. That was kind of fun. I am not basically an
                    academic, but it was fun to do that amount of research and a lot of writing.</p>
                <p>The other project that I was involved in during the period was preparing part of
                    the annual report on international scientific and technical cooperation that the
                    Congress requires. That is worldwide and I wrote a couple of chapters of that
                    and oversaw some other parts of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As far as your report on the Latin American aspect, were
                        you in favor of increased interaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: You know, Ray, the problem there is translating not just good intentions
                    but real policy objectives into concrete projects and programs. You look around
                    to find ways in which there is the time and the money and the impetus on our
                    side to get involved in projects with the Latin Americans and it is not easy to
                    identify them. Many things happen on their own and, of course, we made the most
                    of those in our report. But to find new initiatives from our policy objective
                    position, but without the program need that the different agencies, the
                    Department of Agriculture, the Environmental Protection Administration and all
                    the rest, was not easy. Nevertheless, we came up with some ideas that could be
                    pursued.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is easy to suggest new ideas, new ways of doing things,
                        the hard part is coming up with the resources and the means to do it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, as we are in the State Department rightly admonished for, we are
                    not too bad with coming up with ways to use other agencies' money and other
                    resources. That is nothing to be embarrassed about, but it has to be done in a
                    certain way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And sometimes the other agencies, at least the staff, very
                        much welcomes that because they realize what needs to be done, what could be
                        done, if they only...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: And, of course, we were looking for their ideas at that stage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, Steve, you left OES in 1986 and went overseas. Tell
                        me about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, I hadn't had much experience in Africa, although I had touched a
                    little bit on it, and when I got a call asking if I would be interested in going
                    to Pretoria, my first reaction was one of surprise. Then when I thought about
                    it, it was a time when there was increasing interest in South Africa and it was
                    something new and built on my economic background in a different way, so I said,
                    “That sounds fine.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What exactly was the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, it had two aspects to it—Counselor for Economic Affairs but also
                    the officer in charge. In Pretoria, where the bulk of the embassy was, the
                    ambassador and the deputy chief of mission were there typically for about half
                    the year and the other half of the year they were in Cape Town during the
                    parliamentary session, South Africa having three capitals. One is judicial,
                    Bloemfontein, and didn't figure in this. A large number of people and all the
                    top leaders of government and ambassadors made the trek at least twice a year
                    between Pretoria and Cape Town as the parliamentary sessions required. Twice
                    there were extraordinary sessions, so the ambassador and deputy chief of mission
                    went to Cape Town other than at the usual time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the ambassador and DCM when you first went to
                        Pretoria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Herman Nickel was ambassador when I got there and, of course, he
                    represented the policy of constructive engagement with the South African
                    government, which I continue to think had some reasonable validity and some
                    reasonable chance of success. It was at a time when P.W. Botha was Prime
                    Minister and then President of South Africa. He, in his early years accepted
                    more momentum towards liberalizing racial relations and breaking down the
                    apartheid system and this was encouraging. Unfortunately that process pretty
                    much stopped. I think President Botha worked it up to a certain point and it ran
                    out on him. That was the end as far as he was concerned. So that was a time of
                    considerable frustration for the United States, Britain and other countries that
                    were interested in change, and obviously for Ambassador Nickel.</p>
                <p>About two months after I got to Pretoria and right at the end of Ambassador
                    Nickel' assignment there, Congress passed, over President Reagan's veto, the
                    Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act of 1986. I guess that was about October 4,
                    1986. Of course, the South Africans had recognized the threat of sanctions and
                    there were other types of sanctions that had been in place, but nothing had
                    happened with quite the publicity, the flare, the political force that the
                    Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act of 1986 had. So that had quite an impact on us
                    in the embassy and our relations with the South African government and our
                    relations with the majority of the South African people, and that became a
                    dominant factor in our relationship for the next several years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that impact of the sanctions, the US legislation,
                        primarily political, or did it have a significant economic impact in terms
                        of investment or trade?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>ROGERS: That is a good question. Somebody is going to have to write a definitive
                    study of this at some point and it will be interesting to see what the
                    conclusions are. My own belief is that the principal impact of the Act was
                    political and psychological, rather than economic. I mean there were other
                    factors at work that were having more of an economic impact than the 1986 Act.
                    We had restrictions on IMF loans to South Africa, which weren't necessary in
                    themselves but could have been an important factor in supporting other borrowing
                    that the government might have wanted to undertake in developed countries. And,
                    perhaps, as far as investment is concerned, I think most observers would agree
                    that the more important factor was the tremendous number of state and local
                    actions against those who invested in South Africa. They were of different
                    forms. Pension funds couldn't invest in some cases connected to city employees,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those restrictions were on the investment of money in
                        American companies who were doing business in South Africa. It wasn't
                        necessarily funds being invested directly to South Africa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, that is correct. Or another typical form, I think, was that a company
                    with an investment in South Africa had a harder time getting a contract with a
                    state or city government in the United States. They would have to overcome a
                    certain barrier which might be five or ten percent cost, or something like that.
                    And this sort of thing led to the removal of more than half of the US companies
                    that had been in South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The typical economic and commercial counselor in an
                        American embassy has kind of a duel responsibility. On the one hand he does
                        reporting, analysis, assesses the implications of various actions, and on
                        the other hand is promoting the trade and commerce and investment and trying
                        to overcome difficulties and problems, etc. I assume in the case of Pretoria
                        that you would pretty much do the first, looking at the analysis of
                        sanctions, the effect of apartheid, etc. rather than promoting trade or
                        investment.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>ROGERS: We certainly weren't promoting trade or investment. That was not any
                    significant part of our activities, investment not at all and trade very little.
                    We did follow and try to assist the activities of some American companies that
                    were there to deal with the situation that they found themselves with. A famous
                    case was that of Ford Motor Company, which had a joint venture with
                    Anglo-American or a subsidiary of Anglo-American, in producing Fords and other
                    cars in South Africa. They made the decision that they had to withdraw so the
                    question was what would happen to their perhaps 40 percent in this company,
                    SAMCOR, which was their joint venture. They tried to do this in quite an
                    innovative way by giving the majority of their share to the union of workers at
                    SAMCOR. Well, that was not so easy to set up or to do, but eventually they did
                    accomplish it and Ford withdrew, although they were still selling parts because
                    Fords were still being built in South Africa, but without any direct investment
                    from Ford Motor Company. There were a few things like that and we did interact
                    with American businessmen, but it was not in the same promotional way as
                    elsewhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to talk a little bit about this function of
                        officer-in-charge when the parliament was in session in Cape Town. Other
                        than, in the absence of the ambassador and DCM, managing the embassy, were
                        there elements of the South African government still in Pretoria that you
                        would make representations to, make demarches to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Oh, yes. It is just the top officials, the ministers and their immediate
                    staffs, who would go to Cape Town. The ministers were members of parliament, of
                    course, so they had to be there and their deputy ministers to some extent. But
                    the top civil servants tended to stay in Pretoria, along with their staffs. So
                    at that level, things sort of continued as normal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know that during the period of Ambassador Bill Swing, he
                        tried very hard to straddle this divide and spend part of the week in
                        Pretoria even during the parliamentary session and part of the time in Cape
                        Town. It wasn't done, I guess, during the period you were there. They pretty
                        much went away did they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Most of the time I was there, Ed Perkins was the ambassador and he went
                    to Cape Town and he would come to Pretoria; it is easy enough to go back and
                    forth. I would sometimes go to Cape Town and he would some times come to
                    Pretoria for one reason or another. But Bill did try to do that more. There was
                    always the question of how to handle this situation. The inspectors came and
                    gave their recommendation and, of course, we criticized their recommendations,
                    but it was basically a difficult and ultimately impossible dilemma, and we just
                    had to deal with it as well as we could. That meant I was on the phone a good
                    deal with the DCM in Cape Town. It was important that I find out what the
                    ambassador and he or she wanted and how to handle certain issues. But we got
                    along.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was certainly important for them to know what you were
                        doing and since the bulk of the staff of the mission continued to be in
                        Pretoria, much of the every day work of the mission was done there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Precisely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to talk a little more about certain policy
                        environment. If you come back to the United States side we had the elections
                        of 1988 in which President Bush was elected; sanctions continued to be in
                        effect; the Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act was still the law of the land.
                        Was there much change that took place at that point on our side or were we
                        pretty much just reacting to some changes that were taking place as far as
                        the nearing end of apartheid on the South African side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Of course, we didn't know we were nearing the end of apartheid. In fact,
                    for the first two years I was there, and well into the third year, I think the
                    general feeling was one of pessimism in the embassy. There would be little
                    things that would happen, there were differences in social contacts and that
                    sort of thing. We certainly tried to contribute to them. Ed Perkins made a very
                    serious effort to get closer to the black leadership and get to know them and
                    develop a sense of confidence on their part about what US intentions were. It
                    was done fairly quietly. This wasn't sticking a finger in the eye of the South
                    African government to a very great extent, but it was effectively developing
                    links with the country as a whole and de-emphasizing direct contact, more
                    limited contact, with the South African government than had characterized the
                    period of constructive engagement. That had some effect, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that something he did pretty much himself, or did he
                        encourage you, as the economic counselor and perhaps others in the embassy,
                        also to develop contacts with the black leadership?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>ROGERS: That was clearly embassy policy to be followed across the board. In my
                    time we always had a member of my economic section who spent full time on
                    interacting with black economic institutions. Trying to get to know them and
                    analyze where they were and help them to some extent. We developed in that
                    time—the administrative section developed—a policy of trying to emphasize black
                    companies as suppliers to the embassy. My people cooperated in trying to put
                    that list of potential suppliers together. So that was there and was
                    intensified. We tried in our social engagements to mix up blacks and whites, and
                    that was quite fascinating. We would have a dinner, for instance, and perhaps
                    have ten people around the table, including one or two black couples and one or
                    two Afrikaner couples, or have a reception with a mixed guest list of the same
                    sort, and find that these people who had hardly ever interacted on the basis of
                    social equality on neutral ground, interacting some times quite vigorously over
                    the dinner table. Sometimes there would be quite pointed exchanges and both
                    sides seemed to enjoy it immensely. That was one thing that gave you some hope,
                    that kind of reaction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The American embassy was doing this and certainly it was a
                        great achievement. Were other embassies doing it? Were there other
                        opportunities for blacks and Afrikaners to come together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I couldn't swear to it. I suspect that we did it more than others did.
                    The change had started before I got there, significantly in some respects, but
                    even when I got there, the adventure of our church, the Congregational Church,
                    making a kind of an annual pilgrimage to a black church with which it was
                    associated in the Northern Transvaal, quite isolated, was a major thing, to have
                    that kind of contact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a South African congregation that you attended,
                        it wasn't part of the American community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Oh, no, we were the only Americans there. In fact, the congregation was
                    part of the United Congregational Church of Southern Africa, which in total was
                    80 - 85 percent non-white. So the total context was one of integration, but
                    individual congregations were either black, colored or white. That was just a
                    fact of life regardless of what people wanted. The interaction between
                    congregations of different parts of the community were the interesting
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: South Africa is a very large, complex country. We had
                        consulates at that time and, of course, still do in Cape Town, Johannesburg
                        and Durban. Did you have a chance to travel widely around the country? How
                        did you interact with the consulates?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, I visited all three consulates from time to time. Johannesburg
                    often, of course, because it is the economic capital of South Africa and we have
                    a large and very competent consulate there with many activities. The labor
                    attach� was there, for instance, and the commercial attach� was there. So my
                    staff and I had a lot of contact with them. I visited Durban two or three times
                    and Cape Town quite a number of times to interact also with them. We saw a lot
                    of South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the chance to travel to other parts of
                        southern Africa? Was there much sense of connection between South Africa and
                        the rest of the continent? Certainly the rest of the continent, from my
                        experience, was extremely interested in what was happening in South Africa
                        and paying very close attention to it throughout this period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: All the neighboring countries, of course, had this conflict in their own
                    minds, recognizing that South Africa was by far the dominant economy of the
                    region and yet wanting to put pressure on and distance themselves from South
                    Africa for very understandable political reasons. Zimbabwe was perhaps a prime
                    example, where President Mugabe has always been outspoken in his opposition and
                    his wish to put pressure on South Africa, and yet trade between Zimbabwe and
                    South Africa increased to Zimbabwe's considerable advantage, to its
                    manufacturing sector in particular. It was difficult for those countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I went to Ghana in 1989 and at that time Ghana Airways had
                        a weekly flight in a DC 10 to Harare, which was explained to me partly
                        because there were some special connections between Zimbabwe and Ghana,
                        including the fact that President Mugabe's late wife was a Ghanaian and
                        there were quite a few Ghanaians working there, etc. But I think far more
                        important was that Harare was seen as a way station to South Africa and the
                        rest of southern Africa. So it was not necessarily a commercial proposition,
                        but it was one looking to the future and a political reason for being
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: That is very interesting and makes concrete something that Foreign
                    Minister Pik Botha mentioned frequently and with some enthusiasm, that South
                    Africa had economic relations with all but one African country. These relations
                    were not advertised specifically and not generally by the countries other than
                    South Africa, for good political reasons. But they were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved at all in issues like Angola and
                        Namibia and Mozambique, or were those pretty much handled by other sections
                        in the mission?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Pretty much by others in the mission, yes. These were factors in the
                    thinking for all of us and part of the context for all of us.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left in 1990. What was the atmosphere like at that
                        time compared to four years earlier when you arrived? Had much changed or
                        was it still to come in the future?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: We, of course, always tried to see how things were developing, to look
                    into the future and see how things might go. About the middle of my tour in
                    South Africa, we gave a little more attention to this and developed the usual
                    three scenarios of what might happen, and they were really three degrees of
                    disaster that we came up with. There was no sign of what was to take place just
                    a few months after that. In fact, while we could see the pressures building and
                    we could see some response to these pressures through time, the movement was so
                    slight. We could find examples of progress, but it was the old question of which
                    end of the tube are you looking through. You can look through one end and see
                    that things are moving rapidly from that end, but you look at it through the
                    other end of the tube you can't determine any movement because it is so far
                    away. Well, things were happening but not to satisfaction of anyone in the
                    majority black population. But there were some developments that were completely
                    fortuitous. P.W. Botha's stroke for instance. Also certain developments in the
                    schedule of elections that seemed to be important as things worked out. So, we
                    were quite astonished to see the changes that took place in 1989 with F.W. de
                    Klerk becoming head of the party and then President. In his speech on February
                    2, 1990 he announced that Nelson Mandela would be released and the ANC and other
                    subversive organizations would be allowed to operate inside South Africa, and
                    the process started that led to the change of government on May 10 of this year.
                    [1994]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The speech by de Klerk of February 1990 was when you were
                        still there; however, the release of Nelson Mandela came after you
                        left.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, no, it was a couple of weeks after the speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, while you were still there it radically changed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They radically changed. It was just astonishing the change that took
                    place in that last year that I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To come back to the American side, the anti-apartheid
                        sanctions continued to be in effect though for a while. In the last few
                        months that you were there, did you see much sign on the American business
                        side of new possibilities starting to take an interest, or was that
                        later?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>ROGERS: That sort of thing took time for a variety of reasons. One is that the
                    state and local restrictions were still in effect, which inhibited some
                    companies from even staying in South Africa, much less increasing or starting
                    new investments in South Africa. In fact, if I recall correctly the city of New
                    York was still imposing new sanctions in 1990, which seemed way out of line with
                    the trend of things, but that happened. So, those sanctions were still an
                    obstacle to any investment. But people began showing interest in coming and that
                    was good. But it is a slow process to redevelop interest in a market for most
                    companies and industries, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there under three ambassador; Herman Nickel, Ed
                        Perkins and then Bill Swing. Each obviously had a different style, different
                        approach, and was dealing with a revolving situation. I guess I am
                        interested in the embassy's relationship with Washington. Did you feel that
                        Washington recognized these changes or was the attitude in Washington still
                        very hesitant, restrictive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: In the period I was there, there was no inclination on the part of the
                    embassy to try to change the basic relationship. It was still waiting to see if
                    all this promise that was there would really lead to the negotiation of a
                    solution to the problem. It took three or four more years to accomplish. So, I
                    don't think that it really was an occasion for a change of policy to be
                    recommended. We became more open and more active in our relationships with the
                    black sector of the community. Certainly Bill Swing built on what Ed Perkins had
                    done and did it in a more public fashion, made more of a thing of it. It was
                    presumably the right time to be doing that. We had had an AID program even when
                    I arrived in 1986, a rather small AID program with one or two AID officials, to
                    try to help black business and education and leadership development. That
                    program expanded quite a bit and we set up a full-fledged AID mission with the
                    unique aspect that it had no relationship with the South African government,
                    almost unique in AID experience. So that expanded considerably up to a $40
                    million a year program, I think it was by the time I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you first got there, was the AID operation part of
                        the economic section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: My predecessor had a lot to do with that. By the time I got there, there
                    was an AID person there and the staff was being developed. I had interest and
                    some involvement in it, but it was directed more in the way of a traditional AID
                    program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I seem to remember during this period there was a lot of
                        debate and discussion about the African National Conference, the ANC, in
                        terms of its economic policies if it ever came to power—whether it would be
                        communist, what it saw as the role of the private market. Was that an issue
                        of interest to you at the time and did you have contact with ANC people on
                        the economic policy side?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>ROGERS: We certainly did. It was of interest and we did have such contacts. Not
                    long before he was released, Nelson Mandela in an interview reiterated the kind
                    of statements that had given concern in the past about nationalizing industries
                    and that sort of thing, which was a little bit discouraging. But, you know, a
                    process began and it continued through a lot of very constructive, I think,
                    interaction between white business and black business in South Africa and
                    between academics of different points of view, which has led to the situation we
                    have today. I don't know that there has been any nationalization or talk of
                    immediate nationalization. Certainly the ANC is committed to a basically market
                    economy approach to development with a very large role for private
                    enterprise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the period that you were there, Steve, were there
                        quite a few American visitors, members of Congress, staff members or members
                        of the American academic community coming through?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: There was a lot of interest and many visits. I guess there have been a
                    lot more since, particularly at the time of the change of government and all.
                    Yes, we had study groups coming through and we talked to them. I remember
                    spending quite a bit of time with Senator Simon and others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were there certainly during a watershed period.
                        The last year things really did happen quickly. Was there anything else you
                        would like to mention during your tour in Pretoria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. I think what we began to see then and saw still more in the ensuing
                    three years which I watched from Swaziland, what students might in future years
                    analyze as kind of classic development of a new consensus in a country. Not a
                    complete consensus, by any means, but a large measure of agreement as to what
                    South Africa should be and where it should go. The general lines of that. And
                    considering where the different parties were coming from, that is quite a
                    remarkable event.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that consensus across the political spectrum does, of
                        course, leave out those extreme fringes on both sides.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, of course, there are always going to be people outside the sort of
                    bell curve of opinion in something like that. But the extreme right discredited
                    itself so thoroughly in the Bophuthatswana incident last year. The extreme at
                    the other end seems to have been sort of brought along for the most part.
                    Developing a consensus through this process was a difficult matter with a lot of
                    violence. It was so sad, the number of people who were killed in the process.
                    But through it all the leadership of the main parties maintained a sense of an
                    objective and through time developed a kind of momentum which led to
                    continuation or sometimes resumption of negotiations despite pretty horrible
                    examples of oppression and reaction and all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most observers seem to give Nelson Mandela and de Klerk
                        credit for that primarily, that finding of a common ground. Is that your
                        opinion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: South Africa is certainly blessed with extraordinary leadership and that
                    is a good thing, and those two men in particular, although it couldn't be
                    limited to them. I think there are other factors that are perhaps deep in the
                    various psyches of South Africans, if that is the right term. People talk about
                    South Africa being a violent country and there is a lot of basis for that, but
                    when you look at the characteristics of different parts of the population, the
                    Afrikaners are most hospitable people, and we always found that even with the
                    most conservative of them, with very few exceptions, they wanted to talk about
                    their ideas, their situation and their interests. You go to the black community
                    and you find despite all this experience of oppression, apartheid, increasing
                    separation of the races, especially after 1948, that in spite of that I found
                    almost no sign that the blacks had become racist. That is quite a surprising
                    development, I would think. Sure, there was some bitterness and all that, but
                    you didn't have the feeling that the blacks were out to destroy the whites. The
                    most you could say was that there were black consciousness people who wanted to
                    set the whites aside until blacks had developed their own socio-economic
                    structures and then invite them back in to participate on an equal basis, but
                    even that was a minor part of the black thinking. So, with some underlying
                    positive factors there was the possibility of this extraordinary leadership to
                    develop a consensus of a non-racist South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a very optimistic view of South Africa at the time
                        you left, is that accurate?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>ROGERS: I am optimistic in terms of a long run evolution of South Africa and
                    southern Africa. I wouldn't want that to be misunderstood. In fact, I think the
                    important thing for us as observers from the United States now is to recognize
                    that while the momentum is there and the consensus has been developed to a
                    certain point, there are an awful lot of problems and there will be strains and
                    we can still expect some violence. I am sure that we will hear things from South
                    Africa that we won't like. There will be policies of the new government that we
                    will think are counterproductive and we will find conflicts in our interests
                    with theirs from time to time. So there are going to be occasions when people
                    can say that it looks as if things are going in the wrong direction or that the
                    changes failed, etc. But we need to keep in mind the underlying trends and the
                    fact that tremendous progress has been made and that there is a kind of
                    consensus, I believe. I hope I am right about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the economic side there are enormous disparities I
                        think between those living in squalor, poverty in the townships and those
                        that have been able to be educated and done well. So I see that as an area
                        for change.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: There are tremendous disparities in housing, education, and employment.
                    There are so many unemployed blacks, especially young people, who are perhaps
                    susceptible to leadership and unconstructive direction. It is going to take a
                    long time to overcome this, but if the new government can improve things and
                    then continue a sense of step-by-step progress on the economic side, I think
                    that the fact that there remain great disparities will not be as important. The
                    disparities will become very serious if there is no sense that something is
                    being done, even if at a pretty modest pace, to overcome that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in 1990 you completed your four years in South
                        Africa, came back to Washington and then returned to the neighborhood as
                        Ambassador to Swaziland. Could you tell me how that came about and a little
                        bit about what your responsibilities and duties were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Mary Ryan, who was my predecessor, had been there a year and a half when
                    she was called back to Washington to be the principal deputy to the Assistant
                    Secretary for Consular Affairs, which left a vacancy. I happened to be well
                    situated having had the experience in Pretoria, and the interest and knowledge
                    of South Africa, which is very much the context for Swaziland. I was very
                    pleased to be asked and to accept appointment as ambassador to Swaziland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were nominated when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>ROGERS: It was a long process. From the time we began to discuss this, which was
                    November, 1989 when I happened to be in Washington, to the time I actually got
                    there was just short of a year, November 12, 1990. It was the usual long
                    process. I got the agr�ment, I guess, in April, and it was announced soon
                    afterwards. I had the Senate Foreign Relations Committee hearing and then it
                    moved fairly fast, but with all the clearances it just took a long, long
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you say something about the embassy in Swaziland?
                        You will have to tell me the name of the capital.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: The capital is Mbabane.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How big was the staff when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It depends how you count it because we had maybe a dozen State Department
                    Americans there, but we had FSNs and other agencies. We had a substantial AID
                    mission. We had USIS operation of about ten people, one American and the rest
                    Swazis. We had a Peace Corps contingent of 70 volunteers with perhaps 20 staff.
                    We have a Bureau of the Foreign Broadcast Information Service. Then with all the
                    contract people and everyone like that, I think you could come up to 250 who
                    were responsible to the embassy directly or indirectly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All those people were involved with US programs in
                        Swaziland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, essentially all, although we had some regional responsibilities.
                    Several people in AID had regional responsibilities for aspects of AID
                    operations in Mozambique, South Africa, and Lesotho and maybe one or two other
                    countries, and the FBIS bureau covered several countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the general climate of US relations with
                        Swaziland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I think the relationship was quite good. We had our ups and downs because
                    of one or two things I will mention. The government is two parallel types: the
                    king is very much the king of Swaziland. He and his mother, the queen mother,
                    are the co-monarchs of Swaziland. This is serious. He has a structure of
                    advisors and the royal family and chiefs and other traditional figures who
                    remain important to the Swazis' sense of unity and of organization and to their
                    ability to get things done. The king also appoints the prime minister. There is
                    a two-house parliament with one house elected. There is a cabinet with the usual
                    ministries.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there political parties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Officially there are no political parties at all in Swaziland and that is
                    an issue. That is something they are going to have to deal with, but in due
                    course that will come.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the population?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: The population is something under a million.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of things were we doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They included agricultural, educational, and small business. The Peace
                    Corps and AID were getting more into environmental issues. Peace Corps
                    volunteers were mostly teachers in high schools. They were spread all over the
                    country. One of the great things about being the ambassador there was that I had
                    a reason to go visit these volunteers and that was the basis for seeing
                    practically all corners of the country. That was great fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were teaching science, mathematics or...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, science and math and to some extent vocational subjects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mention that relations were generally good but you had
                        some ups and downs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, the relationship was good. US national interests are not heavily
                    involved in Swaziland. That is fairly obvious. Swaziland is important to us and
                    we have a certain amount of investment and trade, but these are not very large
                    figures. It is important to us that the Swazis understand our votes in
                    international organizations where we both have seats, the UN organization for
                    instance. So there are things like that that are important to us. Swaziland's
                    position of being almost surrounded by South Africa, but also with a border with
                    Mozambique, gives it a kind of strategic position which is important for
                    watching what goes on around and for sharing views and information on relations
                    with South Africa and Mozambique and elsewhere in the African continent, because
                    Swaziland has had some leadership roles in African organizations.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>Aside from these things, our principal concerns while I was there were the
                    political development and economic development of Swaziland. The AID program and
                    the Peace Corps, of course, were related mostly to the economic development of
                    Swaziland. But we also felt that in accordance with US policy towards Africa we
                    needed to pay a good deal of attention to the human rights and democratization
                    aspects of political development in Swaziland. This was coming along. The king,
                    when I presented my credentials, told me about his plan to set up a commission
                    to consult with the people of Swaziland on what political changes they would
                    like to have take place. And, indeed, this process did take place and the answer
                    was, and I think it was legitimately determined, that the people wanted to elect
                    at least the Lower House of parliament, the House of Assembly. And that election
                    did take place a month or two before I left three years later. It happened in a
                    Swazi way and at a Swazi pace, but that was all right, the progress was
                    there.</p>
                <p>On the human rights side I got rather a quick introduction to the problem. Two
                    days after I arrived there was a demonstration on the campus of the University
                    of Swaziland. I think it was not much more than the thing that college students
                    tend to do. They had some complaints and they demonstrated. But the response to
                    this got out of hand and it became rather violent with both the police and the
                    military involved. A number of students were injured, one seriously. I don't
                    think anyone was killed, although there were claims of that happening. The
                    government opted to try to crack down on the people they thought were the
                    leaders of this group. Two of those leaders came to the embassy the next
                    morning, three days after I had arrived, looking for asylum. Well, asylum wasn't
                    appropriate and wasn't feasible. The terminology was wrong and there was no
                    reason for us to give protection. Their lives were not in danger. So we didn't
                    feel we could keep them, but it did take a couple of days to work this out,
                    talking with the Swazi government, with Washington and the two fellows
                    themselves. We ushered them out of the embassy early on a Saturday morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they did stay for a few days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They stayed two days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All of this was before you presented credentials?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Well, they came in on Thursday morning and I presented my credentials on
                    Thursday afternoon, having had a quick visit with the prime minister before then
                    to discuss this issue. It was not an issue in my discussion with the king, but
                    it was certainly on his mind and was on my mind. These two men left Swaziland
                    and went to South Africa, but then South Africa returned them about two days
                    later and they were immediately picked up by the police at that point and
                    detained. Swaziland at that point had a provision that allowed the prime
                    minister to issue an order of detention for 60 days without charges. We had made
                    it known long before that we didn't think this was proper from a human rights
                    standpoint, especially since the 60 days could be renewed for another 60 days
                    continually.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes, that happened in this case. There were three or four other leaders
                    who had not come to the embassy or left the country who were also detained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the concern for us both in the context of our overall
                        respect and human rights policy, but also the particular instance where they
                        had actually come to the American embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It was basically the principle, but having had the experience with these
                    two young men added an edge, at least, to our policy on the subject and our
                    expression of the policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say the embassy in this case, do you mean the
                        office building, the chancery or do you mean your residence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, it was the chancery. We had them for almost 48 hours in the anteroom
                    outside the consular and administrative area and there were no facilities. This
                    was not easy to handle. We allowed them to be fed by relatives who brought food
                    for them. Otherwise it was pretty difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather that access to senior government people. The
                        prime minister, ministers, was pretty easy for you, is that right? Were
                        there other embassies in Mbabane?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Yes. The British have a high commission there. Mozambique has an embassy.
                    I must say that the Mozambique ambassador became a good friend and a colleague
                    with a very constructive role in Swaziland. The Mozambicans I think provided
                    good counsel to Swaziland. The president met with the king and their
                    conversations were good and encouraged the right kind of developments from our
                    point of view in Swaziland and the right kind of relations with Mozambique.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the king, or prime minister, or other Swazi leaders
                        have an impact also the other way in terms of developments in
                        Mozambique?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They were certainly very interested in what happened in Mozambique and
                    until 1992, of course, there was a great deal of violence, the war was on. I
                    don't recall the exact date of the agreement, but since that point it had been
                    quite quiet. The Swazis recognize the importance of that to them. The shortest
                    rail route to the sea is from Swaziland to Maputo. That has hardly been used
                    because of the violence and the losses on the way and particularly in Maputo
                    port.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The rebel movement in Mozambique was Renamo and at one
                        point it certainly had support from South Africa. Was Swaziland involved
                        with that at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: I think the Swazis tried to stay out of that. There may have been
                    contacts on occasion, but basically the Swazis very wisely did not, at least in
                    my knowledge, try to influence developments other than encouraging movements
                    towards peace.</p>
                <p>A couple of things I would like to go back to. One, just for the record, you
                    asked about other embassies. It is an interesting small collection of diplomatic
                    missions there. In addition to the British and the Mozambicans, the Taiwan
                    Chinese have an embassy there. Korea had an embassy while I was there headed by
                    a charg� d'affaires, but it has since been closed. Israel has an embassy in
                    Swaziland. The European Community has a mission there. South Africa had a trade
                    mission which has just in the last few months been upgraded to an embassy. And
                    then there was a set of UN agencies, four or five, there. Those plus honorary
                    consuls, about seven or eight, and a representative of the German embassy in
                    Mozambique, constituted the diplomatic corps very broadly defined, perhaps 19 or
                    20 people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Suggestions are made some times that the United States,
                        essentially for cost cutting reasons, ought to eliminate some of the
                        resident embassies that we have in very small countries and handle relations
                        on a regional basis where the ambassador would rove around. How would you
                        feel about that after being ambassador in a small country like
                        Swaziland?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>ROGERS: Swaziland would be a candidate for that sort of thing, you can't deny
                    that, if we decided to move significantly away from a policy of having permanent
                    diplomatic resident representation in every African country. Mennen Williams, as
                    Assistant Secretary for African Affairs, established that policy when Kennedy
                    was President, at the time that so many of these countries were becoming
                    independent. In fact, for the first several years the ambassador to Swaziland
                    was resident in Botswana. So we could return to something like that. Obviously,
                    I would regret that. I think we have a role there. I think we have a role in
                    every African country. Specifically in Swaziland? Well I can't cite fundamental
                    US interests that would be seriously jeopardized, but I think we have an
                    opportunity to, and I think we do, encourage what is an African country that
                    works. I noticed the Washington Post used that term with Zimbabwe the other
                    day—Zimbabwe works, and it does. We hear so much about African countries that
                    don't work and Swaziland works well. It works better than Zimbabwe,
                    incidentally, but on a smaller scale. I think we can continue to encourage this
                    economic and political development that we have been encouraging, and I think it
                    is worthwhile in the overall context of Africa.</p>
                <p>I might return to a point we were discussing—the detention without charges
                    matter—that we raised as an example. Those five or six people, plus one prince
                    who had gotten on the wrong side of things and had been in detention for a few
                    years, finally were released a little over four months after the incident at the
                    chancery. There were a lot of people in the government of Swaziland who didn't
                    like that provision of detention and there were pressures...one of the fellows
                    went on a hunger strike which had an effect. The Swazis also recognized that the
                    United States, Britain and others felt that this was unsuitable for a country
                    like Swaziland, or any country. So they were released. For the rest of my time
                    in Swaziland and to date there have been no detainees without charges. In fact,
                    last year the king abolished the provision that allowed detention without
                    charges. Well, that kind of thing occurs because of internal pressures rather
                    than external pressures, but we can encourage it by being there in a way that we
                    couldn't otherwise.</p>
                <p>There were other human rights and political issues which we took up in our human
                    rights report, in our chapter of the report now on 179 countries which is sent
                    to the Congress every year. We listed these and made a lot of use of that
                    chapter—12 or 13 pages on Swaziland. We distributed it quite widely. One year
                    the chapter on Swaziland was published in its entirety in the major daily paper
                    in Swaziland. In fact, it was translated and also published in the Swazi edition
                    of the same paper.People have shown interest in these reports. Their interest is
                    in how the world sees them.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>After all that, I have to say that the human rights situation in Swaziland is
                    quite good. The government, both traditional and modern forms, treats the people
                    quite well. There are always complaints and complaints of oppression...I
                    remember I was making a speech one time and in the question period one fellow,
                    who became a good friend of mine, stood up and made a long speech as to how
                    there was no freedom of speech in Swaziland. Well, obviously he was disproving
                    his own point by making the speech and getting away with it. He was never
                    detained. So the situation is quite good but there are things that need to be
                    dealt with and we are in a position to encourage that process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How to conduct the human rights aspect of our foreign
                        policy is always somewhat controversial. Obviously each situation differs
                        somewhat. There is a suggestion that in some cases it may be counter
                        productive by applying pressure and getting just the opposite of what we
                        seek. Nationalism may take over and people dig in their heels and say, “It
                        is none of your business, we are going to deal with it ourselves.” And, in
                        fact, the person may wind up being detained longer than otherwise would have
                        been the case. I assume that wasn't what happened in this case.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: No, it wasn't. We tailored the policy according to the situation. The
                    situation being that the instinct was there to move along both on human rights
                    and on democratization. The king had discussed it in public and had set up these
                    mechanisms to move in the direction of democratization. So it was only rarely
                    that we were in a position of challenging or criticizing the government. We were
                    clear in our positions, in the descriptions in the chapter on human rights, for
                    instance. But for the most part, and particularly on the political change, I was
                    very happy in public to say how pleased we were with certain steps that had been
                    taken and how we were looking forward to the next steps which had been announced
                    and promised and would be taking place. I continued that approach until the end
                    of my time there, and I hope it was useful in encouraging the country to move in
                    the right direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You thoroughly enjoyed your period there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: Oh, absolutely. The Swazis are wonderful people. They are friendly, very
                    nice, interesting and very African. Swaziland in some respects I think has
                    respected the African traditions and philosophies in a way that I doubt that you
                    find with the same kind of purity in most other African countries. It is a
                    homogeneous country, they are all Swazis, they all feel like Swazis. There is no
                    thought that anyone wants to break off or become part of South Africa, or
                    anything like that. That just doesn't come up. Or that they shouldn't be a
                    monarchy or shouldn't respect the king and queen mother and all. I mean these
                    questions don't come up because this is a nation of Swazis. Perhaps five percent
                    are not black, either white or mixed race. But the Swazi culture is very firm
                    and they are proud of their traditions. They have long stories of their families
                    and clans, etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Certainly in economic matters they are dominated by South
                        Africa, but they feel very independent.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: They feel their Swaziness very strongly. There is no question about that.
                    They feel their sovereignty. They recognize that being in a customs union with
                    South Africa is a limitation on their freedom of action on economic matters. The
                    Swazi currency, the lilangeni, is dependent on the rand. They are equal and flow
                    back and forth very easily. The rand easily circulates within Swaziland,
                    although the lilangeni does not circulate in South Africa. And that is a great
                    benefit to Swaziland. So they know that they are dependent on South Africa for
                    their prosperity. Incidentally, by sub-Saharan African standards, they are a
                    prosperous country. But this is dependent on their relationship with South
                    Africa to a significant extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Steve, I think we need to stop at this point. I
                        thank you very much for doing this interview. We will look forward to
                        talking to you some more.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROGERS: It has been a great pleasure, thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
