<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000343">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ainslie Embree </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>AINSLIE EMBREE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Dorothy Robins-Mowry </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 20, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Dorothy Robins-Mowry interviewing Dr. Ainslie
                        Embree, Professor of History, Columbia University, on October 20, 1990.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I would like you to start out by giving me a little on your own personal,
                    professional and life background which would establish for us how your interest
                    in India developed and what led up to your assignment as a Counselor of Cultural
                    Affairs at the Embassy in New Delhi.</p>
                <p>Biographic Outline: The Acceptance Of A College Teaching Position In India And
                    Ten Years ThereBiographic Outline: The Acceptance Of A CollegeTeaching Position
                    In India And Ten Years There</p>
                <p>EMBREE: Dorothy, I'll give you a quick autobiography. When a friend of mine heard
                    that I had been appointed Cultural Counselor in Delhi, she called me and said,
                    why is a Canadian, a specialist in Indian affairs, going out to see our culture?
                    And in a way it was a fair question.</p>
                <p>My interest in India began in a way in an equally peculiar fashion. After the
                    war, that is the big war, I had come down to New York to study at Union
                    Theological Seminary. The first day I was there I met a missionary from India
                    whom I had known before who asked me what I was going to do and we talked. He
                    said there's a job in the college, the Canadian College in Indore, in India. Why
                    don't you apply and go out to teach history? And in a sense it was as simple as
                    that because I hadn't known for sure what I wanted to do.</p>
                <p>And at the same time I met Sue who is now my wife who indeed had signed up to go
                    to India with the Congregational Church to teach in Madurai in South India. It
                    was not, as my students sometimes assume, some profound religious interest or
                    indeed even an interest in India's history.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>We went out to India and we both taught in the college, I taught history,
                    European history needless to say, while Sue taught sociology. It was while there
                    that I developed my interest in Indian history. We had spent a year studying
                    language, and I read a good deal of Indian history during those years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really went out under missionary auspices.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, to teach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Sue also had this missionary education interest. Is
                        that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were born in Nova Scotia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But Sue was born in the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you just happened to come together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Just happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very nice. And when was that, Ainslie?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We met in 1946—we had both served in the War. Sue was an officer in the
                    WAVES, and I was a navigator in the Royal Canadian Air Force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how long were you at the College in Indore?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Ten years, 1947-58.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that was an interesting time right after the
                        war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, it was a very interesting time. There was a great optimism in India.
                    Nehru, of course, occupied a position in national life that's hard for anybody
                    to occupy now. And during those years, my interests were really very much
                    confined to Central India. I had no connection at all with the Embassy world. I
                    think in all those years I was there, I made only one trip that had any
                    connection with the diplomatic world and that was in 1957 to go to Delhi for a
                    celebration at the Canadian High Commission. I forget what the occasion was. But
                    in those ten years that was my only diplomatic adventure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me just a little bit about those ten years as a basis
                        for comparison with the years you were at the Embassy. You were teaching
                        European history, but you were obviously also absorbing the local and Indian
                        history and the language. What were your special interests then in
                        India?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I had very general interests, as I recall, in Indian culture. Indore,
                    where we taught, was the head of an old Princely State, the Hoekar State. And it
                    was quite different in many ways from British India, and, of course, entirely
                    different from India now. It was a small, very pleasant city in many ways. It
                    had American connections because the Hoekar Maharani was an American. And there
                    had been a previous Hoekar Maharani, a very famous one, who was the first
                    American, perhaps the first foreigner to marry a Maharajah. That was Nancy
                    Miller from Seattle who married the former Maharajah in the 20's.</p>
                <p>Indore at the time was still very much out of the main circuit of Indian life. So
                    our lives were much more absorbed in an Indian world then would be the case now.
                    There were some missionary ladies at the hospital and there was also a mission
                    school, but we were among few foreigners in Indore. So that it was very unlike
                    the kind of world one lives in in the capital city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your living hard or easy? To what extent were you
                        living a western life in physical terms?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>EMBREE: You raise one of the interesting questions. When we went out to India in
                    1948, we went out under the intention that we would live like Indians. This was
                    very much the style at the times in missionary circles, to break away from the
                    old patterns and live as simply as people in our own status did. In our case,
                    this meant we would live like the other faculty at the college. Therefore, when
                    we went out, we decided we wouldn't have any servants; we were what was known as
                    simple livers. We eventually discovered we were impressing nobody but ourselves,
                    that the Indians who could afford it had servants. And they assumed that if we
                    didn't have servants, but could afford them, the explanation was because we were
                    mean with our money. Our anxieties to be just like the other faculty in the
                    college really never worked out, but at least we lived in the same kind of house
                    as the Indian faculty, and we didn't have much more money than they did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't want you to be Peace Corps types?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: No, because we were not at all Peace Corps types. The Peace Corps people
                    went out knowing they were coming back and with no thoughts of living in India.
                    We went out with a life commitment, India was going to be our home.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, we had none of the kinds of supports that the Peace Corps had. We
                    were more or less on our own. And so we lived in a fashion that made us much
                    more a part of India than what would be the case now. There was no, of course,
                    no commissary food. As far as food was concerned, we lived exactly the same way
                    as the Indians did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the Indians did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We got whatever was available locally, which in Central India during the
                    rains was often very monotonous food. But it was not a hard life in any real
                    sense. Our children were both born in India, and they were both extremely
                    healthy. Our son was the first European child, as they say, to attend Daly
                    College school meant for sons of Indian chiefs and princes. We didn't want to
                    send him to the missionary school in Woodstock as other people did. It was part
                    of our simple living pattern. It showed somewhat the contradiction of our whole
                    aims. While we were not going to send them to the missionary school, we did send
                    them to one of the most elegant schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: An Indian school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, an Indian school, a public school, in the English sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you worry about his education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, but he had a good time at the school, even though the rest of the
                    boys were all rich. And in that sense the contrast was very great indeed with
                    the India we knew later with much simpler living conditions but with much deeper
                    involvement in Indian life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, if you were there for ten years, what brought you
                        home?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We came home after six years. We had a year's sabbatical and I came back
                    and we both studied at Columbia for a year. Then we went back for two years. But
                    even before I went back for two years, I was very dubious about the whole
                    situation in which we found ourselves. We were the last imperialists so to
                    speak. The British had gone, but we were still running a college and hospitals
                    and schools. They were still supported by Canadian money. And again, it was part
                    of our own ideological feeling that there was really no place for us in the kind
                    of setup that existed. So after two years we decided that we would come
                    back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you came back to where</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We came back to New York, to Columbia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went back for your graduate study at Columbia,
                        what were you studying by then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I was studying history still.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Asian history then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: In 1954, when I came back to Columbia there was only one course on Indian
                    history taught at Columbia. It was a one semester course taught by Taraknath Das
                    who was a famous old revolutionary. He had been one of those who during the
                    First World War had supported the Germans against the British and had been
                    imprisoned by the Americans as a spy. When I knew him in '55 and '56 he had
                    become extremely conservative and a strong Republican. That was the only course
                    in Indian history that was available at Columbia. That shows how American
                    universities have changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Especially how Columbia has changed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>EMBREE: How Columbia's changed. Because at the time, it mostly taught Sanskrit,
                    but there were no courses in modern languages and modern literature.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so then you came back to Columbia and in effect you've
                        been at Columbia ever since with your hiatus out for—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: With exception of three years I spent at Duke, from 1969 to 1972. But
                    otherwise, I'd been at Columbia.</p>
                <p>The Trail Into USIA (And USIS/India)The Trail Into USIA (And USIS/India)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What then was the way you were recruited to go out to New
                        Delhi for USIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: During these years at Columbia and indeed at Duke, I'd become very
                    involved in American academic life affecting India. I was president of the
                    American Institute of Indian Studies. I was very much involved in promoting
                    Indian studies in American colleges, not just at Columbia but elsewhere and I'd
                    written on India. I think my first acquaintance, real acquaintance, with the
                    embassy in Delhi came through Margaret Clapp who was the CAO in Delhi and I got
                    to know Margaret well, partly because I was in New Delhi at that time as the
                    Senior Scholar with the American Institute of India Studies. So I got to know
                    her in a professional way. But then we got to know each other very well. In
                    fact, having a Wellesley wife—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I didn't realize Sue was Wellesley.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: —strengthened the ties. Then I knew the subsequent CAOs after that. So I
                    got some sense of what they did, but I really didn't know very much. But what I
                    did have involvement with in 1977-78 was the new American Ambassador to India,
                    Robert Goheen. As you know, the Cultural Affairs Officer was regarded in some
                    sense as the Ambassador's prerogative to have whom he wanted as a CAO. And since
                    he knew me, he wrote and asked if I would be interested in being nominated for
                    the job.</p>
                <p>1977: Recruited By Newly Appointed Ambassador Robert Goheen as CAO, India1977:
                    Recruited By Newly Appointed AmbassadorRobert Goheen as CAO, India</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were recruited by Goheen. He, of course, came out
                        of Princeton and has his own missionary background.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>EMBREE: And so we had very similar interests in many ways and he knew that I was
                    greatly interested in India. This was a change, of course, having somebody go as
                    CAO who was identified wholly as an Indian specialist. Margaret Clapp, for
                    example, had been an American historian, and most CAOs I suppose, had been in
                    American studies.</p>
                <p>My immediate predecessor whom I knew very well, Jim Roach, had worked on India.
                    So it was a little odd having somebody whose identification was completely with
                    Indian studies going out as American CAO. I didn't know that at the time oddly
                    enough. I thought it was a natural thing to get somebody who knew India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It makes sense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It makes sense in some ways. I went out without any training at all in
                    what a CAO was. I wasn't sure when I was going, but they called and said that
                    there was an investigating team, I forget what it was called, from the State
                    Department going out to look at what was happening in the educational cultural
                    programs in India. And they wanted me to go out that week to be in Delhi before
                    they arrived so that I would be able to meet them. It was somewhat of a peculiar
                    decision. These two young men who arrived to investigate what was going on in
                    the American Center knew nothing about its work in India and the person who was
                    to talk to them was somebody who'd arrived exactly 24 hours before. In a way it
                    was a good introduction to the way the State Department worked because the young
                    men knew absolutely nothing about India.</p>
                <p>They were traveling around in a car and they expressed strong disagreement that
                    we were spending so much money teaching Indians to speak English. And I said, we
                    don't spend a penny teaching Indians to speak English. And they said, how do
                    they know English so well then if we don't teach them?</p>
                <p>Embree Was Sent Out To India Knowing Nothing Of Embassy / USIS Procedures Or
                    Overall Requirements Of CAO Position, But Long Previous Experiences In India
                    Gave Him Easy Access To Journalists, Academics, And High Ranking
                    PoliticiansEmbree Was Sent Out To India Knowing Nothing Of Embassy/USIS
                    Procedures Or Overall Requirements Of CAO Position, But Long Previous
                    Experiences In India Gave Him Easy Access To Journalists, Academics, And High
                    Ranking Politicians</p>
                <p>But indeed trying to explain to them the cultural relations with India was an
                    interesting introduction for me. The point I was going to make was I went out as
                    Cultural Affairs Officer knowing almost nothing about the office and what one
                    was to do except what I had picked up from knowing Jim Roach and Margaret Clapp.
                    I had been out a week once before that in which I had talked to people, but that
                    was all the introduction I had. I guess where I differed was that I knew a great
                    many people in India. I was not an unknown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were not a novice of the community in which you were
                        going to work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: No, not at all. I knew the Indian academic world very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your Public Affairs Officer when you went
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Jay Gildner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: And I will tell the story again whether it's on the tape or not. When I
                    mentioned to an old retired officer that I was going out to be the cultural
                    counselor, he asked who the public affairs officer was. When I said, Gildner,
                    whom I hadn't met at the time, he commented that he didn't think I would get on
                    well in India. “You get along very well at a place like Columbia,” he said,
                    “because your superiors are even more inefficient and incompetent about business
                    than you are, whereas Gildner has a reputation for being the most efficient
                    Foreign Service officer in public affairs.”</p>
                <p>Well, it turned out I got along extremely well with Jay. Indeed, he was
                    efficient, everything that people said, but he also appreciated my knowledge of
                    India and that I had easy access to journalists and academics and lots of people
                    in government and society, through purely personal contacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the heritage of all your previous years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was the heritage of all my previous years that I knew all people like
                    Mrs. Gandhi and so on. So it was a very different experience than other people
                    have had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you arrived really obviously not a stranger in New
                        Delhi, but a stranger within the Embassy framework of operation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: A complete stranger within the framework of Embassy operations. I knew
                    nothing at all, even what I was supposed to do. I was fortunate, of course, in
                    having extremely good Indian assistants in the office. Shanta Chenoy was very
                    well known and had worked there for many years. Shanta knew everybody in the
                    Indian social and political world. Then Jay Gildner himself, of course. I
                    realize now that he was very glad to have a Cultural Affairs officer who didn't
                    want to manage things particularly, but who really wanted to be a—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A cultural officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>EMBREE: A cultural officer and to deal with people. So that really what I did was
                    to meet with people, particularly academics, journalists and politicians. Those
                    were the three groups I had most to do with, and with whom I had easy access.
                    But I had very little involvement, oddly enough, with the management side of
                    USIS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't insist that you become involved in that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: No, I was involved in that sort of thing only when we had visitors or
                    speakers and I entertained them, but I didn't have to get involved in day to day
                    management. I'm sure other Cultural Affairs officers were much more
                    involved.</p>
                <p>From The Beginning Of His Tour, Embree Is Involved Extensively In USEFIFrom The
                    Beginning Of His Tour, Embree IsInvolved Extensively In USEFI</p>
                <p>The other thing, of course, that I was very involved in, from the very beginning,
                    was USEFI, perhaps more than most other CAOs had been. Before I went out, there
                    had been some very serious charges made against the director of the US
                    Educational Foundation. As soon as I got there I was told by Jay Gildner, that
                    the Ambassador wanted me to investigate the charges very carefully. And this
                    again was part of the embarrassment of knowing people because, of course, I had
                    known the Director for many years, as well as all the other people in USEFI. And
                    this occupied a great deal of energy the first six months or so. I became deeply
                    involved in all aspects of the USEFI program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: You mean in terms of the investigation?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. First tell me, USEFI plays what role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: USEFI still plays an important role in India, but it used to be, perhaps
                    next to Japan, the biggest US educational foundation anywhere. It used to have a
                    large number of fellowships, both Fulbright scholars going to India, and
                    Fulbright scholars coming here. In addition, it had many other programs funded
                    through the Office of Education. This, of course, was all supposedly PL 480
                    money. There were also many summer groups of teachers in addition to the regular
                    Fulbrights, and junior years abroad. It was an extremely active program.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>I should have said I'd had one other personal involvement with USIA and USEFI
                    before this. Back in the spring of 1977 I'd been asked to go out by CIES to
                    visit all the Fulbright scholars in South Asia including Afghanistan, India,
                    Nepal, Pakistan, and Sri Lanka. I had at that time a very interesting look at
                    the Fulbright program. I don't think many other persons had had a chance of
                    visiting all of them. I'd also at that same time visited the USIS centers in all
                    the South Asian countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you really then had your training if not in that
                        week before you went out to India after you were recruited, you had your
                        training in this kind of—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: That was an extraordinarily good training because indeed I had met all
                    the public affairs officers and all the CAOs that were there in that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And became an independent thinker about what was
                        happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I made a long report on my trip which I suppose is in the files
                    somewhere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have a copy of that report? They would love to have
                        it attached to this ultimately if you could ever find it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: If I can find it. I'm not sure they do have a report. But it must be
                    somewhere in the files of CIES. Yes, I did look at it very carefully and made
                    certain recommendations, a number of which were followed. The question that had
                    interested me most when I was there was the particular role of American
                    Fulbrighters as teachers.</p>
                <p>Embree Had Grave Doubts Re Utility Of American Fulbright Teachers In India, And
                    Many Teachers Themselves Were FrustratedEmbree Had Grave Doubts Re Utility Of
                    American Fulbright Teachers In India, And Many Teachers Themselves Were
                    Frustrated</p>
                <p>EMBREE: I had grave doubts about the utility of Americans being actually teachers
                    in Indian colleges. I obviously went at this from the point of view of having
                    been one for so many years myself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to say that's a contradiction, isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>EMBREE: It was a contradiction except that I was aware, having been there for so
                    many years, what the difficulties, perhaps the impossibilities, of going into
                    the Indian or Pakistan situation and in a year doing anything effective. The
                    best young scholars I met in Fulbright were very frustrated realizing that they
                    were standing up in front of a class, but the students were not going to be
                    examined on anything they were teaching. That they were really supernumeraries
                    and not, as they had obviously assumed they would be, actively involved in the
                    Indian educational program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this because they were Americans or foreigners? Or was
                        this by nature of the system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It's all three things. It's the nature of the system that South Asian
                    university education is very much a matter of lecturing. What the instructor
                    does is prepare the students for examination. And it's very difficult for
                    American teachers to think of themselves as preparing people for examinations
                    which they don't set and they're not involved in, in any way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this at the secondary level as well as at the
                        university level, or are we really talking about the universities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We're talking about the universities, colleges.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With my background in Japan, certainly what I know of
                        American teachers who go out to teach at universities is that they are
                        equally frustrated because the students really do not have to perform. And
                        they're really advised that they can never fail a student no matter how
                        little or how badly anyone does. This is very frustrating for American
                        professors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was very frustrating because most Indian universities are made up of
                    many colleges with the university setting the curriculum and exams for the
                    colleges. So you're teaching a curriculum that's been set by somebody else to
                    take exams that will be set by somebody else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that allows you no initiative and no freedom of action
                        as an educator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: The other side of it is that many Indian students are very anxious in
                    personal terms to meet the American professors and learn from them. Good
                    students value this very highly, but it's an extra. It's not part of the system.
                    It was that sort of thing that I was raising questions about on the Fulbright
                    program, not the research part, but the teaching part.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's fighting the local system.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes. This was another great source of unhappiness. Many of the people,
                    both old and young Americans, got the impression that they were going out to
                    help change the Indian system and bring it to some new and better level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Kind of an imperialist notion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was indeed a kind of imperialist notion. I once stated in a report
                    that the Ford Foundation and the Fulbright program became the successors of
                    British imperialism and of missionaries. And again, since I had experience with
                    having gone there to do good to the Indians, I understood this very well. And
                    this was enormously frustrating when the young Americans realized that there was
                    no conceivable opportunity of their bringing about any changes in the Indian
                    system. It certainly needed changes but it would have to come from within.
                    Foreigners were becoming increasingly irrelevant to the process which is of
                    course what I had discovered in 1958, 20 years ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And why you left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Why I left. But I think most people still went out as late as '78 with
                    this sense that they were going to bring about improvements and change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is very difficult. Americans always like to do
                        good don't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Indian Academic Community And Government Exhibited Growing Resentment At The Way
                    US Was Conducting Fulbright Teaching Assignments And At Mindset Of US
                    TeachersIndian Academic Community And Government Exhibited Growing Resentment At
                    The Way US Was Conducting Fulbright Teaching Assignments And At Mind Set Of US
                    Teachers</p>
                <p>So it really was becoming counter productive.</p>
                <p>EMBREE: I thought the process of sending out American scholars to teach was
                    becoming counter productive at times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But interestingly, the Indians still clamor to come to the
                        United States to get an education.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>EMBREE: That's the other side of it, of course. Obviously, I had a great deal of
                    involvement in scholars coming and going to India. Indians, in the late ''60s,
                    had come to resent American scholars for a whole variety of reasons and didn't
                    want them involved in research or in the whole Indian education process. I'd run
                    into this as President of the American Institute of Indian Studies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this just Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: All people, but Americans were obviously more than any other. But there
                    was a fundamental difference between, say, the Russians, the Germans, the
                    British and the French, because they all had country-to-country arrangements,
                    whereas we were essentially free enterprise. Our scholars went out on their own.
                    Even the Fulbrighters were essentially on their own. And the Indian government
                    wanted more of an exchange controlled by the government. They especially grew
                    disenchanted with the fact that American scholars were mostly in the social
                    sciences. They were involved in Indian life, studying Indian life.</p>
                <p>Establishment—And Presumed Role—Of The Indo-American
                    SubcommissionEstablishment—And Presumed Role—Of TheIndo-American
                    Subcommission</p>
                <p>What the Indians wanted was reciprocity and control, and this led to the creation
                    of the Indo-American Subcommission, of which I had been a member before I became
                    cultural counselor. It was set up in 1976, and it was to be the great
                    breakthrough of government to government operations on the cultural level.</p>
                <p>Indians Had Expected A Government Controlled Commission On US Side, And Never
                    Understood How The Commission Was StructuredIndians Had Expected A Government
                    Controlled Commission On US Side, And Never Understood How The Commission Was
                    Structured</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's the Indo-American Subcommission on Education and
                        Culture.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes. It didn't work out the way the Indian side hoped because while it
                    was strictly government on their side, wholly controlled by the government, our
                    side wasn't. Ours was a quasi-governmental institution which the Indians had
                    difficulty understanding. The fact that the Indo-American Subcommission got its
                    money from the American government, had very close relations with the American
                    Centers, but that it was from our point of view a private enterprise, Indians
                    found baffling and this always leads to suspicion that we're not what we seem.
                    An important aspect of the Subcommission was that the Indians wanted to send
                    scientists here and they wanted us to send scientists.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Physical scientists.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Physical scientists, which many of us knew was not going to work. While
                    Indian scientists want to come to the United States, not many American
                    scientists want to go to India unless they have a special interest say in bugs
                    or germs or some aspect of the flora and fauna.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this could be considered in some instances a negative
                        interest, couldn't it? But you've now brought up the Indo-American
                        Subcommission. Explain a little bit about what went on with this. I think
                        you were involved in the development of some exhibits and some other things
                        during that period of time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: The Indo-American Subcommission on Education and Culture was one of the
                    half dozen commissions set up at the time. Technically, they were all under the
                    Secretary of State from our side, but in fact involved various people. The
                    Education and Cultural one, I think it's fair to say, is the one that was most
                    active in India, and it had a number of aspects. One was sending Indians to the
                    United States who were essentially selected by the Indian government. They
                    emphasized training in science. Their counterparts on our side were selected not
                    in any sense by the government, but by the CIES, the same group ultimately that
                    ran the Fulbright. But it was strictly a private enterprise. Academics did the
                    choosing and it was in no sense controlled by USIA, except that USIA supplied
                    the money.</p>
                <p>The other aspect of the cultural program that was very important was that it was
                    to be mutual. Anything we did in India the Indians were to do with their
                    counterparts here. And this became very much involved in museums, for example.
                    It wasn't a matter of us sending our experts to India to do things for the
                    Indians. It had to have reciprocity and their people coming not just to learn
                    but to actually do something. This can be very difficult for obvious reasons.
                    And out of this came a number of exhibits, one very interesting one on
                    science-technology. But the big one, of course, was the festival in India /
                    which was run by the Indo-American Subcommission but also by the cultural
                    counselor's office. It was a very complicated operation and it worked remarkably
                    well.</p>
                <p>But again from the Indian side it brought up many of the difficulties inherent in
                    our relationships that from our side it was essentially private groups, the
                    National Gallery, the Metropolitan and so on, with the American [more or less
                    private] side of the Subcommission doing the negotiating, but always negotiating
                    with government institutions in India. Ted Tanen was running the Subcommission,
                    he came essentially as a private individual, but was obviously supported by the
                    American Center.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And of course he came out of the American government.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>EMBREE: He came out of the American government to add to the confusion—to the
                    Indians he was just one more government officer. Although in his own eyes,
                    rightfully so, he was no longer a government official.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Festival of India I think was the first of the grand
                        festivals which have followed so that it did set a very important pattern
                        for cultural exchanges which are still going on in the United States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was enormously successful in terms of what it brought over. However,
                    the question the Indians still ask me was what effect did it have on
                    Indo-American relations. This strikes me as a question we can ask of a lot of
                    our cultural exchanges.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now some very spectacular things went to India under
                        these auspices. The New York Philharmonic went, did it not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: The New York Philharmonic went—the biggest US program that went. There
                    was a long and complicated story about the festival because we were supposed to
                    have an American festival in India. We ran into great difficulties on this
                    because the person most involved on the Indian side, who is now a curator of the
                    National Museum in Delhi, insisted that just as our side had very largely
                    determined what we wanted from the Indian museums, they should have equal claim
                    from the American side which seemed all right on the surface. But of course what
                    people like Stella Kramnisch and the others who were arranging it, Cory Welch
                    and the others, wanted were Indian artifacts, great Indian sculpture,
                    paintings.</p>
                <p>When it came to the American festival in India, what Sahare and the others
                    demanded were impressionist paintings from the Metropolitan. And some of us had
                    the difficult and unsuccessful task of explaining that it's perfectly true that
                    we sent our people to ask for things from the Indian museum but they were Indian
                    things, it was Indian culture. It was very difficult to persuade our Senators
                    and Representatives to pay for an exhibit of French impressionist paintings in
                    India [when our exhibit in India was supposed to be of things American]. But
                    furthermore, that it would be very hard indeed to get the museums to lend their
                    very valuable paintings. We could, in fact, have gotten a very splendid display
                    of American paintings, the great 19th century painters, but the Indian side
                    rejected this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They didn't want those?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>EMBREE: They didn't want American paintings. And they said it was inferior
                    painting and it was insulting, and so on, that we were offering them second rate
                    American materials when they were sending us the very greatest of Indian
                    artifacts, which was true, but it made for difficult relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was part of the negotiations rather than part of
                        the—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Another thing that happened at the same time was that a well-known
                    American critic Katherine Kuh got involved. One of the things the Indians asked
                    us to do was to have an exhibit of modern Indian painting and sculpture in
                    America, which those of us involved readily agreed to. We thought it was a great
                    idea. But it soon became apparent that we would have to have an American critic
                    of some stature make the selection, that the American galleries would not agree
                    to exhibiting materials that they hadn't been involved in selecting.</p>
                <p>So Katherine Kuh came out. She was a very redoubtable woman. And she looked at
                    all of the art that the Indians said was representative of their finest artists,
                    all famous names, the names everyone knew. She looked at them and said they were
                    second rate and derivative from American art. She went around the country and
                    found what she said were wonderful stuff by unknown artists, and she refused to
                    take any of the famous Indian artists. And of course this led to an impasse
                    because the Indians wouldn't agree to her selection. Ms. Kuh is still annoyed
                    with those of us who were involved and she claims that we didn't stand up for
                    artistic principles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, modern art has long been a—modern American art,
                        modern art of any kind, has long been a very controversial issue. It hinges
                        on what people consider art and what they do not consider art.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Her argument was that modern art has its own validity in the country of
                    origin, but it doesn't have validity in another country that simply copies,
                    unless you're willing to look very closely at creativity. It was a very
                    interesting critique. Some of the people that she said then were the best people
                    in India are now recognized as indeed outstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So she's been validated.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: She was right, and I often wondered if she knows. But it was one of those
                    interesting problems in cultural exchange that never gets the headlines or I
                    don't think even gets written up in our accounts.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was also a problem as I remember it about the
                        different facilities at museums in India, Americans are fussy about humidity
                        and temperature controls and general protection of the art which they have.
                        The facilities in most of the, if not all, of Indian museums is at a very
                        different level.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: This was a very delicate matter. We had to say that even if we could have
                    persuaded the US government to pay for an exhibit of French impressionist
                    paintings, the Metropolitan would never under any circumstances allow those
                    paintings to be exhibited under Indian conditions, without humidity and
                    temperature controls. They said, “we allow you to take our sculptures which are
                    just as valuable as your paintings, but there's no reciprocity.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is always one of the difficult aspects. I think one
                        of the interesting projects which grew out of this—we're still really
                        talking about the Indo-American Subcommission and the negotiations—was the
                        big project of Aditi.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, it was a very interesting project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because that was not just an art or cultural exchange. It
                        had other implications.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: There are many implications. I was one of those who would not have
                    approved of Aditi, because I knew that there were many people in India who were
                    very strongly opposed to this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is Aditi, Ainslie?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was a show, I think is the best word, that was set up by a very
                    enterprising young entrepreneur in Delhi called Sethi. It was made up of street
                    musicians, street village theater people, street magicians and performers,
                    really the poorest level of Indian society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is side two. We're talking about Aditi.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>EMBREE: It was a very interesting item in our whole cultural exchange. There are
                    many people in India who accuse the entrepreneur who had arranged Aditi that it
                    was exploiting the most vulnerable people in India, the children who were
                    entertainers, beggars in effect, people who had no place in normal Indian art or
                    culture, but who were not only village performers but were extremely poor. Sethi
                    had been very successful in arranging shows of these people, attended at first
                    very largely by foreigners. And then, as often happens in India, when the upper
                    classes realized that foreigners were interested in these things, they became
                    interested in them, too.</p>
                <p>And at that point he suggested that it be taken to America as part of the
                    festival. There was very strong opposition, largely I think it's fair to say,
                    from Marxist groups who said this was double exploitation. It was exploitation
                    of extremely poor and vulnerable people by an Indian entrepreneur catering to
                    the exploitive Americans. It was, however, a great success in Washington. People
                    whom I respect said nothing had given them as much sense of India as did these
                    performances. Sethi received a great deal of criticism when they went back
                    because the people were literally thrown back to where they had been.</p>
                <p>There was one pathetic story in the newspaper. One little girl was asked what she
                    had liked about America. She said, I was able to use soap everyday. She had
                    never used soap before in her life and she would never get it again because it
                    was so expensive.</p>
                <p>But it was one of those cases in which perhaps some of us were too sensitive to
                    Indian criticisms because it did make an impression here. I think one would
                    still have to ask the validity of using these kinds of people for this purpose,
                    bringing them here and then just throwing them back where they were found.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I remember when this was going on, the arrangements
                        in Washington were very carefully developed with home hospitality and care
                        of these children so that there could be no question about their well-being
                        while they were in the United States. But, of course, any kind of cultural
                        exchange especially when it involves people from two very different kinds of
                        cultures can create all kinds of problems. I think some years there was the
                        same kind of problem with some of the religious dancers out of Bali who when
                        they went home were in effect never again considered truly religious
                        dancers. They'd been contaminated. I don't know how you get over this kind
                        of combination of seclusion and outreach of culture which should provide
                        better understanding of what's going on in that particular society.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, I think that's true. The criticism made of Aditi was that it didn't
                    give a true picture of the Indian society. It gave the impression that these
                    children, the dancers and musicians, occupied as important a place in Indian
                    society as they had in Washington. They were treated very well, as you say, and
                    they all loved it. But the argument is that this gave the impression that
                    Indians valued them the way Americans had, whereas that's not the case. They
                    have no place in Indian culture at all. Any place they have was due to the
                    westerners having taken them up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, it's always very sad. But it's always very hard
                        to go home again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Oh, yes. Some people said of the story, that at least the little girl had
                    soap once in her life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very hard. Ainslie, I know that one of the things
                        you did incessantly was entertain almost every night. How poor Sue ever
                        managed I don't know, but you had a house full of people. This was not only
                        because of your generous spirit but also because of your interest in people.
                        It was certainly one of the great ways in which you contributed to the
                        cultural programs of all kinds at the Embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It's just something that comes very naturally to us. We both like
                    entertaining. One of the interesting features, we did an enormous amount of
                    entertaining, but we never had a real cook when we were in Delhi. But Sue would
                    be able to manage with her people by being a good boss.</p>
                <p>Yes, I think it was very interesting the whole question of entertaining. It plays
                    a very important role in India. I was able to entertain people because of
                    knowing as many people as I did and able to get to know new people. I think one
                    of the things that Americans do well, on the whole, is entertaining, and it
                    occupies a much larger place in India than many people realize.</p>
                <p>One of the things that many people don't know in the outside world is all the
                    other embassies get very large entertaining allowances. Somebody used to say to
                    me, well, it's easy for you to entertain since the government is paying for it.
                    And I never told any of my American friends that the American government is very
                    niggardly with everybody from the Ambassador down compared to other
                    governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It all comes out of your own pocket.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, I discovered that a third secretary at the Canadian Embassy had a
                    larger entertaining allowance than any of us did in the American Center. It's
                    one of those things that you can't make a case for because what an outcry there
                    would be in Washington if we suggested larger entertainment allowances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They always suspect somehow you're going to misuse
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, it's a very important aspect of American diplomacy that I think we
                    do well at the personal level. And some of the young people were very good
                    indeed. I may say in passing that I became very impressed indeed by the caliber
                    of people in the American Embassy in Delhi when I was there, from the Ambassador
                    down. One would expect it at the high level, but it was the younger people—the
                    political officer, economic officers were absolutely first rate.</p>
                <p>One of the criticisms that I've heard from people who should know better is that
                    there were no people in the American Embassy who spoke an Indian language. This
                    was untrue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who spoke Hindi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Ambassador Goheen. Arch Blood, the DCM, spent an hour every day studying
                    Hindi. There were half a dozen of the younger people who had taken training in
                    South Asian studies in this country who were fluent. We had an extraordinarily
                    well trained staff in the Embassy. And I think something that gets the least
                    publicity and the least credit is how good our Embassy people are. I was
                    interested in this being an outsider.</p>
                <p>Assessment Of Ambassador Goheen And Other American Ambassadors Who Served In
                    India In The Preceding Decade Or TwoAssessment Of Ambassador Goheen And Other
                    American Ambassadors Who Served In India In The Preceding Decade Or Two</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything you'd like to say about Ambassador
                        Goheen? He was after all a remarkable individual for that particular job.
                        Did you find in observing him any particular elements which you thought
                        either very good or maybe not so good? He is one of those political
                        appointees who was ideally suited for the country to which he was
                        appointed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>EMBREE: India, of course, had such an interesting series of political
                    ambassadors, an extraordinary group going way back to people like Loy Henderson.
                    The most famous, of course, were Chester Bowles and Pat Moynihan. I would have
                    argued that Goheen from the Indian point of view was an excellent ambassador.
                    But I always remember a comment made about Galbraith when he was there by the
                    British High Commissioner. I asked him what he thought of Galbraith. He said,
                    well, it's difficult to judge a man like Galbraith. I'm never sure—”He's the
                    most brilliant ambassador I ever met, but I'm not sure whether he's the American
                    ambassador to India or the Indian ambassador to America, and I'm not sure that
                    he knows which he is.” And this is an interesting sidelight on the role the
                    American ambassadors used to play. Chester Bowles, for example, played a role
                    that no other American ambassador has ever played. He had instant access to
                    Nehru. He lectured the people at all levels in the Indian government, hectored
                    them on what to do and so on. And reading his stuff, it's amazing. You can't
                    imagine anybody now doing that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, of course, he was there at an unusual time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, he was there at an interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the right man for that kind of time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, it wouldn't have worked later on. It didn't work the second
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Moynihan was famous and it didn't work. Moynihan once said that he had
                    never been asked to speak at an Indian university. But that again was part of
                    the time. Goheen was very popular and this was partly because his parents had
                    been missionaries there. I once mentioned to Goheen before I knew what the facts
                    were, the only two Americans who had been knighted in India had been
                    missionaries. He said, my grandfather was one. Who was the other one? I thought
                    that was a great put down!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That'll teach you! Ainslie, what were your working
                        relations with the Embassy? Did you have to get involved in staff meetings
                        or do any of those other administrative chores? Jay Gildner and the
                        Ambassador with his confidence in you freed you from this kind of
                        daily—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I suppose I did attend one or two staff meetings. I had a friendly
                    relationship for two reasons. One was Goheen himself, of course. The other was
                    his personal assistant, Marshall Booton, whom I had known very well.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>Let me tell you a story. The day I arrived in Delhi a wire came in from the White
                    House congratulating me which created some unhappiness. But people didn't notice
                    the initials. It was Tom Thornton who was working in the White House and thought
                    it would be amusing to send me a cable signed with the President's name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Tom, of course, was a National Security staff
                        member.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, but people thought it was really from the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it's like all these messages from the Secretary of
                        State that go out on the State Department telegrams saying personal
                        message.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I had very close relations, working relationships, with the Embassy
                    people and the Voice of America people. They knew I had access to journalists
                    and so on and I think that was useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a good door opener.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, I suppose I was a good door opener for them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ainslie, what languages do you speak?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Just Hindi. But the kind of people we deal with in Delhi speak English. I
                    think I would have said that was one argument for a Cultural Affairs Officer
                    who's not a career person, but who has some kind of other associations and I
                    think is recognized in this way. So I was useful to a number of people and I
                    used to write, needless to say, things for Ambassador Goheen. I wrote him one
                    important speech and I'd forgotten that I'd written it. And I heard him giving a
                    speech and I went up to him and I said, Bob, that was a wonderful speech. He
                    said, “Aren't you being a little immodest?” I'd genuinely forgotten.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That raises a very important question which has got to do
                        with a cultural officer, the top cultural officer in one of the top
                        countries coming from outside the Foreign Service. The Foreign Service
                        officers who aspire to promotion up the cultural line sometimes find this a
                        very distressing situation. I don't know how you balance the two off unless
                        what you do is really balance it off. But obviously, from everything you say
                        you bring credentials and knowledge of people which a Foreign Service
                        officer would rarely have in a particular country because none stay there
                        that long.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: There were people in India who had been around there a long time. People
                    like Craig Baxter knew South Asia well, and there were others. But even in that
                    case the outsider has advantages in terms of how he can meet people and the fact
                    that he's recognized as an outsider. Even though I had the same rank as the
                    rest, people knew I really wasn't one of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They still admired you because you were Ainslie
                        Embree.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Well, they knew I had these other connections. I had university
                    connections and so on. I would argue for the independent person. I'm not sure
                    about the ambassadorial level. I would certainly always have said we were
                    extremely lucky we had the people we had, especially Goheen who was greatly
                    respected by Indians. They liked his style. When they wanted to say nice things
                    about Goheen, they would say it was because he was born here, he's like us. All
                    they meant was he was mannerly and didn't bang the table and knew how to be
                    polite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Ainslie, during your time in India, were there any
                        delicate diplomatic policy matters that came up that impinged upon what you
                        were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At Time Of Embree's Arrival, Communist Newspaper Falsely Accuses Him Of Close
                    Connections With Right Wing Hindu Organization; Threatens To Run Him Out Of
                    IndiaAt Time Of Embree's Arrival, Communist Newspaper Falsely Accuses Him Of
                    Close Connections With Right Wing Hindu Organization; Threatens To Run Him Out
                    Of India</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>EMBREE: Not really. After I had been there a week or so, the Patriot, the
                    communist paper, published a fierce denunciation of me saying they were going to
                    expose my connections with the RSS, the right wing Hindu organization. And if I
                    wasn't out of India in 24 hours and so on. What had happened I discovered is
                    that they had confused me with Walter Anderson who indeed is the best expert on
                    right wing organizations, who is now in our Embassy in New Delhi. This raised an
                    interesting question. I was surprised by it but some of my very close Indian
                    friends, some in high places, called me and said if you want us to, we will
                    write to the newspaper and say that these charges are absurd. The one man who
                    was the vice chancellor at Delhi said, “You know our country. The best thing to
                    do is to not say a word, for you not to reply and for none of us to reply.” He
                    said, “I know that many of us are going to call you personally, but we're not
                    going to say a word to the newspapers, will you mind?” Of course he was
                    perfectly right. Within a week it was a joke. No, I was not involved in anything
                    delicate.</p>
                <p>On one occasion a man came from Kabul, a reporter from an English newspaper. He
                    said he had information he wanted to give me. It soon became apparent the
                    information was meant for the CIA chief. And I had protested that this was not
                    my kind of information, that I wanted no connection with it. He insisted and he
                    took his little book out to verify it and said, “Oh my God, I was to see you
                    about a cultural matter.” He had turned the wrong page. No, I think I can say I
                    was not involved in anything that—oh, there were some attacks, continuing
                    attacks, on American scholars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this from organs like the Patriot?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: The Patriot or in Parliament with people denouncing American scholars for
                    being engaged in espionage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this is part of that larger disinformation operation
                        which has always been particularly severe in India.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: We never made any public statements. We too used our own channels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sometimes it's the best way of making it go away.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes.</p>
                <p>Embree's Comments On Some Of Most Important Cultural Activities Going On In India
                    During His Period As CAOEmbree's Comments On Some Of Most Important Cultural
                    Activities Going On In India During His Period As CAO</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you consider your most successful undertaking? Do
                        you have a most successful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I don't have a most successful. One of the things that I started that I
                    think has died out, Goheen or maybe it was Jay Gildner, had the idea that we
                    should try to get young Indians who would be leaders in 20 years to meet their
                    counter- parts from America. And we started one program of bringing some
                    together. It was very difficult in either country to say who were the 20
                    leaders, or who are the young people who are going to be leaders, especially
                    difficult in India.</p>
                <p>But I did set up one seminar which I thought was a very good idea called the
                    Chester Bowles Seminar in which we invited some bright young Americans and some
                    bright young Indians. It was much easier for me to identify the bright young
                    Indians from contacts I had. It was extremely difficult to identify bright young
                    Americans. And, of course, it always raised the question of money. How are we
                    going to get ten Americans? We did get ten in the end, taking people who were in
                    India. And it was very interesting and to some extent it achieved what I think
                    we wanted to achieve. And that was to get people who would know each other
                    through the years. I think that could have been a very successful thing if it
                    had been maintained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Of course, like many of these ventures it was personal and too much
                    depended upon one person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, funds shift and priorities shift, but maybe you
                        weren't there long enough.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Another thing I was greatly involved in and interested in was the
                    American Research Center in Hyderabad. I think that is one of the most
                    worthwhile of all our endeavors. I think it as important as the US Educational
                    Foundation, itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, this has got to do with American Studies.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>EMBREE: American Studies. People often laugh when they learn somebody who had
                    never taken a course in American history was running a big program in American
                    Studies. It's an excellent library and it's something that has come in for a
                    great deal of criticism. Why do we have this expensive venture, people have
                    asked. By American standards, it's not an expensive venture, but it's the best
                    library of American literature and history I think in Asia, probably better than
                    in Japan, at least I've been told it is. And it's of enormous importance for
                    Indian scholars who want to work on the United States. It could be of even more
                    value for scholars throughout the area. Some people did come from Southeast
                    Asia, but it is hard for Pakistanis to get there. If I had one institution I'd
                    want to make sure survived, it would be the American Studies Research Center. I
                    think it's very important. The great problem is getting competent Americans to
                    be the directors. We had the wrong approach, I'm convinced, of trying to get a
                    Fulbrighter to go out and run it for two years. It didn't work. We couldn't get
                    the right people. It would have been much better if we'd got a good Indian to be
                    director and an American to go out as a resident scholar for two years. I think
                    we could have done that, and I think we still could if we were going to put more
                    money in. But we couldn't get first class Americans to go for two years for
                    small pay. It just wasn't in the cards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I visited the Hyderabad Center and I've also sent
                        out people as part of that selection process. So I know what you are
                        speaking about, that it is very difficult. But certainly the results are
                        also excellent. In the one educational exchange project in which I was
                        involved, I think this was after you had left India, we used the Center to
                        bring together scholars from all over South Asia, including Pakistan, at a
                        time when we weren't even sure that the Paks would be allowed in. But
                        because of the nature of the Center and what the project was all about, it
                        worked.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I think we could do much more with that. I think that could become a
                    really great center. Again, I think that's one place where a non-professional
                    CAO could play a big role. One of the things that I found interesting with
                    American Foreign Service officers in the Embassy or in the USIS, it doesn't take
                    long before they get out of touch with the United States, especially the
                    American academic world. And then when you think of it, what they knew about
                    American academic life from being a student. You get out of touch quickly. I
                    think there's an enormous advantage in USIS of having an academic who really is
                    into the American scene.</p>
                <p>Frequent Resentment Toward, And Misunderstanding Of Foreign Service Officers By
                    American Academics Visiting Or Living In A Foreign CountryFrequent Resentment
                    Toward, And Misunderstanding Of Foreign Service Officers By American Academics
                    Visiting Or Living In A Foreign Country</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Academic scene.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you know, and I speak from the point of view of the
                        Foreign Service officer, one finds that there's a certain amount of
                        conflict, almost emotional resentment, between the academics who are in
                        country and the Embassy. Part of this has got to do with the so-called perks
                        which one has which they don't realize are not necessarily coming straight
                        out of the government. I found that particularly true in Iran. But I think
                        you're very right about the knowledge, the internal knowledge, of how
                        universities work, who pushes which button and all of those things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: There is also, of course, ignorance on the part of the academics. I was
                    attacked in Delhi by American academics for not pushing some particular policy
                    that was clearly against American government policy. I remember having a very
                    bitter argument with an American political scientist of some repute. I explained
                    to him not only did I have no conceivable way of affecting the policy, that even
                    the Ambassador—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're talking about political issues.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Political issues that were decided in Washington and we were carrying
                    out. Academics have very little knowledge of how the government works, that the
                    Ambassador is the agent of the State Department and the State Department is the
                    agent of the Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: American academics, as you know, have a fashion of criticizing the
                    government. I was talking just recently with a young woman, very well known, who
                    referred to one of my former colleagues, Paul Kreisberg, as a CIA agent. And I
                    said, well, Paul Kreisberg was a very high ranking officer, why would he be a
                    CIA agent? She said, well, he was giving information about Indian politics to
                    the American government. I said, that's what he was paid for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's his job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: And she couldn't get this through her head. I said, you know, if he knew
                    anything of value to the American government or the Indian government, of
                    course, he would communicate it. He'd be a very poor Foreign Service officer if
                    he didn't. And this shocked her. And she said, well, you wouldn't. And I said,
                    well, if I knew anything that I thought would be of value, yes, of course.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>I have great misgivings about second raters, especially in a country like India.
                    They're terribly conscious, for example, of our American academics who go to
                    India that they're often not our best people—that we don't get the people out
                    there whose books they read.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, dear. Let me ask you about one other element and then
                        maybe we will—two other elements. You traveled a great deal when you were
                        CAO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I traveled a lot to Calcutta and Madras. I was very involved with the
                    Calcutta people. Now, you raise a very interesting question into the whole way,
                    you know, what I knew my job was. I didn't do very much pushing, so to speak. I
                    spoke when I was asked to speak. Now, this was a very difficult position for me
                    because all I am professionally qualified to speak on is India. And they would
                    ask me to speak on India. And as you know, this was not looked upon with great
                    favor. But I really wasn't qualified to talk about American subjects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you did talk about India?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Actually, what I talked about a great deal was human rights and foreign
                    policy, remember it's the Carter days. So I could give the President's line,
                    which I wholly agreed with, and at the same time not have to pretend knowledge
                    of American policy judgment.</p>
                <p>Comparisons Of India 1948-58 And India In Late 1970'sComparisons Of India 1948-58
                    And India In Late 1970's</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is very true. And when you do travel around, which I
                        always enjoyed doing, it gives you a wonderful opportunity to really see
                        what's going on instead of being bound in the capital city. And you with
                        your background would be particularly good at this. Well, how did you find
                        living? Are there any comparisons about living—I'm not even talking about
                        your life as a missionary teacher and then your life in the Embassy, but I
                        mean living—what was it? A decade later in India? Did you find that there
                        were many changes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Oh, yes. There were great changes in India itself, enormous changes. We
                    went to India in 1948. We didn't have a flush toilet. We didn't have a
                    refrigerator. They hadn't even heard about air conditioners. None of the helps
                    to living which became commonplace later on. In our early days we would have
                    been very embarrassed to live in the kind of splendor we lived in Delhi. We had
                    got over that meanwhile. We realized the Indians didn't care. I don't think it
                    was the least barrier to our friendships with Indians that we lived in the
                    peculiarly large house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a very particular house. As I recall, it had lots
                        of columns.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>EMBREE: Lots of columns, yes. So there was tremendous change in our own
                    lifestyle. But in that sense the change in India itself, the prosperity in
                    India, the growth of the middle class, nobody would have foreseen when we went
                    to India in '48. That's a change in Delhi, basically in Delhi, and in other big
                    cities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The urban centers.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: The urban centers. India now has a very affluent middle class.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you can see this. It's interesting when you travel
                        around and make these observations. Has there been any special impact of
                        this stint in the diplomatic service on your subsequent thinking or your
                        subsequent academic career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Oh, yes, I'm sure. It's linked me in a very interesting way with the
                    academics, all of whom came through Delhi. I know virtually every American
                    academic who came to India the two years I was there. It's also a very important
                    link with the people in Washington, my involvement at the Foreign Service
                    Institute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You lecture there from time to time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: I lecture regularly. Now, that comes about actually through connections I
                    had made with Sid Sober and one or two others at an earlier period when I was
                    lecturing for USIS in Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you crossed country boundaries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes, that was before I was CAO. I didn't when I was CAO.</p>
                <p>Small Incidents Of Indian Government Denying Embree Trip To BhutanSmall Incidents
                    Of Indian Government DenyingEmbree Trip To Bhutan</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>One interesting thing that happened when you're speaking of diplomatic matters.
                    Bhutan was very anxious to start a program in the United States of sending their
                    young people in the service. And Senator Percy was a great friend of Bhutan and
                    he was pushing this both in Washington and indeed in Delhi. And so I readily
                    agreed that I would go to Bhutan and help them select some people to go study in
                    the United States. They had no idea how to do it. The only catch was that the
                    Indian government wouldn't let me go. Nobody wanted to say this publicly,
                    especially the Bhutanese education minister. However, Senator Percy didn't know
                    and he thought I had refused to help the Bhutanese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Too bad somebody couldn't whisper in the good Senator's
                        ear of the niceties.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: He probably didn't realize the close rein Indians kept on where certain
                    Americans go. That was the other side of it, by the way, that I was watched more
                    carefully by the Indian government than I think other people would have been,
                    because they knew me and I had been there before. They sometimes used to check
                    my guest lists of who went to my house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before the guests arrived.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Oh, yes. Often before the guests arrived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One does not necessarily think of India with such a strong
                        surveillance program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mrs. Embree's Activities During Delhi TourMrs. Embree's Activities During Delhi
                    Tour</p>
                <p>Did Sue have any special feeling about this second stint in India?</p>
                <p>EMBREE: She was very unwilling to go because she remembered our former life and
                    thought that was fine when we were young, but why go through that again? So she
                    was somewhat dumbfounded when she arrived and discovered we had two freezers and
                    two refrigerators in our kitchen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Happily surprised.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Happily surprised. She played a very interesting role. Mrs. Goheen once
                    said to me, you know, there are only two real Embassy wives in Delhi. I said,
                    what do you mean? She said, Sue and I are the only two women who act like old
                    fashioned Embassy wives.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That raises a whole issue, which we will not go into in
                        this interview, about this change which is very true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: It was true. Of course, both Mrs. Goheen and Sue had been used to
                    entertaining for their husbands always and continued to fit in with the pattern.
                    She enjoyed the years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She didn't teach again?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: No, she didn't teach. She didn't have any formal kind of activity, but
                    she was very involved with some of the young Embassy wives who were very
                    interested in learning about India and doing things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any last set of comments that you'd like to
                        speak about this experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: No, the only thing I guess would be to put in a plug anytime I can for
                    the possibilities of old style Cultural Affairs Officers. I think they played a
                    real role. Again, it should be somebody good needless to say. But you've got to
                    have—well, like Margaret Clapp. You know, these were real ornaments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, her stint saw a whole set of problems of a
                        particular nature.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Yes. Well, I didn't know much about that at the time. I think you can
                    play a real role of cultural diplomacy and which I think is useful anywhere. I
                    think it's especially useful in countries like India.</p>
                <p>Embree's Views Of Special Contributions Of Cultural Diplomacy And A Specific
                    Problem Faced By Our International Visitors ProgramEmbree's Views Of Special
                    Contributions Of Cultural Diplomacy And A Specific Problem Faced By Our
                    International Visitors Program</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say cultural diplomacy, how do you view cultural
                        diplomacy? What do you consider that its special contributions are to
                        relations among nations and peoples?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>EMBREE: What I mean by it is not just the academic exchange programs or even the
                    cultural kind of programs we bring. One of the things that I tried to impress
                    people with was that American universities had the best centers for studying
                    other cultures in the world. But if you want to study Russian cultures, you
                    should come to Columbia, not someplace in Moscow, certainly not India. You want
                    to study Japan? If I were an Indian and wanted to study Japan, I'd want to come
                    to—as many have, as a matter of fact—to a place like Columbia, Harvard, or so
                    on. That's one level that I think we really never explored—what we do in terms
                    of world cultures.</p>
                <p>The other thing that I think is very important is not defending what we do, but
                    to try and make clear something of the richness and diversity of American life
                    which Indians had very little conception of. One of the programs I am most
                    critical of and that I've been most involved while I was there and most involved
                    with now is our Visitors Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The International Visitors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: International Visitors Program. A great deal of praise from some people,
                    enormous criticisms from other people. And I'm not sure now having seen the
                    problems from this end what can be done. But as an example of one of the real
                    problems. A well known Indian newspaperman came to America, and he assumed he
                    would meet people such as his opposite number at the New York Times. Like
                    everybody else, he wanted to interview Kissinger and Brzezinski. And they always
                    felt insulted when they discovered that they were going to meet the newsboy down
                    at the New York Times. That was one of our areas of failure I think of our
                    International Visitors Program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess the only way to deal with this is have fewer
                        visitors. All the political scientists, all diplomatic historians, they all
                        want to talk to Kissinger. They all want to talk to the same people. And
                        you've got visitors coming from all over the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: Well, this of course is the other side of it. One tends to think you've
                    only got your 20 people from India. And of course you've got 20 people from 140
                    countries. That is one area that I think needs looking into. I'm not sure the
                    volunteers always realized how ticklish this is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it seems to me there just needs to be more briefing.
                        You should be made to brief the visitor thoroughly before they go so they
                        know what they can expect before they leave their home shores. I mean,
                        they're not going to see a Kissinger or whoever, the leader in the field of
                        their concern is. I have faced up to this when I was in Japan, for they all
                        want to see no one but the best because they consider themselves the
                        best.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>EMBREE: They consider themselves the best and they are the best in their own
                    country. Now, Japan is an interesting case. I assume they wouldn't be so vocal
                    about their displeasure as the Indians are.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They let you know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EMBREE: They do?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, indeed. Of course, one of the other problems. Talking
                        about getting—many of these people really think they know the United States,
                        but they really don't know it. So they have no sense of the geography, of
                        how large it is, what they can do. Then they get disappointed, a whole batch
                        of things like that. From my experience the only way you can deal with this
                        is a tremendous amount of hand holding on all sides.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
