<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001031">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Charles A. Schmitz </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>CHARLES A. SCHMITZ</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Samuel F. Hart </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 29, 1993</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is Thursday, July 29, 1993. The interviewer today is
                        Samuel F. Hart. The interviewee is Charles A. Schmitz. To start the
                        interview, Chuck, where are you from?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I was born in Kansas City in 1938 and spent my first 18 years there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then off to school. Where was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I went to Yale College from 1956-60 and then to Yale Law School for the
                    next three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do after you graduated from Yale Law School
                        in 1963.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I went back to Kansas City to be a law clerk to a Federal District judge
                    there, designed to be a place from which I could make judgments about the local
                    law firms so I could find one to affiliate with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I decided that I didn't really want to affiliate with one at that point.
                    I hadn't been in the military. This was during the Vietnamese build up. I
                    figured I had a couple of years to spend so I decided to spend them in a
                    temporary job with the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you come to the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I arrived in July, 1964 and entered on duty with the Office of the Legal
                    Advisor.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell us a little bit about your experiences
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I went to work for Charlie Runyon, who was Assistant Legal Advisor for
                    African Affairs. I spent a year in a fascinating time learning how the US was
                    operating in Africa at a period during which we were very concerned about
                    inroads there by the Soviets and Chinese. So we were fighting the Cold War in
                    our policies in Africa.</p>
                <p>That experience was punctuated by wars in the Congo; gun running into North
                    Africa; concerns with what we were going to do when the International Court of
                    Justice found in favor of the world on the Southwest Africa case, which we now
                    know as Namibia; and major concerns in the Legal Advisor side with our economic
                    assistance there. Particularly how AID missions would function in these various
                    countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came into State as a lawyer. Was that as a GS? What
                        type of appointment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It was a so-called excepted position. The State Department's Legal
                    Advisor's Office runs like a law firm. The Legal Advisor hires his lawyers. I
                    guess it did have a GS indicator. I think it was a GS-11 that I entered as. I
                    stayed there for a year, until I had managed to persuade my boss that what I
                    would most like to do is to see how the world looked from overseas.</p>
                <p>So he worked with Crockett, who was then Deputy Under Secretary for
                    Administration, on setting up a system to allow some of the young lawyers to go
                    overseas and serve in embassies as a kind of training ground. I thought it was
                    the equivalent of taking your lawyer out to the mill to see how it worked so he
                    would be in a better position to help you. To set it up so that we might go do
                    something in an embassy for a year or so and come back better able to do our
                    legal work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You entered as a lawyer and that, of course...the whole
                        Legal Advisor's Office is one which you can get a lot of different opinions
                        upon in the State Department, some of which say that conduct of foreign
                        affairs is far too much influenced by the lawyers. What would you say on
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, first of all, my own bias, of course, was as a lawyer trying to
                    have some influence on policy and the reason that I decided to come to the State
                    Department instead of being in a law firm was because I felt that the world was
                    in great peril. In fact, I think at that time, 1964, it probably was. One needed
                    to make a contribution to the great issues of his own day. I felt that the
                    greatest issue of the day was how we were going to keep ourselves from getting
                    blown up or blowing up somebody else. So I wanted to bring what I thought was a
                    legal perspective to the activities of the US in the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>At that time the Legal Advisor's Office, under Abe Chayes was quite an activist
                    office. It was a time we were trying to build the rule of law around the world.
                    The US was a proponent of the growth and dedication to inter- national law and
                    regulations. We were trying to build the United Nations as another structure to
                    get some form to the contest of sovereign wills around the world. I felt that,
                    as a result of working for three years in law school and then the Federal
                    District court...we are talking about lawyers being the people who work in the
                    process of resolving issues, whether it is a formal structure as is the case in
                    the federal legal system or whether as a good draftsman of contracts or
                    treaties...which is to say how do you describe what it is you are going to do in
                    a way so both parties will see that the result is in accord with their
                    expectations and is fair.</p>
                <p>These kinds of basic approaches to problems would have an application on the
                    international scene as well and might therefore make a small contribution to
                    making the world a little bit safer. So we, people my age and ilk in the Legal
                    Advisor's Office, felt keen that there was a role for the legal trained mind in
                    applying itself to some of the issues that faced us.</p>
                <p>For example, in the war in the Congo, which was going on at that time, we felt it
                    was very important to use the obligation of the Congo to adhere to the
                    international laws of warfare under the ICRC convention. We made ourselves
                    nuisances in the African Bureau by writing instructions to embassies, draft
                    instructions, of course, or making suggestions, about how to get some moderation
                    in that conflict through legal application.</p>
                <p>A lot of that was unpleasant because our Foreign Service colleagues would keep us
                    waiting in the outer room cooling heels, anything to avoid having to go over the
                    issue again and we felt it was our job to sit out there and cool our heels until
                    they would finally emerge and would have to talk to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this period in the Legal Advisor's Office, did you have
                        any particular role models that you tried to emulate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Abe Chayes, himself, I think was one of the best because he was very
                    active and close to the then Kennedy Administration. He was articulate and
                    forceful. He was succeeded by Len Meeker, a career person who had spent all of
                    his professional life in the Legal Advisor's Office. He knew everything cold
                    about the post World War development in international law.</p>
                <p>But my hero for legal advisor work was Jack Tate, who had been the Deputy Legal
                    Advisor many years before under Dean Acheson and who during his time there gave
                    a lot of structure to the Office of the Legal Advisor, to the approach by the
                    State Department to international law.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>When Eisenhower was elected, Jack's position was politicized. He was allowed to
                    continue but he decided that he couldn't work under the Republican
                    Administration. He wound up at the Yale Law School as Associate Dean and it was
                    there that I worked for him on admission policies into the Yale Law School, as
                    part-time employment. From him I learned that there was such a thing as the
                    State Department, that it had lawyers in it, that it was a place where a young
                    person could get a lot of responsibility early on and possibly make a difference
                    in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that is how your interest in going to work for the
                        State Department started with you professor at Yale Law School.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Absolutely. When I discovered I wasn't ready to stay in Kansas City half
                    way through the clerkship and I wondered what I could do to do something with my
                    life that would make a difference, a feeling that probably would not be
                    satisfied by my immediately joining a law firm and doing dog and cat law or even
                    corporate law, I thought about the Legal Advisor's Office because of him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you ever thought about taking the Foreign Service exam
                        and doing the regular career path?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It never crossed my mind. I never really thought about the Foreign
                    Service as a career or an option. I think the first time I heard about the
                    Foreign Service was when I was in college and we were doing a course on
                    international relations. At that point I had a superficial notion of how the
                    State Department worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came then and spent 1964-65, at least parts of those
                        years, in the Legal Advisor's Office and then you were off to Morocco as
                        second secretary in the political section. What do you particularly remember
                        about those years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: First of all, the basic idea of this was to give me training in how an
                    embassy worked. I thought it was going to be for a very short period, like a
                    year. The Embassy said that it was not long enough, you won't be of any utility
                    during the first year so you have to stay at least two.</p>
                <p>I was impressed by two things. One was the silliness of an awful lot of what we
                    did in the Embassy. At that point we felt that we needed to know everything
                    there was to know about a foreign country, particularly one that we could
                    describe as strategic...and we did so describe Morocco. I had come now to
                    believe that anybody can describe any place in the world as strategic and make
                    the same justification.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>But in any case, we felt that we needed to gather all kinds of data, no matter
                    how irrelevant to any decisions that the US might have to make in its foreign
                    relations. And we did. We did a good job of that. My own expertise was in the
                    Moroccan educational system. I spent a lot of the government's time researching
                    that educational system and writing an excellent report about it. Probably
                    better than was given to the Ministry of Education in the country. In fact, to
                    do the report I talked to the Minister of Education. For that I received a
                    commendation from INR. In retrospect I thought this was a good example of how
                    the US is wasting its time and energies because as far as I know there was never
                    more than a modicum of reason in our wanting to know about that educational
                    system. It had to do with maybe how we could help it so that its people would be
                    more broadly educated and therefore more resistant to the seductions of
                    communism.</p>
                <p>It had a little bit, I think, too, to do with what we then called “nation
                    building.” An era when we thought we knew how to build nations. And that is my
                    second point. I worked a lot with our AID mission in Morocco. The people were
                    good. A lot of the programs were on their own terms excellent programs and yet I
                    dare say that I don't think we did much at all to develop the economy of
                    Morocco. I think what our program did primarily was to give Moroccans the sense
                    that America was trying to help. It gave us a tiny bit of leverage, mostly
                    represented by access of our ambassador and other officials when they wanted to
                    see somebody because Moroccans thought we were important. But we were
                    constrained at using what might have been that leverage in any really important
                    situation because we thought if we used the leverage it would be seen as a
                    condition on our aid or otherwise being stingy or mean spirited and that would
                    eliminate the value that we thought we were getting from aid in the first
                    place.</p>
                <p>So we did spend a lot of our personal time and effort...most of the resources
                    though came from our surplus grain supply which didn't cost us a thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: PL 480.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: PL 480. But it also gave me great pause in thinking how useful this was
                    for the real purpose of building the country. As I think back on the rationale
                    that we made for it and the way we talked about it, it really had much more to
                    do with fighting the Cold War in the third world than it did with our
                    expectation that we were going to build the economy of the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you think we should have been doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Now that I am in my old age, I believe that the parable of the fish and
                    the fisherman is the right one. That is, if you give a starving man a fish you
                    have saved his life and if you teach him how to fish you might have given him
                    something to save his life for the rest of his life, is true. I think our
                    willingness to provide assistance which instigated willingness from other
                    countries and ultimately from the UN, itself, to provide assistance, became a
                    crutch that caused the countries we were trying to aid not trying as hard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you use the parable of teaching a person how to fish
                        rather than giving him the fish, what kind of things...did you voice these
                        concerns and ideas in the Embassy at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I don't think so. First of all, I am not sure I felt them as strongly
                    while I was there. I was kind of picking them up as I went along. And secondly,
                    I wasn't in much of a position to do it effectively. There is always a lot of
                    carping in the political section and, I suppose, the general Embassy, about the
                    AID mission—how much money it was spending and all these vehicles and
                    buildings.</p>
                <p>There were people who came out and knew nothing about diplomacy and although they
                    might be skilled as technicians of one sort or another they offended our host
                    officials and people by their rude behavior. That was really most of the
                    discussion. I think very little of it was related to the utility of our programs
                    to really develop the economy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the ambassador and DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The Ambassador was Henry Tasca, a career officer. He was an economic
                    specialist who had worked on the Marshall Plan earlier on and therefore felt
                    that he knew nation building. The DCM was Leon Doros, a very quiet man. He had
                    to endure the Ambassador's dominant personality and he made his way primarily by
                    keeping his head down and not doing very much. Therefore he wound up not being a
                    very popular leader in the Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So I take it you didn't feel like you accomplished very
                        much during these years in Morocco?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Personally I did. But for the United States I think the results of my
                    being there were highly questionable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So when you left Morocco...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I came back to the Office of the Legal Advisor and wanted to be where
                    the action was. Action at that time was in East Asia where we were fighting a
                    war in Vietnam. So I asked for an assignment with the East Asia area in the
                    Legal Advisor's Office.</p>
                <p>While there we divided our clients into various categories. I wound up working on
                    elements of the war in Vietnam, primarily what we called the status of the
                    contractors in the country and to what extent they were controlled by military
                    law. I dealt with some of the hostages held by the Cambodians and issues of
                    defoliation of Cambodia, trying to defend the value of the Laotian kip and
                    things of that kind in Indochina.</p>
                <p>But as that period developed I found myself being drawn more and more into the
                    work of what I then considered a minor part of my area and that was Japan. I was
                    drawn into it because the preliminary discussions leading to the Okinawa
                    Reversion Treaty were going on. As these discussions proceeded, the issues
                    changed from ones of large policy to ones of technical implementation. How would
                    we square the resulting US presence on Okinawa with their existing treaties in
                    Japan, particularly the Status of Forces Treaty. In the middle of that
                    continuum, between those two extremes, there were policy questions which could
                    take legal form having to do with issues such as how do we take care of the
                    dollars which were being used as legal currency in Okinawa that would be picked
                    up by the Japanese when reversion occurred in such a way that they would not
                    become additional claims on the balance of payments problems of the United
                    States. This was a matter of great concern at the time to the Nixon
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you see as the most important foreign policy
                        issues you were dealing with on the Okinawa problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The principal issue was whether or not we could get the support of the
                    American people to do it at all. We, who were concerned with it, were absolutely
                    certain that it was the best thing to do. I and my colleagues had seemingly
                    endless debates with Americans who thought that giving back Okinawa was a
                    terrible mistake. We had, after all, fought and bleed and even died for it. It
                    was important to national security and we couldn't trust the Japanese. In fact,
                    we shouldn't give the Japanese a thing and we ought to just hang on to it and
                    provide for ourselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this cause you to have certain deja vu feelings later
                        on when you worked on the Panama Treaty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. In fact, I think that experience had a lot to do with why I was
                    working on the Panama Treaty later on.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>There were some subsidiary issues in the Okinawa exercise having to do with what
                    do we do with nuclear weapons, what about the American businessmen who were
                    already on the island. What about American activities which were nonconforming
                    under the Japanese Status of Forces such as our VOA station, Foreign
                    Broadcasting Information Service, some of the special military operations we
                    were running out of there, religious language broadcasting, etc. I think
                    probably there were about a thousand issues that had to be resolved government
                    to government in that negotiation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned special operations being run out of there,
                        could you elaborate on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It is probably still too early to elaborate on that, but the category of
                    things, of course, was having to do with how we used Okinawa in the Cold War
                    context to advance our purposes. We had there a major CIA installation and a
                    black operations run, I think, by all the services, including the famous black
                    bird itself, the SR-71, which operated out of Okinawa. Most of these things gave
                    great concern to Japanese politicians and therefore to the Japanese bureaucrats
                    with whom we were dealing primarily. And we had to make provisions for each one.
                    And those provisions had to be basically whether they could continue or not,
                    which was a heavy part of the negotiation initially.</p>
                <p>And then secondly, if they were allowed to continue how would it be done, how
                    would it be explained? Most of this happened after I had actually gotten to
                    Japan which was a little bit after the time we are talking about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a good treaty or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It took us the better part of two years to negotiate the treaty and its
                    related arrangements and to make sure it came into effect in good form. It was
                    for the United States one of the best deals we had made since, I think, the
                    Louisiana Purchase, because we wound up yielding practically nothing. We made
                    some adjustments, but those adjustments did not make it more difficult or more
                    expensive for us to carry out our functions. We continue to this day to use
                    Okinawa as a military staging base, something which in 1969 we weren't sure
                    would last for even five years after Okinawa was returned to Japan. From that
                    standpoint, any usefulness now of Okinawa for us is a big plus.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>But in addition to being able to use it for almost everything we wanted to, we
                    were relieved of the burden, financial and other, of occupying and running the
                    island, which most Americans didn't realize was costing us millions and millions
                    of dollars every year for doing something which we weren't good at and didn't
                    need to do. Our continued government there made us look like imperialists, and
                    that was causing us a lot of trouble throughout the rest of Asia.What we did in
                    the negotiations was sell the effort that we had already put in to running
                    Okinawa. Maybe was a contribution that I made, because I argued that once we had
                    committed ourselves to giving Okinawa to the Japanese, we would in effect, in
                    legal terms, be yielding our “future interests” to the facilities which we had
                    constructed there. We would then be criticized by the US people or the Senate as
                    it considered the treaty, for having disposed of American assets without making
                    proper accounting of them.</p>
                <p>I did a considerable amount of research on this and discovered that when NATO was
                    thrown out of France there was a similar kind of negotiation when the French
                    took over military facilities. The formula used then was to find the value of
                    the facilities which the French accepted. And that value turned out to be
                    something we came to call the “depreciated replacement value”. That is, what it
                    would cost today to build that same facility with the same amount of years on it
                    as it had had. Obviously it is a purely mathematical construct, but it managed
                    to take into account both the depreciation of the thing and the inflation, which
                    had to be a major consideration. On that basis we calculated a value for these
                    facilities and were able in various ways in the Okinawa Reversion Agreement to
                    have that accounted for by the Japanese and paid back to the United States, not
                    so much in cash, but in very usable forms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened when the treaty went to the Senate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The Senate committee asked for our explanation of what we had done. I
                    prepared the materials for that, including a briefing book for our people with
                    the horrible questions and the best answers that we could make. We were able, by
                    signaling what those questions and answers were going to be, to avoid any
                    difficulty whatsoever in the Senate consideration of the treaty. In fact, when
                    the General Accounting Office, as a part of its responsibility to help the
                    Senate decide what to do about this, asked us to prepare for an audit of the
                    treaty dispositions, I supplied them almost everything we had in the book. They
                    looked at our briefing book and wrote a letter saying that they had been
                    prepared to spend two man years on the audit, but because they saw that we had
                    been completely open with them and had foreseen and taken account of these
                    issues, they gave the treaty a clean bill of health. They suspended the audit
                    and told us we had saved the taxpayers a lot of money by not having forced them
                    to audit the books.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the treaty had a very smooth passage once negotiated.
                        Other than yourself, who were the major players in negotiating this
                        treaty?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The principal player for the US was Richard Sneider, who had been on the
                    Japan Desk when these negotiations first started and then he went to the NSC.
                    When it became time to negotiate the treaty in Tokyo, he was our designated
                    negotiator. It was he who hired me to go with him to Tokyo to do that.</p>
                <p>Shortly after we had arrived and assembled the team, he was then elevated to be
                    DCM of the Embassy. So while he could continue to watch over these negotiations,
                    the day-to-day job of finding solutions to the issues in the negotiations fell
                    then to me. I wound up be, in effect, the chief of staff for that work. He did
                    the heavy lifting on the interagency concurrences and the initial work on
                    Congressional approval of the treaty. He was a very aggressive man, especially
                    relative to other Foreign Service officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Type A?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, type A plus. Type A with sharp teeth and sharp elbows. He was a man
                    who was very effective in getting his way and obviously often bruised people in
                    the process. The reason that I was able to exist under that was that early on we
                    had a disagreement and I was lucky enough that that disagreement was on an issue
                    in which I didn't have any choice. That issue was whether or not this agreement
                    to return Okinawa would be done as an Executive Agreement, as we did in the
                    earlier return of the Bonin Islands, which included Iwo Jima, or whether it had
                    to be done by treaty. His assumption was that we could do it by Executive
                    Agreement and he wanted it to be that way so you did not have to fool with
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>As I looked at the issue I easily came to the conclusion that Okinawa was a
                    different kettle of fish qualitatively than Iwo Jima and the little bunch of
                    islands about which nobody cared: that this agreement to return Okinawa was a
                    matter of policy for the country. I argued that we could not win the legal
                    argument that the precedent of Iwo Jima would apply, and therefore we had to go
                    to the Senate with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a legal judgment or a political judgment?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, it is one of those beautiful ones in which the policy is lying
                    there but the way you decide the policy is that you ask lawyers for views. The
                    Constitution says something about treaties and the implied Executive Powers of
                    the President says something about Executive Agreements, but you then look to
                    see what the precedents are. That is generally a lawyer's job. You look at the
                    precedents, which was my job. I could see that if we were going to assert this
                    was an Executive Agreement, we would have to make an argument about something
                    more important than anything that had ever carried that attribution before; and
                    that then becomes a policy question of whether we want to do it. But, as I told
                    the policy makers, if we try to make that argument, when you turn around to ask
                    your lawyers to help you out, you will see a whole bunch of people diving for
                    cover. The Senate has lawyers too, and so do interest groups, so this is not the
                    kind of issue that you can pass up. This is one of those cases we were talking
                    about before where State Department FSOs, let's say, frequently say, “I could
                    have done it quick and easy if it hadn't been for the lawyers mucking around
                    with me.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You feel in the end that Sneider accepted your views as
                        being the valid ones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Oh, more than that. He admitted that he was wrong. The reason he did
                    that was because had he won, we would have lost in the negotiations because we
                    had on our side in the negotiations a very powerful argument for nearly every
                    one of these delicate issues and that was, “You might be able to persuade us,
                    but how the hell are we going to persuade the Senate of the United States.” So
                    that in the theory of negotiations is the value of having an irrational partner.
                    The person with an irrational partner almost always wins. In fact, that not only
                    gave us that set of negotiating arguments, it gave the whole negotiation a
                    visibility in the United States that clearly had an impact in the way he
                    (Sneider) was regarded in the State Department through the United States
                    Government.</p>
                <p>So the effect was to benefit Sneider, benefit the Embassy, and benefit the State
                    Department because this was a very important negotiation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't he later on become Assistant Secretary for EA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No, he became Ambassador to Korea.</p>
                <p>In any case, as we had the discussion about this, he said, “You can not maintain
                    that position. It is time for you lawyers to think politically.” I said, “I'm
                    sorry that I can't change this position because as far as I am concerned as a
                    lawyer I can not make the argument that you are telling me I can make, and
                    therefore it is really a question of shall we take this together to our
                    superiors and have it out.” Sneider then threatened to throw me off the
                    negotiating team if I didn't change my mind.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>Well, if the issue had been tougher for me, I might well have yielded on that and
                    I would have lost his respect, I think. I might have stayed on the team, but I
                    would have been rolled over. But because the issue took the form it did, I
                    didn't yield, and ultimately my view prevailed . The episode developed a sense
                    of reliability that allowed him to turnover to me a lot of this negotiation
                    while he could attend to the rest of the issues of the Embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, we have the Okinawa negotiations completed and
                        ratified and you moved on to...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: In the summer of 1972, when everything about Okinawa was pretty much
                    concluded, I was asked to stay on at the Embassy to be Counselor for
                    Political/Military affairs in order to provide some continuity with the
                    negotiations. In part, this was because the Embassy felt that there might be a
                    lot of loose ends to the negotiations and that maybe not everything would work
                    well. Sneider was leaving, there was a turnover of ambassadors, and so I could
                    provide the continuity. Moreover, since I had mastered the Status of Forces
                    Agreement and all the military paraphernalia, it made a certain amount of sense
                    that I do that.</p>
                <p>So, for two more years I carried out that function, which had to do in part with
                    making sure that our forces on Okinawa performed well and could do their job,
                    and in part that the whole US-Japan security relationship, which at that time
                    was changing radically because of the reversion, continued to function.</p>
                <p>At the same time I could do things like assist in making sense out of adjustments
                    in our military force structure in Japan, and when I had some spare time I could
                    do some legal work such as what was required to clear the title of Embassy
                    grounds so that we could rebuild the Embassy, which we did at the tag end of
                    that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything else that is particularly memorable from that
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The most fascinating part of that whole thing was an issue which we
                    called the Murasami Bashi problem. That was a problem involving our continuing
                    to fight in Vietnam, very unpopular in Japan, and using Japan to support that
                    fight. We did that in a noteworthy case by repairing tanks and armored personnel
                    carriers at the Sagami depot in Japan. After these things were repaired they
                    were put on big Army convoys and driven down to the piers in Yokohama to be put
                    on ships to go to Vietnam. They moved visibly through the streets. Yokohama was
                    then run by a Socialist mayor. There were lots of young communists. To see these
                    things moving around in Japan they considered were going down to kill Vietnamese
                    was anathema. There were demonstrations about these movements, and ultimately
                    one day a convoy was totally surrounded by demonstrators and stopped. The police
                    told us they couldn't interfere because the load limit of one of the bridges
                    turned out to be less than the weight of trucks in the convoy and therefore if
                    they allowed the convoy to proceed, the police would be a party to a violation
                    of the law, which they would not abide. The short of this was that 104 days went
                    by before we were able to resolve the issue. I don't want to give the impression
                    that the convoy sat on the street for a 104 days, it sat there for 25 hours
                    surrounded by a howling mob with highly disciplined soldier drivers in the cabs
                    of those trucks doing an excellent job. We finally decided to send them back to
                    Sagami so that we would have some breathing room to solve the problem.</p>
                <p>The solution of the problem involved excellent work from some of the finest
                    career public service officials I have ever seen in my life. These were Japanese
                    and they were what allowed the solution to materialize. This is a hot issue in
                    the Diet and with the opposition parties including the Socialist mayor. The
                    Foreign Ministry officials worked out a mechanism with the rest of the
                    government and the political parties that would allow certain kinds of payments
                    to flow into Yokohama, certain kinds of political statements to be made, and
                    undoubtedly lots of other political payoffs.</p>
                <p>The essential capability that would allow this to take place was the US Army's
                    capacity every morning, around 2 am, to throw a Bailey bridge across the top of
                    the existing bridge and rush the convoy across and down to the docks; unload the
                    tanks and equipment onto the ships; turn around and get back across that Bailey
                    bridge so that it could be taken down to accommodate the morning rush hour
                    traffic that began at six-thirty every morning. It was an extraordinarily
                    disciplined act by the Army engineers of throwing this bridge every morning
                    across the weak bridge, allowing the convoy to rush in, unload and rush out, and
                    deconstruct that bridge in time for the Japanese rush hour. They did an
                    astonishing job of it.</p>
                <p>The reason that all of this was important was that these vehicles had been
                    promised to the South Vietnamese military as a part of their Vietnamizing the
                    war and allowing us to get out of the war. This was an agreement negotiated by
                    Kissinger. It had a special code word. It was critical to the political
                    processes of a whole lot of countries, including our own.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That was 1972, in the summer and fall.</p>
                <p>So the US was under heavy pressure to solve this problem. Of course that
                    translated right to the Embassy. I had the job. We managed to transmit that
                    pressure effectively to the Japanese. They felt it and worked literally night
                    and day, by themselves and with us, to get the thing done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During your period in Japan, both when you were
                        negotiating on the Okinawa treaty and while you were Pol/Mil Counselor, what
                        Japanese leaders did you have a good close view of and which ones did you
                        consider were either particularly able or particularly unhelpful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I think probably the Japanese Prime Minister, Nakasone was one...I am
                    not sure that I had a closer view of him than you could mostly get in the paper
                    and by talking to people who worked with him, which was what I did. A very
                    strong personality, hawkish, a great supporter, of course, of the US and
                    security relationship. He was a powerful and effective man who like most
                    Japanese politicians of that ilk gave rise to suggestions that he was not
                    entirely honest. It is very hard to be entirely honest and be Prime Minister of
                    Japan, I think, under those circumstances. I certainly feel that he was among
                    the most able of all the prominent Japanese politicians.</p>
                <p>But the admiration that I have for the Japanese is not so much for the
                    politicians, they are really less of a leader than our politicians are in the
                    US, but for the Japanese career service and many of those wound up in the
                    Foreign Ministry which is one of the two or three premium ministries in Japan.
                    The best of their people they put on the front line to deal with the United
                    States, because we were their biggest problem. Therefore, I had the wonderful
                    job, both in the Okinawa experience and the political/ military experience, of
                    working with what surely was the cream of the crop of an entire generation of
                    Japanese with any kind of public spirit.</p>
                <p>Of them I would say that there were several that were among the very best public
                    servants that I have ever seen. Particularly one named Matsuda who himself put
                    together and pushed through, including in the Japanese Diet, the deal that made
                    possible the resolution of this tank shipping problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about on the Okinawa side? Who sold it on the
                        Japanese side?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Again the selling inside the Diet was done by these professional
                    diplomats. They worked in a team. A lot of the work fell to their lawyers. They
                    had three principal lawyers working on this while I was there. The two most
                    active with whom I worked were Nakajima, who went on to become Japanese
                    Ambassador to Malaysia and then China and is now on the Japanese Supreme Court,
                    and a fellow who was then a youngish officer called Kuriyama, who now is
                    Japanese Ambassador to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned in the context of your time in Japan, the
                        Vietnam war. Would you share with us your views on that whole time? What
                        were your feelings and thoughts then and in retrospect?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I had not been in the military, and that was one of the reasons I felt I
                    had a few years to come and give my time to the State Department, so I was
                    looking at it as a civilian and a political analyst. I felt initially that what
                    we were doing there was justified and congruent with US interests. As it became
                    an obviously unwinnable war and we were beginning to use so much of our
                    political integrity in doing it as well as our money, I thought it was
                    imperative that we get out of there as quickly as we could with a shred of
                    dignity. I therefore was supportive of most of what I could see being done when
                    I was in the State Department and was a little more privy to our policies than I
                    am now. I thought that most of our people were working quite hard, first of all
                    to try to win the war and secondly, when we couldn't, to Vietnamize the war part
                    of which we had in Japan and thirdly to terminate our involvement in it just as
                    quickly as we possibly could. Of course, not everybody seemed to be
                    participating in all of that and I thought it was a brutalizing thing for us. It
                    was causing a lot of our people to show their worst sides in public and in
                    private.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular kind of examples?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Oh, I think of Foreign Service officers running war rooms and picking
                    out specific targets to be bombed because we thought there were North Vietnamese
                    forces there. The macho, cigar chomping, attitude of a lot of our military
                    people at that time which tended to reduce non-Vietnamese issues to minor
                    matters. The huge use of resources which then made it silly to try to save
                    resources in any other way produced a very bad mind set. There was a swagger to
                    Americans even in Japan where a lot of them would come back from Vietnam on
                    R&amp;R and we were out there applying the might of the superpower in Asia and
                    we really came across not very sympathetic folks in the eyes of most of the
                    Asians I knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any particular incident or event that kind of
                        switched you from saying this was a war worth fighting to one in which the
                        game no longer justified the means?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, the thing that helped me along with that judgment was my
                    participation as a lawyer into a claim from French rubber plantation operators
                    in what was then Cambodia for defoliation of their rubber plantation by what
                    they asserted was US forces. I got the job because I was working on Cambodian
                    affairs at the time and did the usual work of asking around to see whether or
                    not we had in fact defoliated anything and was told that we absolutely had not.
                    Therefore, as a part of building our response to this French claim, I got a
                    group of agricultural experts, three of them together, and sent them to Cambodia
                    to examine this, being confident that they would be able to see that this, in
                    fact, was done from the ground by people who were trying to hang this crime on
                    the Americans.</p>
                <p>I remember distinctly that when we had the debriefing session of that team when
                    they came back, the leader of the team was irate. He said, “I want you to know
                    that I do not appreciate having been asked to put my professional reputation on
                    the line to go out there and decide whether or not this was done by the US
                    forces or not when the US government knows perfectly well that US forces did, in
                    fact, do that. We were being invited to provide a cover up for this illegal
                    activity.”</p>
                <p>Of course we denied any activity in Cambodia at the time. I saw from their report
                    that there was no way that this defoliation could be carried out by anything but
                    us and yet the political requirement of the day was that we could not
                    acknowledge it and therefore we were not going to pay for the damage we caused,
                    even if it was to French plantation owners.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is now August 3, 1993. We had a little break in the
                        session. When we cut off last time you were talking about the poor French
                        plantation owners in Cambodia who could not get anything but lies from the
                        US government. Can we continue with that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It was a matter in which the French plantations suffered great damages
                    and had filed a claim against the United States. The issue for us was whether or
                    not, as alleged in the claims, the US really did defoliate the plantations, or
                    whether as argued by the US military, the plantations were defoliated by either
                    the Khmer Rouge or the North Vietnamese and therefore we had no responsibility.
                    As mentioned before we send a team to investigate and they came back and
                    announced in a session that they were really disturbed, annoyed that they had
                    put their professional lives on the line and it should have been clear to
                    everybody...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But when the response to the Frenchmen came out it was
                        total denial.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I had the job of responding to the claim and when the team came
                    back and said this has to have been done by US forces, then we responded
                    accordingly to the claim. Up until that time anybody in the executive branch of
                    the US would have denied that we had done that.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the French plantation owners did get some
                        compensation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Not too long after we processed that, I was gone from that shop to go
                    overseas, so I don't know how long it was before compensation was made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking now about what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That was about 1969. I left that year to go to Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, so we dropped back in time from where we had been at
                        one time when you had finished your political/military tour in the Embassy
                        in Tokyo after negotiating the Okinawa treaty. Let's jump forward again. The
                        year is 1974 and you are back as part of the Legal Advisor's Office,
                        specializing in Africa. Anything memorable about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: In the negative sense, yes. Nothing was really going on in Africa or US
                    attitudes towards Africa. It was a backwater. About all I could find to do there
                    that made any sense was to gather all of the information about the treaties that
                    we had with the various African countries and to look at the pattern of them and
                    see if there were countries with which we ought to have some treaties, including
                    extradition treaties, tax treaties or something fundamental to the way the US
                    conducts itself in the world. I made a matrix of all the African countries and
                    all of our treaties. Of course it was a big matrix. I brought that to the
                    attention of everybody in the African Bureau and got big yawns as a result. I am
                    not sure that would be the case today. I think more of our people recognize the
                    value of extradition treaties, for example, in just making sure that we can get
                    something done. Cases in the recent past like abducting potential dependents
                    from Mexico, for example, contrary to provisions of the extradition treaty come
                    to mind. I think maybe now it would be better. But for that short period I was
                    in African Affairs there really wasn't much going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me go back for a minute to this Cambodian case you
                        had. At any other time in your Foreign Service career were you ever asked by
                        a superior to “lie for your country”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, several times. And as I thought about this since our last
                    conversation, I think all the times I can remember had to do with national
                    security issues. It really involved in having to deny the existence of
                    something. In a couple of cases it was to deny the existence of secret
                    agreements with a foreign country. In one case to deny any knowledge about how
                    we solved a major problem because we had to solve it clandestinely.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>So behind your question is whether I was uncomfortable doing this, my answer is I
                    was plenty uncomfortable having to state something that I knew to be untrue, but
                    I did not feel that this was an evil that my government was asking me to do. I
                    felt, in particular cases where I had to make these denials, that this was a
                    necessary part of the conduct of State policy involved in the Cold War and
                    keeping the world on an even keel and that having to maintain some things in
                    confidence was a necessary part of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was necessary other than a no comment type of
                        answer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, because sometimes you had to actually deny the existence of a
                    secret agreement. So I would do that. But I was never called on to do it as a
                    cover up incompetence or bad policy decision which I think probably would bother
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1974-75 you were in the African section of the Legal
                        Advisor's Office. Then you moved on to the Micronesia negotiation. Could you
                        say something about that, please?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: After the African stint I went to work for a short time on the
                    Micronesia negotiations. It was an interagency operation. I was the deputy to
                    Hayden Williams, who was the principal negotiator and as he liked to say, the
                    personal representative of the President to these negotiations, although he was
                    nothing of the sort.</p>
                <p>The main things that were going on during the period I was there was to see if we
                    could get the completed agreement with the Marianas through the Congress..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hayden Williams, wasn't he head of the Asian Foundation at
                        one time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I knew him when he was associate dean at Fletcher.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: He did a lot of things. He was working with the Asia Foundation while he
                    was doing this with one hand in Washington.</p>
                <p>Our job was to get the Mariana Covenant approved by the Congress with both
                    implementing legislation and agreement to a treaty, and we did that while I was
                    there. So during that period the negotiations with the rest of Micronesia were
                    kind of on hold except for a couple of times when I had to go to the UN and
                    appear before the Trustee Council and tell them how wonderful our stewardship
                    had been of all that.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>The only thing memorable in that period was what caused my demise in that
                    particular job. The head of the Office of Territories with responsibility for
                    the Pacific Islands, a man named Fred Zeder, was a political appointee who in
                    those more relaxed days didn't see too much of a difference between his business
                    interests and his official interests. He was all for development of these
                    islands economically. So one of the things that he brought about was a huge
                    scheme to develop an oil tanker transshipment operation in Palau so that
                    supertankers coming from the Middle East could go into the basin in Palau,
                    inside the reef, and transship their oil into smaller vessels that could go to
                    Japan and deliver the oil there. This would create a great deal of economic
                    development in Palau.</p>
                <p>I visited Palau a couple of times as part of what I was doing. I was a scuba
                    diver and on one occasion went up to the place where this transshipment place
                    was to be built. And to build it you were going to have to dynamite great acres
                    of the bottom of the lagoon. I dived down into the lagoon where this was going
                    to happen and I found that the bottom of this thing, the lagoon was very
                    shallow, was covered with coral growth and on top of the coral were giant clams.
                    These giant clams surprised me a good deal because I had read that they grow to
                    a maximum of four feet but I dived on clams that with outstretched arms I could
                    just barely reach from one edge of the shell to the other, which is about six
                    feet. So in this place there is this extraordinary growth nursery for this kind
                    of sea creature.With me was a man from the fisheries operation of the trust
                    territories. He told me that Palau has about 300 species of coral which are
                    unknown any place else in the world and probably 250 different kinds of fish.
                    The breeding grounds for these fish are on the western end of Palau. The
                    currents run from this basin area down the west coast of Palau. So if there were
                    blasting and industrial activities there the result would be to put sediment all
                    over the western side of Palau and destroy something of great beauty and
                    scientific importance.</p>
                <p>We had a duty under the trusteeship agreement of the United Nations to administer
                    these places with care, to prepare them for independence and to do nothing that
                    would harm the welfare of the inhabitants during that period. I was director of
                    the office that had the job of going to the United Nations and defending our
                    administration. So I took some steps to ask some people who were concerned about
                    environmental consequences to help us look at this project and in the process to
                    slow the project down and ultimately to kill the project.</p>
                <p>When the project was being slowed down I was called on the carpet by my boss,
                    Hayden Williams, for having created a problem with Fred Zeder, who was very
                    concerned that we had stuck out nose into the administration of the territory
                    and had caused this problem. Shortly thereafter Hayden decided that, as he put
                    it, he didn't feel as though we were pitcher and first baseman on the same team
                    and that was the way it had to operate. So he invited me to look around and see
                    what else I might want to do. He did not couch it in terms precisely of that
                    event, but I am sure in my own mind that that was a good part of the reason why
                    I was asked to leave there.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any consequences of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: There is always a consequence when you have to restart something and you
                    leave under a cloud of some sort. I was sad to leave. It was a good job, a
                    responsible one, and once we got the Marianas done we would have gone back to do
                    Micronesia and since I had negotiated treaties of territorial succession, I
                    would have been good at that. As it turned out the job that I went to popped
                    open just at that moment involving the new grievance legislation for the Foreign
                    Service and caused the Director General, Carol Laise, to be looking for a
                    Foreign Service officer who could feel the effects of this legislation, but who
                    also was a lawyer and could bring the legislation to life.</p>
                <p>So, the next day after I was asked to look around for another job, I found one
                    and immediately went to that job in the Director General's office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you tell us what it was like working for Carol
                        Laise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I liked her. She was a bright, sincere, pioneering woman, no nonsense,
                    tough. She had just gotten married to Ellsworth Bunker at that time. She was
                    about the senior-most woman Foreign Service officer in the United States. She
                    was perfectly happy to have this grievance system be produced out of my office,
                    which was the Grievance Office, working with one of her deputies. Therefore she
                    was very gentle in any guidance she provided me. She was also very interested in
                    social justice, justice in the work place, which is what grievances were really
                    supposed to be about.</p>
                <p>As we went through that process, it was an interagency process because AID and
                    USIA had to be involved in that...then we had to negotiate with AFSA, write all
                    the regulations and teach our managers about the regulations so that they
                    wouldn't screw up. In those days we had some money, so I set up seminars around
                    the world and had our embassies send their personnel managers or DCMs to them.
                    We taught a day's school on how to stay out of trouble in their grievance
                    procedures, how to save the government money by not letting these damn things
                    get so big as to go through the grievance process. Each completed grievance I
                    figured cost us about $25,000 to process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were you dealing with in AFSA in those days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I am not sure I remember in those days, it might have been you.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I was on the Board but didn't deal with grievances. I
                        think it may have been primarily staffers. We had a lawyer who was doing
                        most of that. Was that your beginning exposure to AFSA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No, I was exposed to AFSA before that from the time I returned from
                    Morocco in 1968 and had all kinds of horrible things happen administratively
                    after my return. So I became very interested in what was then called the bread
                    and butter issues of AFSA. Reminding our managers in the State Department that
                    they didn't need to resolve every single issue against the employee but
                    sometimes they could look at the issue and make a judgment.</p>
                <p>At that time Ed Peck was very active on the same little committee so he and I
                    worked on some projects of the kind that produced ultimately the transfer
                    allowance, which until that time was just a clothing allowance if you went
                    through two or more clothing zones. The State Department had authority to
                    actually pay some of the costs of the transfer...new carpets, rugs, etc....but
                    hadn't asked Congress for the money. So we jumped up and down on that one and
                    ultimately they asked for the money and we have had a limited transfer allowance
                    since.</p>
                <p>We worked on things like ways that we could actually help people move
                    intelligently and save the government money. Giving them incentive not to use
                    their very last pound of their weight limit. You could do that by sharing with
                    them some of the benefits of saving the government money. It would have required
                    legislation. The idea, of course, was immediately killed by our managers who saw
                    anything that required legislation as something that was not desirable to do.
                    They wanted to administer the regulations as they then had them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you see as AFSA's main worthwhile reason
                        d'etre?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, there are basically two. One is to be the conscience of management
                    in dealing with employees. That is more than being a Jimmy cricket. Sometimes it
                    has to sting in order to make sure that is the case. I think that AFSA was at
                    its best when it sued the Secretary of State over one of his procedures
                    involving nominations of political ambassadors. The State Department, in a most
                    conniving, almost criminal way, connived to keep from the public view the
                    description of how bad a lot of these appointees were, in violation of the law.
                    The law requires the State Department to issue a certificate of demonstrated
                    competence for every ambassadorial appointee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was required by the Senate, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, it became law. It is in the Foreign Service Act. It is much
                    ignored, by the way. Pell required it to be written into the law, but then quit
                    taking it seriously. Therefore, the certificate was produced in name only. It
                    was not a certificate of competency at all. It was a brief, usually one page,
                    description of what the person had done. A typical example was of the
                    model...Mr. so-and-so has been a pillar of his community, a successful
                    businessman in running his used car dealership and therefore would make an
                    excellent ambassador of the United States to Spain. It was so bad that these
                    things were not even carefully done. They had typos in them. In one case the
                    last line naming the country was the wrong country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the worse thing was that nobody noticed it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Nobody noticed it because they classified it. There is a little
                    operation in the State Department that produced these things. They were not
                    really State Department people, they were White House people sent over to write
                    these things. There were two of them. They then sent them as confidential
                    documents to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
                <p>That is why we sued him. We said that you can not classify somebody's resume.
                    Under the National Security Act involving classification this is a violation of
                    the act. We, of course, argued that point until we were blue in the face for
                    months and months with the State Department in negotiations. They refused to
                    move on it, so AFSA sued the Secretary of State in the Federal District
                    Court.</p>
                <p>Before the matter came to hearing, the State Department compromised and provided
                    AFSA all of the documents which it had withheld until that point. It undertook
                    to provide us the documents as the law should require and denied having done
                    anything wrong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it from some of your answers so far, that one might
                        conjecture that you believe there is some kind of virus or something in the
                        water that causes State Department managers to behave in ways that are
                        frequently ill-advised, sometimes illegal and sometimes just plain mean. Is
                        that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I am not sure I would limit it to the State Department. I think that all
                    of these bureaucratic organizations, maybe any organization, needs to have
                    constant course corrections in order to stay on track because there aren't any
                    tracks. It is like being afloat in some place. And to maintain an ethical,
                    mission orientation that makes sense for the United States, in this case for the
                    taxpayers, means that there always has to be something coming out of the
                    environment saying you are too far to the right or left or going to slow or to
                    fast.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>The problem with the State Department, I think, is the problem of any disciplined
                    organization. I saw this happen in the Air Force too when I was working closely
                    with them. It is disciplined therefore the top people can say, “Let's do this,”
                    and there is a tendency for the other people to say, “Sir” right away, “How
                    quick, how fast and how far.” There is no incentive for them to second guess the
                    instruction or make a problem out of themselves. Therefore, unless something
                    from outside does that, it is possible that an entire apparatus will go off into
                    left field. It is one of the values that I think AFSA has, which is to be a
                    bothersome bee to buzz around when the Foreign Service is not doing well.</p>
                <p>There is a second element of it and that is the Foreign Service, a little bit
                    like the Navy, which has ships at sea in which the captain is almost absolutely
                    powerful. Lord Acton had it right about absolute power. There is an ego matter
                    that somehow insinuates itself into ambassadors. As our people get closer to
                    being ambassadors they tend to see that as all right, well and good. Anybody who
                    has been promoted sees that his or her own promotion is certainly just, if not
                    over due, and therefore are entitled to wear the mantle of infallibility just as
                    they have learned the old timers did.</p>
                <p>This would not happen were it not for the fact that ambassadors really are almost
                    kings overseas. They are invisible for what they do internally in the embassy
                    and so, unless a person comes with a very strong internal compass, it is easy to
                    go wrong as ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have you had any personal experiences where that was the
                        case?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, sure. On both sides and that is why I tend to see it maybe in such
                    black and white. It doesn't have anything to do with political versus career. It
                    has to do with the inner character of the person taking the job. I think career
                    people are as much given to the egomaniacal quality of being ambassador as some
                    of the worst of the political appointees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What needs to be done about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Oh, I would like to see installed, as a professional matter, not as a
                    legal matter, but just in terms of the profession of the Foreign Service, a
                    mechanism to constantly remind our people of the need to do a veracity check
                    from time to time, or a reality check from time to time. Maybe it is as simple
                    as having one or two folks in the embassy whose careers are not totally at the
                    mercy of the ambassador to be somebody like a Jimmy cricket.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in the embassy very few people's careers are at the
                        mercy of the ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: But those who are not come from other agencies. They are not the ones
                    who pick up most of the nonsense that I am talking about. I am talking about the
                    silliness of using the resources of the United States for personal
                    aggrandizement of some sort. Whether it is just fancying oneself greater than
                    all else and absorbing full visibility of the embassy into an ambassador when
                    the work is really being done by others. Or whether it is this job is not good
                    enough for me, I am really capable of much greater things and so I will spend my
                    time out of the country or performing a hobby, or something of that sort.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's turn this argument on its head a little bit.
                        Is the ambassador ultimately to blame for this or is the generalized lack of
                        spine in the more junior staff ultimately responsible? If you look at the
                        Foreign Service over a period of time, people that you and I both know, who
                        have chosen to rock the boat, provided they were right and did it in a way
                        which was somehow in the general parameters, frequently found that although
                        their careers may suffer a momentary setback, that some how or another there
                        is somebody around who valued that and will not only hire you but perhaps
                        will allow you to do it. So I wonder if the perception that you intimated,
                        that being willing to be the burr under the saddle, being willing to stand
                        up at a meeting and say, “Sorry, that is not right,” is on the average not
                        all that destructive to the ambition of the people as they may think it
                        is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, you have several issues there. One is the ladder. Do you still
                    have a career if you do make waves. Second is that somehow it is the fault of
                    the spineless juniors that seniors behave the way they do. And the third is what
                    causes the pathology that I was talking about.</p>
                <p>On the first one, I think it is possible for people to stand up and to survive
                    and in fact even have their career prosper. It does, however, have to be
                    accompanied by all those things you mentioned, including the skill by which it
                    is done, because our age dislikes raucous, thorny, scratchy people. So somebody
                    who does that with any frequency is easily going to be identified as a trouble
                    maker and somebody who you don't want to have on your staff or serve with.</p>
                <p>We do have some institutional protection for whistle blowers and dissenters.
                    There is the dissent channel. But I think for most purposes these institutional
                    facilities have absorbed some of the burden of that. So it is not possible in
                    our system to speak up. But you wouldn't speak up about the ambassador's habit
                    of telling his counselors that they need to open their houses to his friends and
                    relatives who were coming to post for his daughter's wedding. That is not the
                    sort of thing that you can speak up about, and yet, it is eroding the morale and
                    undercuts...[end of tape]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were talking about speaking up. I would say that you
                        can never expect to reform all ambassadors to quit asking ridiculous things
                        of the staff. But can't you educate the staff to say no or simply not do
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I don't think you can do that as long as the incentives in the
                    marketplace out there are so inclined against that. We know that selection of
                    adverbs in the annual efficiency report is enough to sidetrack a career or delay
                    or deny a promotion. The ambassador is going to write a reviewing statement and
                    its got to be almost frantic in its enthusiasm for the officer for a promotion
                    to take place. Now any officer has got to be just a little bit dumb or reckless
                    with his career to take on his ambassador on a matter which is not of major
                    consequence. So I think that is one reason why all these minor things go until
                    they add up to being quite a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you find you have the Ed Pecks, you have some other
                        people we could name, who took on ambassadors and others on precisely these
                        kind of issues and yet not only survived but prospered. You talked about the
                        ambassador being the person who holds that cudgel. Actually the ambassador
                        writes very few fitness reports. The DCM writes many, many more than the
                        ambassador, certainly, and reviews them. It is the immediate supervisor in
                        the final analysis who is crucial much more than the ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. But I think the process is exactly the same. It is just as likely
                    that the immediate supervisor or the DCM is going to withhold that frantic
                    adverb because junior officer Smith stood up once and took a strip out of the
                    ambassador. He is going to be marked down for judgment, comportment, maybe
                    dedication to duty, maybe his willingness to sacrifice personally for the good
                    of the mission. Any of that stuff can happen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then as you describe it the organization has a terminal
                        illness.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I think it is maybe not terminal, I think it is like a virus that sits
                    there and gives us the sniffles and a cold and keeps the organization from
                    performing as well as it ought.</p>
                <p>I happen to think that our embassies are important, that US representation is
                    important and it ought to work just as well as it possibly can. I think it is
                    not now working that well and partly because we, ourselves, tolerate this. In
                    fact, AFSA, itself, for very good-intended reasons, has been a major part of why
                    it is now so difficult for the institution itself to separate the good people
                    from the bad people because the evaluation reports have to be now produced in
                    peculiar ways which cause you almost to have to be a code clerk in order to
                    decode what is really being said.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the question of trying to get people to express
                        themselves, one of my great frustrations throughout the period when I had
                        supervisory responsibilities, including as ambassador, was calling everybody
                        in and saying, “Look, here is the problem. I have had certain thoughts about
                        it, but I don't pretend to have all the answers and I am really groping for
                        something which somehow is the best of the solutions. I want you people, not
                        only on this issue, but in general, to always give me your frank, honest
                        opinion. The most unpardonable sin is to allow supervisors to walk right off
                        a cliff that you knew was there and because you were afraid to speak up he
                        didn't know and walked right off of it. So please be frank.” My greatest
                        frustration perhaps was that it was a rare occasion when anybody would
                        respond to that kind of stimulation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I think you and I are looking at this from exactly opposite sides of the
                    chasm. In one case did I have an ambassador who made that point clear in any
                    embassy in which I served. And all other cases, which was six or seven
                    ambassadors, quite the opposite was indicated by body language and word.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it really that damaging for someone to speak up and
                        take the contrary view, if you will, except in cases where the person is
                        relying on a shoe shine and a smile to advance his career? What I am really
                        suggesting is this reluctance to speak up, I think, is probably the
                        strongest among political officers where one person's political judgment may
                        be a good as another. At least you can't prove him wrong. Whereas if you
                        have some other skill...very good B&amp;F officer, or very good
                        economist...you have a little firmer ground under your professional
                        feet.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That may well be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other points to make on that general subject or shall
                        we move on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Let's move on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right. You were now on the grievance staff and the
                        years are 1976-78. Any memorable events?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. I dreaded the assignment but I took it in part because I did need
                    something to do and I was grateful to be asked to do something I began to be
                    persuaded was important.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>It was a dusty place. It had really not done very much. And the people in it
                    showed that. There were almost cobwebs on them. I came in as the chief of that
                    staff and never really had done any personnel work before. So a lot of the
                    effort was to get people to apply some energy, to raise the octane of their
                    application to process these things. At the same time to then to devise ways to
                    complete the new regulations and then to get them promulgated in a way that
                    would have them taken seriously. I had the usual difficulties in any kind of
                    interagency negotiation in getting agreement on what these regulations should
                    say. The problem then was to communicate this to our people in the field. And as
                    I mentioned, I got some good cooperation from our B&amp;F people in those days
                    who made it possible for us to have these kind of high profile symposiums around
                    the world to introduce this whole thing to our embassies. I think it is
                    unrecognized in the Foreign Service that as a result of the process that gave us
                    the new Foreign Service grievance system the Foreign Service has probably the
                    most expensive grievance process in the United States government. It involves
                    processing at so many different levels and has such procedural protections to
                    the person finally getting through it and bringing his grievance before the
                    Grievance Board, which in itself is a very expensive process.</p>
                <p>So a lot of what I was doing was trying to keep as many of these from going
                    through all that as possible. As you know I am a lawyer by training and in the
                    function of being Chief of the Grievance Staff, I really was acting as a judge
                    of the grievances as they were presented, which is not easy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Judge and jury.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, yes, judge and jury. Except the real court is a level above us. A
                    grievant could always take a declined grievance to the Grievance Board. At that
                    point I became advocate for the State Department management.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Prosecuting attorney.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, a defense attorney because they were the plaintiffs. I will
                    confess that I often enjoyed that process of being able to finally after maybe
                    having worked with a grievance for a couple of years and maintained a judicial
                    attitude towards it, to finally be able to cut, slash in a court of real law
                    about the issues that were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think in most of the cases which you were in
                        contact with in the end some kind of justice prevailed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, by putting weight on the words “some kind” that was true.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I don't mean Judge Lynch's kind of justice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I will give you an example of an unusual event. We got a complaint
                    from a retired officer that the State Department, particularly Security forces
                    in the State Department, continued to hound him after he had retired, because he
                    had been thought to be homosexual when he was on active duty and he was in
                    effect forced out of the Service because he was a homosexual. He had no
                    pension.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So he was not retired in the usual sense?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No, he was fired. He then went to law school for three years to become a
                    lawyer and was then unable to find good employment. The circumstances of his
                    being disappointed at these interviews were such that he became persuaded that
                    it was because the State Department was poisoning his well in each case. He
                    wrote a letter to the Secretary of State and it really called for an
                    investigation of our Diplomatic Security people. They would normally conduct
                    such an investigation, but in this case the Director General asked me to conduct
                    the investigation. So I did that under cover of a writ really from Larry
                    Eagleburger who at that time was Special Assistant for Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Under Secretary for Management.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: He was, that's right. With that writ I went down and held little
                    informal hearings and interviewed the security office and found out, as far as I
                    could tell, that his complaint was not well founded. It was caused really by
                    finding reasons to blame somebody besides himself for the failure to get the job
                    outside.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>But in the course of the investigation I found that the witness that the DS
                    relied upon primarily was his secretary when he was on duty in a country in
                    Latin America. She seemed to be quite central to this. She made the principal
                    accusations using such observations as he wore a swimming cap when he swam in
                    his swimming pool. We found his own complaint not well based and nothing we
                    could do about it, but out of something, excess curiosity maybe, I asked for her
                    records...the records of this witness...to be brought back from St. Louis where
                    they had been sent and promptly buried. I looked in there and found one of the
                    most horrifying stories that is an indictment of our system.That story was that
                    this was the second time she had made heinous allegations about one of our
                    officers. The first time was when she was on duty in a border post in Mexico and
                    there had been allegations made about the person she worked for of actually
                    trafficking in American bodies... selling the rights to families to get them
                    back from Mexico for proper burial. The State Department sent down a special
                    investigator and the investigator's report was in her file. He said, “I have
                    spent six weeks in this town. I have tracked down every source of these
                    allegations and they all come from her. There is absolutely no truth in them.
                    She did this as a malicious effort to ruin the career of the consul at this
                    post. She should be immediately separated from the Foreign Service.”</p>
                <p>That recommendation went totally unheeded and she lay like a time bomb in the
                    system for about 15 years until this other hapless guy came along with his
                    bathing cap. She got him accused and worked over by DS in such a fashion that he
                    never recovered from the investigation, even though DS cleared him of
                    homosexuality. The experience had been so scarifying to this guy that he could
                    never then perform in a way that allowed him to be written up decently.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the years this was going on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I conducted the investigation in the late '70s and I think he had been
                    separated from the Service in the early '70s. The border incident was probably
                    in the '50s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This raises an issue which I had no where written on my
                        pad here about the State Department's attitude toward sexual preference. I
                        suppose if you ever ran head on in some way or another with the security
                        people, this became an issue, but in my experience over a long period of
                        time, the prevailing policy in the State Department was pretty much like the
                        new “don't ask, don't tell.” That is, even though everybody might know or
                        think they did that some member of the embassy was not heterosexual, absent
                        something that was absolutely flagrant and outrageous, nobody said or did
                        anything. What was your experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Mine was the same as yours. I never noticed anything about it except
                    when you had to go through the interviews to get a security clearance and they
                    asked if you were a homosexual. You had to say no in order to get the clearance.
                    But when I was looking into this case and interviewed some of the DS people and,
                    macabre almost, one of these guys was remembering in a nostalgic way the good
                    old days. “In the good old days,” he said, “we found five thousand homosexuals
                    in the Foreign Service and got rid of them.” Now five thousand is too big a
                    number I think, which is part of the bizarre quality of this discussion anyway.
                    But the fact is that he described to me the standard operating procedure for
                    when somebody was accused of being a homosexual. It was a third degree
                    operation. They didn't beat them with truncheons, but they sure as hell put them
                    in a windowless cell, used all the FBI techniques of indicating the person is
                    going to be drummed out of the Service unless he confesses. So, if you take
                    somebody who is not absolutely solidly self-confident to begin with, that
                    process by your thought employer for life, could have really deleterious effects
                    on people's behavior and functioning. That I think I saw happen more than just
                    this one time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would it help in this whole process about how you get it
                        wrong doing it, how you instill a greater integrity into the people in our
                        personnel system, if there were an established channel to bring to light
                        certain things that are going on where confidentiality is respected up to
                        the point where it is reasonable and you have an impartial outside office
                        like the Inspector General looking into things in a way which can generate a
                        certain amount of confidence, both in management and in non-managerial parts
                        of the system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, I think so. You know, in civil law there is a term called malicious
                    abusive process. It is to penalize people who bring frivolous complaints or who
                    use the process in order to just do harm without really moving the inquiry
                    forward. We don't have that kind of thing, so far as I know, in the executive
                    branch. It is important to protect whistle blowers and keep them from
                    retaliation, but right now there isn't any real disincentive for somebody to let
                    his or her imagination run pretty freely in deciding what somebody else has done
                    and to write a complaint about it. Potentially that complaint can derail
                    somebody's career or cause them great embarrassment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I will interject a personal experience here. Once upon a
                        time someone I was supervising shortly after having gotten promoted to the
                        old FSO-2, claimed that I had influenced members of the FSR promotion system
                        against promoting him from FSR-2 to FSR-1 because I had known these people
                        and told them under no circumstances should he be promoted. This person
                        filed a grievance against me. People went out and interviewed a dozen people
                        around town who were on promotion panels or in my car pool, etc. People
                        started coming to me asking what terrible thing had I just done? In the end,
                        of course, there was nothing to the complaint, but the people who got
                        interviewed never knew. That doesn't seem fair does it. But then the world
                        is not fair.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>Okay. You went to the Senior Seminar after the Grievance Staff.</p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, it's, as anybody who has been through it knows, one of the better
                    experiences in the Foreign Service because it is a paid year organized as a
                    sabbatical in which you are invited to dine at a heavily laden table of
                    delicious intellectual issues about our country. It was done in the most
                    beneficial way, I thought, of providing us huge amounts of challenge for
                    discussions with excellent folks, both in our own class and those brought in to
                    help us; travel and then a six or seven week period for the writing of a paper
                    on something in depth. I personally felt it was one of the best adult
                    educational experiences that I ever have had. I think it is a magnificent luxury
                    to have to train our people who we believe are going to be holding important
                    positions in our Service. I am not sure how long it is for the world, in part
                    because we have a certain amount of trouble in predicting who are the really
                    good ones, and part because we haven't been able to persuade all of our people
                    that it's that valuable, they really ought to have it, unlike the military
                    services. I thought it was just splendid.</p>
                <p>I did my own research on energy. This was during the early Carter period and the
                    energy issue was a major one I thought. I thought it was important that we take
                    a look and see what this country could do to lessen it's reliance on hydrocarbon
                    based energy and see if we couldn't improve our performance by at least taking a
                    look at how the Swedes are able to turn out a per capital gross national product
                    approximate to our own at a consumption of half the amount of energy that we
                    use. And so, I did my research in Swedish energy conservation. I learned an
                    awful lot and wrote a paper which I don't think was very good, but certainly my
                    own understanding of the issue was vastly improved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back tracking again. You mentioned Larry Eagleburger. Did
                        you have a fair amount of contact with Larry over time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No so much. He was, of course, Carol Laise's boss and would hear about
                    him. Several times I would go up in his office with some other people when we
                    were dealing with these issues. But not intensively, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I ask because Larry is frequently cited as perhaps one of
                        the greatest stars the career Foreign Service ever produced and other people
                        have a very different attitude. I was just wondering if you had formed any
                        particular judgment that you would care to share?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I admire him more than I attack him. I admire his appetite for
                    work, his absolute dedication to doing it and willingness to ruin his health and
                    probably his family life to carry it out. Also, he's got a good breath and set
                    of judgments about him on the issues that he has come to know well. Like the
                    Yugoslavian issues, for example, where he was absolutely right at the closing
                    days of the Bush Administration. He was refreshing, I think, in that he was so
                    brash and frank, unlike the classic model of Foreign Service officer, that I
                    felt better having him around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he brash and frank before he became a Kissinger
                        prot�g�?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I didn't know him before he was a Kissinger prot�g�, so I can't say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything further on the Senior Seminar?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No. I had a great time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we move into the next topic on our list here, the
                        Panama Treaty, since we don't have a lot of time left this afternoon, I
                        suggest we call it quits now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Okay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We will pick it up again at another time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Today is August 6, 1993 and this is a continuing interview with Charles A.
                    Schmitz. Chuck, now it is 1979 and you are in Panama in the Panama Treaty
                    Implementation slot there. Tell us what was important about that.</p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The State Department worked hard to negotiate the treaty and worked, I
                    think, even harder to get the Senate to give its consent to the treaty coming
                    into force. It spent so much time worrying how to do that and mounting a big
                    public relations campaign that it had not given a whole lot of thought to what
                    we were going to do if the treaty was actually approved.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>The day after it was approved I got a call from the Latin American Bureau asking
                    if there was any pertinence of the Okinawa Reversion arrangements to Panama and,
                    if so, whether or not they thought I could make a contribution to that. There
                    was a great deal of pertinence to it because it is not very often that we
                    transfer territory from one country to another and this was what was happening.
                    It involves lost of state's succession and making sure that you have accounted
                    for a whole lot of matters just to make sure everything functions right. Account
                    for the legalities of the old and the new system and protect things like ongoing
                    court cases, claims, and make sure that the fire department and police worked
                    the following day, etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was also similarity that you had major military
                        installations in both cases.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That was an additional kicker for both. I said that I thought I would be
                    useful even though I was at the time in language training to go to Indonesia to
                    be political counselor. But that assignment was broken and I was transferred to
                    Spanish language training so that I could prepare to go to Panama, instead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much Indonesian had you had?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I had had about 40 days worth of working during my lunch hour while at
                    Senior Seminar so it wasn't a huge investment.</p>
                <p>It may have been a mistake doing what I did because had I gone to Indonesia I
                    would have been in the mainstream of the political system in the State
                    Department Foreign Service and since there was no US domestic political issue
                    about Indonesia at that time I would not have run the risk of winding up on the
                    wrong side of a domestic issue. But in the case of the Panama Canal Treaty,
                    which was President Carter's baby and probably his only real success in foreign
                    policy...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He would argue that Camp David counted too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: He would, but I am not moved by that argument. I guess it never occurred
                    to me that anybody who was seen to be associated with the Panama Canal work
                    would fall out of popularity in the State Department, but that is exactly what
                    happened when Carter was defeated for reelection and Reagan was elected. While
                    Reagan had not in the presidential campaign made an issue about the Panama Canal
                    Treaty negotiations, as he had four years previously, still when he came in and
                    appointed his people to run the State Department, including Assistant
                    Secretaries for this and that, it was natural that they saw it was important to
                    pick people who had not shown a lot of sentiment for the previous
                    administration. I think that was in part why I had difficulty in assignment
                    after the Panama Canal Treaty work was over.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>In any case, at the time I was happy to go. I thought that my highest and best
                    use as a sort of combination lawyer and Foreign Service officer lay in doing
                    precisely this kind of thing. I knew that just because we had signed the treaty
                    there was no guarantee that everything would work smoothly in bringing the Canal
                    Zone to an end and incorporating the US continued presence in Panama into the
                    Panamanian system. And that is really the capsule of what was involved.</p>
                <p>The problems were several fold. One was that there were involved three major
                    elements of the US government... the Embassy, the Panama Canal Company, and the
                    US military...and for the most part they did not see eye to eye on most
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you elaborate on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Sure. The first thing they didn't see eye to eye on was that the others
                    should have much to say about what should be the future of either the Canal
                    operation or the military operation. The Embassy was seen as interloper. It was
                    really the exponent of the Carter Administration as far as the people who lived
                    in the Zone were concerned...the Zonians. The Zonians despised the idea of the
                    Panama Canal Treaties because of the development of the Canal Zone...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are you talking about the employees of the Canal Company
                        or the US military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Zonians primarily means those who spent a long time in the Canal Zone.
                    So it is the employees and their dependents and contractors of the Canal
                    Company. The military tended to rotate through there every couple of years so
                    they weren't really Zonians, although many of them felt that it was a matter of
                    national pride that we have the flag there and that we run the place. The
                    Panamanians, of course, would not be capable of doing it, etc.</p>
                <p>So you had basic attitudinal differences and the Embassy had a major problem in
                    establishing itself as the exponent of carrying out the obligations of the
                    United States and requiring the Panamanians to carry out their obligations.
                    Ambler Moss, who had been an assistant to the negotiations and a former Foreign
                    Service officer himself, was designated the US Ambassador to Panama. He and I
                    were classmates in school and so we got along just fine. So that much was fine.
                    He was an able ambassador, articulate in Spanish, affable and tried very hard
                    not to make the usual ego related mistakes of ambassadors. But he did need to
                    operate in this quite hostile environment in which to both the military and to
                    the Canal Company, we who were associated with the Embassy were seen as being
                    the buddies and defenders of the Panamanians. So his arguments invariably broke
                    down with us on one side and the other two on the other.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a different situation than you encountered in the
                        Okinawa treaty?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. Considerably different. Part of it is in Okinawa we didn't have
                    huge numbers of Americans residing there as though it was home. We had a small
                    number who had gone out accompanying the military in one form or another and had
                    stayed behind to open a hamburger stand or something. But in the case of the
                    Canal Zone, people began living there in 1910 and so we had cases where there
                    were three generations of Zonians. They had no homeland other than the Canal
                    Zone, so there was a much more inflamed sense of territoriality.</p>
                <p>The second thing was that the military in Okinawa had a sense of itself as being
                    part of a giant American defense parameter of great consequence in the world and
                    therefore could be generous on small things. The whole purpose of the US
                    military in the Canal Zone was to defend the canal in ways which were obvious to
                    anybody totally apposite to the modern methods of conducting warfare. It was
                    really an army to confront guerrillas who might want to throw a grenade or
                    something into a lock. You don't defend a canal by having artillery batteries at
                    either end of it, which is how the US military inherited this position.</p>
                <p>It was a little bit different for the Air Force, but even there there was no
                    sense of it being a serious and global issue. It was really much more of a local
                    one.</p>
                <p>And the Navy, which should have been the most interested of all in the Canal, of
                    course, had only a tiny little set of operations there devoted to protecting the
                    mouth of the Canal from attack by small boats and nonsense like that. Their
                    sense of unreality and being a backwater all intensifies small issues.</p>
                <p>Appeasing the Americans residing in the Canal Zone was a major part of what we
                    had to do.</p>
                <p>Second was to insure that the legitimate concerns of the US were served under the
                    new administration. A third was to insure that the Panamanians would do as they
                    were required by the treaty or we felt by the treaty they were required to do.
                    And it won't surprise anybody to know that there is considerable differences of
                    view as to who had what obligation and how it should be worked out.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Over the period of time, the two and a half years I was there, the Zonians came
                    slowly to accept their fate and, in fact, the officials of the Canal Company,
                    soon to be known as the Canal Commission, threw themselves into their new kind
                    of work with a good deal of professionalism and even involvement. They took
                    pride in some cases of actually working themselves out of a job. They wanted to
                    do it right. In some cases this was not short of nobility, I thought, on their
                    part. They had fought against the treaty, against the Carter administration,
                    against the State Department. Then they saw that the treaty had become the law
                    of the land and that to carry out their jobs as they considered themselves
                    employees of the United States government, they needed to turn about and do
                    something quite different. I was astonished at how almost universal the
                    acceptance was of this new function. In the end the Canal Company did an
                    extraordinarily good job of preparing for the treaty to come into force,
                    preparing to train the Panamanians, preparing to hand over equipment, showing
                    how the maintenance worked, doing the training, etc.</p>
                <p>Oddly enough some elements of the military, these transient members of the Zone,
                    caused some of the greatest problems. It is just astonishing how people can
                    focus on tiny problems of their own and make them big problems for a government
                    or maybe a couple of governments. My favorite example of that was the person we
                    called the kitty litter lady. She was a person who was used to shopping in the
                    special stores operated by the Canal Company and they had a brand of kitty
                    litter that her cats had gotten used to. Under the agreement there would be no
                    more stores run by the Canal Company, but Americans would be allowed to use the
                    military commissaries and PXs so that their standard of living would not be
                    affected. So the military would in effect take over the old Canal stores and
                    administer them the way they do their own PXs and commissaries. Well, it turned
                    out that the Army PX system had a different brand of kitty litter than the one
                    that was used by the Canal Company.</p>
                <p>So it was only a few weeks after the treaty came into effect that the woman began
                    to object strenuously to this substitution of one brand for another and made it
                    a federal case. She first called and met with the commissary folks and then
                    wrote letters and went on the radio and came to visit all the installations and
                    made a thorough and utter nuisance out of herself going to the extent of saying
                    that if she didn't get action she was going to come in an dump boxes of used
                    kitty litter on peoples desks to show how inconvenient it was.</p>
                <p>The other major part of the problem was to get the Panamanians to take over some
                    of the responsibility of administering this territory but not immediately the
                    responsibility of running the Canal. They had a problem in doing that. The first
                    problem was that they had seen it as a great economic boom to be given 500
                    square miles of territory worth...completed infrastructure, sewers, streets,
                    bridges, telephones, etc. and much more land in places that could be leased for
                    port operations, free zones, etc. So they set about to create a canal authority
                    which had huge notions of what it should become.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was under Omar Torrijos?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, while he was still alive, but he had sunk back into some obscurity
                    in his determination to let the civilian, which he really had installed,
                    actually govern. That government turned out to be not very decisive to the great
                    frustration to nearly all of us that had to have some decisions. There was a
                    tendency, that everybody had, to take things to Torrijos in order to get
                    something done. Several times we did that with important issues. But usually he
                    refused to do it. He said that it was important that the government do these
                    things. In a way he was right. If he had continued to do everything, continued
                    to be the strong man, there never would have been a hope for the government. As
                    it was, the governments, I thought, never did rise to the occasion. They left
                    decisions unmade.After two and a half years of trying to resolve all of the
                    issues coming out of the treaties, when I left there I left with two or three of
                    significant importance still unresolved. Part of that was an unwillingness to
                    grasp a nettle and make a difficult decision. So that was a big difference right
                    there between the Japanese treatment of Okinawa and the Panamanians on the Canal
                    Zone.</p>
                <p>The Canal Authority was set up to be a big deal. It quickly became a political
                    pork barrel with people being hired on there with nothing whatever to do with
                    the function but were there just to be given a job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a Panamanian operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, Panamanian. After a huge mushroom like growth, on one day it all
                    fell apart. It was just abruptly terminated one day. At that time they had
                    something like 360 employees scattered in three or four different buildings
                    around town. I remember hearing that this was happening and I got into my car
                    and went over and just walked around some of these places. I found the most
                    amazing scenes of almost devastation in these offices of furniture upturned,
                    papers all over the floor, most of the equipment gone, and people gone. It was
                    as though a gang of furniture thieves had come through and cleaned these offices
                    out.</p>
                <p>Obviously since the Authority was an important element of the Panamanian effort
                    to deal with us on the Canal's remaining issues, it took them a while to recover
                    from that. In fact, I am not sure that they ever did recover from that. They
                    didn't have the machinery available to them to really do their responsibilities
                    and they failed to set up any machinery to substitute for the Authority. As a
                    result, those of us in the Embassy who were working on these issues had to
                    identify individuals and various Ministries around the government whom we
                    thought might have something to do with the issue and then see in effect if we
                    could open negotiations directly with them. It was a messy operation.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>In any event, we achieved our principal objective which was to remove the Panama
                    Canal as an issue that was an obstacle between bettering our relations with all
                    of Latin America. You have to remember that everybody in Latin America had
                    seized upon that issue, or at least had been unable not to seize upon it, to
                    beat the US over the head for its colonialism in Latin America and as a sign of
                    what our real intentions and nature were.</p>
                <p>We removed it as an issue and with that gone it eased our conversations
                    throughout the hemisphere on the US address to our neighbors. We removed it in
                    such a way that the Canal would continue to operate at least until the year 2000
                    more or less as efficiently as it did before. And that is probably a pretty good
                    deal for the US, although now as the year 2000 is right around the corner, it
                    takes a different shape than the one it had in the 1970s when the treaty was
                    negotiated. In any case, that Canal has operated beyond its anticipated capacity
                    up and 'til now and undoubtedly will until the year 2000.</p>
                <p>My own guess is that it will operate well beyond that. That is to say, after the
                    Panamanians have full legal control over the Canal because it will be
                    extraordinarily important to them to keep it functioning efficiently. It is no
                    longer a monopoly on getting things from one ocean to another and they will have
                    to insure, probably by hiring some of the existing talent, that it continues to
                    function well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Panamanian Treaty a good treaty from the point of
                        view of the United States and in terms of being a well drawn piece of legal
                        material which served the purposes for which it was intended?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. The Treaty, itself, was drafted as an excellent piece of legal
                    workmanship. The difficult parts were the parts that were added on by the
                    Congress after the Treaty was drafted. Things that said, “Not withstanding what
                    the Treaty says, here is what we are going to do.” Those were difficult like the
                    Di Consini resolution that says, “Whatever the Treaty says, we reserve the right
                    to come in and defend that Canal for whatever purpose.” But the Treaty itself
                    was fine. Our job was to do implementing agreements or carry out the meaning of
                    the Treaty itself. The clarity of the original document made that part of our
                    job quite easy.</p>
                <p>We spent a certain amount of the time after a year and a half just designing the
                    ceremony for the coming into affect of the Treaty. How that would be done. How
                    we would symbolize the change of jurisdiction. How we would do honor to it from
                    the US standpoint. And that turned into a huge side show in which the then Vice
                    President Mondale came down to Panama with two 747 loads filled with folks who
                    were out for a joy ride and had virtually nothing to do with the Treaty and who
                    were rather an embarrassment to the United States in my judgment.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>We, nevertheless, had to shoehorn this into the festivities and get them invited
                    to dinners and participation in all the various functions that the Panamanians
                    had wished to be smaller and more intimate. They had invited a maximum of five
                    people from every other country and had intended to invite about 25 from the US
                    and then wound up with about 179.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was my experience in dealing with the Mondale and
                        Carter White House staff and travel staffs that they were the most inept and
                        most difficult White House staffs during my Foreign Service career. Did you
                        have a similar impression?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. Maybe it is because I was more directly the target or object of
                    this particular White House preparation than any other that I knew of. But I
                    felt a lot of the injury that was being done by the advanced team to I thought
                    US interests. It took a good six or seven weeks after the event was over of not
                    only me but a number of us going around town just trying to smooth the feathers
                    that had been ruffled in the process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were arrogant and inept as I recall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Arrogant, yes. Inept, I felt they were all together too competent in
                    their arrogance that I saw. They were effective bullies and that was exactly the
                    wrong image of the US to be showing at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned a while ago the lack of cooperation, the
                        resistance, of the US military in the Zone. Who was the SOCOM Commander at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I can't remember the name. There were several, at least two during that
                    period. I can't remember their names.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you attribute this reluctance of the military
                        essentially to the SOCOM Commander or was it something that came from the
                        bottom up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I think it was from the bottom up. It was a conservative mood, really.
                    It was: We don't like change. We don't like Carter. We don't like giving away US
                    stuff. We don't like anything which might impede our security concerns and of
                    course anything which allows somebody to do something where we previously were
                    the only ones to do it would so impede they thought.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would this have been changed if there had been a strong
                        and effective SOCOM Commander?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I don't know the answer to that because I think if a Commander tried to
                    get too far out in front of his people he might have become in effect a tool in
                    the process. My own view at the time was disappointment that neither the SOCOM
                    heads, not just the Commander, but the others, nor the Canal Company leadership
                    were more disciplined in accepting that even though they may not like it the
                    policy of the US had been made and they should really salute smartly and get to
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe the SOCOM Commander after 1980 was Wally
                        somebody. A great big guy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Wally Nutting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He looked like a soldier and he didn't have a whole lot
                        between his ears.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: He arrived from NATO to take up that command. He was brand new to the
                    hemisphere, to say nothing of Panama. I liked him because he was affable. He was
                    friendly. His predecessor had not been affable and friendly and I thought,
                    therefore, we might have better communications with him. He may not have been up
                    to that kind of difficult job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did General Torrijos die?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I am not sure about the exact date. It was after I had left Panama.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After you left Panama.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, in the early '80s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a lot of speculation about the circumstances of
                        his death. Do you have any theories on it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I buy the theory that we have put about which is that it was a
                    helicopter accident in nasty weather. There is a lot of nasty weather in Panama
                    and helicopters are flying low in mountains and storms are given to that sort of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you are not part of the conspiracy theory?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No, not in that particular case. I don't even think Noriega would have
                    done that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Panama at the time of the change of
                        administration in January, 1981. You mentioned hostility. When did you start
                        to note this hostility from the incoming administration directed at
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: When I left Panama in the summer of 1981 without an onward assignment.
                    When I checked to see what was available, I really found a lot of folks just not
                    so interested in finding an assignment for somebody who had been working on the
                    Panama Treaty. I realized that because when they had to go up to their new
                    political bosses and explain who this person was, it might have put them in a
                    difficult spot with their superiors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What grade did you have at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I was at that time an O-2.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of job did you try to get?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Oh, DCM some place. I had spent three years working with about 25
                    different people in our Embassy to have a coherent Embassy unit for Canal Treaty
                    implementation and had done apparently acceptable jobs with the usual sort of
                    commendations and things of that sort. But everybody I had worked for and done a
                    good job for, of course, was out. They just weren't around. So I felt that first
                    when I left Panama in 1981 and felt it again when I left my subsequent
                    assignment in 1985 and again was looking for a job and discovered that the
                    people I had done a good job for were no longer in the system. The new folks
                    tended to be pretty unsympathetic with anybody who had done a good job on
                    Panama.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you name some names of who you considered the new
                        folks to be in that context?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I eventually wound up back in the East Asian Bureau and the then
                    Assistant Secretary was Gaston Sigur who had arrived there having worked in the
                    Reagan White House in the National Security Council. Sigur was willing to have
                    me come aboard his Bureau because I had a lot of contemporaries and peers who
                    had explained me to him, but I felt that he was giving us all a political
                    evaluation whenever we recommended things or called things to his attention. His
                    recommendations had quite a severely conservative bent to them, I thought. So I
                    found myself not being able to do as much in that particular job as I had hoped
                    I would be able to.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you describe yourself politically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I have never been a partisan person and so neither Democrat nor
                    Republican. I felt innately to have roughly even sympathy for them, especially
                    as they came into office to redress what I thought had been some of the excesses
                    of the previous administration. Philosophically I think of myself as a centrist.
                    I don't think I am a liberal in domestic politics, but probably some think I am
                    a liberal in international politics just because I believe it is important to
                    keep talking and to avoid shooting as long as you possibly can.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you can't be labeled then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I would not label myself, anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Eventually you went from Panama to be Political Advisor in
                        the Air Force in Europe, in Ramstein. Anything noteworthy during that period
                        of your service that you want to get on the record?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, two or three different things. The first one is administrative.
                    That is that these jobs of having our diplomats be invited into the high
                    councils of our powerful military establishments overseas are very important
                    functions. This is the place where if the State Department wishes to be
                    effective in having the military understand what the political environment is,
                    or even the economic environment is, these jobs are key. But we, State
                    Department Foreign Service, have traditionally ignored that potential at least
                    since the Second World War we have, or at least since Eisenhower was at NATO,
                    and have not felt it a good thing to do and certainly not career enhancing.</p>
                <p>I found it to be the opposite in all effects, except career enhancing. I found
                    being considered a grown up, to have one's views of the world taken seriously by
                    people with great power and authority without having to go through 35 different
                    clearances or write memoranda on the like, seemed right for a senior officer of
                    the United States State Department. Quite unlike, I think, working in a large
                    embassy or the State Department itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>I got, and I think none of us acting as POLADS did get, any instructions from the
                    State Department. I don't mean just on specific issues, but on general approach.
                    We were given no idea of what we ought to be trying to do at these military
                    organizations. Now the case that I became associated with, the Air Force, it was
                    scattered all over Europe. It was concerned, of course, with not only Western
                    Europe, but Eastern Europe, and its jurisdiction extended to the Middle East and
                    to the northern tier of Africa. So it was a huge extent. I have forgotten how
                    many facilities, but it was 80 or 90 facilities in those areas.</p>
                <p>Everyday they flew 500 sorties out of this thing and every one of them has the
                    capability of causing trouble somewhere for the United States or for somebody
                    else. And operating listening posts and huge logistic systems being the tip of
                    the lance to defend Europe against Eastern aggression. Very powerful things.
                    Much more stuff going on than was going on in a typical Foreign Service
                    establishment. I think it was a mistake for us to have paid so little attention.
                    I think a lot of things could have worked more smoothly during the Cold War
                    period had we given more authority and attention to these positions than we
                    did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have as your model Robert Murphy when he was
                        Eisenhower's POLAD?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That's right. Murphy made it possible for Operation Torch to succeed at
                    relatively low loss of life because Eisenhower was smart enough to see how a
                    political skill could be useful to the military. And then, of course, Eisenhower
                    created these POLAD positions when he was NATO Commander. Then they fell into
                    bad repute in part because the Foreign Service then started to use them as
                    dumping grounds for guys who just wanted to golf their way quietly into
                    retirement and had no particular interest in doing much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A place to put failed DCMs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, or even failed political counselors.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>In 1981 I saw this in a different light for myself, although I began not wanting
                    to touch it either for all the reasons we know about. Not career enhancing and
                    good Lord I knew some people who did that and I did not admire them and I didn't
                    see that people were rewarded for having done it. But in 1981 we had a big
                    military buildup. It was clear to me that we were putting our resources into the
                    military. That was where things were going to happen; that the focus of this was
                    in Europe; that a major part of that was building up our tactical forces, our
                    intelligence capacities and to put in a whole bunch of new weapon systems in
                    Europe to compensate for the SS-20s the Soviets were putting out.And for the Air
                    Force this turned out to be primarily an effort to put in the ground launch
                    cruise missile which had to be installed in six different countries in Europe.
                    And in every case the six countries had presented different political problems
                    for the installation of these things along with the use of the land, the
                    constructions, the huge number of people that would be part of all this, the
                    nuclear element of it...by the way the cruise missiles were emphatically and
                    specifically nuclear and everybody knew that and that was the purpose of them.
                    It made a mockery out of our neither confirm nor deny rule because you couldn't
                    talk about them without noting their nuclear capability, but we couldn't admit
                    it. We couldn't say anything about the nuclear business at all but yet in every
                    single country the nuclear element was the most significant part. So there is a
                    little bit of nonsense there.</p>
                <p>In any case, the Air Force had the job of negotiating with six different
                    countries about where these would be put, how it would be done, under what
                    circumstances and the timing and the like. A lot of that was done in ways where
                    a Political Advisor could be extremely helpful to his military colleagues.
                    Sometimes I found myself really pretty much on the front line in helping that
                    kind of thing work.</p>
                <p>The run of the mill business there was to make sure that what the Air Force did
                    made some sense for the host countries. Often there is not a whole lot you could
                    do in the case of an airplane crash or an accident of some sort except to make
                    sure that the reaction to it was sensible and sensitive and had to be sensitive
                    in that context. What you did in Germany was different than what you did in the
                    UK or in Turkey or Greece. So I thought a lot of my function was to help the
                    military commanders in these various bases understand more about the environment
                    that they were operating in.</p>
                <p>Now the Air Force traditionally doesn't like to pay attention to the ground
                    environment. They joke and say that the only connection we are likely to have
                    with the ground is going to be bad news so we try not to do it. But in fact a
                    base or operating commander has a big impact on surrounding communities and
                    sometimes on even the national politics of the place where that base is. So, I
                    spent some of my time trying to figure out how to bring this sensitivity home to
                    these people.</p>
                <p>I began in the usual Foreign Service way of writing good, interesting memoranda
                    directed to my commander, the Commander-in-Chief of the US Air Forces and then,
                    of course, the memoranda would be spread around the system.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall his name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, there were three that I worked for. When I first went there it was
                    Charlie Gabriel, who later became Chief of Staff of the Air Force. A very nice
                    man and very sensitive in himself. The second was General Billy Minter, a
                    logistician who was trying very hard during the time he was Commander-in-Chief
                    to be a good operations man, but it was out of character. And then a third was
                    Chuck Donnelly, who was a tactical Air Force commander all his life and brought
                    to the job a flare and kind of informality that was totally different from
                    either of his predecessors.</p>
                <p>Coming back to the business of writing memoranda, I found that nobody read the
                    memoranda. I knew that because there would be an occasional exception when
                    somebody would call up from some base and say, “Hey, I read that and it was very
                    interesting.” But there was just not enough of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why is it that they don't read memoranda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, to be uncharitable, I think it is because they don't read. I
                    realized that what we have here is a culture gap between the Foreign Service and
                    military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you expand on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. The military does not communicate with itself by writing memoranda.
                    It communicates with itself by giving briefings and talking and by looking at
                    pictures. I realized that by sitting in on meetings myself, senior staff
                    meetings three times a week, at which there would be no written materials at all
                    except for charts and graphs up on the screen. But there would be a lot of young
                    nicely uniformed lieutenants and majors with pointers speaking. As they spoke
                    they would have a picture behind them. It didn't matter if it was weather or
                    maintenance capability or intelligence or report of a base, there was always a
                    picture and description. It was done concisely and tightly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you say this was true of the military in general or
                        particularly of the Air Force?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: It is certainly true of the military in general and inside that there
                    may be different variations. The Air Force having an image of itself as being
                    high tech and razzle-dazzle may have more of that. The Army, I think, does have
                    more intellectuals in it...we call intellectuals people who read books, history,
                    etc. And I would put the Navy probably somewhere in the middle. I have been
                    briefed by all of them. I would visit all these headquarters. The basic method
                    is the same.</p>
                <p>So to be a part of this I felt that I needed to make the cultural leap, not they.
                    I was the one who was supposed to be trained in cultural leap and I was aboard
                    their organization, not the other way around. So I began to write less and
                    create more events in which there could be more talk and shows. And I did that
                    through visiting the commands and during commander calls; through a television
                    program that I arranged to make and then we would put on the Armed Forces
                    Network so that people could turn on their television and see things in their
                    living rooms; and through the creation of what we called the Council on
                    International Relations which began as sort of a social gathering for the young
                    officers who wanted to talk to a visiting ambassador or minister and in the
                    usual course of events never got near one.</p>
                <p>So in these three devices I found very good reaction to them. At first the
                    military officers thought that it was funny that I would stand up at a
                    commanders' conference and throw some slides up behind showing in a funny way
                    the political and dynamics of say, the Middle East. But I did that. I had color
                    coded maps showing degrees of hostility of one country towards the other. And I
                    showed them how you could drop the shape of the map and just have the color and
                    do matrix of the colors and after I did that a couple of times I could show the
                    changes in the matrices by having a delta chart. All of this was conscientiously
                    aping their own briefings to themselves about military preparedness. They used
                    red, green, blue and yellow and orange to show degrees of readiness. A lot of
                    them who knew me could not get over the possibility that this was all a joke and
                    that I was really ribbing them when I did that. But all that helped the
                    communication in any case because they thought it was funny. They thought that
                    it might be appropriate to laugh at it, but they were nonetheless engaged by
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Over your career you have had a lot of assignments where
                        you worked very closely with or for military people. Did you ever find that
                        your own lack of military service was a handicap?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Sometimes I felt it was, but as I look back on it I think on the whole
                    it wasn't. What that did was to make them feel that I was pure civilian and pure
                    civilian, like being a foreigner some place, gets you cut a lot of slack. They
                    say, “Okay, how could he possibly know?” They also have a lot of fun introducing
                    military things to you because they choose to believe you know nothing about it
                    so they can explain things in a very engaging way. So I felt that for the most
                    part it was no problem at all and maybe I even benefitted a little bit from
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you make some general comment about how you
                        perceived the leadership of our military with whom you came in contact with
                        over the years? What kind of people were they and how skillful were they at
                        their jobs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I found them to be of all different competencies and
                    attractiveness. I had assumed at the start that anybody with an eagle on his
                    shoulder and certainly anybody with a star was going to be a superior person of
                    great discernment and judgment. I guess the first disappointment I had in that
                    was when I began to deal with the military from my second and third day in the
                    Legal Advisor's Office in 1964, to discover that there was a bellicose,
                    bombastic, hostility to anybody who might interfere or influence in a
                    non-military way any operations. I thought that maybe when you went up the ranks
                    you would find more statesmanship. I think that is generally true, but what is
                    astonishing is that it is possible for people to rise to high ranks in the
                    military without having even a hint of statesmanship. Maybe it is because they
                    are very good at driving a tank, a boat, or whatever they do, but I would say
                    that there were a handful of two and three star generals and admirals that I had
                    something to do with who I thought were disappointing people for the important
                    jobs that they had and the power they could display. Not so dissimilar, I must
                    say, from my attitude about our own ambassadors and other high ranking people in
                    the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was going to be my next question. How does their
                        senior selection process compare to the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: The big difference that I noted was that the people they select are
                    selected in part because they are leaders of their subordinates. That they
                    really do, if not care about the welfare of their subordinates, they know that
                    looking after them is a main feature of their mission. An example of that is the
                    way the Air Force evaluates their people for promotion in their general officers
                    ranks. They assign to the highest ranking general officer in a theater the
                    responsibility of knowing personality every other general in that service and to
                    report orally and personally to the Chief of Staff of the Air Force from time to
                    time about how they are being developed and doing in their jobs. In the European
                    Command, that I was associated with, the CINC, the Commander-in-Chief did that
                    about once a quarter with the Chief of Staff of the Air Force. I think that is
                    good. We don't do that in the Foreign Service. We don't give responsibility to
                    our senior most career people, even, in any area to look around to see how the
                    other career people are doing and so we have a more brittle and, I think, less
                    effective way of knowing how we can promote our highest ranks in any case.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>I would like to make two more points about the Air Force in this period, the
                    middle 1980s. One was that the NATO policy that we were supporting of getting
                    these new missiles into Europe to counter the Soviets SS-20s, worked like a
                    charm. Nobody, of course, knew that it would. We just hoped that it would. We
                    did an awful lot of work and spent a lot of money to build these cruise missiles
                    and to build the hugely expensive facilities in six different countries to bring
                    them into Europe. They no sooner arrived at some of these facilities when the
                    Soviets said, “Okay, we will take out our SS-20s if you will not deploy your
                    Pershings and cruise missiles.” And so in a way the missile system was the most
                    cost effective weapons system ever developed by the U.S. Without firing a shot,
                    it did away with the whole class of Soviet missiles. Probably as we look back on
                    it that decision by the Soviets not to try to face us down in the heart of
                    Europe, we will see that was an important turning point in the Cold War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think what happened subsequently in the Soviet
                        Union was linked to that directly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, it certainly set up a lot of stresses in Soviet defense
                    establishment. And, of course, whenever that happens, irritations under the
                    surface can come to the top. I can't describe the dynamics with precision, but
                    every time you punch the opponent, you are doing some good at persuading him to
                    give up just a little bit sooner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. You conquered the military and were in Ramstein for
                        four years, 1981-85. And then the personnel system said that Chuck Schmitz
                        deserves a reward and it gave it to him—a job with the Council of Foreign
                        Relations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I wish it had worked that way. In fact it was not true. The personnel
                    system had utterly forgotten that I was there and what I was doing and I finally
                    said, “If I stay here any longer I am going to be utterly ruined, so I've got to
                    come home.” They said, “Well, what would you like to do?” I said “Well, I think
                    I would like to be a DCM or perhaps ambassador at a small post.” I was offered
                    an opportunity to go to Rwanda as ambassador. At the time I did not see that
                    that was the particular place I wanted to be so I probably made a mistake and
                    said that I wanted to do something else. The system then lost interest in me
                    totally and suggested about the spring of the year that I needed to come home in
                    the summer and that I go into the President Executive Exchange program with
                    private industry, which struck me as being a very good thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If, indeed you were a serious candidate after being a
                        POLAD in Europe then you must have been rehabilitated politically from your
                        Panama experience.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I am not sure Rwanda counts.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I think it does. I think even Cape Verde counts and
                        Rwanda isn't as bad as Cape Verde.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well it may be because I got over there and really dug in to do
                    something with the military, I won back somehow some trust. But in any case what
                    passed as the system said to try the President's Executive Exchange program.
                    That sounded to me good. It was run out of the White House. It was a Reagan
                    operation. I went there and found out that the thing had run out of gas, that it
                    no longer carried much interest in the business community. They tried, I think,
                    pretty hard to sell us to industry and industry, for the most part, was yawning,
                    not interested. I went to interview several different companies that had some
                    military connection like TRW, United Technologies, and finally decided on United
                    Technologies. I went up there and received an offer from the International
                    Operations at United Technologies to begin work on Monday. I had my family in
                    Hartford who had pretty much just come off the boat and picked out school and
                    house and sitting in a motel in Hartford and I got a call from United
                    Technologies saying, “We are not going to be able to do this. We have just
                    spoken with higher ups in the corporation and they have other priorities this
                    year.” So with virtually no notice, this was probably September, I had no job at
                    all and, as far as I could tell, no prospects.</p>
                <p>After some effort I finally got the nomination to go to the Council on Foreign
                    Relations in New York.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything you would like to say about that
                        experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Again, I think it is a valuable experience that is underrated by the
                    Foreign Service. It is underrated for exactly the same reason the POLAD
                    experience is. That is because its main purpose is to put State Department and
                    Foreign Service presence towards the public. The public can see it and respond
                    to it. But you don't write telegrams back to the State Department and therefore
                    as far as the system is concerned you are largely invisible. There is also no
                    strong Bureau that supports that. This was done with the Bureau of
                    Personnel.</p>
                <p>In any case I was again cut loose to do anything I wanted at the Council on
                    Foreign Relations. I found it a congenial place. I didn't get enough money to
                    live in New York. I lived in a hovel on Madison Avenue. I was embarrassed to
                    tell people where I lived and couldn't invite anybody there. It was really a
                    bohemian existence. My family stayed in Washington so I would quit working and
                    come home on weekends. I enjoyed it. I did a paper on the connections of the
                    Ford Foundation on international disaster assistance which I felt was good. It
                    helped shake up a little bit the United Nations disaster assistance office in
                    Geneva which was desperately needed then and still does now. I made a lot of
                    good friends in the New York area and the outside world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Then it was off to the Director of the East Asian
                        Regional Affairs Office from 1986-89.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, that is right. I had hoped very much to do some more work with
                    Japan. I was married to a Japanese and I did my best to keep up with Japan and
                    hopefully have some involvement there. I was told that there wasn't anything
                    open then and that I should come back some place in the Bureau and bide my time
                    until something opened up. The place available was the Director of Regional
                    Affairs. It was a backwater, very quiet. It wasn't very much. It had literally
                    cobwebs in the office. It was an extraordinary thing. I was depressed when I saw
                    it and my predecessors had all retired in obscurity. But I took it anyway
                    because I hoped I could make something of it and felt that I would be able to do
                    something especially useful in the political/ military side because of the huge
                    military involvement we still had in East Asia at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: No. I was pretty much frozen out having anything to do with military
                    matters because these were conducted in person by the Assistant Secretary
                    directly with his counterpart in the Department of Defense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: That was Gaston Sigur, Assistant Secretary for East Asia, and he was
                    dealing with Rich Armitage in DOD. The political/military thing was supposed to
                    be in my jurisdiction, and my background by that time was pretty strongly
                    political/military. So, I was not happy to be cut out of the State-DOD loop.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a lot of experience over the years in
                        political/military affairs. Would you like to discuss your views of the
                        political/military affairs offices in the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I guess there are a couple of things I could mention. One, as I
                    mentioned, is that it seems to care a whole lot more about being strong
                    administratively and bureaucratically at home rather than what it should be
                    doing to expand the influence of folks who think diplomatically into US
                    political/military policies. One example of that is the decision that was made
                    some years back, it had been made several times, to reduce the number of people
                    we have in our field positions in political/military affairs, and to bring them
                    back and increase the number of people we have in Washington doing bureaucratic
                    matters. That actually did away with my previous office as Political Advisor
                    with US Air Force in Ramstein. Not while I was there, but a couple of years
                    afterwards. I was dismayed that that was the case because here as we are
                    adjusting our status in Europe of course you run the risk of making a whole lot
                    of mistakes in the way that is done and you need somebody with perspective
                    outside of just the defense perspective to get that done. And the irony is that
                    we pulled people back from those jobs to do arms control and arms negotiating
                    jobs in the State Department at just about the same time those negotiations
                    became irrelevant to the whole process of disarmament.</p>
                <p>The other thing is that there is a practice that is common in the Department of
                    State when we deal with other agencies rather than have our people trained in
                    the substance of other agencies we bring other agency people into our home
                    office as their experts and in the political/military field this is primarily,
                    of course, bringing military people into the political/military office in the
                    State Department. While this is an excellent practice from the standpoint of
                    giving us access to the expertise that we need to speak the language, it is a
                    self-defeating practice when it comes to the necessary bureaucratic tussle which
                    at bottom and most importantly, is a tussle between diplomatic, civilian
                    approach to problems and a military or a kind of strength support problems. I
                    thought that we almost methodically gave to ourselves a handicap by having so
                    many military people in our political/military jobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I agree. And in regional offices, the same thing happened.
                        In ARA we had a colonel who sat in our regional office.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I had a colonel in East Asia too. He was paid for by DOD and that is why
                    we had him. Fortunately he was one of the more competent people in the
                    office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Kind of last assignment at USUN as senior advisor to
                        Dick Walters had to be interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. It had begun as an assignment for just the Fall General Assembly
                    season. Again, I could have stayed in Regional Affairs, but I thought it would
                    be devastating to my career if I spent more time there. I had tried for a couple
                    of assignments that were breaking open in Japan and I was frustrated in not
                    getting them when they went to others.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>I discovered there was nothing else particularly open for me at that period and I
                    had, I guess, already been notified that since I had been a class 1
                    minister-counselor for six years and was not going to be promoted to career
                    minister or made ambassador anywhere, I would have to be leaving the Foreign
                    Service within a year. So with that being the case, to spend some months up in
                    New York with the US Mission to the UN seemed to be a decent use of my time,
                    better than just sitting around in Washington doing nothing. So I did that.</p>
                <p>There was nothing particularly noteworthy about my assignment. The major effort
                    there was to increase the vote in the Kampuchea question by one or two more.
                    That was about the only requirement that we had and I did that by another two
                    votes over the year. That was a lot of fun doing the campaigning but very
                    strange kind of thing and strange thing to be doing really.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't get to know Dick Walters very well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I did not get to know him very well. Naturally I bounced off of him a
                    number of times and did the usual thing of setting him up with appointments and
                    sitting in while he...some would say mesmerized his audience, I would say not so
                    much mesmerized as overwhelmed them with constant noise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And name dropping.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, sure. A lot of name dropping, place dropping and a lot of
                    repetitive commentary about countries which were lines that apparently worked
                    very well. One of his lines which I think was flattering to anybody he talked to
                    was: “You must have a place where you put your less than competent people in
                    your country because every time I have been there I look around and just see the
                    signs of competence all over. I wonder if you have any who are not so
                    competent.” He said that about. almost any country in conversations that I was a
                    part of. That he was able to dominant a conversation and artfully work in at
                    some point the point that he needed, get that point and then quickly move on,
                    was undeniable. And he was able, therefore, to get a lot done that even
                    surprised the people who he was talking too. Before they knew it they had their
                    wallets ripped right out of their back pockets and he was walking down the
                    street. So we all admired that.</p>
                <p>And we admired his strength at dealing with the Washington establishment. On the
                    whole I think he was pretty good up there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After that you were back and the last thing before
                        retirement you spent a year as the State Vice President for AFSA.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Right. I was asked to stay a bit longer at USUN because we ran out of
                    East Asian specialists, we didn't have any. So I was asked to do that and
                    Southern Asia things too. At that time it was Afghanistan, Pakistan. This was
                    for a brief time, it was a matter of several months. At that point the State
                    Vice President position was becoming vacant and I was approached to see if I
                    wanted to do that as kind of a parting shot for my career, and I thought I
                    would. It was a full time job and at that point the new Bush Administration was
                    lining up its ambassadors and a large number of them, to my way of thinking,
                    were not competent to be ambassadors. And I thought that was a matter on which
                    the Foreign Service should take some sort of stand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you retired in 1991.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes. Let me just say that the main thing that I did during my stint
                    there with AFSA was to have drawn attention to the low quality of the political
                    ambassadors at that point and focused attention on it by having AFSA sue the
                    State Department for having falsely classified the certificates of competency of
                    the nominees. Those certificates are supposed to be done in the State Department
                    to assure the Senate that the people nominated have a certified competency to do
                    what they are supposed to do. These things turned out to be laughable in
                    practice. They were slipshod, superficially done, just marking the boxes So we
                    had to expose that in some fashion. And that was important that it was exposed
                    and ultimately, as I said before, what caused a certain amount of embarrassment.
                    This didn't defeat any of those nominees, but it may have had some effect on
                    other potential appointees, or the nominators anyway who realized it wasn't
                    going to be just a free ride to nominate anybody as ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Am I wrong in detecting from the way you described these
                        last few years of your career a certain amount of frustration or unhappiness
                        over the way things were going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, I think you are right about that. Everybody, of course, coming into
                    the Foreign Service sees himself after a couple of years maybe qualifying for
                    some responsibilities. I never felt that I ever had any real responsibilities as
                    we looked at them in the career service. I was never even a political counselor
                    overseas. I certainly was not a DCM. I was not a deputy assistant secretary. The
                    most responsibility that I ever had in the traditional service was office
                    director for several different offices.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you like to wax philosophical about your career or
                        about the Foreign Service? What is the sum total of your experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I am not sure that I am able to wax philosophical about my career
                    yet, because first of all I haven't concluded that it has ended. The State
                    Department, a portion of it, has.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is what I meant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, once upon a time we thought we would come in and serve until we
                    dropped in the harness and it was our life. But now, just as we are trying to
                    demonstrate here with Global Business Access, that is not true. It can be seen
                    in some respects as preparation to do some other things.</p>
                <p>On American diplomacy, itself, you have to have some observations and those of us
                    who have been in it, I suppose, would observe primarily that it is a frustrating
                    thing to have done this at a time in which it seems that real diplomacy is very
                    seldom practiced by the United States. One example is the phony diplomacy of
                    conducting our international relations through special emissaries, who jet into
                    a country and fix something with just a few hours of effort. This is exactly
                    what has cost us so dearly in many of our relationships and yet we have the
                    repeated Presidential “summits” now. These are considered to be the great things
                    in our diplomacy, but they are used to create decision-forcing events rather
                    than to resolve the underlying issues themselves. At the other end, I think we
                    do phony diplomacy by having our embassies indulge themselves in gathering not
                    very significant information and then reporting on it in great quantity in a
                    cycle which creates specialized readers at the other end who say, “That is
                    great. I really liked your telegram because I spent a whole hour reading it and
                    it filled my day.” But in fact that kind of reporting system becomes an
                    ingrained mechanism that simply bites its own tail. I don't think we do very
                    much for the interests of the United States in having that kind of petty
                    reporting activity as a center for what we do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If you had to do it over again, would you repeat your
                        State Department career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Yes, because I still feel that I was able to do a good deal of what I
                    actually came into the Service to do. That is to bring a legal perspective to
                    bear on a couple of the great issues of our day. The Okinawa issue, which was in
                    a way “how do we keep Japan as an ally?” In the case of Panama, it was another
                    example of how we could, by bringing legal talent to bear, knit up a raveled
                    sleeve of empire, which desperately needed to be knitted up because it was
                    causing us big trouble. In the case of our military confrontation with the
                    Soviets in Europe, I felt quite useful there in doing the kinds of things that I
                    did. Of course, I would have loved to have had a career that would be marked by
                    recognition by the system, but there is a reason why people say that virtue is
                    its own reward: sometimes it is the only reward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any people who you consider real heroes or
                        real models in the Foreign Service? Who are the people you most
                        admired?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I think the best ambassador I worked for was Bob Ingersoll in
                    Tokyo. He was a Nixon appointee, a businessman from Chicago. The reason he was
                    good was that he was well traveled, bright, excellent manager, a statesman in
                    his own expertise who realized when he came to a totally new calling that he
                    needed to rely pretty heavily on his professional assistants. I thought he ran
                    the embassy the way an ambassador ought, giving it some general guidance,
                    depending on his staff for specific guidance and doing everything he could to
                    promote morale and welfare of the people who worked for him. At the same time he
                    did an excellent job of representing the interests of the United States. He was
                    a well-spoken, obviously successful man, self-confident. He did not allow his
                    ego, if any, to get in the way of conducting his mission.</p>
                <p>Maybe it was consequential that I always thought his DCM was an excellent one too
                    and that was Tom Shoesmith, an excellent career officer who was brought into the
                    Foreign Service from the non-professional side years before, studied Chinese and
                    then Japanese and ended up as DCM in Tokyo. He had a similar kind of inclusive
                    managerial style. It was a relaxed one but still seemed to get the most out of
                    the people who worked for him.</p>
                <p>I felt that under that combination of Ingersoll and Shoesmith, we had one of the
                    most effective embassy I had ever worked in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about people you thought were particularly injurious
                        to the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I am not sure that I would say injurious to the Foreign Service, I would
                    say disappointed in their leadership in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>I came across a couple of those when I had a fishing license in Europe because my
                    job was to keep in touch with all of our embassies. We had some political
                    appointees in Europe who were absolutely disasters in countries where they were
                    appointed. I don't mean disasters in just missing opportunities, I mean
                    disasters in being an embarrassment to the United States.</p>
                <p>In one case I think that I helped solve the problem by being the instrument that
                    informed the IG of the State Department that there was a real problem out there.
                    They had not been informed about it because our post was too disciplined. Our
                    officers would not rat on their superior.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Disciplined or frightened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: Well, I think it was disciplined. I did talk to a number of them about
                    the problem and asked them why they don't just blow the whistle and the answer I
                    got struck me more of a discipline answer than a fearful answer. They really did
                    feel that they shouldn't do that. That they were working for that embassy to
                    make it work best and could not bring themselves to turn in the top man. But I
                    wasn't working in the embassy so I could and did.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Thanks very much for the interview. In due course
                        you will see it in black and white.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SCHMITZ: I don't look forward to that, but I thank you for spending all the time
                    with me.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
