<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001546">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="interview">Interview with Ms. Dorothy A. Eardley </title>
<title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
<name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and scholarship.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or greater.</p>
</editorialDecl>


</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
<body>
<div>
<p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History Project</p>
<p>DOROTHY A. EARDLEY</p>
<p>Interviewed by: T. Frank Crigler</p>
<p>Initial interview date: February 15, 2008</p>
<p>Copyright 2008 ADST</p>
<p>[This interview was not edited by Mrs. Eardley prior to her death.]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Your first State Department assignment was in Djakarta. For whom did you work there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Joseph Vander Laan.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And what was his job?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He was the economic officer, head of the economic section.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So that was your first assignment in the Foreign Service. Was that a shocker? What kind of experience was that for you?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Fascinating. A whole new ball game. I got there on a Saturday — Oh! It took five days to fly direct from New York to Djakarta.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Five days!</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: KLM, great airline. It had one overnight, the last night in Bangkok. Then we stopped in Singapore and then Djakarta. I got there sort of early afternoon, I think, and I started drinking [laughs]. These people were fascinated by my coming fresh from the United States, so they were listening to every word.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: These were embassy people?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. I lived in what was called Crommat [phon.] House. It was a house that had — I don't know how many rooms. Had a big ballroom, marble floor, with a piano in it, that's all, and then it was lined by bedrooms. And we were assigned there. I had two roommates in that bedroom, girls. The next door bedroom had three men. Separate from that building was another whole row of bedrooms, and you graduated out of the three-to-a-room to one-to-a-room over there. We had bucket baths. That was my introduction to bucket baths. But you had to walk past the breakfast room to get to them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was in 1951?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. I got there on April 2.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean about bucket baths? What is a bucket bath?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: You had a tile fixture about this high, and it was filled with water.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: About three feet high.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, about my height. And then there was a bucket. You splashed it on you, then you scrubbed yourself and then splashed it on you to rinse off.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And was there drainage somewhere?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think so. I think in the floor. Men and women both used that. That was the only bath room on that side.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: If it isn't too personal, were there toilets somewhere too?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: In each bedroom. Each bedroom had its own toilet and wash basin, but that's all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was your office like in the embassy?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Boy, that's a long time back to remember. I think it was normal. AID (Agency for International Development) was in these — what do they call those moveable structures?</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Quonset huts?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Something like that. But we were in a building.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Djakarta was not Paris, was it?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, it was hot, humid. I loved that weather. I don't like being cold. And the first time I was borrowed there was for the accounting section. I'd had accounting in business school.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean “borrowed there,” “the first time you were borrowed there?”</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Why, I got borrowed all the time. At all of my assignments.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Because there wasn't enough to do in the economics section?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, it wasn't that. They needed help. I was an expert at shorthand, typing, accounting. So, for instance, about a year after I arrived there, the United Nations brought out an ECAFE (Economic Commission for Asia &amp; the Far East) conference. They were there for a whole month, in Bandung, Indonesia, which is sort of a nice place. Good hotel. We always stayed in a hotel, all of the delegates, and I was assigned for the whole month. So I took my typewriter, a safe, and writing material. Our delegation had two men from Washington, both affiliated with United Nations. One was very good, the head of the mission, Merrill C. Gay. He was good, but his cohort was lousy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Braderman, Eugene Braderman.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: These were not State Department people, though, these were UN people?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They were . . . not Treasury. Gay was with the United Nations. An American. He was the head of the American section.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Of the U.S. delegation to the conference?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. But Eugene Braderman was Washington. I would guess his . . . Was there an economic section?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: In the State Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, he wasn't State Department. This was strictly economic. Anyway, Merrill Gay got up early, and he would knock on my door, and I'd go down to his room. He would dictate the day's program, what all he was going to talk about that day. I'd go back to my room and transcribe it. Well, that dumb Braderman. One night he knocked on my door, said bring your book. I went down there. That jerk was unclothed. He had a dumb shawl wrapped around him, that's all. I guess he'd been drinking, I don't know. Anyway, he was disgusting. I said, “You don't need to dictate anything. I'm going home.” So I left. He never bothered me after that. I didn't tell Mr. Gay about that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You did not? Why not?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I thought I could take care of myself, and I can. One funny thing, though. You know, we looked down on the Soviets, we didn't trust them at all. There was a Soviet attached to their delegation, nice guy. We were all in the lounge, dancing. He asked me to dance. I was almost afraid to accept. He offered me a cigarette (I was a heavy smoker then). I was afraid to take it, afraid it was loaded or something. Stupid?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Not so stupid.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: But that's the way we looked at the Soviets at that time. Anyway, no problems. After a month I had to go back to Djakarta, to the embassy. But it was great fun. I enjoyed it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you live in Djakarta?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Djala Lambard. Djala means street, Lambard was the name of it. Not too far from the ambassador's house. First I lived in Crommat House. We all lived there when we first arrived. Married couples, singles, single men, single women. And you graduated out of that by tenure at the post.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Now this is not the place you were describing that had the water bucket, and you had to . . .</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes! Crommat House. Probably still exists there, I don't know. I've never been back.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So seniority got you a better place to live, but always in the same building.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, no no no! Well, that too, but we got out of that into a house with two other people by seniority at the post. So that was all right. I liked that. We had our own cook and I guess we had shower baths. I don't remember that part.</p>
<p>What I do remember, though, is Eleanor Roosevelt came to the post. And we always had receptions for any VIP (Very Important Person). She was about, I thought, 78 years old. She stood in that reception line for over three hours.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: A reception line just to see her? What was the reception for?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, yes! To meet her. She was very interesting. I still like her to this day. She wasn't attractive but she was intelligent. I liked her.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did she take part in the conference?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Not that conference, no. She came to visit the ambassador and get acquainted with the post.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The ambassador was who?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: H. Merle Cochran.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did they have a personal connection of some sort?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think so. I think, as far as I can remember, he was a political appointee, not career. He was very good, though. A nice guy. We all liked him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why do you suppose she would have come to Djakarta?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: To get acquainted with it, as all these other people came visit posts.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, there are so many . . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know. Maybe she was interested in the economic aspect. Maybe she even went to Bali. I went to Bali . . .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, did you?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: . . . before it was spoiled by civilization. It was very nice. Honest as the day is long. I left my diamond ring on the counter of the wash basin while I went out all day long at the beach. It was still there when I got home,</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That's amazing.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes it is. For Asia. And Africa.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So she might have been just there as a tourist?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They usually had something on their minds. I don't know what her field was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But she was the guest of the ambassador?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: She was the guest of the embassy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who else came your way?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Who else I met?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: What was his name? The third. John D. Rockefeller III. While he was still living, he came to the post. See, I think Djakarta, all of Indonesia, had an important economic status at that time. I don't know what for. They didn't raise opium. I don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, to have attracted Rockefeller, they must have had something important there.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, also, for Roosevelt. I think it was their economic status. I can't remember what crops they might have raised, except rice, of course. All of Asia raises rice. And you live on it and you learn to eat it year around with the rest of them. I still like rice.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: In general, did you have trouble with food there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. A lot of Americans complained about it. Our “beef” was water buffalo. I couldn't tell the difference. Now I'm not even a beef eater, but not for that reason. I don't want Mad Cow disease, and beef promotes colon cancer.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But for the others, they just didn't like the taste of water buffalo?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They wouldn't be able to tell the difference if someone hadn't told them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a commissary there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, that was long before the days of commissaries. Once in a while, we ordered food from overseas, but I can't remember where.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How were relations with the Indonesians generally?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Good. Suharto was the president, I think. He was very popular with everyone.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling the embassy was getting along well with the government?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes. Yes. There were no problems as there are today, because most of the present problems are caused by this fellow in the White House. He has created more harm. All of those years we had such good relations with almost all of those countries. That's way gone.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was the embassy most concerned about in those days? Did you sense that the reporting reflected some particular concern?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I can't think of it. I wasn't worried about anything.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: No security problem?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: And I was too old to date. The people my age were already married; the other ones were too young. I went seventeen years without a date! And then I got sent to Turkey. The “southern flank of NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization)” was loaded! I at my age could go out every night with a different nationality. There were that many!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Let's move on to Berlin. After your tour in Djakarta, how did you happen to be selected to go to Berlin?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: You tell me! I haven't the foggiest notion. Well, in Berlin, I worked only on Soviet affairs. It was called the eastern affairs division, headed by Nathan Barnes, a very nice guy. And some of the people you might have known. James Ruchti. He had I think three children, a wife at the post.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his job?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He was in the eastern affairs division (EAD). Also someone whose name begins with an M. McElhiney.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So this section was basically looking over into the Soviet part of Germany.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: And the Soviet curtain hadn't been built yet. We were encouraged to go over and prove that it was open. So I went to the opera all the time in East Berlin. I enjoyed Berlin. I even played the organ at McNair barracks for their Sunday night service. I had taken my first piano lesson in Indonesia. I was age 30. That's all I'd had. When I got to Berlin, I had a very good piano teacher. She was excellent. She thought I had possibilities. When I first lived there, I lived in a conscripted house with two other women.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean “conscripted”?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: It means the Army took over the German houses. We lived in them. They were all furnished. Mine had a grand piano in it. So, I was taking piano lessons. But my work was so heavy there. Long hours. I didn't have time to practice, and I didn't think it was fair to the teacher. But she said, “Oh, no, you keep on! You've got talent.” I just felt I couldn't do it, I couldn't use the teacher like that. I should have stayed with her, because in the two years I lived there I'd have been playing like a professional. It was a shame I didn't stay with it.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why was the workload so heavy? What kind of work was it?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: It was dictation, to me. We also had an economic section in the EAD, which was across the hall from us. I was in the political end of it. There was a lot going on at that time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think I have clear who your boss was.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Nathan Barnes, B-A-R-N-E-S. And Tom McElhiney. He was the number two, and then Ruchti was number three on the political side. And then across the hall in the economic side was Al Stoffel. Let me think of those other names now. I think one was named Crosby; can't remember the first name. That's all I can remember. Anyway, Eleanor Lansing Dulles, the sister of the two Dulleses, Alan and John Foster Dulles. She was his sister, but she went by Eleanor Lansing Dulles. She was a Soviet economic expert. She came over there a number of times. I was always assigned to her. She would dictate.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So she wasn't actually posted there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, she would come to visit. And she'd go over into the Soviet sector. But she would have a three-martini lunch and then come back. She sat in Tom McElhiney's chair. She would sit with her back to me, her feet upon the window ledge, and dictate 250 words a minute, non-stop. She was good!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So were you.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I know I was. I think I could have topped the world's record if I had known there was such a thing, because in 1957 I learned that the world's record was held by a man who took 296 words a minute, with one error, and I took 315 words a minute. I could have topped his record!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Now, was she reporting to the State Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, she was reporting to whoever or whatever she represented in Washington. There again, I don't know who that economic boss was in Washington but it was not the State Department.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was the final product sent by cable or by pouch?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't remember. I imagine by pouch, because I would type up this stuff and give it to her and she handled it from then on. She was quite a woman. Not very attractive, but she knew her business.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was she there secretly? I mean, was it general knowledge that she was there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, sure! Except for the Soviets. I think she also used to visit the Soviet Union, Russia, but I guess it wasn't very easy at that time. So, she had the Soviet Union right there, as part of the quadripartite city.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Any further ideas or recollections about Berlin that we ought not to overlook? What these people were doing there sounds fascinating.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: That was before Bonn became the capital. I thought it was a fascinating assignment.</p>
<p>Well, finishing up Berlin. Thomas Dodd, who was then Senator Dodd, worked on the Nuremburg trials which were held shortly after World War II. And one of the criminals was sentenced to jail in Spandau Prison in Berlin, the only inhabitant of Spandau. All those years. He came back in about 1954, I would guess. He wanted to see how this was working out, and then he dictated to me. Whiz-bang dictator, 250 words a minute non-stop. I could understand everything he was saying except the last remark. It had to do with Hitler. Something blah-blah-blah. But he said “If blah-blah-blah” (if I could remember this) “he must have had it with worms.” Now whatever that means, I should have remembered it, but I don't.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was something that referred to Hitler?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, no. Thomas Dodd was quoting something that Hitler had done or had said but, if so, he must have had it with worms.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Strange.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'd love to know that that was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Generally, he was reporting about what he found at Spandau. Do you remember who the prisoner was?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember anything he said about the situation he found when he went back?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. He was just interested in seeing how that prisoner was making out. You know, like people check up on what they cause to happen. That's all. And that's the end of Berlin. There were other things in Berlin, but I can't remember them now. It was not my favorite post, because as we got moved out of conscripted housing, we were moved into former barracks, and on the way to my office I walked past the PX (Post Exchange), the grocery store, all that military stuff. I did not like this crossing, all these military things, because I was in Foreign Service.</p>
<p>There was one interesting thing there. It happened on Easter Sunday. The colonel, head of the Soviet slice of Berlin, his son, 15 or 16 year old son, had defected to the American side.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: His son!</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, the military does everything wrong. Do you know what they did? Took him to the PX and fed him all that crap, then took him to the movies, showed him American films. It was the wrong thing to do!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he turn around and go back?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, but they forced him back. We returned him on Easter Sunday and I had to be there, because I worked on nothing but Soviet affairs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did they force him back?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: His father, who was the colonel, probably threatened him with life, that's my guess. I don't know. But anyway we were returning him then, on Easter, so I had to skip church. Church was in the afternoon anyway. This was Easter morning.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What year would that have been? Fifty -five?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Fifty-three, fifty-four, or fifty-five. I can't remember. I left in November of 1955, so it could have been any time in there. Well, we handed him over. He didn't look too happy. That's the end of that story.</p>
<pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Never heard from him again?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What on earth brought about your transfer to a remote place like Chengmai?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: God only knows!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did you learn about it?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They sent a telegram transferring me. Home leave and transfer. So, I got ready and went.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Saluted and went.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I always went wherever they told me, so if I didn't like a place I could gripe about it. The only place they had trouble placing me was the last assignment. Do you want to hear about that now?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: No, I think it would be better to go step by step, don't you?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Okay, let's go to Chengmai.</p>
<p>I knew it was as one-man post, because I was told that. I didn't know how many other agencies were up there — CIA, AID, military, and . . . I don't know what that outfit was called. It was training Thai police. Then there was JUSMAT (U.S. Military Assistance to Thailand [?]), our military (I think they were Americans).</p>
<p>I lived in a house out on a country road. A big yard with fruit trees in it. Behind it, there was a kitchen, housing for a houseboy or cook girl, whatever, and there was a next-door neighbor, with sort of an alley that separated the two places. I didn't know who or what it was, but I often heard screaming over there, couldn't figure out what it was. One night, I drove in and my windshield was splattered. Something had hit it as I came in, as I drove into my driveway. And I went right to the police, who were a couple of roads behind me. I learned a lot. They told me I lived on the opium trail from China! That house next door was a house of ill-repute, and the man who lived there was a police officer. Had all these girls locked up in the house. I mean, his girls.</p>
<pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Nice neighborhood.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I knew enough Thai at that point. I learned Thai phonetically. I can neither read nor write Thai. I said something to the police when I was at the police station about opium. Thin [phon.] was the word for opium. And I said, “I think I live on the thin trail.” “Well,” they said, “you're right.” They were shocked, though, about the screams from next door. That was one of their men who was living there with these women. It was funny.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Yeah, I guess so. Tell me about your principal officer, your single officer. Who was the Consul?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Karl Sommerlatte. He was PNG'd (expelled, persona non grata) out of Moscow. They should have sent him to Paris where he'd get lost in that big embassy. Instead they sent him to a one-man post where he stood out like a sore thumb. He was supposed to be up there in a “walking” position. That's walk here, walk all over the countryside. It was a listening post. (Maybe I'm not supposed to say that. Maybe that's classified.) But anyway, they should never have sent him there. For the despatches that they were supposed to send back to Washington, he simply copied the British consul general's walking tour reports to his government, but he had me change the spelling to American spelling. We put it on our forms, sent 'em in. I thought it was a crock! But I wouldn't report him, the dumb stoop.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't do any of his own reporting?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Nope, he wasn't about to get his feet dirty.</p>
<p>He had a wife, Jane. They didn't get along very well. She was over on the consulate porch every morning when I arrived, crying her eyes out. She hated the post, and I guess she didn't care much for him anymore, either. They had a little boy, I've forgotten his name. He was a sweetheart. I felt sorry for him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was he there for the whole time of your tour?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes. Two and a half years I spent there. I liked it. I liked the people and learning their language — it was tough. It's a five-tonal language, and as you can tell, I'm a monotone. I needed singing lessons.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you teach this to yourself, or were there teachers?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, the number one local (employee) in our consulate, it was his wife. They had ten children. She was a nice lady. She taught me phonetically. That's pretty tough with a five-tonal language, but I learned it. And strangely enough, I didn't think I learned that much, but my farewell speech when I left the post in was Thai. And when I went back about then years later to visit, it came back. The speech came back! The first place I visited was the market, because I did my own marketing, got up at five in the morning when they butchered meat. Bought my meat. All meat was just fifteen bhat a kilo. And it was all cut into squares, so I didn't recognize the cuts. The only thing I could recognize was a very expensive cut. What do they make filet mignon out of?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Beef tenderloin?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Okay, I bought the whole one each time I went. And I was acquainted with all of the vegetable sellers also. When I left Chengmai (I left on a Sunday morning, there were only about two planes a week), I went to the market to tell them goodbye. I passed the first little stall. That news traveled all over the shop, all over that market, and they were all crying. “Mem [phon.] is leaving! Mem is leaving!” It was priceless. I was loved!</p>
<p>Carl Sommerlatte was not the nicest person on earth. Every year, you could just about pinpoint the date, the floods came. And when it flooded, the whole compound where the consulate was located was flooded. He didn't tell me about that damn flood. I drove down as far as I could toward the consulate. And there at the gate was our number one local employee. Pancho [?] was his name. I guess he was waiting for me. He knew I couldn't get in there. But he had his bicycle, and he had me hang onto the handlebar of his bike while he led me inside, through all that washed-out garbage. They had open latrines. I threw my skirt over my shoulder (in those days we all still wore skirts) and Pancho led me in there through that mess.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: On foot?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yep. That dumb Carl Sommerlatte! And I'm thinking, “How could anyone be so stupid?” Well, he never became an ambassador, I'll tell you that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did his wife survive the two and a half years?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Barely. They were divorced after that. He married some older woman, I don't know who. I don't know how that turned out.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me more about Chengmai. What about the other personnel in the consulate. Did you have much to do with anyone else?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, the head of JUSMAT (Joint U.S. Military Assistance Team). I think his name was Major Shawfelt. He came over to my house every night and had drinks with me. I liked him. I didn't care for the sergeants he had, though (I think there were two of them), so I didn't have them over. Anyway, I liked that organization. They were training the police. The Shawfelts lived down the road apiece from me. They had a little girl, sweetest thing, Melissa was her name. We had a cultural affairs officer, too, and a little library that was also on the compound.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did you think the police training team got along with the Thais? Was it a good relationship?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know. When I entertained, they would all come to my house. One thing I should tell you: the Thai colonel who was governor of the province where Chengmai was located had studied Gregg shorthand in the United States. He was fascinated when he learned that Gregg was what I used. He gave me his books, and he ask me if I would teach the Thais shorthand. I could neither read nor write Thai, so I taught them in English. But the Thais have marvelous memories, and that's what it takes in shorthand. We have a lot of brief forms which you had to memorize, and in the colonel's day (I think he was in the United States in about 1927) they had had to learn a lot more word forms than I did twenty-five or fifty years later.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It's hard to imagine what he used his Gregg shorthand for.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know. What did these 'children' he brought in for lessons use it for? He brought in seven. I think they were all men except one. They were all bank employees. But they didn't know English, and that's what I dictated to them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So they could write English in shorthand.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: But they had terrific memories. The brief forms, they memorized all of them. Do you know that in six months they took sixty words a minute? Not in their language?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That blows my mind.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
<p>EARDLEY: It blows mine too. I don't know how they did it! Anyway, that's all I can think of about Chengmai. I loved it. That's why I went back to visit. You see, in the meantime Vietnam came along, and they made Chengmai an R&amp;R (Rest and Recuperation) point for our GI's. You can imagine what they do to cities. I was worried. I didn't want them to do that to Chengmai. I went up to check on it. That's why I went to the market. Right off the plane I went to the market, and when I got there, those sellers recognized me and word went through the market “Mem is back!” I loved them. They were so sweet.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And that was ten years later?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have anything to do with the embassy while you were posted in Chengmai? Were you a courier or anything of that sort?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, I think they ignored us.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So much for “listening posts.”</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, we did the listening.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But I mean the embassy needs to listen to the consulate. You had nothing to do with — was it Ambassador Bishop at that time?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, he was there at that time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he ever visit?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'm trying to recall whether he did or not. I don't think I met him. However, there was one interesting thing: the King and his wife visited Chengmai, for only the second time in their lives. I had to learn the official curtsy for the occasion. Took me two weeks to learn and I kept losing my balance. [Laughs] I learned it. And you always back away from royalty. You don't turn your back on them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the impression that the royal visit was a very popular thing? The people there were impressed?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, the people there were happy to see him! It was a very peaceful country at that time. It still is, I think, but strange things have happened since.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, why don't we talk about how you got from there to Paris.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'll tell you what Washington told me. That since I'd been at a one-man post, I needed to be at a large post. But I didn't want a large post. I went, though, and I loved it from the day I arrived. So, never judge a book by its cover.</p>
<p>Well, for one thing, I didn't think I could afford it. I had to go back on base salary. I'd been at a hardship post. Twenty-five percent helps a great deal. I was supporting my parents just then, because all my brothers and sisters were married and had families. I didn't want them to have to give up any of their hard-earned money, so I chose to do it this way. But boy! I gave them ultimatums. I said, “If I ever hear you're not giving them moral support, you're gonna pay.” They took care of my parents, all right!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where in the embassy, then, were you assigned?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The Special “Asst” for Atomic Energy. That's Special “Assistant” for Atomic Energy. The special assistant to the ambassador for atomic energy. Max Eisenberg, was his name. I liked his wife and daughter. I liked him all right too. He meant well. He just was lazy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So that meant you didn't have much work to do.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: None. And so he was all in favor of my learning French, and so was I. I had already enrolled in the Alliance Fran�aise my lunch hour. In those days I didn't eat lunch anyway. I was overweight, and I was trying to keep my weight down. So, I went there every lunch hour, on a pass. I rode the Metro. It went a little over my hour, but he wouldn't complain at all. And that's how I learned French, in eight months. I read and write French. And strangely enough, when I got to Gabon, which was right after France, one day one of the locals in the embassy said, “You're not an American.” I said, “Oh yes I am.” And he said, “But you have a Parisian accent!” I didn't know that. I still don't. I don't sense it. I took that as a great compliment. I'd finally arrived.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did the atomic energy section or office fit into the embassy? Was it part of the Political Section?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
<p>EARDLEY: It was an entity all its own.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who did it report to in Washington?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know that it ever reported anything. He would report to the ambassador. That's all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So you weren't busy typing reports that you had to send in.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, no. I think that's how (political section chief) Kidder discovered me. He could see that I wasn't doing anything.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did Mr. Eisenberg have contact with others in the community, outside the embassy?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, he was interested in music. I don't know whether he himself played an instrument. I don't think so. But his daughter may have.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He didn't have lots of people from other embassies coming to call on him?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY:, No, no. I don't think they had the equivalent in other embassies. The Atomic Energy Commission, though, used to be stationed in Paris. Then it moved to Vienna. I think it's still in Vienna.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me more about how you worked in the political section with Mr. Kidder.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I loved it. I was so glad when he asked for me. I can't be idle. I am now, but this is a different kind of idle. I don't think they had anyone in the atomic energy thing after I was moved. But I loved working with Ambassador Kidder.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He was not someone to sit around idle.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, we worked till eight o'clock every night. Yeah, I got called in after hours, too, because the Algerians kept threatening to blow up the Place de la Concorde. And we were right there on it. I'll never forget the last time I was called in. I think it was five in the morning. I drove across there. When I got up to the Champs Elysees, the tanks were all lining both sides of the Champs Elysees with their turrets pointed. And I thought, “Is it going to be safe for me to drive across the Place de la Concorde?” There was a bicyclist going by . . .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was at five in the morning?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, that's when Algeria would threaten to blow up the place, and evidently there'd been a new threat. That's why I was called in.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When would that have been approximately? Was that in 1961, or . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>DE; Fifty-nine or 'sixty-one. Sixty or sixty-one.
"
Q: I take it that the threat came to nothing, though.</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. But I asked this bicyclist, I said in French, “Is it gonna be safe for me to drive across there?” He said, “Oh sure.” I got across and got into the embassy, parked my car right inside the embassy entrance, and I got inside. The minister, Mr. Lyon, was waiting for me, and Kidder was waiting for me, and so we got busy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Doing cables?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. That I think was the last really bad threat that they had. That's when what's his name, de Gaulle, decided to rid himself of all the countries under French control. He forced independence on all those Sub-Saharan African posts which weren't wanting it, they weren't itching for it, they weren't ready for it, Gabon being one of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When you were working for the political counselor, how much did you have to do with the front office, the ambassador and the DCM (Deputy Chief of Mission) at that time? Did you see a lot of them?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The DCM, yes. That's how Lyon swiped me from Kidder.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And so you actually went to work for him?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, my last year there I worked with Ambassador Lyon. Strangely enough, Lyon and Kidder both became ambassadors at about the same time. Kidder was designated for Phnom Penh. He asked for me to come there with him. I said I'd love to. Okay, they cut my orders, they even threw in home leave, which I wasn't quite entitled to. (I was not in Gabon two full years, but they threw that in.) Kidder got to Bangkok, but he was not permitted to present his credentials in Phnom Penh. So my orders to Phnom Penh were canceled. Oh, I was furious! They said, “Oh, you just go on, take this home leave they've given you, stay as long as you want, and if it gets too boring you can come in here.” Do you know what they do with us when they bring us into Washington? You walk the halls. That's what you do. So, anyway, when Lyon got his assignment as ambassador to Colombo, Ceylon, and he asked for me, I was delighted. That was only a week after I went out on this junket of home leave. So I got out there in January of 1965.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But let's back up to how you worked with Kidder in Paris.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Kidder and I worked beautifully together. So did Lyon and I. You had to sort of straighten out Lyon once in a while. He knew everyone, Lyon did. Well, I guess Kidder did too. Did you know his wife? Quite a character. She was not pretty, but she was liked by everyone and she was a character. I think she liked me all right. Anyway, I would love to have gone to Phnom Penh.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When you say “they,” the Kidders, knew a lot of people and were liked by everyone, you mean within the embassy or among the French?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, all the way, yes, yes. I was also borrowed a lot while I was in Kidder's office. Whenever the secretary of state came to Paris I was borrowed to work with him and anyone else, any other VIP who came. And when, in 1961, John F. Kennedy came, I met all the Kennedys. They were sort of related to Lyon, so they all had to call on him when they came through Paris. First there was John — no, Ted I think was the first one. He was a red-faced, scared to death guy at that time. He was just married. I'll never forget when he walked across my desk. This was when I was Cecil's secretary.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Walked across your desk?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, in front of it. He was scared to death. He was out of his league. But they all had to call on the minister. One of the minister's daughters was married to Hugh Auchincloss.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Jackie's family.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. And then Robert Kennedy was attorney general when he came to Paris. He worked out of the Crillon Hotel, so I got to see him only once. He sent his dictation over to me with a courier.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You mean on tape?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, it was scribbled. He should have brought his secretary with him. Anyway, I guess he made his call on Lyon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember what kind of problem or activity they were working on when they visited Paris at that time?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I have no idea., no idea. I know what John F. Kennedy was working on, because he pulled a surprise on us. We thought we had put him on a plane at Orly — no not Orly — Charles de Gaulle airport, to go back to the United States. He didn't. He went to Vienna and met Khrushchev. That was the time when Khrushchev slammed his shoe on the table. And at three o'clock on a Sunday afternoon, I got a call to come back to the embassy. “The President is coming back!” So, I poured coffee down me. I'd been drinking martinis ever since I got home from church. Another secretary and I went to Georges V Cathedral every Sunday, and then we came back to my apartment and drank martinis the rest of the day. We did it every Sunday. So, I was loading myself with coffee after that telephone call. They told me to be at the embassy by six. I got there by six, sober, and they didn't get there till ten-thirty that night. Now, the President did not come in to the embassy, but his two aides came in. They dictated until seven-thirty in the morning.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And you stayed awake?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Sure! I loved dictation.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the aides, do you remember?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Have no idea.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was the secretary of state along on that trip?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think he had already left. He had preceded them.</p>
<pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: To Vienna and back?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, no, no! No! The secretary of state had nothing to do with this Vienna thing. This was later. The President did this on his own. He was gonna talk turkey to Khrushchev.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me more of your adventures in Paris. Where did you live there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I lived on Rue Maspereau [phon.] the first two years. The second two years I lived in Boulevard St. Germain, west — left bank. Then, the last year, I lived behind the Arc de Triomphe, in Rue des Acacias. I guess that was the name of it. I liked that. I had a one-floor, ground-floor apartment, and I loved it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What were working conditions like in the embassy? Were the offices ancient?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: What do you mean?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The building was old, wasn't it? Was difficult to work in?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Heavens, no! I didn't feel it was old. I liked working there. I had no problem.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well then, let's go on to Gabon. How did you get to Gabon?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They assigned me. Oh! Lyon fought that assignment! No, they first assigned me to some island in the Caribbean. Martinique? Cecil Lyon wouldn't have it. I said, “Don't bother, I go wherever they send me.” My car had already been sent, my clothes had been sent. I get home and Washington calls me and says, “You're not going to Martinique, you're going to Gabon.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was a favor that Cecil was doing for you?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, because Martinique wasn't an embassy, it was a consulate general. Boy, he didn't know Gabon! But anyway, there was one good thing came out of it. I met Albert Schweitzer. I tried to turn him away from communism. He was a communist! I don't think most Americans knew that. He would scribble up the daily paper with red pencil, marking anything that was unfavorable to America. Every morning. Well, I went to visit him. I sent a telegram saying I would like to come and visit, and he sent me back a telegram saying he'd love to meet me. He didn't know the half of it. Anyway, two other people from the embassy and I went, One was Irwin Hicks who became an ambassador later on. He was a code clerk at that time. The other one was a woman whose name I can't remember.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: A staff person in the embassy?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. We were in an embassy jeep, open air jeep, and we drove there, got into a storm on the way and had to stop a bit, but we got there. I didn't know anyone took pictures, but two years ago, on my 85th birthday, we were all celebrating in Illinois, and there on the wall someone had posted a picture of Dr. Schweitzer — and me!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Really!</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I didn't remember that picture. Evidently it was one that I'd given to my mother, but I don't remember ever having had one. After my mother died, evidently my brothers and sisters who cleared out her house picked it up. And so I saw it again.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get along with him face-to-face?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I was civil. But . . . .</p>
<p>[Session was interrupted at this point.]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Dorothy, tell me some more about Libreville, please, and the embassy there, and the ambassador.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Is that what the embassy was called, Libreville Gabon? [Laughs.] Sorry. Charles F. Darlington was the politically-appointed ambassador. I didn't care for him very much. I loved his wife, though, and his son.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who appointed him? Must have been President Kennedy.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I guess it was Kennedy. Anyway, Darlington had served in Brussels in his economic capacity several years, I think. But he was cheap, chintzy, and he even used the embassy's postage stamps. And for cocktail parties, he put down the name of a nonexistent waiter and collected money.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: For the waiter's services?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. He went down so in my opinion! Now his wife wasn't like that at all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was her name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Alice. Alice Darlington. She was a marvelous person. And so was their son, who visited there, a grown son — I don't remember his name. Anyway, my reaction to Gabon was violent. I did things I absolutely would not have done under normal conditions. I bought a boat, for instance.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Motor boat?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: It had a motor in back. It was 19 feet long, had no life vests, no insurance. I drove it twelve miles every Sunday to an uninhabited island.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You drove the boat there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. Outboard motor is what they called it. And I took a French family that I adored over, and we spent the whole day there. Nothing ever happened. But on the way back, every Sunday afternoon, a squall came up. Tossed that boat twenty feet in the air. But we never capsized or whatever they say. We all got back safely, and I put it away for another week. A miracle. God took care of me all the way.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Could you start that outboard motor yourself?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, sure.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were there Peace Corps volunteers there when you were there?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Let me think . . . . I don't think so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I seem to recall reports that some had been some expelled by the Gabonese government at about that time.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't recall that. I don't remember much about Gabon because I've tried to erase most of it out of my mind and get on to better things.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then, let's go on to better things. Where did you go next?.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I was first assigned to Phnom Penh. Randolph Kidder was named ambassador to Phnom Penh. Well, he got to Bangkok but he didn't get — Phnom Penh wouldn't let him present his credentials. So, even though I hadn't been in Gabon two years, they threw in home leave. They canceled my orders to Phnom Penh and sent me on home leave, so I went. And in Washington, they said just go on leave, stay as long as you want to. If it gets too boring, we'll bring you in here to Washington.” And what that means is walk the halls. That's all it ever meant. So I went on. A week later, I got a telephone call from Cecil Lyon that he had been named ambassador to Ceylon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Sri Lanka now.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I know, but Ceylon it will always be for me. And the tea planters. And Ambassador Lyon asked me if I'd come there. I was delighted. So in January I got to Ceylon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That was in 1965.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. And I was there for four years. I loved it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about it. You mentioned planters, the tea planters.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The tea planters and I were great friends. We will always call it Ceylon. Sri Lanka doesn't mean beans to us. They never should have changed. They set the country back 100 full years over that nonsense. They forced the children in school, who already spoke fluent English, made them learn Singhalese.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who are “they”?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I'm trying to think who was there after Bandaranaike. Sirimavo Bandaranaike was the Prime Minister when I arrived. Who replaced her, I don't know. This was 1968 when they began this nonsense.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I remember reading about it.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know if it was Senanayake . . . I just can't remember who was in charge at that time.</p>
<p>Trying to think where Andrew V. Korry fit in here. Andrew Korry was a friend of Mike Mansfield, and that's how he got an ambassadorial assignment. He was a funny little character. Never married. And he lived with his mother until that assignment. I don't know if she died or what. Anyway, he was a lonely man. Had never been married. He took the ambassador's chauffeur to the beach every weekend, and they spent the weekend there together. Swimming. That was his way to get away from things and enjoy life.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did this affect the embassy? Were there strained relations?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think so. I was not aware of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did the ambassador have difficulties personally with the new government crowd?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, no.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Your relations with Ambassador Lyon were obviously very good — continued to be very good.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, oh we had worked together for years, and I liked his wife too. As far as I know she's still living.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How were his relations with the other members of the embassy staff?</hi>
</p>
<p>ED: Good. Oh, yeah. He was a likable guy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He was an economic specialist, is that right? No, political. OK.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
<p>DE; No, he was in Foreign Service from the 'twenties. He came in as a young officer and stayed in. Career officer, he was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I take it he got along well, then, with the Ceylonese government.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think so. Let me tell you about one of his predecessors who was PNG'd out of there. He was called back by Washington. I'll give you his name, even though you may have to delete it. I did not meet him. I got all this second hand.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'm trying to think now. He owned dress shops in New York City. That was his claim to fame. He was recalled because he could not learn to pronounce the Prime Minister's name, which was Sirimavo Bandaranaike.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That's a mouthful in any case.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: All their names were. They all had six or seven syllables in the last name. “Wichigunawardide.” What's that, seven syllables? And Bandaranaike And Senanayake, that was a very common one. Ceylon was an ex-Portuguese colony, so there was still a lot of the Portuguese names there. Fernandos. Tons of them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many Portuguese living there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: None that I know of. But I was good friends with this one Fernando family. She was later arrested for embezzling jewels, diamonds and things from Singapore.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Bringing them in illegally, smuggling them in?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. Her husband was a lawyer. Fernando, good guy, I liked him. Titi [phon.] Fernando.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: We're going to skip here and talk a little about [Ankara]. You were there a little over five years, with ambassadors Handley and Komer?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: A little over five years, with Ambassadors Komer, Handley, and Macomber.</p>
<pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Start from the earlier part, anything you remember.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: All right. Have you ever heard of Robert W. Komer? He was with CIA running the Vietnam War CORDS (Civil Operations and Rural Development Support) out there. Well, who was the president? Johnson. He named Komer to leave Vietnam and come there as ambassador. Well Komer was delighted. That was a feather in his hat. But Turkey was not pleased, because of his CIA connection.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Really. They knew that?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh yes. So we had a time getting him off that plane.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Just getting him off the plane?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh yes! The Turks came out to the airport. It was pouring rain. Night time. They weren't going to let him land. The plane was on the ground. We got him off the wing of the plane, got him into the car, and drove off.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You say the Turks came out to the airport. You mean officials or a mob of some sort?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Mobs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The authorities didn't keep them away, though?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. I was out there. I think I remember it pretty well. Anyway, we finally got him settled in the residence. Then he started doing his official calls. I've forgotten which one he was calling on. Minister of education, something like that. He called on him. Of course, his chauffeur was no good either. Scared to death. And while he was in there calling on the minister, the Turks set his car on fire, his Cadillac. The poor chauffeur — he was a good chauffeur, but he was scared to death. He evacuated.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Left the ambassador behind at the Ministry?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yep.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He wasn't accompanied by any security detail or anything when he went there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, I'm sure there was someone in the car. Anyway, we had some tough days.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The ambassador's relations with the government people were pretty good?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: All right, as far as I know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there was the big issue over whether Cyprus should become part of Greece, and the Turks obviously didn't want that. And it was a difficult question for the United States to handle because we wanted friendship with both sides.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: But, we didn't get into that too much, I don't think.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Weren't we involved in discouraging the Turks from making a military move there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I can't recall.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember his dealings with the Prime Minister, who I guess was Demirel, wasn't it?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, he was there part of the time I was there. But there was another one. Foreign minister. What was his name? We were good friends.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You and the minister?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, he was well married. But I sometimes think I knew more than the ambassadors did in Turkey, because he talked to me all the time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The foreign minister did?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. He trusted me. I've forgotten his name, I think it began with an E.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did you happen to have so much contact with him?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
<p>EARDLEY: He liked me, I think.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, did he come to the embassy, or were you at the foreign ministry? or at receptions?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I was always with the ambassador. Everywhere. You see, that's where we went through that opium poppy business. We were together a lot. We got the opium ban at one o'clock in the morning, after hours and hours of going over this thing.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was a ban on growing poppies in Turkey? (Yeah.) And when you say “we got it,” you mean you had persuaded , , ,</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The ambassador and I. [laughter] And the foreign minister. He finally gave up. And it was a shame, because they were not in the opium business. They used the seeds for cooking and oil. The culprits were the French and the Germans with their — what did they call those?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The little factories where they processed the opium?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. They had them all over Europe. They would get that opium out of there by devious methods, and that created all this problem for Turkey. So Turkey finally had to stop growing it. Of course Afghanistan didn't.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That must have been some economic shock for Turkey.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well it was. It was one of their main things, and they needed it to eat, to cook with. It's too bad that some countries have to pay for the dishonesty of other countries.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, you and the ambassador wrestled the foreign minister down and finally got the government to agree to impose a ban.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Right. It was one in the morning.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where, at the foreign ministry?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think we were out in the country someplace. But maybe it was the foreign ministry.</p>
<pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The ambassador was pretty effective at this?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh yes, very good. Ambassador Handley was excellent.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But this was still Komer when you got this agreement . . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, Handley! Komer was recalled. Didn't I tell you about making him sign and then send the message in to Washington? His resignation? He said, “Oh, no,” he didn't have to resign; he was a friend of the president. “Yes, everyone has to,” I explained to him. I showed him the regulations. I had it all typed up for him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He must have appreciated that.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He thought sometimes I knew too much.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He went willingly in the end?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, he said it wouldn't be accepted. It was, immediately. So, Komer had less than one whole tour of duty. I liked him. I even liked his wife. She was kinda forward, but I liked him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where did he go from Ankara? Into retirement?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, I think to Washington D.C., back to his CIA. He's never had another assignment, to my knowledge. But we got along all right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Handley came right away after Komer left?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, he came May 13 [1969].</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was the DCM in charge in between?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Must have been. Do you recall who it was?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, Bill Burdette was there. He was the Deputy Chief of Mission when I arrived, I think. And then there were two others: David Cuthell and James Spain, but I don't remember in which order.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Casell or Kafell? I didn't understand his name, the second one.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: David Cuthell? C-U-T-H-E-L-L. His wife's name was Dawn. Very pretty lady. Very nice. James Spain, his wife Edith.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The atmosphere at that point was still rather hostile on the part of the Turkish public, wasn't it? Or had that died down?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, that died down.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Despite the ban on opium production? Or rather poppy cultivation.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't remember hearing anything more about it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So it didn't create a great fuss.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think so.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was that a military government at the time? The Turkish government?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: NATO. Huge NATO. It was our southern flank of NATO. We leaned on them very heavily, depended on them, they were our greatest ally at that time, I think. And there were military people all over the place, from every nation. I could go out every night in the week with a different nationality, and I was old.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well that's what made it awkward for the United States, over Cyprus. We depended heavily on Turkey, didn't we?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: We did indeed, and I'm glad I was part of it.</p>
<pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who were the important military figures in the embassy?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Let me see if I can think of his name, I liked him. There was one guy, a Navy guy, I didn't like. I could have slapped him. He hated it that I had to seat the people they invited to their house for official functions. They were going to have their husbands and wives sitting together.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, military style.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yep. But what was that nice one's name? He never gave me any trouble. He once got caught in Russia. Lost his hearing aid. Tall thin guy, very bowed legs. He was a Texan and rode horses.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his position? Was he an attach�? Head of the military group?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He was a general and he was head of the military mission in our embassy, the attach� office. So there was this navy guy. Can't think of his name either, he was sort of short — and I could have slapped him!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were their titles “attach�" do you remember?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yep.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Any other figures in the embassy that you could have slapped?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think so. We got along pretty well. And the ambassador counted on me very heavily. I'm glad I could do it. I got tired of country team meetings, though. I had to sit in on every one of them and take notes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How often did they meet?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Once a week.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: For how long?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I guess the whole five years I was there.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. How many minutes or hours during the day?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Quite often over an hour.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The Ambassador ran the meeting?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. Sure.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did it play out? Did he go around the room and ask “What do you have to say, and you, and you?” Or did he give a lecture, or what?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: When they had something on their mind, they would jump in and put it in words. I would take it down in shorthand.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were they cordial meetings among all these agency chiefs, or was there a lot of argument?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: There was never any problem. Not with Handley. Handley was a great guy. It's too bad he drank himself to death.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, no! That's sad.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Because he was only about sixty-one.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So it was not at post that he drank himself to death.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, it was after he retired. He went up to Laos. They sent him up there to look into something. I can't remember what it was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: All the way to Laos from Turkey?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, he retired. I've forgotten what that junket was.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I'll bet it had something to do with poppy-growing somewhere.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think so. Well, also, Laos and northern Thailand where I was stationed — Chengmai. What was it that China had? It was the road from China down to “civilization.” What was it they grew? It wasn't legal.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't poppies?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The opium trail, yes! And it went right past my house!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That's right, you told me before.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: And the policeman that lived next door to me? He was part of it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You think maybe that was why Ambassador Handley was sent up there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: It could very well be. 'Cause he had gotten that ban in Turkey,</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you hear from him afterward?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Whenever I came back to the States, which was every year the last ten years, I visited him at The Citadel, where he was ambassador in residence. I had a house built in Florida for my retirement, so I went to Florida every year when I came back. And in 'seventy-nine, when I knew I was going to retire the next year, I decided there was no way I could ever live in Florida. The house was finished, but I couldn't do it. So that, I think, was the last time I saw him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, he was replaced then by Ambassador Macomber.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a gap, do you recall?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Not much. We were all surprised by the Macomber assignment.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
<p>EARDLEY: He wasn't too well liked. You know, he was this exercise nut, and he married his secretary, what's her name, Phyllis. I got along all right with him, but I made a real effort.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But you say people were surprised that he was named to Ankara?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why? Was it because they thought he wouldn't get along well with people?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, he was controversial.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Within the embassy or among the Turks?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think more outside. I got along all right with him. But she, Phyllis, was a little difficult there.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think Macomber was sent there with a mission, that is, to get Turkish cooperation on something? I mean, Handley had already got them to cooperate on the opium trade.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Strangely enough, I don't remember very much of that. I barely remember that Macomber came.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You must not have overlapped with him very long.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: There were never overlaps.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he bring a secretary of his own when he came?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, he used me.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How was he to work for?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He was all right. He was nice to me.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Serious? I know he was hard-working.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes he was. The problem is, when you've known people that long you have preconceived ideas, and I thought, “Oh, he'll be awful to work with.” He wasn't. But Phyllis, the girl he married, she was terribly bossy. I guess you get like that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his style?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He was sort of a little gruff, a little rough around the edges. But he was a kind man. He knew his business.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was his “business?” How would you sum up what he mainly did?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He kept the house in order.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he spend a lot of time out of the “house”? In the community? In the country?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. He spent a lot of time taking care of himself physically, keeping well, exercising.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And was he in fact generally well?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He got along all right with just about everyone. I don't think anyone was against him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What were the topics he was most interested in, dealing with the Turkish government or problems with Turkey?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't even remember what our topics were at that point. We had taken care of opium and NATO.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And issues involving Cyprus didn't come up by then?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he get on with the Russians, the Soviet ambassador, the Soviet embassy people?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't remember the Soviets very much in Turkey. I guess I was getting old.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: About how long did you stay after he came?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I had less than six months with him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they weren't a very troubled six months, then; things were pretty smooth. (Yeah.) Where did you live there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: On Reza Shah Pahlavi, I think,</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: In a private house? An apartment?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: An apartment, an upstairs apartment.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Government owned?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. The people on the ground floor worked in USIS (U.S. Information Service), and they rented. It was a nice apartment; I loved it..</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember who they were? Their names?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't a partying place, then.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. It was serious. I did most of the partying.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You said Macomber was interested in exercise. Did he get into sports and so forth with other people in the Embassy? Softball teams?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
<p>EARDLEY: No. He exercised by himself, every noon. Took his clothes off in his office, threw them on the floor. He was like an untrained kid. Nice guy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he exercise with the Marines?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, but he got along fine with the Marines.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I'd have thought they would have taken to that exercise routine.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, I think they stayed pretty much to themselves.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Have we figured out who was DCM then?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Jim Spain? Jim Spain was there a long time. He was a political officer. So was Cuthell. But they both became DCMs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Cuthell was DCM before Spain, right?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, I think Cuthell was in the embassy when I arrived. He was in the political section.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He moved up from the political section to be DCM?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They both did.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You liked Jim Spain?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, sure. He was tall, good-looking. I was so surprised to find out that, after he retired, he moved to Ceylon and lived in the Golf-ace [phon.] Hotel. I couldn't believe it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think he's still living there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think so. [NOTE: Ambassador Spain died in Wilmington NC on January 2, 2008.]</p>
<p>EARDLEY: His wife Edith was in a bad car wreck, if I remember right.</p>
<pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where was the car wreck?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Must have been in Washington, I don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Not in Ankara.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Can you tell me any more about the USIS people? Not necessarily the ones who lived downstairs, but what their program was. We had some bad times with the Turks not many years before that, and I wondered whether you thought USIS was doing a good job.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I thought they always did a good job.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Your apartment building was near the ambassador's residence. Did that mean you were at his beck and call?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yep.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were you often called there outside of hours?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I'll tell you, it evolved to the point where, if he wanted to get out, I went out and got him. I left the security people behind. Otherwise he had no freedom whatsoever.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You mean you snuck him out, then?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes. For sure.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where would you go in that situation?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: To my apartment. What would we do? Drink. I drank a lot. So did he. I was also dating a Turkish admiral at that time.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about him.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I can show you pictures of his two daughters. They're over in my other room, downstairs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember his name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: . . . . [No answer.] If I could pronounce it. It's a long time ago.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did Ambassador Macomber meet with him there?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Meet with whom?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Your Turkish boyfriend, the Admiral.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, no.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I thought perhaps that's why you were sneaking him out of the Residence.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: On, no..</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did he meet with others in your apartment?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Sure, I had lots of parties.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And he would attend them? Enjoy them?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. I was a good cook, and I liked to cook.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And Macomber liked to eat?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know about Macomber. That was later. I don't think he was that friendly. And . . . . [Interruption]</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When you spoke of sneaking the ambassador out of the residence and coming to your apartment, were you referring to Macomber or was that Handley?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: That was Handley.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Ah, okay. We have to keep these guys straight here.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes! Handley was the one who was there the longest and I liked the best. He, and you, were my two favorite ambassadors out of twelve.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I'm flattered. Let's move on to Ottawa.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I got to Ottawa after more than five years in Turkey. Not much to say about Ottawa. It was cold nine months of the year.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Shortly after you arrived in Ottawa, Ambassador Schmidt was replaced by . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: William J. Porter and his wife Eleanor, whom I liked very much. We were there for a short time — two years? At that time, Kissinger was secretary of state. He hated Porter. So, he was shipping him off to Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. That was before Riyadh became the capital.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why did Kissinger hate Porter?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't know. I guess it was because Porter was very smart. Anyway, Kissinger shipped him off to Jeddah. And Porter asked me if I'd go along. I danced at the chance.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you “dance at the chance”? Why did you want to go to Jeddah?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Because I wanted out of Ottawa. These fancy posts were never my cup of tea. I liked hardship posts. And it was nice being close to the United States. While I was there, I was once sent to Washington to work on the selection boards, promotion boards I think they were called. Also had a chance to visit my family periodically, the ones in Detroit and the ones in Illinois. So it was pleasurable. But Ottawa wasn't my kind of embassy, and I was very happy to go to Jeddah. Twenty-five percent post.</p>
<pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
<p>So we went there, and I lived on the compound. The embassy was on a big compound. To get off the compound you called for a chauffeur and a car. And that was how you got out and how you got back. It was great. I loved being hauled around. I wanted to hire a chauffeur and bring my car over, but they wouldn't let me do it. The Saudis wouldn't permit it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: They wouldn't permit you as a woman to drive, would they?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Right. But they wouldn't even let me own a car. No movies, no cinemas, no television, no . . . no fun except for the men. Anyway, my sister Grace and her husband came over. He was ex-Air Force, so they always had free transportation. They got to Saudi Arabia and landed in Dhahran. Mike, my brother-in-law, was permitted to continue on to Jeddah; Grace was left behind. I had a terrible time getting her to Jeddah. I called our consulate there. I said, “Please help. I'm worried about my sister, who's been stranded there for two days.” They couldn't do anything.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why was she stranded? Why couldn't she have come with her husband?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: She finally did, but not through the consulate's help, not through the embassy's help. You've never been to Saudi Arabia. Oh, you have? Were you ever at the airports? Did you notice how the Saudis, the Saudi men, climb over the counters and grab a boarding pass and get on the plane, and the women are always left behind? That was what was happening to Grace. Women don't mean anything. Anyway, I think it took four days to get her from Dhahran to Jeddah. I had a nice little apartment on the compound with a concrete patio in the back, and I walked to the office every day, through the sand.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Another word about getting Grace there. Why was the consulate or embassy unable to help?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: You don't balk the Saudis. You just try to get along with them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you know whether anyone from the consulate went to the airport to help Grace get through?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Here's how she finally got to Jeddah: there was an American military man who was I think married to a Saudi. They were waiting to get on a plane. They knew that Grace had her boarding pass and everything. But she was always shoved aside by these thoughtless men. Anyway, he said he would help her, and he did. He was the one who finally got her on a plane, because he was trying to get his wife on a plane too. And he succeeded, he finally got them both on a plane.</p>
<pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Just muscled his way through?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. That's what you have to do. One funny thing I noticed at Jeddah. You didn't often get out of the city, but if you did, you saw that all the roads were lined with wrecked cars. They drove like idiots, but they could get a new car the next day. They drove big cars, and they loved them.</p>
<p>Oh, we went swimming one day. We had a Palestinian there who was head of general services in our embassy. He was an excellent scuba diver. He was married to an American woman. Nice guy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember his name?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I wish I did. It may come to me. Grace will probably remember it, and Grace will be here Wednesday. Anyway he said he would take us swimming. We got into our swimming clothes, we walked at least a mile across the desert, to the beach. I think the men wondered what the heck this was. We got down close to the water finally, then you walk another mile to the falling-off place, just a sudden drop-off. And if you don't fall over, you can see all those fish down there, and the colors are for real! It's a sight I'll never forget. Besides, it was fascinating to be able to dress like that and go across that long expanse and not run into any problems.</p>
<p>We were led by this Palestinian, and he did some scuba diving while he was there. I still have a shell that he caught down there. It was still alive, and I put it in my back yard and buried it in the sand. That's how you kill those animals that grow inside. And I still have that shell. Beautiful shell. I don't have anything that looks like it at all. But while I was digging down there I found a great big . . . now what do they call those big shells you can hear with?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Conch shells?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, conch shells. (I think there's another name.) Anyway, I found a great big one that someone had buried there. I dug some more and found more shells, but nothing that big. It was huge, that big. I still have it. I never throw anything away. That's my problem.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How about the others working with you in the embassy there. Were they happy with their lot there, or was that a miserable place to be assigned?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, we had a secretary in the political section who was rather well-endowed with boobs. She wore skin tight t-shirts and skin-tight blue jeans. She'd come back from the souk every time she went in tears, because they sprayed her.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: With what?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Whatever they had — ink, or paint. She also had long black hair which she didn't put up in place. It was her own fault. Most people I think were satisfied with the place. I didn't hear any groaning, really.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: And did they like Ambassador Porter?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes, I think they did. I didn't hear anything.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How about your relations with Ambassador Porter?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: That jerk! That stupid ass! Men can be stupid, and they don't need to be.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He misbehaved, I take it.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Uh-huh. He did indeed. I would be shocked were Eleanor to ever learn about that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Is she still living?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: As far as I know. I've never seen an obit. But she was way up in age. I don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It would be interesting to know where he “misbehaved.” Are we talking Ottawa or are we talking Jeddah?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Jeddah. One day, he overheard me making an appointment for Eleanor to call on one of the women, like around one o'clock in the afternoon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: A wife of one of the other ambassadors?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. And, he never came back to the office from lunch. Never. He would come in about five o'clock in the afternoon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: After a siesta.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Uh-huh. Well, I ordered the car for Eleanor, and had everything set up. He knew it. He could hear me from his office at my desk. And right after we all got back to our desks, the phone rang. It was the ambassador. He said, “Bring your book.” “Aye, aye, Sir.” But I thought, well that's funny. Fortunately, I didn't walk up through that sand-trap. I ordered a car. A chauffeur and the car. And when we got up there I told the chauffeur to wait for me. I had no idea. It was stupid. And I got inside. It was all dark, all the shades were drawn, drapes. He was sitting on a sofa, and I got out my book. He tells me to sit on the sofa. He throws his arm over my shoulder, and I just looked up at him and I said, “You don't want to dictate.” And I got up and walked out of there. Jumped in the car, told the chauffeur to take me back to the embassy. I stayed there. But the rest of the weeks were a little bit uncomfortable. It was so stupid!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Men do stupid things, just like you said.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: He shouldn't have done it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I imagine your relations were strained then.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They were. And for no reason at all. He had never pulled anything like that before. I knew he had played around a little bit in Ottawa with my junior secretary, because she told me about it. But he never tried anything with me.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's an interesting story.</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't experience difficulties with military personnel there?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
<p>EARDLEY: No. We didn't see much of our military there. They weren't in the embassy. We had an economic section — can't remember the name of the head. I can't remember the head of the political section, either. It was a very small political section, one secretary, one officer, I think. Consular section. One secretary in th e mission had a chance at a better job, but it required shorthand, dictation. She asked me to teach her, which I did. She was good. I hope she got the job. I never heard. But anyway, as a thank you, she gave me these earrings, out of the souk, you know the gold souk in Jeddah. All that gold is manufactured in Italy, designed in Italy, so it's good gold. These are 18 carat. I think it was a very nice thing for her to do. I wear these all the time.</p>
<p>We had clandestine church service in the basement of the embassy. We also had square dancing, and I learned to square dance in Jeddah! We were called the Red Sea Squares. It's strange. I learned to play volleyball. I'd never played before. I had bowled in Paris. In fact, I may still, fifty years later, hold the women's single game champion. I bowled 213 — one time. And I was the champion in all Paris, with all those military people. So, my career in Foreign Service was very helpful in many ways.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Jeddah? I guess we've finished with Jeddah.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh! No, we haven't! Mine had been a direct transfer from Ottawa to Jeddah, so they sent me a telegram saying I could go on home leave and return to post, which I was willing to do. I was happy there. Shortly after I got home, though, I got a telephone call from Washington saying I would not be going back to Jeddah. I hadn't packed up or anything. That I should just go on leave as long as I wanted to (another one of those run-around things). They said ambassador Porter had been replaced. That was a shocker. He was replaced by the former governor of South Carolina, a man named West, I think was his name.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: John West.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I insisted that I had to get back to Jeddah because my whole apartment was there, my freezer was full of meat. But there was one person in the Department in an administrative capacity who helped me out tremendously. She said she would arrange for me to get back to Jeddah if I was willing go on TDY afterward. I was delighted!</p>
<p>However, while I was in Jeddah, when I got back there to pack up my things and get out of the way, I called on Madame Ambassador. She didn't know beans about people calling on her. I still smoked at the time.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: This was Mrs. West?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes. I smoked for fifty-three years. I smoked 3-4 packs a day! Can you imagine the price of them now? All that money I could have saved, except I got them for $2.80 a carton.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: In Jeddah.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, all over the world. I ordered through the mail. I don't think I ever paid much more than that except maybe at commissaries. Anyway, enough of my smoking. I got over it.</p>
<p>Well, I got out a cigarette, so she went across the room and got an ashtray and handed it to me. It was full of cut toenails! I couldn't believe my eyes. Evidently, before I got there, she was busy cutting her toenails. It was a very stilted meeting. She was very much out of place.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: She was not a success.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: She wasn't up to the task. I think she was out of place. I think he probably did all right, but I don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: He was there for four years.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Was he? He must have done all right then,</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What else about Jeddah do you recall?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Square dancing.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who square danced?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: All of the embassy, I think. It was something to do. I guess we played cards. (I don't recall bridge there.) We had parties at each other's apartments. And there was a swimming pool on our compound.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you detect problems within the Country Team, any elements of the Country Team that weren't on board?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Nope. I thought we had good relations all the way around.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember being inspected there, by any chance?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think so. We were inspected I believe in Colombo.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I think it's time now to make that leap to Kigali.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes! Yes, indeed. . . . Were you afraid of my arrival in Kigali?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I don't recall being afraid of your arrival. Why?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: You seemed a little bit edgy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, sure. You had come from working for all the top ambassadors in the hemisphere, and I was at the bottom. No, I don't think I was fearful, but I was fearful about embarrassing myself dictating and that sort of thing. Because I'd never dictated, not really.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'll never forget your remark on the telephone. In Eugene, Oregon. You said that you had looked at my personnel record, and I had worked for so many high-ranking, important ambassadors that you couldn't figure out why I'd be willing to come to Kigali. I don't remember whether I said, “Mr. Ambassador, because they won't give me a job.”</p>
<p>No, they really wanted desperately for me to resign, because they could have hired three secretaries for my salary. And I couldn't get a raise. I was at the top. Do you know, two weeks before I retired, I got the eighth step on a Three? They waited that long. Instead of giving me a Two. They could be nasty sometimes. I earned every bit of that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, that was just as President Carter was getting started, after Gerald Ford.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Seventy-seven. Well, fortunately for this girl, an old Africa hand stationed in Washington at that time saw what they were trying to do to me. They were shafting me. And she took me under her wing.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was her name?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Mary . . . . not Rosemary. Nice person. Young.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't Mary Ryan, was it?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. But she saved my life. Because the next time I got a telephone call from Washington, it said they had news for me. They had Kigali, Rwanda or Conakry. I said, I'll take Kigali. And there was utter silence. Couldn't believe it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why? Because it was so remote and unimportant?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No, not many people wanted to go to either of those places. I did not want Conakry, so I chose the right one. And that's when she said, “That's interesting, because our ambassador to Rwanda happens to be in the department right now.” So they had you call me, after you had read my record. I don't know if you had all my record at that time. Did you have the Carl Sommerlatte stuff?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I don't think so.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: What a bitch he was!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you could have worked for Bill Harrop in Conakry or Oliver Crosby.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I didn't need it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Harrop was one of my great friends.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, I liked Harrop, what little I know of him. I think I chose the right one. And then they threw in that TDY. It was one of the good points about being assigned to Rwanda because the TDY included Johannesburg, South Africa. I would never have got to South Africa otherwise, and I loved it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That was before you arrived in Kigali.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. And the principal officer there was Mac [William McKinley] Johnson. We had sort of parted Canada on not too friendly terms. He felt I had done him dirt when I was on the selection boards [about?] his secretary. I wasn't there. I was out on the beach with Ambassador Handley. And the other members of the selection board wrote that he had not written a very good, substantive report on Mary Keim. Do you know Mary Keim? She was very well known in our Foreign Service. A very good secretary.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Is that K-i-m-e?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: K-E-I-M, I think. And he took exception to that. But anyway, we cleared things up. I was there for six weeks. Loved it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You got along well with him after you cleared the air?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes. He was a nice guy. Anyway, that's all about Johannesburg I can remember.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Then we go back to Kigali and the volleyball games, and the DCM.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I loved Kigali. That's one reason why I retired from there. I could leave with a very good taste in my mouth after 30 years in the Foreign Service. And that's the way to do it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What did you enjoy about Kigali?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: The people.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The embassy people or the Rwandan people?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Embassy people. Both. And especially the Tutsis.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You had Tutsi staff in your apartment?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. Our guard, our main guard, was a Tutsi. And I liked all the Tutsis in the embassy too.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the administrative officer when you were there? Was that Rick Kramer or was that Joe Sikes?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Rick Kramer. But I know Joe Sikes. How do I know him?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, he preceded Rick in Kigali.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Was he there when I arrived?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not sure.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh yes, Kramer came after.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Now, did you travel outside Kigali? Did you get up to Dian Fossey's camp?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. I deliberately stayed away because I did not want to do anything to alienate her. And it could happen just so easily. She stayed at my apartment when she stopped staying at the ambassador's residence.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Why did she stop staying at the ambassador's residence?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I think she found she was more comfortable in my funny little place. She would come down, she would be filthy dirty. Unkempt. She'd go in the bathroom and stay at least two hours, come out looking like a fashion model. I loved her. I think what happened to her is so tragic,</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get to know Rosamond Carr?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, sure, very well.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever visit her home?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes, many times.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: She had such a pretty place.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I ran across a picture of her place the other day and I couldn't believe my eyes. It was all overgrown with . . . I don't know what it was . . . ivy? All across the front.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How much did you have to do with government people?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'm afraid not enough.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The ambassador didn't have you making appointments for him?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, calling on the other ambassadors.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember dealing with the Russians, for example?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I can't remember Russians there.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You don't recall that they had a residence right behind our residence, separated by just a fence? We played volleyball a couple of times.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Did they come over? I don't recall that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe that's my imagination.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No . . .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were there others in the diplomatic community that you were in touch with?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I don't think we had a very active community, did we?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: The diplomatic community as a whole, not very. The Germans were there, the Brits and the French were there, and of course the Belgians.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. I wish the Belgians had managed to speak proper French. I couldn't understand them. And especially Ruth Median [Mrs. Eardley's predecessor as secretary].</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When did you encounter Ruth?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: She was there when I arrived.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: So there was some overlap?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah. I didn't appreciate it. I didn't need her.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the nervous one about your coming was Ruth.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, really??</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Sure. She knew that she was going to have a successor who was very accomplished.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I'm sorry.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: She was a very fine person. But she had something to worry about, because she was outranked!</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: We had some good times, I'll tell you. I wouldn't give that up for anything.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Any more of those good times you want to recall here?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, I spent quite a bit of time talking to other secretaries who were miserable. I said, “Look, you're guests in that country. Act like it. Learn the language. Get acquainted with them. And then you will reap the benefits.” I guess a lot of people thought I took it too seriously, but it was my life and my livelihood. And I loved it. Sometimes it was tough.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: But you never got shot at?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Oh, yes! In Chengmai. I also drove over a python in Chengmai.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I did that in Kinshasa too. It was the scariest thing! [Both laugh.] Well, do you have more to say about Kigali? Oh, you didn't talk about Ambassador Melone!</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
<p>EARDLEY: I liked him. I thought he was a nice guy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Was he a competent guy? Did he get along well with the Rwandans?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yes. And of course he was fluent in French. I liked Dominique [Mrs. Melone] also, except she did him wrong.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How so?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: She left him!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: From Kigali?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Well, she never did come to live there. I felt sorry for him.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know how an ambassador could live there as a bachelor.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Yeah, tough. But he had all of us, Judy Chidester [code clerk] — Also, Melone played bridge, and he enjoyed our company. You know, the swimming pool was at my apartment. He came over almost every day and swam.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Good for him! Did he have children who came to post?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: They had a daughter. I felt sorry for her too, because of this. Dominique just wanted to live in France, that's all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember Martin Brennan?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: Ah, yes indeed. I liked him and I liked his wife Efron [sic, phon.] What was her name?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Her name was Giovanna.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I called her Efron.</p>
<pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: She didn't object?</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: I didn't think so. I thought that was her name.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: [joking] Maybe he changed wives after I left.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: No. But he did something that he shouldn't have. He took a picture, or several pictures, of her giving birth. And showed them to everyone. I don't think he should have done that. Well, it's all right for their own privacy but not to show around the embassy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: A little bit indiscreet.</hi>
</p>
<p>EARDLEY: . . . .But I say, “Chacun � son go�t.” (Each to his own taste.) [laughs] I've pulled some awful things too, I guess.</p>
<p>[Mrs. Eardley passed away on June 4, 2008, at her home in Burlington, six weeks after this final interview session.]</p>
<p>End of interview</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>