<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000698">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Elizabeth Kennedy (Liz) Lion </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>ELIZABETH (LIZ) KENNEDY LION</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Jewell Fenzi</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: June 18, 1987</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What I am really interested in is how you spent your time
                        in Rio and Recife. There were very few people who the staff at the consulate
                        [in Recife] talked about, but the one name that kept cropping up was, “When
                        Liz and Donor Lion were here... When Liz and Donor Lion were here.” So you
                        really made an impression.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: We were there longer probably than others. We had two tours that were
                    interrupted by a year and eight months. So between the time we started and the
                    time we left was about seven years - no, well whatever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not to detract from your effectiveness in any way, but
                        could it have partly been because that is when the military took over, or
                        came back into power about the time you went....something happened around
                        that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, that was 1964, the revolution... That happened just as we moved to
                    Recife the first time. But also that was when the US was pouring lots of money
                    into AID in the northeast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is why you were there. Is that when they were
                        building all of those magnificent highways that are there now and things
                        like that? What was the thrust of the AID?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: They did build highways and a lot of infrastructure but they did a lot with
                    schools and I think they did a good bit with agriculture. Donor tried very hard
                    to get some land reform going with something called GERAN. And they had all
                    sorts of things worked out to compensate people who gave up land. But I think
                    the mistake that they made was that they did not take into the planning the
                    people who had the power.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who had the land to give up.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>LION: And I also came to the conclusion, and I have read since people who agreed
                    with it, that they [the Brazilians] will give up anything in the world except
                    land. And I don't know, you probably have opinions on that subject, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I was absolutely astonished when I went down to a
                        huge usina [sugar plantation], a feudal manor about two hours, not even two
                        hours, south of Recife... Lais Cabral da Costa was her name. Did you ever go
                        down there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was like something out of the middle ages.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Of course it is. They have their own schools, they have their own police,
                    they just [control] the entire lives of the people there. I think she told me
                    that they had 3,000 people living there. She also ran a creche to take care of
                    children of working mothers, the empregada[servants] who were working in
                    households. She had some sort of social conscience. At another usina they built
                    a school and a clinic and a recreational center with a pool for them, and they
                    had some housing they built, a little bit. But they also decided who was going
                    to be mayor of the town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:I think even if Donor had consulted them, people like that
                        family, I don't think they would have given up anything [land] to those
                        [workers]. As you say they are generous to a point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: It wouldn't have worked. They think that the system is right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's it. They don't think there is anything wrong
                        with the way things are.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I agree with that, and I don't know what's going to happen. Apparently a
                    communist governor has been elected in Pernambuco [state], or either mayor of
                    Recife in the last year or so. And my friends the Petribus apparently got pretty
                    uneasy about the situation. It seems to have settled down now. They want me to
                    come visit them in October. I am in frequent contact with them. They just sent
                    me a nice gift for Ann's baby.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, do they come up here occasionally.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, they visited me in my home, but they insisted on staying in a hotel.
                    They had just come to see me in Richmond.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you still do your bed and breakfast?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, I do. I have generally had a student living in the house, and I seem
                    to have people most of the time. I had a French professor all last fall, and I
                    had a young Quaker couple from January to March, I guess. No later, and the next
                    week friends of mine who were redoing their kitchen moved in - they didn't have
                    any water and lights and so forth - and they are still there. They're not making
                    much progress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When I stopped to visit you on the way to see my mother
                        and her college friend, you were in social work, and then how did you decide
                        to go into the Peace Corps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, I retired six months after I was sixty-five. And went into the Peace
                    Corps in January, 1984, and I returned at the end of my tour in March of '86.
                    And then most of '86 and several months of this year I was back working
                    temporarily at Social Services, where I worked before [in Richmond]. And then I
                    started working just half time there because I had intended to work at the Peace
                    Center when I came back. So I worked there mornings and worked at Social
                    Services in the afternoon.</p>
                <p>The Peace Center is seven or eight years old. It is a clearing house for peace
                    activities in Richmond. Richmond has lots of organizations that are connected
                    with peace in one way or another. From very conservative sorts to liberal ones,
                    Witness for Peace, for instance. They go regularly to Central America. But the
                    Ginter Park Presbyterian church, for instance, has been running a series on the
                    roots of violence and other things to do with the penal system and so forth, in
                    the mornings before the regular service on Sunday mornings. The man who actually
                    started the Peace Center is Methodist and Quaker. The secretary when I first got
                    there was Unitarian and the current secretary is Mennonite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Interesting combination.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: These churches are the predominant in our membership. But our newsletter
                    goes out to about 600 people every month. And Richmond is a fairly conservative
                    area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How can the Administration continue talking about Star
                        Wars and building up in the Middle East, how can they do that when I really
                        believe most people in the country are against what they are doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>LION: I know. Because that sort of person wants to be macho and needs an enemy to
                    keep things going that they want to keep going. I don't say that their
                    intentions are bad, they think they are right, as we think we are. But they're
                    organized, and all the peace groups are sort of splinter groups.But for
                    instance, the percentages in polls for nuclear freeze have been 60, 7even 80 for
                    years, years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was interested to see that the Soviets have put that
                        satellite up there to try to create solar energy because maybe they learned
                        something with Chernobyl. Maybe they have had this capacity - it's either up
                        or they are putting it up - and it will generate solar energy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: That sounds good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds great to me. I didn't mean to get that far off
                        on Peace, I wanted to ask you about Jamaica and your Peace Corps. Did you go
                        back to Jamaica and do in the Peace Corps more or less an extension of what
                        you had done while you were there with AID.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:There were two things I did when I was there as an AID wife. I taught people
                    who couldn't read and write, but it was actually adolescents. Mostly it was an
                    adult program but I taught the 15 year olds and up. And I did that four days a
                    week, I guess, but other times I worked several hours a week in Bankra Craft,
                    and it was run by a woman I got to like very much, Marian Skinner.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was the name of it again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Bankra Craft. It's a type of basket, and it also means load. It was started
                    for very poor women, who lived in lower Kingston, and had children and there was
                    just no - they had no income, and Marian Skinner started it. Well, she was there
                    within the first year. There was a group of about six or eight women that
                    started it, but only Marian kept on. For years and years and years it was only
                    Marian. She never made money from it, it only cost her money.She was Jamaican,
                    she was one of my heroines, so I went back to work with her.</p>
                <p>It isn't easy to go to a particular place in Peace Corps, usually they just
                    assign you somewhere. But Marian is very determined, and she kept on writing and
                    I kept on trying too. But she died two weeks after I got there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>LION: Yes. They had a Peace Corps volunteer there already, so there were two of
                    us. So actually it went very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually you had known from before what her goals were and
                        what she was trying to do, so it wasn't as if you just stepped into
                        something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:Well, the Peace Corps volunteer who was already there had been there a year.
                    And she was doing all the bookkeeping part of it and keeping track of whether
                    they were earning money or not, and things of that sort. And what I came in and
                    some of the things she did not do, was design and working with - some of the
                    women were very crabby and did not do good work, and what I did was establish -
                    they were paid, it was piece work entirely when I went there. But I added
                    quality to the way you arrived at what they were paid, which meant that you had
                    to judge every single piece, and you had to have in writing what you were
                    judging them on.</p>
                <p>And that took quite a while to get everybody on board. And there were two or
                    three who were really crabby and that took a long time, but we did get them so
                    that they wanted to do good work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your interest in handicrafts begin in Rio, or Recife,
                        or before that? Did it begin in Brazil and you took it to Jamaica?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I had an undergraduate major in art. And I had always taken little craft
                    courses here and there and I consider myself a jack of all crafts. And when I
                    got to Recife that was the first time I had ever worked with poor people to get
                    them to make saleable products. And I sold them for them, in my dining room, and
                    we had plenty of visiting firemen in those days that helped with sales. And
                    Recife, as you know, has wonderful crafts, and I think that they really got
                    recognized along about that time. Several Peace Corps volunteers worked with
                    crafts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have been early 60s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:Yes, right, mid-60s, 1964. And now I have seen guidebooks that talk about
                    Recife crafts, and there was a song about Brazil that talked about crafts in
                    Recife that I heard. I think it really is known now for that, and what I love
                    about Recife crafts, is that there are things that they have always done, many
                    of the skills, it's not something - you know, Jamaica tries very hard, and they
                    need to, but they have had all kinds of UN people and American and so forth
                    coming in teaching people how to do different things, and that sort of craft
                    doesn't necessarily last.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>And I've seen some wonderful designs from Jamaica, and then the people who taught
                    them leave and they just sort of fade away and get worse and worse. There are
                    certain things that Jamaica makes well, particularly their hamper baskets - they
                    make wonderful baskets - but a lot of the things are not native. Seaga has tried
                    very hard to get the crafts on a good basis, but I think their management has
                    been poor, because money has been POURED into it. They have lots of machines and
                    things and some of them are not used any more. For instance, they had a weaving
                    section that had many looms in it and while I was there it just folded. And the
                    pewter, they had a pewter section that made knives, forks and spoons, and some
                    other things out of pewter, and as far as I know that was very limping along,
                    almost closing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The thing that interests me, even though you were busy as
                        principal officer's wife in Recife, you had time to develop something that
                        you thought was worthwhile on your own, too. You weren't overwhelmed
                        by...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, I had lots of household help.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But that's it, we all had lot's of household help. I've
                        talked to several women who had the potential help that you and I had in
                        Brazil, in Africa, where ever, and couldn't come to terms with it and had a
                        terribly unhappy experience there, because I am sure that every day was the
                        white glove treatment. And finally all servants were banished and she did
                        everything herself. Of course, anybody who will come in and do my house work
                        for me is welcome.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:Well, I think that in poor countries you really should hire people, give
                    them work, even if they don't get paid very much, at least they get fed and
                    probably housed if they live in. I have no patience with people who... There was
                    a couple, he was hired as principal of the American School there, and they said
                    they were sort of Jeffersonian democrats, they wanted to do all their own work.
                    And I thought, this is really unchristian of them to not hire people when there
                    are so many people hungry. I think they didn't take my advice, as I
                    remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I just can't imagine in the tropics, when your house is
                        open like that all the time, my house was always dusty, no matter what the
                        steward did every morning, it was always dusty because winds blew through
                        all day long, and it wasn't air conditioned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Donor was supposed to have been kidnapped you know, so we had to have
                    people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, no, I didn't, tell me about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>LION: They apparently found the plans and everything like the night before he was
                    supposed to be kidnapped.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who found them? The police? Someone must have tipped them
                        off or something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I don't remember any more. They also had a safe house and they had written
                    a confession for Donor. And one funny thing about it was there was an American
                    girl, she was half Brazilian, half American, I think her grandfather had been
                    governor of one of the states, not Pernambuco, who was also involved, and the
                    police broke into where they were, shooting, and shot off a finger of her hand
                    or something and Donor, however, didn't want her being tortured or anything, so
                    he had somebody from the consulate visit every day to make sure. And she was
                    eventually exchanged for some prisoners in Algeria or something, I don't know
                    what. And her mother wrote Donor a very nice letter, thanking him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is a new twist on kidnaping and terrorism. That must
                        have been before C. Burke Elbrick was kidnapped. He must have been...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: It was about the same time. We were there during that time. He had just
                    been up to visit Recife and he was kidnapped the next weekend, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, really? So when they couldn't... When the plans to
                        take Donor were foiled...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: No, I think Donor was supposed to have been kidnapped after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As part of a series?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: We were during that kidnaping time is all I was saying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had never heard that in all my years in Recife.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I remember that we went to a party that night, it came out that day and we
                    went to a party that night, and I was a little shook, and normally at a party I
                    always visited with everybody and so forth. But that night I just didn't feel up
                    to it. I just talked to another American woman who was there because I just felt
                    sort of done in. I hadn't even wanted to go out, but Donor said that it was the
                    safest time of all, everybody was alerted at this point.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, and to show that you had confidence in the police,
                        in the community.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Of course, they wanted Donor protected because you see they were kidnaping
                    in hopes of getting some of their people released. So they would protect...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's why they kidnapped Ambassador Elbrick, isn't it,
                        because they wanted to trade him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, at any rate, in the newspaper the next day the society columnist
                    noted that I didn't circulate and only talked to an American woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you save all those clippings from the Di�rio de
                        Pernambuco (local newspaper in Recife)? About what you wore, and where
                        you...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Oh, no, not any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I saved them all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: You did?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:And you know what I did with them, I clipped them out and
                        put them in our photograph album, more or less with pictures we took at that
                        time, the pictures have nothing to do with the little squibs. My favorite
                        one was, I mentioned to somebody at a reception at the [governor's] palace
                        that I had sent home a copy of the Di�rio with the Carnival pictures because
                        I thought it was such a splendid way to show someone in the United States
                        what Carnival was like in Recife. Of course, the next day on their
                        equivalent of the Style page, it was in a box that “J�ia Fenzi had sent home
                        the copy of the Di�rio with all of the Carnival pictures.” It was sort of
                        sweet in a way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: There was one society columnist. I've forgotten what his name was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was his name? Isn't that awful!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: We made a real attempt not to be identified with the sociedade, and he got
                    real upset with us because we never invited him to any parties. And one time we
                    had an enormous party and did invite him and he didn't come. He sent somebody
                    who worked for him to the party, but you know, we didn't mind about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Guido also absolutely refused to get involved in it. But
                        there was a cute little reporter, Fernando, and he was assigned to the
                        consulate and he would call - was L�cia - Oh, I should have looked all these
                        names up before we started talking! L�cia who was Guido's right hand woman
                        and his commercial assistant...Fernando used to call her a couple of times a
                        week to find out what we were doing, and where we were going, and the one
                        thing I made him promise, and he was very, very good about it, I said don't
                        say that we're going, write about it when we come back. Because I said that
                        I don't want anybody to know that we're not there and it's only the guard,
                        who no longer had weapons at that point, their weapons had been taken away,
                        and by that time people were robbing with guns in Recife and machetes and
                        what have you. I said I don't want anyone to know that we are not there and
                        the guards are there alone. So write about it after we've come back. He was
                        very good about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Good. I don't know that we ever saved them. I don't even remember. We had
                    clippings to do with AID, but I remember one time that this reporter whose name
                    we can't remember remarked about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joao Alberto!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:No, that's not the one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you had another one before us, but Joao Alberto took
                        over exactly the same attitude and everything.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: He remarked that my dress was almost franciscana - so plain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were always being told that we were muito simples,
                        muito simples, which meant very homelike and unaffected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Unaffected is what it means, not homelike. It's a compliment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a compliment, well, just like yours was a
                        compliment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: No, it wasn't. You know St. Francis went around in rags all the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I know, but maybe it had come to mean
                        understated.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>LION: Well, that's what the surface meant, but I think underneath he was getting
                    back at me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't remember that they ever directly commented on what
                        I wore because it disinterested them so. It wasn't dripping with gold chains
                        and loud, big prints to make me look bigger than I already am.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, I thought the Brazilian women do an awfully good job of looking
                    beautiful at any age.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I couldn't get into the dyed hair. I just refused to dye
                        my hair.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, I color my own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But yours is tastefully done. It's not raven, black.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: No, I leave a little gray, a little irregularity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you obviously had a good time in Recife.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I had a wonderful time. I loved it, I loved it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was exhausted all the time, but really it was great fun
                        in retrospect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: And our predecessors, the consul general there, her attitude was that it
                    was really a hardship post and what everybody should do was to take care of the
                    poor other wives. And I had a ball, I loved Recife. You know I also wrote a
                    little book Beira Mar, the little book I wrote and illustrated (about shells and
                    sea life).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You always had the interest in crafts. You had a minor in
                        crafts in college, is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I had a major in art. And I always took every little craft course that I
                    could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually, there weren't very many crafts in Rio, were
                        there, as there were in Recife?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>LION: I think Recife is more known for their crafts, but my daughter and
                    son-in-law lived in Brazil year before last, in Brasilia and Rio, and they have
                    loads of beautiful things, many crafts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go back. You had an art major and you always took
                        all of your crafts. I remember the last time we talked, you referred to
                        yourself as a “jack of all crafts.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: That I am.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you took that interest to Recife. I had just asked
                        you, although you had that interest in art and crafts all along, was, in a
                        way, what you did in trying to get the rather impoverished women some sort
                        of income in Recife, was it both an extension of AID work in Brazil, plus a
                        development of your own interest in crafts? This is when you told me you
                        were a social worker and a bleeding heart.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: A social worker by profession and bleeding heart by temperament.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. So where did the crafts fit into this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, crafts were a great way to help poor people get some income.
                    Generally, I worked with people who already were doing something or other. In a
                    few cases, I taught people to do a craft from scratch.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the women doing in Recife — the embroidery and
                        the appliqu� and lovely towels and tablecloths and napkins and things, or
                        did you teach them to expand on a craft like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: The one woman that I worked with a lot was Maria Jos� Neponucena.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Neponucena. Do you have any idea how to spell it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, she didn't know exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm not surprised.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: But Neponucena is good enough. Sometimes she would call it Neponucena, but
                    I saw Neponucena written occasionally. I never saw the other, that's my
                    recollection, at any rate.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was she, exactly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: She is quite well-known. She did woodcarving. She worked entirely in wood.
                    She started out when she was very poor, making knives and forks and spoons for
                    people to use as cutlery, and almost everything she ever made had a utilitarian
                    purpose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, she made those for people in the favelas to use as
                        cutlery?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For people to buy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: She just walked along the residential streets and knocked on the door. That
                    was my impression. She made me some of the knives, forks and spoons, samples of
                    what she had done early on. They're very nice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The lovely woods they have there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes. She used dark wood on the handle part, appliqu�d to the handle, and
                    lighter wood for the functioning part of the cutlery. Very nice. I think the
                    first things she became known for were the wooden chickens that came apart.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I think that the tail was a spoon inside, and it was used for farofa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. And I sent some of those home.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: They're very well known. I've seen them in magazines from Brazil, and I
                    think she generally had more orders than she could fill. She made every sort of
                    animal, finally, for containers. What else did she make?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if she was up in the old slave market in Olinda?
                        Did you go there when you were back in Recife?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>LION: Oh, lots of times but that's not where she was. She lived outside of
                    Recife, I believe. I should have prepared this and looked up some of these
                    things. When I first met her, she was on an abandoned sugar mill, and I don't
                    know where the owner was; he lived in town or something. But she told me one
                    time, she was inviting me to come again, “sou euo que manda” — “I who order.”
                    But I think she was eventually ordered out. I don't know if somebody bought it.
                    But she, by that time, was able to buy a house in town, in Jaboat�o, where she
                    lived, and a refrigerator, when I was there. When I went back to see her she was
                    employing other people. She always put color on the things that she did, and she
                    had so many orders that she would have to hire other people. She did have one
                    man working for her that did turning, which really wasn't her thing. He made
                    wooden candlesticks and sometimes colored those. The colors were perfectly
                    lovely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was she able to keep up the quality of her craft? One of
                        the things that happened in Tracunh�en, for instance, when Maria and Nuca
                        made those marvelous lions and giraffes and things, was that, there again,
                        they had so many orders that they couldn't fill, and so they started
                        bringing in their nephews and what have you, and immediately the quality
                        went down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes. Well, her quality went down, too. She became allergic to the paints
                    and the varnish that she was using, shellac, whatever it was, her hands would
                    break out, and she also got very depressed. I went back to Recife twice and
                    visited her both times. She moved to Sao Paulo to be with her daughter. I sort
                    of lost contact with her, so I'm not sure where she is now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But she was one of the people that you were able to help,
                        or was she started already when you arrived in Recife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: She was started already, but we sold a lot of crafts in my dining room,
                    because I kept the things out with prices on them and so forth. And whenever we
                    had visiting firemen, it was much easier for them to buy there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How nice!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: We sold really a lot of stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were doing these visiting firemen a favor, too,
                        because you probably didn't have the Casa de Cultura in those days, did
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: That was the old [prison]. No, they did not have that then.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that opened shortly before we arrived. Of course,
                        that was marvelous, because sometimes you could take a visiting fireman over
                        and just turn him loose, and say, “The driver will be back at such and such
                        an hour.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: That's a wonderful place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I never got tired of going through there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I loved it myself. I just loved it. Well, I had fixed prices, too, and
                    maybe they would like what I selected, and I could oversee the quality.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:So you probably did save them a lot of time, because you
                        had quality things, and at Casa de Cultura you did have to wade through an
                        awful lot that you weren't interested in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, they had a lot of wonderful things there, and the prices were
                    wonderful. Actually, I was told that the prices were fixed there, too. I'd
                    forgotten that. And I do remember one time, though, that Helena Petribus tried
                    to bargain with somebody and they would not bargain, and I was glad they
                    wouldn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So starting with the woman who worked with wood, then you
                        also worked...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:Actually, that isn't where I started.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I'm just remembering now. The first time we were in Recife, there was a
                    young man — how did I — I found out that he was a very good wood carver.
                    However, he was in the Casa de Detenc�o, which was still a prison then. I went
                    around and looked at all the wooden fruit that different people had, different
                    wives who had other posts, and the nicest fruit was from the Philippines. So I
                    got them to making that, and it was great for the Casa de Detenc�o because it
                    required a great deal of time to make the fruit nicely, and they had plenty of
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Plenty of time!</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>LION: They loved to put varnish or shellac on it. Finally I said, “I'll pay you
                    45 [whatever it was] for the ones without varnish, and I will only pay you 30
                    for the ones with varnish.” They never put on another coat of varnish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good for you! Not a drop of varnish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: And the quality was beautiful. One of the former inmates took to selling
                    them all over Recife, and they sold extremely well. But when I went back to
                    Recife some years later, they were nowhere. One of the reasons, I think, was
                    that the wholCasa de Detenc�o was moved way outside Recife and I don't think
                    they had any way to get the stuff back and forth easily.But I learned another
                    thing, which was that if you introduce a craft that's not indigenous, that
                    doesn't have roots there, it will probably die when you leave. There were
                    excellent Peace Corps volunteers in crafts in Recife when I was there. One of
                    them did wonderful cloth animals; another did black pottery, which wasn't very
                    strong, however; weak, in fact. It got black by putting in leaves when you fired
                    it. The other Peace Corps volunteer — there were two couples and a single
                    volunteer — was smart, he bought stuff that was already made from all the people
                    all around, and helped them. Whereas the other couples tried to start new
                    crafts, which were absolutely nowhere to be seen. Also, there were really nice
                    batiks when we were there. They faded after a while but the taste was very good,
                    the colors were nice, the designs were of everything Brazilian, though I
                    wouldn't call them Brazilian designs. Then they too totally disappeared.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know, they weren't being made in Recife when we were —
                        they were coming up from somewhere else.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:To what do you attribute the lack of a craft that has some
                        momentum when it's started by a volunteer but that dies when the volunteer
                        leaves? Why couldn't the Brazilians, if they were making money on it, why
                        couldn't they realize that, if they kept it up, I wonder?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I believe that lack of management skills is a really big thing. But the
                    couple that made the animals said that they could do the work beautifully, and
                    it was beautiful work; but I guess they really rode hard on their people to do
                    everything perfectly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Quality products.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>LION: But they said that there was so much fighting among the people who worked,
                    and it was a cooperative, I guess. So much fighting about who would be — I don't
                    know, the leader, whatever; that they felt that it would fail on that account.
                    But the wife of the governor, when she saw those animals, which I thought were
                    spectacular, said, “A child would be afraid of those.” They were quite
                    contemporary design, and in fact this nice young couple copied them out of an
                    American book. The girl's father had started the New York Craftsman's Guild, or
                    something and she was very “into” American design, I guess. But I do think the
                    best thing the Peace Corps volunteers or anybody could do, helping out in
                    crafts, would be to help them improve their quality and maybe their sources of
                    raw material or find new sales outlets. But the thing you have to be really
                    careful about — that I think people in that situation have a hard time doing —
                    is not to be the manager, not doing things for people and then trying to train
                    them to do what you were doing. I don't think it works very well.</p>
                <p>In Bankra Craft — that's where we made the dolls, in Jamaica — they got a lot of
                    help off and on but they had a Jamaican woman there from the outset, for about
                    l2 years. She died; that's the only reason she wouldn't still be doing it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned her, Marian Skinner?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Marian Skinner. But they did get a lot of designs over the years from
                    different people, and they're still using them and still making money off of
                    those designs. So that part was good. That worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really cut your teeth on helping the poor make
                        money with their handicrafts skills in Recife. And so then when you went to
                        Jamaica, how did you get involved when you were the AID director's
                        wife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I started out teaching in JAMAL, a program for illiterate adults. From
                    there I was referred to Marian Skinner because they knew I was interested in
                    crafts. I worked about one afternoon a week with her — did drawings, wrote down
                    steps of production, costing, etc. Marian and I have kept in touch. She came to
                    see me a couple of times and I saw her when I returned to visit Jamaica. Then
                    when I entered Peace Corps I asked to be sent there.It required considerable
                    persistence to get in, I guess I wore them down. Persistence was the quality
                    that got you into Peace Corps. I was glad they told me that! Otherwise, I might
                    have concluded they didn't want me. I was tempted to use some connections but I
                    didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, you got in. You mentioned the lovely house you
                        had, as AID director's wife, with a swimming pool; and obviously a much more
                        active social life.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>LION: Well, the house I occupied as PC volunteer was perfectly acceptable; and my
                    landlady was very famous in Jamaica — Olive Lewin. Through her, I had contacts I
                    would not have had as AID director's wife. For instance, on Christmas morning we
                    breakfasted with the prime minister. It was he who gave away our daughter at her
                    wedding, he attended the wedding dinner in our home. I met many interesting
                    people through her, more than I met as wife. Marian was head of art and culture.
                    She started the Folksingers, who are very well known. I don't know what her
                    title is. She initiated the Youth Orchestra, started the Oral History Project,
                    and is supposed to have collected something like l,300 folk songs. She attended
                    the Royal School of Music, or some such school, the school for musicians in
                    England. She had received the highest marks ever reached in the Caribbean for
                    entrance at that school.</p>
                <p>Marian's father was a very well-known person in education in Jamaica, a close
                    friend of the prime minister (I don't recall his name) for some years. Marian
                    Skinner's sister was a folk singer, she knew of me and asked me to come stay
                    with her before I even met her. I felt well accepted as a volunteer. I feel that
                    when you're not working for pay and you really enjoy the country and have skills
                    to offer, the doors are open. I could have worked at a number of different sites
                    — indeed, I worked at four. Including in Kingston. I did some design work for
                    Allsides, a lot of work for Things Jamaican, and for Bankra: that was supposed
                    to be my main site. I worked at Women's Bureau a bit. I started the straw bags
                    at Operation Peace — they're still going pretty well — knock on wood!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you've now been back for more than a year. I hope I'm
                        not being facetious, but really, which was more fun — being a volunteer or
                        the AID director's wife?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Being a volunteer, I guess. I think that doing “your own thing”, if you
                    feel you're doing it well, and having some success, is more fun than doing what
                    you're supposed to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: More rewarding?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I'll buy that! Or if “rewarding” sounds too weighty, more exhilarating.
                    Sounds more elegant than “more fun.” Marian let me rent her car. Before I went
                    back to Jamaica, I had some uneasiness about the change from being AID
                    director's wife to Peace Corps volunteer. It seemed to me that I'd be standing
                    on a street corner in rain, waiting for a bus, my former friends would ride by,
                    and I'd hope they wouldn't recognize me. Perhaps they would not pick me up
                    because of my change in status. I have a little reverse snobbery in me, though!
                    For instance, I'd never buy an expensive car; I generally buy one a year old.
                    I'm like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where I come from, that's called Yankee practicality.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>LION: Yes. Well, I think I said earlier that I'm a Quaker, I belong to the Quaker
                    Meeting in Richmond. I'm not impressed by a lot of things to do with money and
                    position, unless the possessors earned those attributes themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So many of the people we dealt with in Recife really had
                        done nothing to earn what they possessed in life, had they? It had just been
                        handed down generation to generation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, well, particularly women. It doesn't apply to my friend Helena
                    Petribu, however. She did an awful lot for her people. And really, I knew a
                    number of women who were tremendously busy, who had strong social
                    consciousness.I worked with Ivanise Pessoa and with others on the board that
                    started the Community Center in a favela.</p>
                <p>I also worked with the Associa��o Crist�o Feminina, the YWCA. Ruth Hillis, you
                    know, was there from World War II on for a long time, then she was hired to come
                    back and establish this Community Center in a favela, which had classes for
                    women, day care, a dental clinic. I think they even had a family planning clinic
                    after a while, and a mothers' club.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I met Hillis. She had come down to run the hotel in
                        Mac�io. And what was the name of the woman, very, very wealthy, who'd been
                        married to someone who was — she'd married a vice consul who had quit. Their
                        name was Helena?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, yes. I would find that in some of my address books. She was very nice,
                    I liked her, but she was weird, very weird. Ruth Hillis was very nice to her and
                    supportive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. And the family's father came from Sweden, the name
                        was Scandinavian, and they made their money in gunpowder.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Oh, I didn't know that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. And the logo for the gunpowder was an elephant. I
                        think my husband would recall the last name. (they agree they'll probably
                        think of it shortly) But Ruth Hillis came back to run that hotel in Maceio,
                        which was being terribly successful, not with foreign tourists but from all
                        the Brazilians coming up from S�o Paulo, mainly. The reason she came back
                        was because her medical insurance wasn't valid outside the U.S. Worry over
                        possible catastrophic illness had brought her back.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>LION: Yes. Well, she's been doing very useful things in, I believe Arizona or New
                    Mexico, where she lives. She told me over the phone, “I find things that need to
                    be done and I do them, and I get people to help me.” I think that's one of the
                    best recipes for success. I would like to have it on my wall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now you have it, on tape.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Okay! She's a wonderful person, and a very simple person. Very bright, she
                    knew everybody, and she's totally fearless. But she could keep her eye on the
                    ball and get things done. She had no pretensions of dress, money, things like
                    that. She knew how to establish boards. I guess she established the AC[the YWCA]
                    there. And she taught generations of Brazilian women how to run organizations,
                    how to raise money, how to have board meetings, take minutes. And there are any
                    number of organizations spawned by people who were trained on ACF boards. If you
                    want to search for something successful, look at Ruth Hillis's training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think I mentioned to you when we talked earlier the two
                        people at the consulate who were cited over and over and over again were you
                        and Donor, and Ruth Hillis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: When we went to Recife the first time, she was due back. Everywhere I went
                    they'd say, “Ruth's coming back!” They loved her and she loved them. A wonderful
                    person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm getting back to Jamaica now. You said the house you
                        stayed in was closed up at night.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes: the lizards. They drive me crazy. A great many Jamaicans — mostly
                    women but some men, too — are scared to death of little lizards that don't bite.
                    They're not poisonous, they don't “do” anything, they're scared of you, too. I
                    don't understand it but the fear goes from generation to generation. Olive
                    Lewin's sister, a nurse, was living there then. She'd worked in Canada, lived in
                    England. She had the helper close all the windows in her room every day at dusk.
                    Everyone in the house did, except me. My room only had windows on one side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had no cross draft.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>LION: Right. Two things that would keep me from returning to Jamaica for any long
                    term would be the heat and lack of a car. Perhaps I should have gotten a fan, I
                    never had much faith in their utility, then. But another factor: Olive was very
                    economical. I would have been glad to pay for an increase in her electricity
                    bill. Frankly, I didn't live on my Peace Corps income. I had a little thing that
                    paid me $l75 a month and that I deposited in my checking account in the
                    U.S.Bankra always had a surplus in their account, or at least good credit, so I
                    could always cash a dollar check immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really lived as a guest in Olive Lewin's
                        house.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION:Yes. Of course, I paid rent. I loved having all my meals taken care of,
                    though they weren't usually what I woulhave chosen. Boiled vegetables, for one
                    thing — Jamaicans boil them all to death, with a bit of salt; that's all. No
                    vitamins left. Most Jamaicans don't care for salad, and if they do, it's only
                    shredded cabbage with a few slivers of carrot and no dressing.</p>
                <p>Absolutely delicious in Jamaica are the fruit drinks. Drinks are made out of
                    everything and they're universally delicious, all of them. Even out of some
                    really curious things like cucumber and pumpkin. They season them nicely, though
                    they insert a lot of condensed milk, whicstrikes me as improper — all that
                    sugar. But the drinks are delicious, especially the soursop.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about food. For instance, the Brazilians'
                        ambrosia.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes. If I had to name something that was ambrosia on this earth, it would
                    be theirs.And their fruit ice creams, particularly at Devon House in Kingston,
                    which I think are the best in the world, certainly the best I've ever tasted.
                    Brazil grows every sort of fruit. Their soursop is wonderful, and the guava, and
                    coconut, and many sorts of fruit. They also make some wonderful dishes. They
                    have a curry chicken, and curry goat not curried. I don't believe there's any
                    difference between “curry” and “curried,” it's just called curry goat. Also,
                    their pumpkin soup is quite good, and a sort of sauce they put on chicken or any
                    other meat — of tomato, onion, thyme, etc. which they use on all meats; very
                    tasty. Unlike their vegetables, the meat is generally flavorful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember, in Recife, if we were having, say,
                        visiting firemen from Brasilia, for just an informal lunch, if it were for
                        Brazilians, no vegetables: they just didn't eat them. Only rice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: They wanted the rice and beans and meat; maybe a little bit of kale. And,
                    like you, I loved the fruit drinks in Recife. They never had condensed milk in
                    them, just fruit juice with a little sugar.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We used to add water. I loved the names: pitanga, mangaba,
                        caj�, maracuj�, goiaba, graviola — they were wonderful names!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Graviola is soursop, isn't it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: When we were in Recife, graviola was not well-known, not much used. I
                    remember somebody gave us one once, brought from some place on the Amazon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We always had a pitcher of those juices in our
                        refrigerator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I loved the pitanga.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So did I, I liked the color of it, which is about that of
                        your blouse. The flavorings for the meats in Recife are cooked fresh every
                        day — all fresh, the coriander, onion, pepper, tomato. I was fond of
                        coriander already. We had it in Morocco. Did they use that in Jamaica,
                        too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Not that I remember. However, they could have included it in sauce and I
                    not have noticed, because actually, I didn't cook in Jamaica.A tree-grown fruit
                    is ackee, very beautiful. Jamaicans often make it a design motif. The fruit is a
                    lovely rosy red on the outside. The inside resembles scrambled eggs. There are
                    generally three very black, shiny seeds hanging on the ends. The fruiis
                    tripartite — three parts to its shell, three seeds, and three parts to the
                    fruit. If you eat it before it has burst open, some sources say, it may be quite
                    poisonous — some say it causes deaths every year, for instance of children who
                    can't wait to open and eat it. Such occurrences don't appear in the papers
                    because of reluctance to advertise them. A medical professional told me, “Oh no,
                    there are antidotes you can take if you have eaten it, it's not all that
                    dangerous.” But I often heard that it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was surprised to learn that casava has cyanide in it,
                        that it must be properly cured. I heard that animals in Brazil die if they
                        eat it. Those woven things that the Indians have —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, for squeezing the juice out of the grated casava.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have a West African post?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>LION: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We started in Sierra Leone, went from there to Cura�ao,
                        then to Brazil, and lastly to Trinidad. You're sort of southern, aren't
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would a southerner ever admit that their lovely cuisine
                        —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Had African strings?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Absolutely has African roots, because all the cooks were
                        the black slaves who had some from Dahomey [Benin] and Togo and Nigeria or
                        wherever. I thought one time of writing a book on the various African foods,
                        just those using plantains. What does a Venezuelan do with a plantain? A
                        Trinidadian? It's amazing, all the variations there are. Wouldn't that be an
                        interesting project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes, absolutely!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And our jambalaya, I'm sure comes from the West African
                        jollof rice, having made its way across the Atlantic. The Brazilian version
                        is marvelous.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Jambalaya is a New Orleans dish.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, but I'll bet you anything in the world it came
                        from —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, they consider that most of their things are French, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of them are, but many are —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: French or Spanish. The creole food, which is supposed to be a combination
                    by French and Spanish aristocrats.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, yes; with a little African slave cooking added. I'm
                        looking up the dishes' names.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>LION: I once lived in New Orleans, and it was there I first became interested in
                    cooking, although as a southerner I've always been interested in food.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm looking up the African — well, the moquecas, I love
                        that. It's Brazilian, basically a stew but it has oleo de dend�, palm oil,
                        in it. If you wanted to get some here, I'd call the Sierra Leone embassy and
                        ask them, or inquire of the Brazilian embassy where they get oleo de dend�
                        for their Brazilian dishes like bobo de camar�o.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I recall a dish of fish with white sauce that had oleo de dend� in it,
                    called vatap�.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And bacalhau —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Is that like vatap�?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, it's more like moqueca but it doesn't have — the
                        shrimp with coconut cream didn't have palm oil in it, but there was thick
                        coconut cream in all those dishes. But one of the things, perhaps I told you
                        — I went out to the Joaquim Nabuco Institute to talk to Dr. Mario Soto de
                        Maior in fear and trembling, because he was having a series of articles in
                        the Di�rio de Pernambuco about called “Our Local Cuisine is Dying.” You
                        know, no one was making vatap�. So in some anxiety I intended to say to him,
                        “Dr. Soto de Mayor, the reason is because they are so much work.” But what I
                        said was, “There's no reason why they can't be more or less adapted, or done
                        ahead of time.” I mean, I don't think any Brazilian cook in Recife ever
                        thought of doing her sauce or her bobo or the base for it a day ahead of
                        time. And I had a few words with my Josefa, and showed her that it could be
                        done so that she wasn't an absolute rag at the end of her day.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: What did Dr. Soto de Mayor say?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, he was so amenable I couldn't believe it. Gradually
                        I got so I would go out and see him again, which would add to the
                        credibility of my cookbook, and got from him a quote to put on the back of
                        the book if he said something about it. He and I exchanged recipes for
                        drinks. He had one that I must admit I filtered because it was so
                        evil-looking. It was one of his — you know, made of one of those liqueurs of
                        theirs, and it was the most evil-looking stuff. After being filtered it
                        looked like a urine sample. No one wanted to try it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Never mind! You could say apple juice, couldn't you?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, no, no you couldn't. It just looked like nothing
                        more than what you put through that little door at the State Department when
                        you were given your medical. But I'm talking too much: let's get back to
                        Jamaica...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One of the primary reasons I originally wanted to talk with you was because I was
                    so impressed with what you had done with your life after you were divorced, and
                    you've just proved to me you had a good time, you went back to Jamaica, you
                    built on what you'd absorbed as an AID wife. You've continued to grow and move
                    forward, and I think that should be set down.</p>
                <p>LION: Yes. I was able, also, to go back to work for the State of Virginia, in
                    Social Services; because social work is my field, you know. When you came down
                    to see me I was engaged in that. Within a couple of months after I got back I
                    went to work for the Richmond Regional Office. I had been working for the
                    Northern Virginia Regional Office before I went to Jamaica, and then I moved to
                    the central office, staying there until I entered the Peace Corps. Since coming
                    back I've worked there, mostly for half-days, for a little over a year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went back to work. A half-day is enough, isn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes. The reason I worked half-days is because I wanted to work half-days
                    also at the Peace Center; and I did a little work for Steve Hodges' political
                    campaign. But I can probably go back to Social Services. The jobs were
                    temporary, and indeed they've invited me back for another stint, but I had to
                    see about my daughter Ann's baby. I really am a bit bored here. As I mentioned,
                    I'm thinking a little of going back to Jamaica. So we'll see.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what capacity? What would you do? Because you're not
                        doing anything with crafts. Maybe that's your first love.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, I'm interested in working on Olive Lewin's Book of Songs, on which
                    she's dragging her feet. And then this craft anthology that the Prime Minister
                    wanted written, which hasn't gotten off the ground. I did do an outline of it
                    which everybody thought was very good. Both of these, particularly the music. I
                    don't know anything about music but I know the people, and I can push on it.
                    Maybe it would get done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if that goes back to — well, one of the problems
                        in the corporate world is that you're not necessarily given a project to do
                        so in a way permitting you to see it through to the end. It's justhat you're
                        always chugging away at something. I wonder if going back to Jamaica and
                        being able to work on a project and maybe see it through fruition doesn't
                        have more appeal than what you're doing now.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>LION: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe I'm oversimplifying.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, no, I think that's true. There are certain things that Social
                    Services — that I would like to do even as a volunteer, because they're not
                    being done properly and people would be glad to have me do them. It's just that
                    there's nobody sufficiently interested who will pursue them. The things that I'm
                    interested in there are not momentous, but they are things that I had a part in
                    and that I'd like to see finished. So I might even do that, might work for
                    nothing for Social Services.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In playing back our tape, you sound more southern than I'd
                        expected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I always sound more southern than I had hoped. I live in Richmond now. I
                    grew up in South Carolina but I haven't lived in the South for 30 or 40
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It interests me that you seem to build on your past
                        experiences, you profit from what you've learned, you use it and take it on
                        to your next — if you want to name it, passage in life. I'm interested to
                        see there seems to have been a certain direction in your life that you've
                        maintained. You went to Rio, then to Recife, you came back here, you went to
                        Recife, you went to Jamaica —</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Well, Oslo was the first post but I really didn't “do anything” in Oslo. I
                    can't remember anything useful that I did there. For one thing, it took a while
                    to get used to the cold, and the shopping — it was right after World War II. I
                    was much younger then. I recall being interested in one of their crafts but I
                    never did anything about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another of the women I've interviewed had had a tour in
                        Oslo and she said, “I didn't do anything in Oslo because the Norwegians did
                        it all and there wasn't anything to do.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: You know, she had a point there. Norwegians are a very “adult” and
                    competent people. I did learn how to ski a little bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an accomplishment. I'd think about the only thing
                        you'd do there would be to go out and help with some volunteer or charitable
                        thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>LION: Yes. I did work on the post report that we rewrote there. That's being
                    useful, I think. In Recife we did a post notebook, so-called. I think it's a
                    very helpful thing to newcomers. We said that the post report was what you read
                    before arriving at post but the notebook was on matters you needed to know after
                    you got there — such as hours that places were open, directions for finding
                    them, names of people including doctors that Americans used. I remember
                    converting fever temperatures from Celsius to Fahrenheit. The notebook was loose
                    leaf so we could periodically update it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The cover reproducing a woodcut is so attractive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I bought a few woodcuts there that enchanted me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I used your notebook as the basis for one we did called
                        “Welcome to Recife.” This is a project that needs to be updated and it's a
                        very worth-while project for women to take on. We found it so useful to hand
                        to VIPs and other visitors when they arrived. We had hoards of visitors —
                        security people, members of the embassy, Washington bigwigs, all presumably
                        looking over the situation in the northeast of Brazil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I think Recife ought to be a tourist town. It's a very interesting place in
                    South America — buildings in Olinda, the Casa de Detenc�o, all the crafts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. But even in the Oton Palace, which was the new hotel,
                        absolutely no one spoke English — not even the bellboys and desk clerks. And
                        we had several of those — oh dear, the Executive Service Corps, whom you
                        recall the locals call “the paunch corps.” And we had a number of women who
                        typically came down with their husbands for three months and who were
                        ensconced in this lovely luxury hotel. Many of them, knowing no Portuguese,
                        couldn't even talk to the bellboy, couldn't talk to anyone, since the people
                        they dealt with knew no English. There's a need to have the little man in
                        the street know some English, as is true in other developing countries.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As you well know, things didn't “work” in Recife. But they don't always work in
                    other places either. Ruth Hillis was doing such a superior job of running that
                    hotel in Mac�ifor tourists that maybe the foreigners will discover it in time.
                    Tourists were coming up, however, as pollution and overcrowding and other ills
                    affected the south of Brazil.</p>
                <p>LION: I understand the problem of flooding was partially taken care of. It
                    reached the second floor when we were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have pictures of the whole consulate gardens under
                        water. When we were there the usina [factory for processing sugarcane] was
                        still dumping chemicals into the two rivers, the Capibaribe and the
                        Beberibe, which were absolutely foul and black, killing all the fish. People
                        with all that money would spend nothing on pollution control. They did run
                        some tests up and down the Boa Viagen Beach, pretty far away from the
                        river's mouth, where we found a place to go that was rated as least
                        polluted.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: You know, it seems to me that so many of the rich South Americans think
                    they're very close to the United States because they're against communism. To
                    them, however, communism means enabling the poor to get even a tiny piece of
                    land. People in the U.S., you know, don't favor particular view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did Jamaica have the violence? Was it becausof the
                        huge, pressing urban problems in Kingston? Why did it have the violence that
                        some of the other islands didn't?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Frankly, I never really understood why. It seemed to be all in lower
                    Kingston, and between the two political parties. A lot of Jamaicans are
                    violently political. And it's true that Michael Manley and Seaga apparently
                    really hated each other, but I doubt either of them, certainly not Seaga,
                    favored violence. I don't understand it but purportedly 700 people were killed
                    during the election that took place in l979 after we'd left. Things were heating
                    up before we left in '78. Manley was a very good friend of Castro, you know, who
                    used to visit the island. The two of them would tour the island together while
                    Castro was speaking.I think Seaga is a very reasonable, nice, hard-working
                    person. Olive Lewin's family adored him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Obviously, there is the Jamaican elite, whose parents
                        studied in England, the lettered professional people. How large a portion of
                        the society are they? In Trinidad, for example, many people were white.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: A number of people in Jamaica told me that there used to be much better
                    relations between blacks and whites than is true now. My impression was that it
                    had to do with worsening of relations with the United States, as blacks in the
                    U.S. increasingly voiced wrongs they had suffered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you think our civil rights movement had adverse effects
                        there, evoked violence.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I'm all in favor of the civil rights movement, certainly, but now the
                    government is all-black — Seaga is white but I believe all the cabinet members
                    are black. Certainly they're dominant. Manley is probably about three-quarters
                    white, possibly more.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever feel afraid when you made your Peace Corps
                        rounds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: I never felt — well, officially it was held that the violence is not
                    against whites, nor Americans, it's the poor vs rich, or the really poor vs
                    people who are comfortable. Those that live in lower Kingston are desperately
                    poor. How they survive I don't know. Nor can I imagine how the Jamaican civil
                    servants manage to live on their salaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:Those are the people I feel sorry for in Recife, too.
                        They're just squeezed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Absolutely squeezed. One would think people could not live decently on a
                    Jamaican monthly salary, but they did. By practicing many, many economies. For
                    instance, watering down their liquid soap. They'd put a bit of it in an old
                    bottle, then fill it with water. I'm not sure the resulting liquid did the job,
                    one had to squirt so much of it. When I planned to paint a wall for Olive Lewin,
                    one of her friends insisted that I mix the water-based paint half paint, half
                    water. She also said she had put three coats on her walls. But in non-compliance
                    with her advice, I put on only one coat, non-watered-down paint.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The house boy who had been in our house when we arrived in
                        Recife had been very good. He was literate, and our predecessor had arranged
                        for him to step up in the world, to move into a white-collar job. It wasn't
                        four months till he came back. Josefa the cook said, “Ah! that young man
                        needs a good meal.” She sat him down and fehim. He simply could not live on
                        his salary as a typist in an office, his white-collar job. And of course
                        there was no place for him when he came back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Another example: Our servants had their refrigerator, we had ours. They never
                    threw anything away from our table, eventually it went out to people in the
                    street in the closest favela.Sometimes I went into their refrigerator and made
                    them throw food out because there would be fish that had been saved for five or
                    six days. I said, “You're going to kill those people!” All I needed was for
                    someone from a favela to die because they'd had a handout from the American
                    consulate residence!</p>
                <p>LION: Perhaps you've hearabout the AID business causing children to go blind? In
                    northeast Brazil the AID people gave away a lot of powdered milk. The children
                    grew so fast on it that they needed vitamin A supplement or something for their
                    eyes. I don't know whether they really went blind but some damage to their eyes
                    did result — because they hadn't had the supplements, because they were growing
                    too fast on the milk. The U.S. was severely blamed for “blinding all these
                    children.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another case of good will going awry.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>LION: Yes. To tell the truth, I think helping people in a way that helps them is
                    very difficult. I'm sure that with the best intentions in the world and billions
                    of dollars, we've done things that didn't help at all. Perhaps did the opposite
                    over-all. I don't know.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHICAL DATA</p>
                <p>Former Spouse: Donor</p>
                <p>Date Entered Service: 1952</p>
                <p>Left Service: Divorced 1978</p>
                <p>Posts: 1952Oslo, Norway 1964-67Rio de Janeiro, Brazil 1968-71Recife, Brazil
                    1977-78Kingston, Jamaica</p>
                <p>Status: Divorced spouse of AID director</p>
                <p>Date and place of birth: Nashville, Tennessee - September 11, 1918</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Kennedy</p>
                <p>Parents:</p>
                <p>Henry Lee Kennedy, lawyer (never practiced) road building firm, Handricks and
                    Kennedy</p>
                <p>Corinne Peale Kennedy, housewife, violinist, and vocalist</p>
                <p>Schools: * Winthrop College, U.S.C. * U.N.C. * Boston University * Louisiana
                    State University, Tulane</p>
                <p>Date and place of marriage: 1952, Oslo, Norway</p>
                <p>Profession: Social worker, Peace Corps Volunteer</p>
                <p>Positions held at post: Oslo* Contributed to notebook for new arrivals at embassy
                    Rio* Volunteer in Orphanage</p>
                <p>* Wrote resource booklet on charitable agencies where U.S. personnel
                    volunteered</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>* Helped draft constitution for embassy/AID wives' group and served as Board
                    memberRecife* Directed an employment service for domestics for USG personnel</p>
                <p>* Wrote and illustrated a book on marine life of the Beira Mar, Recife's coastal
                    waters</p>
                <p>* Sponsored and wrote the notebook for new arrivals at post</p>
                <p>* Served on Board of YWCA (Associa�ao Cristao Feminina)</p>
                <p>* Served as Board member for settlement house</p>
                <p>* Served as Board member for Women's Club</p>
                <p>* Worked with crafts, i.e., directly with craft producer, with committee on
                    crafts, sold crafts in my dining room to visiting firemen</p>
                <p>Honors: * Member of highest scholastic and honorary organizations as an
                    undergraduate * Meritorious Service Award, received from Mrs. Lincoln Gordon,
                    spouse of ambassador to Brazil * Commendation from Ambassador Frederick Irving,
                    Jamaica * Meritorious Service Award, Virginia State Department of Social
                    Services</p>
                <p>Children:</p>
                <p>Amy Lion</p>
                <p>Ann Lion Coleman</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
