<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000877">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with John R. O'Brien </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Information Series</p>
                <p>JOHN R. O'BRIEN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Hans Tuch </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: February 5, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Jack O'Brien was born in 1918 in Seattle, where he also
                        started his career as a journalist. He went from Seattle to Hawaii, where he
                        worked as a journalist, both as a reporter and as an editor until the
                        beginning of World War II in December 1941.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After the war, he suddenly—or maybe not so suddenly—got involved in the kind of
                    work that we are doing now, namely public diplomacy, and stayed in that work
                    until he retired from USIA. When was that, Jack?</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: 1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just by way of starting this conversation, I've always
                        felt that the whole impetus of public diplomacy, United States Information
                        Cultural Activities aboard, started out from two different sources. One of
                        them was the Cold War, really, with President Truman's “Campaign of Truth,”
                        in which he declared that the U.S. Government, the United States, must
                        project itself abroad in whatever way it can to tell other peoples about its
                        ideals and its own foreign policy in order to be able to oppose the efforts
                        of the Soviet Union and Communist countries to project their ideology on
                        other peoples. That's one source of our work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The other one, in my view, was the experiment that we undertook in the occupation
                    of Germany, Japan, and Austria, the experiment of trying to reorient and
                    re-educate an entire people toward democracy. We used all kinds of new
                    methodology, both in the way of information and cultural programs. In this we
                    were not always successful; in some areas we were successful. I think recent
                    history has shown that we were, in many respects, successful in this.</p>
                <p>At any rate, this was the other side of the coin that we practiced in what is now
                    known as public diplomacy. The first question I want to ask you, Jack, is how
                    did you get into this work. Tell me.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Having been brought up in Seattle, my outlook was toward the Pacific. On
                    the way to a job in Tokyo or Shanghai, I stopped in Hawaii to make some money.
                    By the time I had done that as a reporter and editor, Pearl Harbor changed plans
                    for all of us. So it was not until after the war that I was able to continue my
                    journey, as a civilian employee of the Army, in the occupation of Japan.</p>
                <p>The first job was rather routine, but as time went on, the job got better, and I
                    found myself becoming deeply involved in a most exciting enterprise.</p>
                <p>Japan Occupation: Civil Information and Education (CI&amp;E)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What specifically did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: The first part of it was to analyze the Japanese press and magazines.
                    That was routine. That developed into a job which was under the policy and
                    programs part of the Civil Information and Education section of the occupation.
                    This section of the occupation, SCAP, as it was called, Supreme Commander Allied
                    Powers...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was General MacArthur.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That was General MacArthur. The purpose of this section was to revise
                    the educational system in Japan and to preserve their arts and monuments, which
                    was well done by Ken Bunce, and to work with the Japanese Government in
                    explaining to the people the importance of their new constitution, their new
                    civil code, their criminal code, land reform, the range of astonishing
                    developments that took place in the late Forties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was in 1947-48?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Under the Supreme Commander, under General MacArthur, how
                        was that organized? You said Ken Bunce ran it. Was it an office of Civil
                        Affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, Ken Bunce was a branch chief. Civil Information and Education was
                    on the same level as other large parts of the occupation. We had the misfortune
                    of having as a chief a lieutenant colonel in the United States Marine Corps.
                    Nothing against him, but he was up against two-star Army generals, his opposite
                    numbers in other sections of SCAP. But he had been in Japan before the war and
                    was a competent enough guy.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>We had, then, the responsibility, as I mentioned, of working with the Japanese,
                    both their private and government groups, in explaining these tremendously
                    important reforms, and to win acceptance for them. Now, clearly, you simply
                    couldn't go out and say, “General MacArthur says you have to believe in this new
                    constitution.” We had to win Japanese support and develop with them information
                    programs involving all the media that were available, and they were all
                    available.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually what methods, what media, what programs did you
                        employ in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, as an example, the press, although technically under SCAP control,
                    was fairly free. It could not, obviously, argue against the occupation, but by
                    using our connections with the press, we would encourage interviews with people
                    who were free of a taint of the militarism of Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you, for instance, license editors to start papers and
                        have them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: No. The old Japanese papers were permitted to resume, including Akahata,
                    the Japanese Communist newspaper. Now, as I said, it was quite clear they could
                    not declare war on the occupation. They had to mind their P's and Q's on that.
                    But we had a determined policy that came from MacArthur himself—freedom of the
                    press short of saying that MacArthur is a bum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was, at that time, under the auspices of the U.S.
                        Army.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Approximately how many Americans were involved in this
                        kind of a major re-education program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, gosh, Tom, I don't know. I worked side by side with people in
                    uniform. Many then converted to civilian status. You'd be working with the same
                    person again. So it's hard to put a number on it. I just don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, if I remember correctly, the whole concept
                        of cultural centers, information centers, in Germany they were called Amerka
                        Hauser—in Japan, I don't know what they were called—also got started at that
                        time and became a very prominent element of this program.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>Our first effort was to strengthen their own libraries and to bring in books that
                    they needed. The actual cultural centers began, as I recall, after the
                    occupation, and as part of what USIS brought in. [Editor's Note. Before the
                    Occupation ended, the CI&amp;E section had established 24 libraries (Bunka
                    Senta) all local costs of which were financed by the Army from GARIOA, local
                    currency accounts controlled by SCAP. American center directors, books, and
                    vehicles were supplied by Army appropriated funds. These 24 centers were taken
                    over by the Department of State's U.S. Information and Education Office
                    (USIE—the predecessor of USIA) when the peace treaty became effective on April
                    29, 1952. Abroad USIA installations are called USIS.]</p>
                <p>Success of Occupation Program: Role of Information and Education Effort</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you evaluate this overall effort? Do you think
                        it largely contributed to the democratization of Japan, or was it, in a way,
                        tangential or inconsequential to the overall development of the new
                        Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, I'm clearly prejudiced. I think that it was a remarkably
                    successful occupation, one that you only need to turn to the Wall Street Journal
                    any day and see how successful Japan is economically. We find that their
                    democratic system works, there are honest elections, there's a vigorous free
                    press. Land reform has certainly taken root. We introduced reforms that have
                    become permanent. Now, the constitution is referred to from time to time as
                    imposed; that's correct. But it hasn't been thrown out. When we take a look at
                    Japan's recovery and its power today, I think we have to say the occupation
                    deserves some credit for innovation, for ideas that won acceptance by the
                    Japanese. They could not be imposed; they had to be sold to the Japanese. They
                    were sold, and I give them much of the credit, clearly. So I look back on a
                    joint enterprise with pride.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you agree with me in what I said at the beginning,
                        that I thought that these activities that we carried on in Japan—and, of
                        course, in Germany, too—were among those that really started this whole idea
                        of public diplomacy blooming, as far as the U.S. Government was
                        concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: I think that's a fair conclusion, Tom. We certainly learned much in
                    Japan that had validity later when the peace treaty was signed. But there was a
                    momentum created in that period, because in Japan, we were clearly dealing with
                    dynamic people, people of great intelligence, determined to get back into the
                    mainstream of world society. As one of my Japanese friends said, “We want to get
                    back to dealing with respectable people.” They had been cut off so long that
                    they were hungry to get back into the mainstream. This is where, in my job, I
                    found myself increasingly becoming a bridge between Japanese groups, who were
                    out of touch with people in America. The United Nations was the first example.
                    The Japanese were eager, eager, eager from the beginning of talk about the U.N.,
                    to become a part of it. They saw this as a return to decency, and I found myself
                    swamped with requests for information about the U.N., set up a relationship with
                    Wilder Foote, who then was Press and Publications chief at the U.N., and with
                    American groups, private groups that were supporting the U.N., all of which the
                    Japanese would have done in due time, but they were out of touch with much of
                    the rest of the world. So it was in that sense that we were a bridge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had experience with Japanese people and Japanese
                        culture. Was it difficult for an American or Americans who had entirely
                        different history and different cultural experience to relate and be able to
                        work with Japanese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, of course. Of course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that resolve itself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, you simply had to rely on good interpreters, in many cases, or on
                    Japanese who had lived abroad. It would be a truly arrogant American, with the
                    exception of those who were perhaps born in Japan, who would say he understood
                    the Japanese and their reaction to all things. So, sure, that cultural barrier,
                    the language barrier was always there, but that didn't discourage us, because
                    both sides were willing to try to make it work. This was the key to it. The
                    Japanese saw it was in their interest to make it work, and that was the big
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did we never broadcast in Japanese on the Voice of
                        America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: We did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did this start?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: It started just after the war. Yes, and went on until—oh, it was the
                    Fifties when it was decided that the Japanese had such an astonishingly
                    effective radio system of their own that we weren't reaching much of a market.
                    We had at the time, also, to bring each year from Japan the latest announcers,
                    because the Japanese language was changing. And so we had to constantly improve,
                    but it finally became a budget victim. Q: When?</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: I would say about the late Fifties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is there anything else that you find significant that you
                        would like to mention about your Japanese experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Roger Baldwin, who was founder of the American Civil Liberties Union,
                    was brought out to Japan by Douglas MacArthur. An unlikely combination, isn't
                    it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Absolutely.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: MacArthur—people can find fault with him in many, many ways, but he was
                    a liberal in the sense that he wanted to have the Japanese people become aware
                    of civil rights. Baldwin came out and worked mainly with the legal section of
                    the occupation. Then there was this job of trying to explain who he was, what he
                    was doing, what his thoughts were, how they might apply to Japan. That fell in
                    my lap, and it was a wonderful experience. It was curious that Roger Baldwin, a
                    very well educated and sophisticated man, had to be convinced that the Japanese
                    did not attach as much importance to the rights of the individual as they did to
                    the rights of the family, but he learned that you had to convert the idea of
                    civil liberties into a different context in Japan, and to relate it to the
                    family importance. Roger and I became good friends, and we continued our
                    friendship when I came back here. Norman Cousins came out. He was editor of
                    Saturday review then. I forget how I happened to get in touch with him, but he
                    was looking for a woman named Shizue Kato, who, before the war, had been a very
                    active feminist and a peace leader in Japan. Through some Japanese friends, we
                    got Norman in touch with her. There were many other people of such caliber who
                    came through. They were often turned over to us because we had the connections
                    with the press, with other media, so they could pass on their message.</p>
                <p>The Indonesian Experience</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's close off with the Japanese experience and possibly
                        go on to something else. Your next foreign assignment, Jack, was Indonesia,
                        where you were the public affairs officer, in this case the country director
                        of USIS program. By that time, we had USIA and we had a fairly regular type
                        of organization and program in Indonesia. Am I correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about something that particularly you found of
                        great interest in Indonesia at this time. First of all, let's get the dates
                        down.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: I went to Indonesia in '53 and left in '56. I was there two-and-a-half
                    years. I had been absolutely enchanted by Indonesia when I went through the area
                    as Far East branch chief for IPS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Press Service. O'BRIEN: Yes. The country was just
                        overwhelming—13,000 islands, over 100 million people. Communications
                        problems of the first order, but again a willingness to hear from the
                        outside, a desire to. We had a first-rate library in Djakarta, we had
                        branches in Surabaya and in Medan. Surabaya is in Java; Medan, of course, is
                        in Sumatra. Then we opened one later in Padang, also in Sumatra. We had
                        active exchange programs, a very good use of our material by the press, and
                        we turned out a monthly magazine which we had printed in Holland for
                        financial reasons. There was a fairly good staff, but it was hard, frankly,
                        to get first-rate local employees. English was a problem. We could get those
                        who spoke Dutch fairly well. But we, nevertheless, got some good ones. I
                        would describe the program overall as being rather soft. There was no market
                        for vigorous anti-Communist material.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was when Sukarno was President?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That's correct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the government put restrictions on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Not directly, but as an example, if our publications went out of line,
                    I'd get a call from the foreign office or someone else saying, “Let's not get
                    into that subject.” But overall, you had to sense how far you could go. A couple
                    of interesting developments during that time. Ted Streibert had become, as you
                    know, the first director of USIA, and I believe it was his first trip overseas
                    in that capacity that brought him to Indonesia.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Ted brought with him a packet of books. This was during the period of the Army's
                    campaign to promote people's capitalism, and he wanted to present the books to a
                    ranking Indonesian official. I arranged for us to call on the foreign minister,
                    a rather gentle, shy Javanese gentleman, who was pleased to receive us and
                    pleased to receive the books, which Ted explained very carefully—the man
                    understood English quite well—that it reflected an idea about America that was
                    not commonly known overseas, and he hoped that the foreign minister would find
                    time to read some of the books. The foreign minister thanked him and said to
                    Ted, “I wonder if I may make a suggestion about this program.”</p>
                <p>And Ted said, “Why, by all means. Please give me your ideas.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, I just don't think that our people will understand the term
                    'people's capitalism.' It's not a phrase that we're familiar with and it doesn't
                    translate well into Indonesian.” He said, “Perhaps some other term could be
                    used.”</p>
                <p>Streibert said, “Golly, I'm glad to hear you comment on this. What would your
                    suggestion be?”</p>
                <p>The foreign minister said, “Well, maybe a term something like 'New Deal.'”
                    [Laughter] Streibert, a card-carrying Republican if there ever was one, looked
                    at me as if, “By golly, what kind of trap have I fallen into?” He sputtered and
                    said, well, he didn't think that was quite appropriate for this administration.
                    I had to explain later to the foreign minister the meaning of New Deal in the
                    United States. It brings to mind, Tom, some of the other campaigns that we had
                    over the years. You remember at one time we had one called “Philippines:
                    Showplace of Democracy.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Then we had one called “Militant Liberty.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Then we had one called “Atoms for Peace.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: These were . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Open Skies.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: “Open Skies.” Well, this reflects the American desire to capsulize these
                    ideas and concepts as they do on Madison Avenue. Which reminds me that at a
                    later date, when Ed Murrow became director, and he was on the Hill trying to
                    explain to a congressional committee that we were not in the business of selling
                    soap. Little did he know that at that very minute, his man in Bangkok, Jack
                    O'Brien, was selling soap, in effect, because Lever Brothers, which manufactures
                    various products in Thailand, was using messages that we had devised on the back
                    of their soap packages. [Laughter] And so around the country you could see Lever
                    Brothers soap selling a program originated by USIS. Anyway, unfortunately, Ed
                    died before I had a chance to tell him that story.</p>
                <p>The 1955 Bandung Conference</p>
                <p>In Indonesia, also, I'd say the high point when I was there was the Bandung
                    Conference of 1955. This was the Asian-African Conference of some
                    consequence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a Third World conference.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Yes, and it brought such people as Nehru and U Nu and Zhou En-lai, a
                    really impressive gathering. Our instructions were to stay the hell away from
                    it. It had absolutely nothing to do with the United States, we were not to
                    become involved in it in any sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: '55. And so that was the word, a joint message from State, USIA,
                    everybody else: “Stay away from it.” Well, there was one little problem—American
                    reporters were pouring into the place. There was never any hotel space in
                    Djakarta anyway that was any good; it was always a tight situation. So a man
                    named Roeslan Abdulgani, who was the ranking career man in the foreign ministry,
                    called me up one day. He said, “Jack, old friend, I've got a problem.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Now, Roeslan, what's your problem?” Roeslan Abdulgani had been giving me
                    some bad times in the past about getting American correspondents in, so I was
                    going to milk this for all I could.</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, some of your people (trying to put the blame on me), some of your
                    reporters are coming to the Bandung Conference, and we have room for them at
                    Bandung, but we hadn't realized that some of them want to stay at least
                    overnight in Djakarta, and we simply have no room.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I'm not in the hotel business, Roeslan. What do you want me to
                    do?”</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>“Oh,” he said, “come on now. Some of you Americans have big houses, and maybe you
                    could squeeze them in.”</p>
                <p>Well, I said, “I've got to get permission from the ambassador to get involved at
                    all. You know this is not our party; it's yours.” So I went to Hugh Cumming, who
                    was the ambassador, and he said, “Well, I'll try to find out.” So word came back
                    in a day or two that PAO O'Brien and press officer Jerry Donohue would be
                    permitted to meet the planes coming in, to try to assist American
                    correspondents. So Jerry and I did that, and there were a lot of them. My wife
                    went literally door to door to Americans and said, “Have you got a mattress or
                    anyplace you can put up these guys?” And I would call from the airport—once in a
                    while the phone would work—and say, in effect, “Put more water in the soup,
                    because we've got extra guests that we didn't know about.”</p>
                <p>Well, among the correspondents who came was one Adam Clayton Powell.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Congressman Adam Clayton Powell at Bandung</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: He was Congressman Adam Clayton Powell from New York State, and he sent
                    a wire in advance, saying he did not—repeat not—want to be treated as a
                    congressman, but as a reporter for the—I've forgotten the name, some paper in
                    Harlem. So he came in on a plane that was owned or leased by Carlos Romulo, then
                    the foreign minister of the Philippines. Powell got off the plane, a very
                    impressive, big guy. I introduced myself, and he said, “Where's the
                    ambassador?”</p>
                <p>And I said, “Well, sir, we had instructions from Washington saying you did not
                    want to be treated as a congressman. You're being treated as a correspondent,
                    and therefore you are being met by the public affairs officer and press
                    officer.”</p>
                <p>“Take some notes,” he said. He wanted me to arrange a party for all the press
                    people, he wanted me to send a telegram to President Eisenhower saying that he'd
                    arrived safely and everything was under control, send a personal message to his
                    wife—at that time, it was Hazel Scott, the wonderful jazz pianist. And so that
                    was the beginning of my association with Adam Clayton Powell.</p>
                <p>Well, he went up to Bandung, and he was on the phone every night. We soon got to
                    be on a first-name basis. For some reason, he wanted to get copies of Esquire
                    magazine, which in those days, I guess, was sort of the Playboy of its day. If
                    we ever got it at all, it would come in about a year later by schooner.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>Anyway, he was really after the liberation of four or five American pilots who
                    had been downed in what we then called Communist China. So one day, at a
                    screening of some kind at Bandung, Adam Powell arranged to seat himself next to
                    Zhou En-lai, and to make a pitch for the release of these American pilots. Zhou
                    En-lai heard him for a while, and then he turned to him and said, “No speak
                    English.” Zhou En-lai spoke English as well as Adam Powell did. [Laughter] So he
                    didn't score well on that one, but when he left Indonesia, I saw him off, he in
                    Carlos Romulo's plane, and I was not sorry to see him go. He'd been of no help,
                    though I had come to like him personally. So he was in the plane, and the
                    propellers were revved up, ready to take off, and I said, “Now, Adam, you've got
                    all your papers?”</p>
                <p>He felt around and said, “Oh, my God, I've lost my passport.” Well, I had
                    happened to see Adam Clayton Powell with a local woman, and he was showing her
                    his passport, apparently to let her know where all he'd been.</p>
                <p>So I raced back into the airport, and there this woman did have his passport, I
                    snatched it from her and took it back to Adam, put it in his pocket. He fastened
                    his seatbelt. I lied and said, “Adam, come back anytime, really. You should see
                    more of the country.”</p>
                <p>A month or so later, an article appeared in a magazine in the States in which
                    Adam Clayton Powell criticized the American embassy for not giving him proper
                    treatment during the Bandung Conference. I never saw Adam Powell again, and I
                    didn't want to. But the Bandung Conference was an important gathering, and it
                    set in motion a lot of activities around the Third World.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the USIS operation at that time and the administration
                        of Ted Streibert in the late Fifties a sort of normal operation, the type of
                        which we have now in our major countries, major country posts?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: I think so. It was limited, as I said earlier, because there were
                    certain political boundaries you had to observe. There was no point in coming in
                    with a heavy anti-Communist dose; it would not have been accepted, nor would it
                    have been permitted. But there were a number of things you could do. There was
                    always a great interest about the United States, and you could build a lot of
                    activities around that. Our library was first-rate, and indeed, it was drawn
                    upon heavily by government officials. We had good relations with the press. Yes,
                    I would say pretty much from what I understand is going on today, it was a
                    normal program.</p>
                <p>The Exchange of Persons Program</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have an exchange program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Martha Graham Troupe in Indonesia</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, yes. It was active. One of the most successful exchanges we ever had
                    was when Martha Graham and her people came to Djakarta. Martha Graham was an
                    absolute whiz, a wonderful woman who did exactly the right things. She made
                    clear to begin with that she had drawn heavily on Javanese dancing in creating
                    her own modern dance. This, of course, struck just the right note with the
                    Indonesians. She gave demonstrations and seminars and all that. A guy named
                    Charlie Tambu was editor of the Times of Indonesia, an English-language paper,
                    and he just loved to pull the eagle's feathers. It was just before Martha
                    Graham's visit that John Foster Dulles declared that Goa should not be returned
                    to the Indians. Well, this outraged Tambu. I had dinner with him one night at
                    our house, and I mentioned that Martha Graham was coming. He said, “Why do you
                    bring these silly dancers out here? We don't care about that. Bring us somebody
                    that's important.” I said, “Charlie, she's pretty good, I hear. Let's see.” So
                    when she came, I made a point of inviting Charlie and his wife to the
                    performance, and we had a late dinner at our house after the performance. I
                    invited the Tambus and arranged for him to sit with Martha Graham. It wasn't
                    more than ten minutes later that I looked around, and Charlie had his face in
                    his hand, and he was looking up admiringly at Martha Graham; she had absolutely
                    enchanted him. She knew a lot about Islam, and she was talking about that.
                    Charlie, in a couple of days, had an editorial in his paper, “Why can't the
                    United States Information Service bring more people like Martha Graham here to
                    Indonesia?” the editorial asked. [Laughter] It was a triumph.</p>
                <p>Exchange Program: Sammy Lee, Olympic Diver</p>
                <p>Sammy Lee, the diver, the American of Korean ancestry, who won at two or three
                    Olympics, was a sensation. Sometimes you'd get some Swiss bellringers you didn't
                    really want or need, but in those days, State would say, “Well, they are going
                    to Singapore anyway, they might as well go to Djakarta.”</p>
                <p>The VOA Years</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Shall we leave Indonesia for the moment and continue,
                        especially your years in, first, Burma and then Bangkok. Before we get into
                        that, I think it would be of interest, because you were the Deputy Director
                        of the Voice of America from 1959 to 1961, and in view of the fact that my
                        own interest and my own involvement with the Voice before that time, as a
                        reporter in Munich and later on the same job that you had, my interest is
                        considerable. I think maybe we'd just like to talk for a few minutes about
                        your job in VOA. Who was the director at that time of Voice of America?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Henry Loomis.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Henry Loomis was the director. He was the director,
                        actually, for a very long time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Voice of America, which moved from New York to
                        Washington in 1953, was ensconced during those years already in Washington,
                        and the one thing that is of particular interest to me and maybe to others,
                        too, is the Voice of America, until about 1958, had really been a major Cold
                        War anti-Communist instrument. In 1958 or thereabouts, the policy in regard
                        to the Voice changed. I'm interested in the development of that change for
                        the Voice to become really similar to the BBC as a worldwide reliable
                        authoritative source of information and news emanating, of course, from the
                        United States. Were you involved in this change from one side to the
                        other?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Those forces were in motion before I arrived. Incidentally, I had been
                    scheduled to go to Cairo as PAO, and Henry Loomis decided that he wanted me. So
                    I struck a deal with Henry. I said, “I really want to go back to the field. One
                    year is no good, but perhaps two years.” So Henry said, “Fine, Jack,” and kept
                    his word, as he always did.</p>
                <p>Origin of VIA Charter</p>
                <p>I'd been there less than a week when Henry gave me a stack of papers—I'm not
                    exaggerating—at least eight or ten inches deep, which represented the efforts of
                    a number of people to create either a charter or a directive to the Voice of
                    America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Even then. And those documents were written by, among others—the names
                    will be familiar to you—Barry Zorthian, Bob Goldman, Sandy Marlow, Len Reed.
                    There were many others. They varied in length and in philosophy. Underlying many
                    of them was the hope that VOA could become another BBC. Henry asked me to come
                    up with something that would be acceptable “uptown,” as the term was in those
                    days for headquarters of USIA, and said he could use a draft fairly soon because
                    of the trend toward a BBC-type directive. I decided to stay home one day, and I
                    went through all these ideas. It was largely a matter of boiling down some of
                    them. The following day, I turned a draft over to Henry. With the exception of
                    three or four words, what I put together is now called the Voice of America
                    Charter, which is now the law of the land.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>In 1984, USIA World carried an article about the Voice of America Charter, and it
                    said nothing about how it really had evolved. So I wrote a letter to Henry—which
                    I happen to have a copy of and will give you, Tom—in which I reviewed just what
                    I've told you, and said that he might want to search his memory and see if
                    that's what he recalled as well. Within 48 hours, I had a call from Henry in
                    Middleburg, saying his memory was absolutely the same as what I reported was the
                    origin of the Voice of America directive-charter. The main point then was not to
                    call it a charter. George Allen told us, “If you do, you're not going to get it
                    by the Hill. You're not going to get it past the White House. It suggests too
                    much independence. Call it a directive.” So that's the way it came out then.
                    What prompted my letter to Loomis at this time was a statement by Chuck Percy,
                    then a senator from Illinois, who claimed that he, in effect, was responsible
                    for the charter. Well, he was the man who got it through the Senate, so in that
                    sense, he was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In many respects, if I might just interject, even though
                        this is an interview of you, just since you mention Chuck Percy, when I was
                        at the Voice as deputy director, at that time I was acting director because
                        there was no director at the Voice, at one of the authorization hearings
                        before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Senator Percy was chairman at
                        that time, and among the statements he made which I certainly appreciated,
                        he said to me, “Under this charter, under this law.” Mind you, this was in
                        1978, and the law had been passed in 1975, capsulating or incorporating this
                        charter into public law. He said, “Mr. Tuch, if you let anyone in this
                        government or outside of the government, in this country or abroad, if you
                        let anyone interfere with the news broadcasts of the Voice of America, you
                        are breaking the law.” Which is something that any VOA news editor or VOA
                        director took to heart.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, I have a copy of my letter to Loomis, and you may want to add this
                    as an attachment to the tape, Tom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>VOA Transmitter Construction Program</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That was one. Another activity that took more time, and which also is
                    extremely interesting, was VOA real estate. Henry was a first-rate guy to work
                    for, and when he'd go out of the country, you were in charge. If you goofed, too
                    bad, but you'd sink or swim. On real estate, we had a megawatt we were trying to
                    peddle. It was on the docks in Beirut, and Ed Martin, VOA's chief engineer, and
                    I looked all over to see if it was intact, looking for a place to put it. (We
                    didn't find one until later.) Then we had a deal with Turkey, and the Turks were
                    literally poised to sign an agreement—we were going to have a facility in
                    Adana—when overnight, every Turk we'd been doing business with was thrown out of
                    office in a coup and were sent to some island God knows where. So that
                    negotiation went down the drain.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>An easy one was with BBC. They wanted to increase the power of transmitters we
                    shared with them. But then there was the megawatt—medium wave, of course—and
                    Thailand. We could not sell the Thai on the megawatt at that time. But three or
                    four years later, in 1964 or 1965, the Thai were in a different mood because of
                    the Vietnam War, and we worked out a very satisfactory agreement. They got to
                    use it and we did, too.</p>
                <p>So all these take time, clearly. We won't permit a foreign government to put
                    transmitters on our soil. Look at it from that point of view, and you realize
                    what we are up against. I'm astonished, frankly, that we don't have more trouble
                    in some countries today, where there is violence, internal disputes, and where
                    they could easily take the anti-American form of blowing up our transmitters.
                    I'm astonished and proud that that hasn't happened so far.</p>
                <p>That's why this megawatt transmitter in Bangkok is one that I was involved in
                    during my time with the Voice. It was a medium-wave transmitter at the time, but
                    it was able to broadcast into the People's Republic of China, in the southern
                    part. It was listenable within China. It was a very, very effective
                    instrument.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the things I wanted to ask you about in VOA, George
                        Allen, contrary to some of his predecessors and also to some of his
                        successors, his idea was the Voice should broadcast in English 24 hours a
                        day, like the BBC, and that English was really the important element of the
                        Voice of America. Did that become a major issue during your time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: English was increased, but we also at that time created what was called
                    special English.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: This was the one with a very limited vocabulary, and one that, I
                    understand, has been very successful. So that satisfied George. I think he saw
                    that as a reasonable compromise.</p>
                <p>1959 Cessation of Russian Jamming of VOA</p>
                <p>A story that would interest you especially, Tom, is of how we learned about the
                    stopping of jamming when Khrushchev came to this country. Q: Yes, in '59.</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: In '59. We had a nice little guy—I don't remember his name—who had a
                    monitoring gimmick on top of the VOA building, and he kept us aware of changes
                    in what other international broadcasters were up to in a technical sense. This
                    little guy came down to me one morning and said, “Jack, they've stopped jamming.
                    The Russians have stopped jamming.”</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>I said, “You've got pretty hard evidence, have you?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Yep. My little machine tells me it's true.”</p>
                <p>So I called George Allen, the Director of USIA.</p>
                <p>(Henry Loomis was out of town.) I said, “I think they've stopped jamming. I'm
                    putting in calls around the world to see if it can be confirmed.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Get me word as soon as you can and I'll call the White House.”</p>
                <p>So I put in calls to our people anyplace. I couldn't get them for one reason or
                    another. I finally said, “Get me Lee Brady, the PAO in Moscow.” I said, “Is it
                    true, Lee?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Of course it's true.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Okay, I can go with that, then?”</p>
                <p>“Sure, go with it.”</p>
                <p>So I called George, and George called the White House, and you know how that
                    ended, with selective jamming after Khrushchev left. That's when our problems
                    began.</p>
                <p>Eisenhower personally was interested to know what they were jamming, what
                    sections of broadcasts were being jammed. It was an absolute nightmare. Wanda
                    Allender, now Wanda Washburn, was one of the special assistants in the front
                    office, and she did a wonderful job of keeping track of this. The Russian
                    service had to go on with their regular programs. In the meantime, they had to
                    listen to a tape of what was being jammed and tell us so that we could tell
                    Allen so he could tell the White House. It was a nightmare! How in the world we
                    functioned then, I simply don't know. Wanda has more answers on that than anyone
                    I know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just to add to this, again, my job when I was in Moscow as
                        the sole USIS representative in '58, '59, before Lee Brady came and I became
                        Lee's assistant, was to monitor at that time the jamming of the Voice of
                        America. I had a schedule. Every night I had to listen to all the
                        frequencies, and I had to record the identity of the jammer, who identified
                        themselves every 30 seconds by Morse Code. You had to learn the Morse
                        Code.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, it's amazing you survived!</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then, of course, when jamming stopped or was switched
                        to partial jamming, to content jamming, I was relieved, of course. I didn't
                        have to just listen to the damn signal, but I could at least listen to some
                        transmissions. But it became much harder, because before that, I just had to
                        record the Morse Code signals. Now I had to record what was being jammed and
                        what was not being jammed every night.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Burma Assignment</p>
                <p>After your Voice tour of duty, you went as PAO to Burma for a relatively short
                    time. But that also was a rather significant period, so if you have any comments
                    about Burma, please tell me.</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, again, Burma was a country that fascinated me, and as I said
                    earlier, I'd asked Henry to agree to a two-year hitch at the Voice, and he kept
                    it almost to the day. Burma then was a fairly wide open program.</p>
                <p>We had two active branch officers, one at Mandalay and one at Moulamein, with
                    good libraries at both, and by all odds, the best library in the country in
                    Rangoon. The library was run by a most remarkable woman named Zelma Graham.
                    Zelma Graham had been in Burma before the war. Her husband was with a Baptist
                    missionary group, and he died there. Zelma was in Burma when the Japanese
                    marched in and marched out through India. As they walked along the road in
                    India, an American Army captain in a jeep spotted her, picked her up. His name
                    was Henry Byroade, Hank Byroade, who later became ambassador to several
                    countries. Zelma worked for OWI during the war from India, wanted to go back to
                    Burma after the war, and John Steeves, an OWI friend, said, “Zelma, go back and
                    get yourself a library degree and you will come back.” Zelma did that, and she
                    had, I think, an all-time record for USIS personnel overseas in serving in
                    Burma. She had the supreme satisfaction of having as people coming into her
                    library, people who had come to it as children, in the children's part of the
                    library. So there was a continuity that was unmatched in the country. Moreover,
                    by hook or crook, Zelma had arranged to have a number of Burmese women come and
                    take their library training in the United States. A number of them were at
                    Catholic University] here. So there was built up, in addition to a first-rate
                    library, a first-rate corps of librarians. It's been said by many Burmese that
                    there were three Americans who have had the most lasting impact on that country.
                    One would be Adoniram Judson, the Baptist missionary; number two—this is not
                    necessarily in order—would be Gordon Seagrave, the Burma surgeon, and number
                    three would be Zelma Graham. So that when halfway through my tour in Burma, Ne
                    Win, a military officer, came back into power, and he closed our branch posts,
                    closed Fulbright, and decreed the library in Rangoon to be closed. Zelma was
                    shattered, and she deserved to cry, as she did. This was her baby, something
                    she'd built up over the years. The Burmese were devastated. On an earlier
                    occasion, they threw stones at the American Embassy, but they carefully stayed
                    away from Zelma Graham's library two or three blocks away; it was their library.
                    But we had to break it up and send books all over the area.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Ken Bunce, then the area director, saw that it was almost a dead program, and
                    Thailand was exploding in every direction, so he transferred me to Bangkok.</p>
                <p>Thailand: 1963</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: That was in 1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1963 is when our real involvement in Vietnam and the
                        war started escalating also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there for how many years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Four years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Four years, from '63 to '67, a very significant period not
                        just for you, Jack, but also for American history.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Well, it was a very exciting time. We had, I think, an important role in
                    that war. I had an excellent arrangement with Lionel Mosley, then the director
                    of personnel. He would send out people, and I would then assign them wherever
                    they were needed in-country. At one time we had either 12 or 13 branch posts, an
                    American at the post, not each one with a library, of course. All spoke Thai and
                    were the eyes and ears of not just the United States Information Service, but I
                    made available to the CIA and one or two others, very informal reports of these
                    people who would write to me on their activities working with the Thai
                    Government on security and developments. Security and development—those were the
                    key themes.</p>
                <p>Graham Martin was the ambassador, a tough, cool character. We were separated by
                    half a mile from the chancery. I would four times a year bring in my branch
                    people to review what they were doing. Martin asked if he could come over and
                    sit in on our meetings. I said, “Of course. We'll come see you.” No, he wanted
                    to come over. He'd come over and take notes on what our people would observe as
                    they were going through a joint Thai-American information project. They'd
                    observe the status of agriculture, they observed the status of a dam-building
                    project, whatever it was, all very informative.</p>
                <p>American Bombing of Vietnam from Thai Bases Begins</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>Our people were also active in the war, in a special sense. One day in Ubol, one
                    of the country's northeast towns, Rob Nevitt branch PAO, a first-rate guy, was
                    astonished to find some of the hottest airplanes the United States Air Force had
                    zooming in and landing. He didn't have any advance word of it, nor did the
                    governor. The governor came to him. “Who are these people?” [Laughter] I had not
                    been told about it either, but Nevitt, from that point on, worked with the
                    governor to explain who they were, what they were there for, getting the Thai
                    officials to come out and talk with the commanding general, and getting the
                    Americans to be considerate of Thai pride and culture. So the war was being
                    fought in large measure from Thai bases, which the Thai would not admit. Now, in
                    some parts of Asia—it may also be true in other parts of the world—there's
                    reality and the confirmation of reality, two quite different things. So an old
                    correspondent friend of mine, Keyes Beech, of the Chicago Daily News, would come
                    through Bangkok, and he knew every bit of what was going on, the bombing of
                    North Vietnam from Thai bases. I couldn't confirm it. I'd have Keyes out for a
                    drink, and say, “You know, they're just big mosquitos out there, Keyes.” We
                    joked about it. We had to, because the Thai Government would not confirm reality
                    until—and this became a very delicate operation; it was about as elaborate as a
                    Japanese tea ceremony—the Thai Government, for reasons I'm not still quite
                    certain of, decided at a certain time that they would confirm that American
                    planes were using their territory to bomb North Vietnam. So we had to work out a
                    scheme with the foreign office, State, CINCPAC, and the Pentagon. It was to be
                    at 11:35 p.m., after a dinner at a Chinese restaurant in Bangkok that a Thai
                    reporter I knew would say, “Jack, I understand that tomorrow we're going to have
                    a tour of some of the activity at Thai air bases.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Yes, Thah, that's correct. The Thai Government has arranged that.” He
                    and I had rehearsed it in the afternoon.</p>
                <p>“What will we see, Jack?”</p>
                <p>I said, “You'll see American planes taking off.” I left it open.</p>
                <p>“And they'll be taking off for where?”</p>
                <p>I said, “North Vietnam.” I said this at 11:35. This was the first official
                    confirmation of what we were doing.</p>
                <p>Well, it satisfied the Thai, doing it that way. Of course, we played their game.
                    We needed their real estate. It was done with a delicacy that the Thai
                    appreciated. I don't take credit for it; I was a part of it. So that was an
                    interesting part of the war there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an insurgency in Thailand at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, indeed. The northeast part of the country is the poorest, and the
                    Communists had a foothold there. That's where AID was putting its big
                    projects.</p>
                <p>We concentrated in the northeast in publicizing everything that AID was doing,
                    and we were doing a lot. It meant that our people would spend an awful lot of
                    their time out in the boondocks with the Thai officials, making friends, passing
                    out material, showing our films, getting reports on problems, and so on. So it
                    was very active.</p>
                <p>You mentioned, Tom, that we were getting into psychological warfare. We were,
                    indeed. Leonard Marks, then the director of the agency, came through, and he
                    called Barry Zorthian over from Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Barry, at that time, was . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Barry was my opposite number in Vietnam. The three of us sat in my house
                    and reviewed what we were doing. Leonard was very good about it. He said, “Look,
                    you guys. I know that Barry's gotten much more deeply involved because he's had
                    to.” He turned to me and said, “Now, Jack, I only tell you don't get me into
                    trouble. Don't get me into trouble.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Leonard, I'm following the instructions we've had so far, and I don't
                    see any possibility I can get you into trouble.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Trouble in what way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Trouble in getting us too deeply involved with the Thai Government in
                    ways that would reflect, possibly, on the United States or on Lyndon Johnson. So
                    it meant we were cooperative, but not to appear that we were leading the Thai
                    into war. Now, I think that same problem plagued Lew Schmidt, my successor, and
                    his successors. When I was transferred back to the front office of USIA, Frank
                    Shakespeare called me in and said that he had heard from Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Frank Shakespeare was then . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Then the director of USIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He became that in '68, succeeding Leonard Marks, and
                        remained director until 1972.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Yes. I'm jumping ahead just to keep in line talk of psychological
                    warfare, because Frank had heard from Henry Kissinger that USIS in Thailand was
                    doing too many things that the Thai should be doing for themselves.</p>
                <p>I've jumped ahead, as I just said, Tom, but I want to follow up on this matter of
                    psychological warfare. When Shakespeare became concerned because of Kissinger's
                    call, he then brought out a lot of the publications and posters that we had been
                    turning out in Thailand, and he kept asking me, “Jack, you've been there. Is it
                    necessary for us to do it? Why can't the Thai do it?”</p>
                <p>I said, “They're simply not prepared to do it, and we work closely with them, we
                    share a lot of the costs with them and ideas, but it's a joint enterprise and we
                    look upon them as partners in this.”</p>
                <p>Frank was scared, frankly, and he didn't want to cross Kissinger on it. Kissinger
                    apparently read it as our going down the path of getting involved, as we were in
                    Vietnam. I believe our joint programs were then curtailed. Lew Schmidt, my
                    successor, should know.</p>
                <p>The Great Success of the Binational Center</p>
                <p>But the Thai program was a vigorous one in almost every sense. We had a
                    spectacularly successful binational center. It was created long before I was
                    there, so I take no credit for it. It was called AUA, an abbreviation for
                    American University Alumni Association. It was built on land that was donated by
                    the royal family. The United States Government contributed a little piece of
                    property to round it out. It had night and day English-language teaching. There
                    were all sorts of artistic performances. We had a number of people on contract
                    as teachers. It was the symbol of American-Thai cooperation, and it would be the
                    last thing, as I told many visitors, the last thing I'd want to give up in our
                    program, because it was bedrock solid, still goes on to this day, as far as I
                    know, one of the most successful in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A huge English-teaching program.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, tremendous, yes. People paid for it, too. We had a very active
                    Fulbright program, first-rate. It's interesting to look back on the Thai
                    experience overseas. The Thai, first, oh, since the First World War would send
                    their brightest people to France or to England. Since that time it's
                    overwhelmingly been to the United States, so there's a very, very large number
                    of Thai who have gone to school in our country. Indeed, there's sort of a
                    special club there of American women who have married Thai, and they have
                    regular meetings, when we were there, at least, at the AUA. Our friendship is
                    deep. We all know about what the Thai did in World War II, in providing
                    hospitality to OSS and helping us in a number of ways. So we were dealing in a
                    very, very favorable atmosphere, and you could go almost as far as you wanted,
                    except—and I'll never forget this—the first Thai graduate of MIT, a wonderful,
                    dignified man named Phra Bisal, and I used to have lunch regularly. He was head
                    of the AUA.</p>
                <p>One day I got word from the agency that they had a very elaborate Berlin Wall
                    exhibit they'd like to send out. So I brought it up in the course of lunch with
                    this distinguished Thai, and saw a sort of cloud over his forehead. He said,
                    “Jack, don't put it at the AUA. It's a little too political. Put it in your own
                    library. I want to see it, but put it in your own library.” He was right. We did
                    as he suggested.</p>
                <p>We had very good relations with such organizations as the border patrol police, a
                    good outfit. Of course, they had a big job. They had borders with Burma and Laos
                    and Cambodia and Malaya. The head of the border patrol police invited me one
                    time to come with him in his helicopter to the borders and to see what was going
                    on. I said, “Fine.”</p>
                <p>We were returning in late afternoon, the last part of the journey back to
                    Bangkok, when the skies literally turned black. It was a big storm. So the
                    general directed that the helicopter go down. Well, it was right in the middle
                    of a rice field, and out of nowhere came dozens of little Thai kids. How many
                    times do you get a helicopter land in your rice field? The storm was heavy, so
                    the general turned to his aide and said, “Break out the whiskey.” So we all sat
                    and drank and watched the kids playing. The storm showed no sign of letting up,
                    and the general, however, kept looking at his watch. I said, “General, there's
                    no hurry as far as I'm concerned. I have plenty of time. Don't worry about going
                    back to Bangkok in a hurry.”</p>
                <p>“Oh,” he said, “I think we'd better take off.” Well, it was still black, but the
                    plane shot up, just like an arrow. Thank God, about a thousand feet up, it was
                    beautiful, crystal clear, sunny. I'm sure my face showed the relief I felt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The program in Thailand at that time, would you say that
                        it was motivated or guided by our tremendous involvement, because of our
                        efforts in Vietnam, or was it because we realized that Thailand was an
                        important country in terms of U.S. policy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>O'BRIEN: Oh, I think all those factors worked, Tom. Our program was based upon a
                    long friendship, really, and so we had a solid foundation as represented by the
                    AUA. It was on that, then, that we could go into other programs relating to the
                    war in Vietnam, and it was that that enabled us to do things on radio and in
                    joint publications. I never forgot that there was a foundation that had its
                    origins long before we got into war in Vietnam. As far as I'm aware, that
                    friendship still exists. Thailand was and is important to us because of
                    geography, and we've been fortunate in having them as good friends and allies
                    over the years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to touch on one more subject this afternoon. What
                        was it like to work with and for Frank Shakespeare? You were special
                        assistant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Assignment to USIA Front Office The Experience with Director Frank Shakespeare
                    and “Teddy” Weintal</p>
                <p>O'BRIEN: After I came back from Bangkok. I went to a job at State, the worst job
                    I've ever had, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, which was set up
                    solely to try to sell the American people on the Vietnam War. It was a loser
                    from the beginning, and I finally recommended it be abolished. It was, and about
                    that time, Henry Loomis came back into the agency as number two guy at USIA. So
                    Henry said, “Please come back,” and I was delighted to do that, having worked
                    for him before at the Voice. Frank I did not know, and I was surprised to find
                    that he didn't know Henry very well. Frank was not well organized. He found the
                    Washington rhythm took some time to get used to. He wasn't quite certain who all
                    the people were, didn't know much about the budget, didn't know anything about
                    it, really. And I think he came in with a certain distrust of career people. My
                    work was primarily with Henry, anyway. I knew his style, I knew how many times I
                    could go in to Henry and just say, “Henry, don't sign this.” I could do his
                    staff work for him, and he would, nine times out of ten, follow my
                    recommendations. We set up an executive committee, which decided on major ideas
                    and allocation of resources for the agency. I would prepare the agenda for that
                    and arrange for the paperwork. Right there on the spot, when Henry had made a
                    decision, I'd record it and see it was carried out. Frank did not participate in
                    that. He didn't seem to understand it. Then an interesting thing happened. On a
                    Friday afternoon, Henry Loomis told me, as he was leaving the office, “Jack, a
                    guy named Weintal is coming in Monday morning. I don't know who he is.
                    Apparently it's a White House deal. Frank doesn't know him either. Will you find
                    out what he's here for, what we're supposed to do with him?”</p>
                <p>I knew who Teddy Weintal was. He was a columnist for Newsweek, and he really
                    wanted to work at State, but they sent him over to USIA. A very dignified old
                    fellow, born in Poland, of aristocratic background. In came Teddy, and I
                    introduced myself. I showed him an office, and he said, “What do I do now?”</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>I said, “Well, I think the best thing to do is get you acquainted with some of
                    the traffic.” So I arranged to have low classified stuff sent in to him. I could
                    see he was becoming bored and he kept turning to me for advice and counsel.
                    Neither Frank nor Henry seemed to know how to use him.</p>
                <p>So Teddy one day said, “Jack, let's go to lunch.” He took me over to the
                    Metropolitan Club. He said, “This is terribly embarrassing, but I just don't
                    think I'm doing anything worthwhile here.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Teddy, you've got to go in and tell Shakespeare what you want to do,
                    what you think you can do.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I can't. He's a busy man.” I said, “Look, on the way back after lunch,
                    I'll see if his door is open. I'll go in. I know he's going to go to Europe next
                    week, and I'm going to suggest that you go with him.”</p>
                <p>“Oh,” he said, “I can't do it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “What do you mean?” So I went back, and sure enough, Frank's door was
                    open. I said, “Frank, we've got this guy Weintal here. I think, really, you'd
                    get more out of him if you'd let him see what we're doing overseas. Why don't
                    you take him along on your trip?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Good idea.” One of the major mistakes of my life, Tom, because that
                    started Shakespeare-Weintal trips all over. They would spot a guy in a certain
                    country, didn't like the way he wore his tie or something, transfer him. Orderly
                    personnel procedures were frequently ignored. Weintal endeared himself to
                    Shakespeare, because Teddy knew his way around Georgetown, which Shakespeare was
                    interested in. Teddy arranged for him to meet Alice Roosevelt Longworth. This
                    was one of Frank's ambitions. Teddy warned him not to play poker with her
                    because she cheated. And Teddy arranged for him to get into the Metropolitan
                    Club. This was a very awkward afternoon. Teddy and Henry were both members of
                    the Metropolitan, and they had to bring the new applicant for membership, Frank
                    Shakespeare, to meet some of the boys. But they needed a couple of standbys
                    there. So for about an hour, we sat around the room at the Metropolitan, and
                    none of these boys would show up. Terribly embarrassing. Finally, Henry went out
                    and grabbed a couple of guys off the floor, brought them in, introduced them to
                    Frank, and that constituted membership, I guess.</p>
                <p>But then as time went on, Frank became interested in budget and personnel.
                    Without preparation, without real knowledge of what was going on, he would
                    arbitrarily make decisions overruling the executive committee which had staffed
                    things out. It was difficult for Loomis, because he knew where the money was and
                    how to prepare the budget, and Frank was sort of a dilettante getting into
                    it.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>Frank was a very charming guy, but I cannot say that I learned to respect him. He
                    was always very kind, and he found out, as time went on, that although a career
                    guy, I could be helpful. I knew a lot about the agency, knew a lot of the key
                    people, and so many times, when he was packing up to go on a trip, he'd say,
                    “Jack, would you follow up on this and this and this?”</p>
                <p>And I'd say, “Sure, of course.” That's what special assistants are for. So it was
                    a very friendly relationship, but never, never as close as I had with
                    Loomis.</p>
                <p>The time came when I wanted to get back overseas. I was seeing the same thing in
                    papers on my desk every day, and it got to be, frankly, a bore. But by that
                    time, my wife's health had become such that she couldn't get a physical
                    clearance. We had been separated for one year when she was back here at the
                    Naval Hospital, and I had returned to Bangkok. I wasn't going through that
                    again. So I put in my resignation. It was on a Friday that I resigned. On Monday
                    I reported for the same job and did that until—I think it was Henry Dunlap who
                    succeeded me. Then I did a number of things that consultants do: inspections of
                    Japan and Indonesia, study of the Voice, chairing the selection board. Then I
                    got into the Milton Eisenhower Committee on Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty.
                    Then I went to work for Loomis again when he became president of the Corporation
                    for Public Broadcasting. I got caught in a political squeeze there and had to
                    get out, still very good friends with Henry. It was about that time that I came
                    down with cancer, but that's another story.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thanks very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
