<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001074">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Joseph J. Sisco</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>UNDER SECRETARY JOSEPH J. SISCO</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Michael Sterner </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 19th, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>This is an interview with The Honorable Joseph J. Sisco conducted by Michael
                    Sterner. The date is March 19th, 1990.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, tell us a little bit about your background and how
                        you got started in a career in international affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, Mike, I think there were really two things. In undergraduate school
                    I was a history major and that included European history. But the real catalyst
                    was World War II when I served in the Pacific and where I had an opportunity to
                    see more of the world than I really wanted to at that particular juncture. So
                    that when I left the service after the war I went back—I had already started
                    graduate school at the University of Chicago—and I got my master's degree and my
                    Ph.D., interestingly enough in Soviet affairs where I took Russian language
                    studies as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you ever tempted in the direction of being an
                        academic? You also got a Ph.D., but that was later on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: No, no. I got my Ph.D. before I came into government, and actually, Mike,
                    my notion at that time was, I really ought to get a couple of years of
                    government experience before I went to the academic field to teach. But two
                    years became twenty-five. I liked what I was doing in government. And
                    interestingly enough I had applied a foreign affairs position in State, but
                    there were no openings at that time and therefore I took a job in the CIA. I
                    started my government career in the CIA, and then after six months I was able to
                    transfer because there was an opening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your first assignments in State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: They were largely in the UN Bureau.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I associate you as being almost entirely in the UN Bureau
                        until you came over to Near East and South Asian Affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: The wonderful part about being in that bureau, and not enough people in
                    the service really realize this, is that it has two dimensions that are very
                    broadening and I found very helpful. First of all, by virtue of the fact that
                    every General Assembly opens in the fall and there are over a hundred items on
                    the Assembly agenda, it covers the world. And while obviously it covers specific
                    issues from the point of view of what is happening in multilateral diplomacy,
                    the fact of the matter is that when you're dealing with that particular issue
                    you have to get into the substance. That's the first thing. The second thing is
                    that there is the practical experience at the UN in itself that goes beyond the
                    normal bilateral interactions that are so typical of the work in one single
                    embassy vis-a-vis one country. There at the UN it was not only a set of
                    negotiations on different specific issues, and a variety of countries that were
                    involved, but there was a private dimension as well as a public dimension, as
                    well as a legislative dimension. So that those factors, I think, tended to give
                    me what I considered to be an excellent practical experience very early in the
                    game. And moreover because one was involved as well in the public dimension. The
                    demands of the job were to be able to write, and to be able to write quickly,
                    particularly if some public statement had to be made. So there was the public
                    affairs dimension as well. I can't say enough for that experience in terms of
                    being helpful in whatever I may have done in later years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, you've seen in the course of your IO career, you've
                        seen many American UN Representatives up there. Who were the most effective
                        in your opinion? And in particular what issues do you think were well
                        handled?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>SISCO: We had a tremendous variety, and you will recall, Mike, that a number of
                    the United States representatives to the UN were selected for their stature,
                    their visibility, and certainly in the earlier days—say the first twenty years
                    after World War II—it was a position that was consciously attractive to a number
                    of outstanding figures and therefore you had people originally like Warren
                    Austin. You had people like Arthur Goldberg, Adlai Stevenson, and President Bush
                    as an ambassador. Goldberg, I would have to say, was an outstanding negotiator,
                    and in my book is really the architect of Security Council Resolution 242. I
                    think he did a remarkable job, and because President Johnson gave him broad
                    latitude in what might be acceptable to the United States, he had great
                    flexibility and therefore in many respects, in addition to putting to good use
                    his negotiating ability that he had achieved in the context of being a labor
                    lawyer, likewise Secretary of Labor, and so on, he was able to get positions for
                    the United States of a much more flexible character than perhaps others might
                    not have been able to do. Adlai Stevenson, of course, was remarkable in the
                    sense of his popularity. He was sought after. He was particularly strong in the
                    speech making, in the public dimension of the UN work. He was less interested in
                    the nitty-gritty of negotiating a tough resolution, in sharp contrast, I might
                    add, with his successor, namely Arthur Goldberg. I think George Bush was one of
                    our most effective UN ambassadors. He was not there a very long time, but one
                    outstanding feature that I can recall is that he was a real team player: he was
                    popular with other representatives, he did a very strong job of representation.
                    But what struck me was that he worked so closely in harness with the
                    administration in Washington. And historically, if you look at that job, that
                    wasn't always the case because there was a tendency, first of all, on the part
                    of our presidents to oversell the UN job. President Johnson, in effect, made the
                    job sound to someone like Goldberg as a second Secretary of State job. And you
                    know the number of the difficulties that resulted from the notion that that job
                    was tantamount to that of Secretary of State. And we had our difficulties under
                    Stevenson, we had our difficulties under Goldberg. We didn't have that kind of a
                    difficulty with George Bush who concerted very, very closely both with the State
                    Department, as well as the White House, and therefore did a highly effective
                    job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you see his attachment to the UN in his selection
                        of Tom Pickering who is one of our outstanding professionals now. As you
                        look back over your association with that institution dating back to World
                        War II, how do you see the evolution of the institution itself? Many people
                        feel that the UN started out with a great deal of promise, but that it has
                        lost its impact in the world and particularly that it has become very
                        seriously distorted away from the notion of solving world problems, toward
                        being a sounding board for the third world.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>SISCO: First, Mike, let me say that the expectations at the outset were much too
                    high. The UN is made up of sovereign states and it reflects an international
                    consensus to the degree to which a consensus can develop. The fundamental
                    assumption of the UN was that the major powers would cooperate—the permanent
                    members of the Security Council—in achieving Pacific Settlement and collective
                    security. Shortly after World War II the cold war began between the United
                    States and the Soviet Union, and therefore the fundamental assumption that the
                    major powers would cooperate was undermined, and there was no cooperation. It
                    was a question of the United States taking the lead, and the achievements that
                    were possible were largely because of the fact that we had broad support in the
                    world, and therefore at the UN most of America's policies were adopted.</p>
                <p>That changed mid-way when twenty-one new members were added to the UN, and at the
                    time the UN came under challenge from Khrushchev when Dag Hammarskjold was the
                    Secretary General. What happened at that particular period was that the UN moved
                    from a U.S. dominated organization to one where there was a stalemate, where
                    neither side could really put together the kind of majority that allowed the
                    organization to do its work. And that's where the phrase came into being that
                    many people are not very familiar with, namely, “give it to Dag”: Meaning hand
                    the problem over to the Secretary General largely because East and West could
                    not really get together.</p>
                <p>But I'm hopeful now, simply because, one, we've gone through a very difficult
                    period and there's much more realism about both the capacities and the
                    limitations of the UN. But the most fundamental fact is that to the degree to
                    which the United States and the Soviet Union can continue to reduce tensions,
                    and to cooperate in and out of the UN, this will allow and permit the UN to be
                    more effective because it is an indispensable third party element. And what you
                    have here in 1989 and 1990 are magnificent examples of where the third party
                    role of the UN is acceptable to both major powers and therefore making a major
                    contribution. And we're talking about a UN role in Cambodia, the ongoing role in
                    a place like Kashmir, certainly a very significant role over decades that you
                    and I are particularly familiar with, namely the Middle East. You have the UN
                    having played a role in the recent Nicaraguan elections.</p>
                <p>The Soviets, for example, are now using the phrase “collective security”, because
                    that was, after all, the original concept of the charter. And we invented the
                    phrase “peace keeping” largely because of the fact that it was somewhere between
                    Chapter 6 (Pacific Settlement) in the Charter, and collective security
                    (enforcement action, so-called Chapter 7) in the charter. Peace keeping was
                    somewhere in between, six-and-a-half, if you will. We may very well get back to
                    the original concept of collective security if in fact Soviet and American
                    parallel interests can develop further because the organization will be of
                    greater utility to both major powers and to the world generally. Also the UN is
                    experienced and well suited to play a role in the social agenda of the
                    90's—health, environment, and the like.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, let's talk a little bit about the 1967 Arab-Israel
                        crisis because this is a very good example of an effective role of the
                        United Nations. But to begin with there was U Thant's precipitate withdrawal
                        of the UNEF from Sinai. Do you share the view of many commentators that that
                        was really a failure in statesmanship on his part?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: I do, and I'm afraid our good friend, Ralph Bunche, contributed to that. I
                    believe there was an opportunity to delay matters rather than bring them to a
                    confrontational stage. As I've reviewed the record over the years, it seems to
                    me Nasser didn't expect that kind of a precipitous and quick withdrawal. And
                    therefore, unfortunately, the precipitous move tended to deepen the crisis,
                    rather than alleviate it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you think the United States did everything it could
                        during that three week preliminary period before the Israelis finally
                        decided to invade? To defuse it, and to prevent war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: I think we did. We, of course, were very concerned about the Soviet
                    position in all of this. I think it took us all a bit by surprise, and it was a
                    crisis that, at least the perception within the State Department was, that it
                    was a crisis that need not have occurred. And it was one that was precipitated
                    in this particular instance by Nasser and Egypt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I remember it there was a plan by Nasser to send over
                        Zakaria Mohieddine toward the very end, and Egyptians tend to claim that he
                        was coming with a deal of some sort. Do you credit that? Do you think the
                        war was avertible if we had been able to hold off the Israelis for another
                        ten days, or whatever?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Very difficult to speculate, and I don't really have a very clear judgment
                    to make. I rather doubt it, quite frankly, but I don't think I add anything to
                    the historic record other than this kind of intuitive reaction. There's no way
                    to really know in hindsight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Israelis, of course, won a stunning victory in that
                        conflict and in a sense, I think, all of the United States policy makers
                        were enormously relieved that it was as fast, and as decisive, as it was,
                        particularly because there was a real danger of a U.S.-Soviet confrontation
                        if it had gone wrong, or if it had been prolonged.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Looking now at the aftermath, tell us a little bit about your role at the time.
                    Also, whether you played a part in the formulation of the United States position
                    coming out of the war. And as I remember it, the first comprehensive
                    announcement of American post-war policy was Johnson's June 20th speech in which
                    there was really a decisive change in American policy from the 1958 period when
                    we brought pressure on Israel to withdraw. In this case we were saying, in
                    effect, “You're entitled to hang on to the territories until the Arabs come
                    forward with some kind of negotiation for peace.”</p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, yes. One, it was viewed, of course, as an important “victory”,
                    largely because of the denial of opportunity to the Soviet Union, because it was
                    a period, of poor relationships between Moscow and Washington. So in that sense
                    it was an example, in the view of some, of where the Israeli action helped the
                    interests of the United States in the broader, big power, context.</p>
                <p>As I look back on that particular period, I think that's the one development that
                    changed the whole course of the Middle East right to this day. Because while
                    that June '67 Israeli military victory was overwhelming, it ushered in a period
                    of stalemate. And it wasn't until war came in '73 when the military result was
                    inconclusive, in sharp contrast with the overwhelming Israeli military victory
                    in '67, that it was possible to get to the negotiating table. Largely because of
                    the fact, as you well know, that inconclusive result in '73 was viewed, rightly
                    in my judgement, at least as a partial Arab victory, and reduced the
                    psychological feelings on the Arab side that they would be going to the
                    conference table as an inferior, defeated power. So '67, in my book, is really a
                    watershed event which has influenced a number of the developments in the area to
                    this day.</p>
                <p>My own role focused largely on the UN context. And interestingly enough much of
                    the policy that developed was really in the UN context, much more than in the
                    bilateral setting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell us a little bit about that. You were
                        backstopping that whole effort to get Security Council resolution 242, and
                        as I remember it was quite a complicated and also lengthy negotiation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes, almost six months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...almost six months it took to negotiate that. There were
                        many drafts, including a “Latin American” resolution, as I remember. Dig
                        into your memory a little bit and tell us how the resolution in its final
                        form finally evolved.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>SISCO: Well, you put it very accurately. One, the UN was seized of the problem,
                    and it was viewed rightly, as the number one political problem at that
                    particular juncture with all of the risks that it entailed. The Latin Americans
                    were involved, but just about every area in one way or another, at some point,
                    played a role. But the lead throughout was really the United States, as might be
                    expected. And the situation really was multi-dimensional in the sense that we
                    were a central feature in the negotiations between the Israelis and the Arabs.
                    And again, these are negotiations being conducted in an indirect sort of way.
                    And, of course, the critical factor was the degree to which we could work
                    matters out with the Soviet Union as well. So that it was a constant round of
                    negotiations in and around the setting of the UN Security Council. The British
                    played a role. But when you got to the end of the line, the critical division
                    can really be stated very simply: the Arab position was that the resolution 242
                    should say, total Israeli withdrawal to the pre-June '67 lines. Whereas our
                    position was that there should be withdrawal, but the question of how much
                    withdrawal, and to where, was a matter that was subject to negotiations. And
                    therefore the ultimate compromise came about in a preambulary paragraph in
                    Security Council Resolution 242 which expressed the principal of non-acquisition
                    of territory. But by the same token the critical operative paragraph, calling
                    for withdrawal as a matter of principle, leaving out the articles, and leaving
                    open the question of partial or whole, and to what lines, was subject to
                    negotiation. And the interesting feature is that when you then begin to look at
                    the Egyptian-Israeli treaty subsequently, even though that resolution never said
                    “total Israeli withdrawal to the pre-June '67 lines” in the case of the Egyptian
                    treaty that's exactly what the Egyptians got. So that's, I think, a very, very
                    interesting feature. Not that it would be precedential in terms of the West Bank
                    and the Gaza, or Syria, but interesting to show that there was flexibility in
                    the negotiation.</p>
                <p>Moreover, there were different positions because at an earlier phase there were
                    some who were disposed to accept a cease fire on the basis of the then existing
                    constellation of forces, and then subsequently the question of withdrawal to the
                    status quo ante being really the predominant factor.</p>
                <p>There is historic argument as to who should claim credit, and certainly Lord
                    Caradon of Great Britain has claimed credit for being the sponsor and the
                    draftsman. What happened really was that the language was developed by the
                    United States, and for reasons of legislative tactics the final compromise, in
                    terms of the language, we put in the hands of the British as a sponsor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later on, the Israelis, or at least the Begin government,
                        made quite a point of the fact that Resolution 242 doesn't have to apply
                        equally in terms of its withdrawal provisions to all fronts, and they have
                        attempted to say, the resolution could mean total withdrawal from Sinai, but
                        it could also mean no withdrawal from the West Bank and Gaza. Do you recall
                        in the genesis of Resolution 242 that the Israeli government at the period
                        argued along those lines.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>SISCO: Not at all. In fact the Israeli position was the same as ours. At the time
                    of the adoption of Security Council Resolution 242, there was no ambiguity,
                    either among the members of the Security Council, or between ourselves, and
                    Israel. That Security Council resolution (242) applied to all of the
                    territories. It applied not only to the Sinai, it applied to the West Bank, to
                    Gaza, to the Golan Heights. And we, in the later years, in many of the Camp
                    David documents, and so on, developed the phrase that the resolution had to be
                    applied “in all of its parts”. There was never any doubt in this regard and the
                    beginning of the revisionist view started with Prime Minister Begin. It was
                    interestingly enough not a view, held by the prior Israeli governments. And even
                    to this day, as a matter of fact, there is a distinction between the Likud
                    position and the Labor party position. The labor party position continues to be,
                    that in order to achieve peace, you have to exchange territory for peace.
                    Likewise, Labor has not adopted the position that by virtue of the fact that
                    we've achieved an Egyptian-Israeli treaty, that Security Council Resolution 242
                    need not be applicable now to other parts of the occupied territories. It just
                    isn't so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. Joe, on Jerusalem, we're seeing the issue of
                        Jerusalem now coming up front and forward once again. In those days, as I
                        remember it, there was a sort of sliding process whereby at the very
                        beginning the Israelis...treated East Jerusalem as part of occupied
                        territory. But in the course of, about the six months that it took to
                        negotiate resolution 242, there was an evolution in the Israeli position
                        where they treated annexation of the whole city as being a fait accompli. Do
                        you remember how that evolved, and what is your feeling about the American
                        position as it finally took place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: There's nothing that occurred within the context of 242 in so far as the
                    American position is concerned that altered the original American position that
                    Jerusalem should be a corpus separatum, and that Jerusalem was a matter of
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So what you're saying is that really in spite of the
                        result of the '67 war, the earlier premise that Jerusalem was a special
                        case, and to be treated separately, was carried forward.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: ...carried forward, and when I said that 242 was applicable I didn't mean
                    to imply that there was a specific applicability to Jerusalem as such. It was
                    recognized that whatever occurred had to be negotiated between sides. We
                    underscored at that time the need for access to the Holy Places. And later on,
                    and I can't really put the exact date on it, we also began to emphasize that
                    Jerusalem should no longer ever be divided again. But as I recall, that was at a
                    later stage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, you were Assistant Secretary for IO during this
                        period of '67 and then as I remember in the early days of the Nixon
                        administration you came over to NEA.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>SISCO: I came over to NEA in about February of '69. I was in IO from '64 through
                    '68.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course in that interim period we had the efforts by the
                        UN Special Representative of the period, Gunnar Jarring. I remember Jarring
                        ran into a very frustrating period. Do you think the UN could have done
                        better in that period, looking back on it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, the usual criticism of Jarring was that he wasn't active enough, and
                    so on. I think basically that's an unfair criticism simply because of the fact
                    that the UN had no separate power as such, and that what Jarring could do
                    basically really was dependent on what we primarily could do behind the scenes.
                    Jarring was a very able person. I'm really responsible for Jarring having been
                    singled out for appointment. Dean Rusk called me into his office, and said, “We
                    need a UN representative here. Do you have any thoughts as to who it might be?”
                    And after we considered it, I recommended Jarring for the simple reason: a) I
                    knew him. He had had UN experience, he'd been the Swedish ambassador to Moscow,
                    and he'd been the Swedish ambassador to the United States. And I pointed out to
                    Dean Rusk he was just ideal in this regard, and a first rate diplomat. So that
                    we chose Jarring, if you will, and there was never any doubt in that regard.</p>
                <p>It was a very frustrating period. He was very cautious, there's no question about
                    it. And he came up with a variety of points during that particular period, but
                    there was just no common ground between the two sides. And at that particular
                    juncture we really were in no position to move things forward. You had, after
                    all, a Security Council Resolution 242 that had been adopted. You had an
                    absolutely overwhelming military victory on the part of the Israelis. The others
                    were the vanquished, and there was no disposition for a serious negotiation at
                    that particular juncture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And in the meantime, of course, the Israeli problem was
                        made even more difficult by the fact that Begin led his party out of the
                        coalition specifically on the issue that the resolution didn't...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: ...the non-acceptance really of 242.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. All right then, in 1969 Nixon came in with
                        Henry Kissinger as his National Security Adviser. You came over to the NEA
                        bureau, and there was really a burst of new enthusiasm for the idea of doing
                        something in the Middle East, and of new energy, including a lot that took
                        place in your bailiwick. We had the famous Scranton mission which produced a
                        sort of public affairs bombshell calling for even-handedness, which was new
                        language at the time, followed very quickly by the Four Power talks in New
                        York. At the same time you had a very interesting diplomatic experience in
                        sitting down with Dobrynin and conducting talks attempting to develop a
                        United States-Soviet agreement on the principles of the peace settlement.
                        Tell us about that Joe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Sure. Let me make a comment first of all on the Scranton mission. That was
                    largely a mission whereby Nixon indicated to Scranton he might really take a
                    look at the situation. That was before Nixon took over in any serious sort of
                    way. In fact, if I recall, that may very well have been prior to the actual
                    inauguration, or shortly thereafter.</p>
                <p>The genesis is very simple. President Nixon made very clear to me that what he
                    wanted was a test of Soviet intentions in the Middle East. Whether, in fact,
                    they were serious about trying to achieve some progress towards peace, or
                    whether they could live—much better than we felt we could live—with controlled
                    tension in the area. And therefore the first task I had when I came over to NEA
                    as Assistant Secretary was to develop some options. That was also in the context
                    that the French had already taken the lead and called for Four Power talks.
                    Nixon was getting ready in the next few weeks to go to Paris, and both he and
                    Henry Kissinger were very anxious not to affront de Gaulle and they had a
                    substantially deferential view of de Gaulle. There's no question. That came out
                    loud and clear. So we in NEA developed a set of options based on the fact that
                    the president wanted a real test of the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>And I can recall we had two or three National Security Council meetings at which
                    I made the presentations, laid out the options, and so on. We had a full
                    discussion, and to set the record straight, if one reads the chapter on this
                    period in the first volume of Henry Kissinger's book, I think there are two
                    things that really need to be made very clear. It just is not so that he was not
                    brought into this. He was part of the whole National Security Council mechanism
                    and was at all the meetings, and participated in the discussions. He didn't
                    agree with the decision, although never said so at the NSC meetings. He didn't
                    agree with the fundamental decision that the Middle East was the only area that
                    had been handed over to Bill Rogers, the Secretary of State, by President Nixon.
                    Kissinger was heavily involved with dozens of papers on Vietnam, and the rest of
                    the world, and China, and what have you. So that there was a fundamental
                    cleavage right there, a strong underlying objection on the part of Kissinger
                    that that responsibility had been placed in the hands of Rogers, the Secretary
                    of State, and the Department of State in particular. And he makes no bones about
                    it in his book that all the way along during that period he did whatever he
                    could to deflect, and to defeat, and to spike the whole initiative.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>But Nixon was very clear that he wanted a test of the Soviet Union and therefore
                    we began to undertake in detail these negotiations with the Soviets with
                    Dobrynin. Now what is not clear in the historic record that needs to be made
                    clear, and I might add there is a marvelous article that has just come out in
                    the Middle East Journal by David Korn, a former colleague of ours, who covers
                    this entire period in great detail. The instructions were a) a genuine test, and
                    b) we would go ahead in the Four Power talks, but the understanding was that
                    Ambassador Yost could not take a substantive position in those Four Power talks
                    that went beyond the substantive position that we were taking in the bilateral
                    talks with the Soviet Union. And therefore the guidance to New York was really
                    based on the substantive positions that were evolving in the context of the
                    U.S.-USSR talks in Washington.</p>
                <p>I must say I don't think Ambassador Yost liked that too much because he felt
                    confined, but that was the reality of the thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, let me just jump in here with a question. As we all
                        know the Israelis over the years have been particularly sensitive to the
                        idea of an imposed settlement from outside. It seems to me that in agreeing
                        to these, not only just one format in which it had that implication, but two
                        formats that Nixon and his lieutenants were laying it pretty heavily on the
                        Israelis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It made the Israelis very nervous because, as you say, a Soviet-American
                    negotiation that fundamentally ran through that whole period of time. The great
                    Israeli fear that an imposed settlement would occur. You will find in the
                    Israeli historical record a contention that they were not kept informed. Not so.
                    They were kept informed all the way along. We regularly called in Rabin as the
                    then Israeli ambassador. We didn't, at that particular juncture, very candidly,
                    make a prior check with the Israelis on a number of the positions that we were
                    taking in our discussions with the Soviet Union. This was a negotiation with the
                    Soviets that was being conducted by the United States, and the Israelis were
                    being kept informed without giving them a veto over the position that we
                    took.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got to the point where you were beginning to
                        develop formulations with the Soviets the idea, of course, all along was
                        that as the two sides came closer together, and could agree on things, that
                        we in turn would go back to the Egyptians on the part of the Soviets, and
                        the Israelis on the part of our talks, and try to sell them to those
                        positions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: That's correct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you relate these two processes? How far did you get in
                        the first, that is to say U.S.-Soviet formulations, and then what happened
                        with our clients, if you can use that term?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>SISCO: Well, with respect to the Soviets, by August or September of '69 we had
                    developed a joint working paper, part of which we negotiated in Moscow. I went
                    to Moscow in July negotiating that with Deputy Minister Vinogradov, and
                    subsequently with Gromyko in Moscow. That working paper by September called for
                    total Israeli withdrawal to the international border, which was the pre-'67
                    line, subject to three conditions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was that in Sinai?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: In Sinai. Clearly one has to underscore that the Soviet-American
                    negotiation only focused on the Sinai. The Four Power talks went beyond that.
                    They dealt with the Jordanian aspect, and the West Bank, and so on, and we were
                    not keen on those Four Power talks, as you know. They were agreed to largely in
                    deference to de Gaulle, but we used to refer to them as the “two-and-a-half”
                    power talks because we made the assumption the Soviets would be against us, the
                    French did not share our position at that time, and that was two against us. And
                    the British were half-and-half. So we used to refer to them as the
                    “two-and-a-half” power talks at that particular juncture.</p>
                <p>But to get back to this, the joint working paper called for total Israeli
                    withdrawal to the international border subject to three conditions. There would
                    be direct negotiations between Egypt and Israel to achieve the following three
                    things: a demilitarization of the Sinai; some sort of a security arrangement
                    along Sharm el Sheikh; and three, that there would be a negotiation that would
                    focus both on the security arrangements and the question of sovereignty in Gaza.
                    That proposition was really never tested, Mike, and I'll tell you why. Because
                    the Soviets went to Nasser and to the Egyptians, and the Egyptian position was;
                    “no”, they didn't want to negotiate those three elements. They wanted the answer
                    to those written right into any treaty. And therefore, what happened was, there
                    was a protracted period of no response from the Soviets. And in the meantime
                    they were beating us over the head from a propaganda point of view in the area
                    distorting our position because we kept those negotiations and the substance of
                    the position quiet as agreed by the two sides. And from the Israeli side, we
                    never really asked them to sign onto that simply because we didn't have any kind
                    of an answer from the other side. We felt there was no need to involve President
                    Nixon in trying to press a position on the Israelis that was unacceptable to the
                    other side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, the version that you get from the Egyptians
                        is...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: ...is just the opposite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...is just the opposite. That we were unable to deliver
                        the Israelis on a couple of positions, but you don't think that's a...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>SISCO: I'm very aware of this, and that's not the right sequence. That's not the
                    way the procedure developed. We said, “All right. Here it is. Here's the working
                    paper.” We were primarily responsible for drafting most of that, even though it
                    was a joint working paper. Remember, that was a time when the concept of peace
                    as a formal contractual relationship—I can hear Eban's words today—was something
                    which the Arab side had not accepted. So what we were really talking about was a
                    formal peace treaty for the first time. That was what we felt we were getting
                    for the Israelis. So the elements of a treaty were never properly tested. We had
                    a very difficult decision in September, 1969, and it was this: the Soviets were
                    misrepresenting our position publicly in the area Sinai, we had no real conduit
                    to the Egyptians other than through the Soviet Union. We felt we were losing all
                    kinds of ground in the Arab world simply because our position was being
                    distorted publicly by the Soviets. This was so despite the fact the working
                    paper called for total Israeli withdrawal subject to certain conditions; the
                    essence of what the Egyptian-Israeli treaty became later on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...the Sisco-Dobrynin talks, and Four Power talks. I
                        wanted to ask, Joe, whether the Egyptians were, at that time, insisting
                        on...were they content to see a negotiation going on between you and
                        Dobrynin that dealt only with the Egyptian-Israeli aspect? Or were they also
                        saying, there has to be a linkage? Or is that something that only appeared
                        later on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: No, the linkage came later. That never came up. But you see we also had
                    the Four Power talks going on, so the advantage of the Four Power talks going on
                    was that this forum was focusing on other parts of an possible comprehensive
                    settlement. The Egyptians therefore were not as vulnerable to the Arab argument
                    that a separate peace treaty was being pursued. We saw the Egyptian-Israeli
                    peace treaty as an integral part of a comprehensive settlement based on Security
                    Council Resolution 242.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the end did the talks fail on this specific point, or
                        was it more the overall objective circumstances in the area? Or was it
                        perhaps because we were beginning to get into this bureaucratic problem
                        within the U.S. government of differences between the White House, and the
                        State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>SISCO: Well, I think in retrospect, what you've got to say is that the objective
                    conditions for agreement didn't exist in the area, Mike. I don't think Nasser
                    was ready to make peace. I don't think the Israelis were ready. And in that
                    sense, I think that was the fundamental factor. The mistrust, at that particular
                    juncture, was still far too deep. But I would underscore that proposition
                    contained in the joint working paper remained untested. And the reason why
                    Secretary William Rogers made the famous Galaxy speech in October '69 was
                    because our position was being misrepresented in the area by the Soviets. It was
                    felt that we needed to expose the substantive position that we had taken in
                    these talks. And, of course, that really then caused an even greater storm
                    simply because of the fact that while the Israelis were unhappy throughout that
                    whole negotiation, and making that very clear to the White House, as well as to
                    us, the fact of the matter is that when the proposal, which became known as the
                    Rogers plan, was exposed in the Galaxy speech, it made it possible for
                    politicians in Israel to react negatively as well as its supporters in this
                    country. So that chapter closed.</p>
                <p>But there is one major result that emanates from that long, drawn out negotiation
                    with the...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...just on the Rogers, the so-called Rogers plan which was
                        the Galaxy speech. There was no real thought that by running this up on the
                        flag pole publicly, that you might shock the two sides into public
                        acceptance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It was closing a chapter, Mike. Even though the Soviets came in latter in
                    the fall of '69, with a few little wrinkles in their position, it was far too
                    late. It was another lost opportunity. As a result of that, we in the Near
                    Eastern Bureau prepared a memorandum which we sent through the Secretary of
                    State to President Nixon in which we said that, “Mr. President, we've given you
                    the test of the Soviets. The Soviets have failed. They've not been able to
                    produce for whatever reason, their concerns, or the Egyptian, or a combination
                    thereof, and that from here on in, in the peace process, the United States
                    should seek to do this unilaterally.”</p>
                <p>This memorandum went to the White House, and I was on a trip in Air Force One,
                    when the President called me into his compartment, with this memorandum right on
                    his lap, underlined all over the place. And we went over it very, very
                    carefully. And President Nixon said, “Joe, I agree fully with this
                    recommendation. From now on we're going to go it alone in the peace process. The
                    Soviets had their opportunity.” The interesting feature is that that decision
                    taken by Richard Nixon became the continuity of the American peace process, the
                    third party role of the U.S. continuing to this day. And I can recall that
                    memorandum. I can recall it underlined. I can recall being on Air Force One,
                    going over the memorandum with President Nixon. And there was no doubt in his
                    mind as to how to proceed. It was a very, very impressive involvement on the
                    part of the President, as far as I was concerned. This was the birth of the
                    unilateral third party role of the U.S. in the Mid East peace process.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And, of course, I think it's fair to say, as you suggested
                        earlier, that the Rogers plan had another legacy, which is that it really
                        set forth many positions which later became embodied in Camp David in the
                        Egypt-Israel peace treaty.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Sure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this is the way negotiations work. You know, out of
                        many failed examples, sometimes things get put together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: If you look at that document, the U.S.-USSR working paper of '69, and then
                    you compare—which I've done, the Egyptian-Israeli treaty—I marvel at the amount
                    of exact verbiage in that Egyptian- Israeli treaty that was contained in that
                    original '69 working paper we produced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the meantime, of course, on the ground you had the war
                        of attrition beginning to heat up, which became more and more of a concern
                        and not simply because the Israelis and the Egyptians were having at each
                        other again, but because the Soviets were beginning to get more and more
                        involved, in a very real and unprecedented way. Soviet pilots appeared
                        flying Egyptian MiGs. And even in one instance several of the Soviet flown
                        MiGs were shot down by the Israelis. So things were pretty dicey. But we
                        achieved—certainly one of the major accomplishments of the period—what was
                        called the cease-fire and standstill agreement.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes. “Stop shooting, start talking” was the phrase that I coined.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, right. Well, tell us about that episode, Joe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: That was a negotiated cease-fire in 1970. What's amazing about it is that
                    it was done in diplomatic channels. Right from our Assistant Secretary's office
                    in NEA, to Israel, and to Cairo. Dayan being the principal element in Israel.
                    Rabin playing an important role here as Ambassador.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Golda was still Prime Minister?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>SISCO: Golda Meir was Prime Minister. What we did was to negotiate the
                    cease-fire, and linked it to a standstill of missiles and a call for indirect
                    negotiations between the parties. In this instance, Ambassador Jarring of Sweden
                    was still involved so that the agreement, this “stop shooting, start talking”
                    initiative, the cease-fire agreement, was encompassed in one UN document. There
                    were two major crises. One was that after we had worked it all out, Golda got
                    cold feet. It had been agreed to by the Israelis, Dayan, and so on. And at about
                    7:00 o'clock one night Rabin came to my office, very disturbed, and said, “We've
                    run into problems with Mrs. Meir. She wants to talk to you.” And I said to
                    Rabin, “Well, Yitzhak, I can't talk to the Prime Minister. I'm just an Assistant
                    Secretary. Let me report this to the Secretary of State and we'll see what can
                    be worked out.” He said, “No, she wants to talk to you.” And what could I do? So
                    she got on the phone—I have a memorandum of this— we had a fifteen minute
                    discussion in which I said to her that she could not now back off. We had the
                    agreement of the other side. The point of difference was not significant; it
                    emanated from domestic political concerns. Rabin was helpless in the situation
                    because first of all, he had committed himself. He had agreed earlier, with the
                    approval of his Prime Minister and government. Mrs. Meir finally agreed. But the
                    real crisis came later when, as the cease-fire was being implemented, Nasser
                    decided to move his missiles forward into the zone contrary to the standstill
                    element in the agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was after the agreement?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: ...after the agreement. There was a cease-fire and a standstill, and there
                    were four or five different points to the standstill as well. Now one of the
                    real difficulties, and I can recall the intelligence people on this, and Ray
                    Cline in particular—he and I worked together on this. We had maps, and the
                    Israelis had maps, but our map and the Israeli map apparently had differences of
                    where the missiles might have been located originally before the cease-fire, and
                    after the cease-fire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have to interject here because my memory is quite good.
                        I'd just checked on as your director for Egyptian Affairs, and I went down
                        to the national reconnaissance center down at Anacostia and looked at the
                        photographs. And mind you, as Director of Egyptian Affairs, I felt I ought
                        to be very skeptical about this and protect my clients if I possibly could.
                        But I came back absolutely convinced, Joe, that there was a problem about
                        the base photography because for some reason the U2...it was not as
                        cloudy...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: ...cloudy, or something, yes, twenty-four hours later...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But even allowing for that factor, there was just no
                        question that activity was going on. There were two theses and I'd welcome
                        your recollection of how you came out on this. One was that Nasser had been
                        so weakened by the 1967 catastrophe, he was so dependent on the Soviets with
                        Soviets flying his aircraft, that this had to be coming from Moscow. It had
                        to be the Soviets attempting to gain an advantage over the United States
                        which was backing the Israelis. I was always a little skeptical personally
                        and my theory was that Nasser had caught short his own generals—air defense
                        generals—by agreeing to the Sisco plan before the missiles sites could be
                        completed. And that indeed he was weakened but not so much vis-a-vis Moscow,
                        as with his own military. They were saying, “We're not going to be caught
                        with our pants down when warfare resumes.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: I'm inclined to this latter view. Nasser did have a problem at that
                    particular juncture with his military. I don't know that the record is any
                    clearer today than it was then, but my feeling would be, that was it. The other
                    problem, if you will recall is, that during that period our intelligence people
                    indicated to the Secretary of State that all this Egyptian activity was going
                    on. He did not believe the Egyptians and positioned the missiles forward within
                    the agreed zone. And therefore, we arranged to take him to NSA. I can recall the
                    room was three times this size, and they had all of these photographs pinned on
                    the wall, and they showed him here, here, here. I'd never had had that
                    experience before.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The evidence was unmistakable.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It was clear to me that the Egyptians violated the standstill. We went
                    back to State and Rogers was still doubtful. I think that was a mistake.
                    Subsequently, a White House decision was taken to provide additional arms to the
                    Israelis. In order to rectify the situation, added military assistance was
                    provided to the Israelis. But there was a loss of Egypt's credibility. That was
                    the critical thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course in September of 1970 we had a momentous change
                        in leadership in Egypt. Nasser died and a new man took over. At the
                        beginning no one thought very much about that. It took about a year or two
                        to develop, but then we entered into a very interesting diplomatic period as
                        it became apparent that there really was a difference in leadership, and a
                        change of mood. You recall that period well. Sadat began to sketch out some
                        ideas. We attempted to grab hold of them. You made a trip to Israel in the
                        summer of 1970, as I remember, to try to sell the Israelis on the idea that
                        Sadat was for real. It was pretty tough to convince them. And then as I
                        recall it, Joe, you got undermined by our own government in what I think
                        would have been the right thing to do. But you tell us about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>SISCO: We had an NSC meeting in San Clemente. That was at the time of the
                    Nixon-China initiative, Mike. The first part of that meeting was on China and it
                    was about the time that Bill Rogers was informed of the whole China episode. And
                    the second part was on the Middle East. The mandate that I was given by the
                    President with Kissinger right there, was that I was to try to get a modest
                    disengagement of some sort, and that I should push it very hard—I can remember
                    President Nixon's words—”But if you find, Joe, that Mrs. Meir isn't going to
                    buy, don't push it to the point where it creates a major crisis with the
                    Israelis because we will take another crack at her subsequently.” I'm almost
                    quoting him literally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By “subsequently,” he had something in mind about
                        elections, I take it, because weren't you coming up to an election
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes. In any event, he wanted it pushed, and pushed hard. And so Roy
                    Atherton and I went to Israel. We developed a very modest disengagement
                    proposal. Dayan was very attracted to it. Eban was. And we met for a day and a
                    half with Meir, Dayan; Allon, Rabin; Pares and Eban. Just the two of us. It's
                    good to be young, I did not feel intimidated at all. We had a very sensible
                    piece of paper. And I can recall my pleading with Mrs. Meir saying, “Look, we're
                    only talking about 500 riflemen crossing the Suez canal. What Sadat needs is
                    merely political symbolism, I know, and that this can be achieved.” Two days of
                    intensive talks. She wouldn't accept it, even though some of her ministers
                    wanted to. That was the time we injected humor in the situation. We needed a
                    little lighter moment or two. The humor that you may not recall, Mike, is as
                    follows: Roy and I stayed at the U.S. Embassy in Tel Aviv the last night. Then
                    on Saturday morning, and we drove to Jerusalem for the concluding session. She
                    had turned it down. We were going to pay our final courtesy call, and say all
                    the right things to keep it open for the next time, as President Nixon had
                    instructed me. I decided to buy her a bouquet of flowers at a stand on the way
                    from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem. I walked in, to the Prime Minister's office in the
                    cabinet room, hundreds of photographers, and TV, and so on. And I said—I didn't
                    call her Prime Minister that time—I said, “Golda, I've brought you some
                    flowers.” And she said to me, coyly, “Well, Joe, now you're saying it with
                    flowers. It won't work.” I responded, “I am leaving no stone unturned.” I'll
                    never forget that. It was a marvelously human and funny end to a long,
                    unsuccessful negotiation.</p>
                <p>But to get back on the serious side. As I noted earlier several Israeli ministers
                    were in agreement with us, quite desirous of achieving such a disengagement
                    agreement between Israel and Egypt, but Mrs. Meir said, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your reading of her...I mean, was she unhappy with
                        the nature of this proposal, or was she just profoundly skeptical that Sadat
                        could deliver any of this, and that it would lead to something in the
                        interest of Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>SISCO: It was not so much the proposal, Mike, it's what you've just indicated.
                    Clearly she kept saying throughout the Arabs are not ready, they don't want to
                    have peace with us, this fellow Sadat is a hothead. She changed her mind years
                    later when Sadat flew to Jerusalem. Sadat did have that kind of a reputation at
                    that particular moment. So, again, I believe even a modest disengagement
                    agreement proved unachievable because of lack of trust. Just a very, very deep
                    suspicion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As I recall there was also some...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: One has to say objectively the correlation of forces, to use a Soviet
                    phrase, favored the Israelis. I mean there was no real threat. Israel had
                    overwhelming military advantage and strength. They had the upper hand in every
                    respect. The objective conditions were such the Israelis did not feel any
                    concessions were necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. As I recall, also, that there was a question of some
                        arms to be delivered, some aircraft, or something like that to Israel at the
                        time, and that you felt strongly that that ought to be brought into play in
                        some way in these negotiations, in trying to bring the Israelis aboard. In
                        the event, however, as I recall, the White House did not agree with that
                        idea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: I was trying to use that as an inducement, a carrot. There was never any
                    threat that was involved in terms of a cut-off of military aid. That wasn't in
                    the ball park. But I was using that as an added way to contribute to their
                    security, and to give them greater assurance that their security was not going
                    to be jeopardized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. But in the end you backed off precisely because the
                        president had put it to you in those terms, which was, don't really drive it
                        to the wall.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Right. And you know some things have come out, Mike, we ought to
                    straighten out the record. In Sy Hirshberg's book he indicates that whole
                    mission was just a sheer facade, that there was no serious intent on our part to
                    do anything. Hirshberg's book is very inaccurate on this point. He says in
                    effect that I had been instructed ahead of time to just go through the motions,
                    which of course, was not the case. It was a serious attempt by the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: However, it was the case, I think, that Henry Kissinger as
                        a National Security adviser, was becoming increasingly skeptical of the
                        State Department approach. You could see this developing. In a sense he had
                        a hands-off period for a period of time in '69 although, as you say, his
                        advice was really one of skepticism to begin with. But it became more
                        prominent as time went along, and eventually you got the president listening
                        more to Henry, and less to Rogers and Sisco.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It began in an explicit sort of way, Mike. Right after the breakdown of
                    the Egyptian-Israeli cease-fire and the standstill in early '70; it gave
                    Kissinger the opportunity to wrest the initiative from Secretary Rogers. There
                    had been a year of Soviet-American negotiation—Kissinger did not agree with
                    those either—so these two factors led Kissinger to convince President Nixon he
                    should take over. Moreover, Kissinger then had more time for the Middle East.
                    The initiative began to flow to the White House, and it started then with a
                    meeting in New York between Hafiz Ismail and Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were a couple of secret meetings that they had. The
                        State Department was not involved.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, yes, there was an insistence on my part we not be excluded. I argued
                    forcefully on this, and we were able to include Roy, my deputy, Roy Atherton. I
                    knew that I couldn't press myself into the situation simply because he was
                    seeking to exclude me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and of course, those got nowhere.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Hal Saunders, Kissinger's Middle East expert on the NSC, was involved on
                    the White House side.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But in the meantime things were...Sadat had quite clearly
                        made up his mind that negotiations would not be possible until there was
                        some kind of new tests of arms, and was preparing for the 1973 war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, you remember “the year of decision” by President Sadat. We didn't
                    really take it seriously. We should have, but we didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Coming to that period, you were in the forefront. In 1973,
                        of course, we were all taken by surprise including the Israelis by Sadat's
                        decision. He disguised it very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Very well.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, at this point, just in the '73 war, were you
                        still Assistant Secretary of NEA? You were, as I remember it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: I had not shifted to Under Secretary until '74.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That war went on for a longer period of time, of course,
                        than the 1967 war, and there were some interesting decisions. At some point
                        during the conflict the United States took the decision that it made better
                        sense not to revert to the kind of 1967 policy decision that we made, but
                        rather to call for a cease-fire in place. What do you recall about that
                        policy decision?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It was influenced by the situation on the ground, Mike. First of all when
                    the hostilities started the Israelis assured us they could contain the
                    situation, they could handle the situation militarily. After forty-eight hours,
                    as you well know, the Egyptians were on the verge of a fundamental, major
                    military breakthrough. And it was at that particular juncture the Soviet Union
                    was willing to settle for the then existing status quo on the ground.
                    Subsequently, as the counter force of the Israelis made itself felt, the Soviet
                    position shifted, and they were willing to accept a cease fire based on the
                    original lines.</p>
                <p>But what is interesting in that period is this. Kissinger was unfairly criticized
                    by the Israelis as wanting to squeeze them during that particular period in
                    order to achieve political results. That's just not the case. He was very
                    conscious of the fact that after the war—wars are fought for political
                    reasons—and after the war there would have to be some kind of a negotiation. We
                    made very early contact with Sadat during the period of hostilities. We told
                    Sadat: “When this war ends, we want to sit down with you and work these things
                    out.” That was a very wise move, by Kissinger, and that told Sadat, I think,
                    that in the aftermath of the warfare the Americans were genuinely interested in
                    doing something to move matters toward peace. Sadat was impressed.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>The other thing which Kissinger is criticized for, unfairly again, is that
                    somehow or other he held up the aerial resupply effort to the Israelis. Not the
                    case at all. Israeli Ambassador Dinitz came in about the third day of the '73
                    war in a panic. They needed more equipment, he said, and so on. They were having
                    difficulties on the ground. And at that time the situation was very, very
                    uncertain as to whether the Israelis in fact could contain the situation.
                    Kissinger moved very rapidly to resupply, but quite frankly, there was a
                    disinclination to do anything about that in the Pentagon. I can recall about six
                    different conversations from the top on down by Kissinger, by myself, shouting
                    and arguing—with Pentagon officials at the top—to no avail. And I finally said
                    to Henry, “There's just no way you're going to get this done. You've just got to
                    go to the President, and the President just has to order it.” Up to that time
                    the Pentagon was contending no aircraft were available, that they had to be
                    leased. A preposterous argument. There was a difference of view between State
                    and Defense. Schlesinger did not want it done. And so the President picked up
                    the phone and told the Pentagon to get on with it. The resupply effort then took
                    place and the Pentagon did a fine job once they were allowed to do it. So it was
                    not Kissinger that delayed resupply of the Israelis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He did, however, squeeze the Israelis pretty hard on the
                        question of encirclement of the Third Army.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: He certainly did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And, of course, that was justified because we did have an
                        agreement on a cease-fire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: We had an agreement. We'd been to Moscow, and we jointly agreed on the
                    cease-fire, and we got for the Israelis in return the first Soviet endorsement
                    of direct negotiations which became part of Security Council Resolution 338.
                    That it was a remarkable achievement, something the Israelis had sought for
                    years. We drafted that Security Council Resolution 338 in the Kremlin. And it
                    was the only time in my diplomatic history, when from the Kremlin we sent
                    parallel instructions to the Soviet and the American representative at the UN
                    that they were to co-sponsor the Resolution, and get unanimous agreement of the
                    Security Council. We had trouble communicating it because of some problem. Larry
                    Eagleburger had to go to Air Force Two, in order to transmit the cable to New
                    York. That's the human interest side of that episode in October '73. Kissinger
                    saw that political steps would have to be taken in the aftermath of the war, and
                    he moved very rapidly after that. That begins a new chapter, and a very positive
                    chapter. It led to disengagement agreements between Egypt and Israel, and Syria
                    and Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a quick-learning experience, I think, for
                        Kissinger, because before the war he really took the position that, “You
                        don't have to worry about the Israelis, they're not going to be challenged
                        militarily, and the United States can rest its interest on Israeli strength
                        in the area.” I think many of us in the State Department were skeptical of
                        that proposition, although, of course, we couldn't predict when hostilities
                        might break out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Well, we relied too much on Israeli intelligence before the '73 war. Even
                    on the morning that it all started, we had met within the last 24 hours with
                    both the Israeli and the Egyptian Foreign Ministers. We'd been given assurances
                    by the latter that only military maneuvers were accomplished—that there was no
                    aggression. He did not lie to us. He was not informed by his government. It's
                    interesting because some years later the former Egyptian Foreign minister called
                    me just to reconfirm—his credibility was involved, that he had not lied. The
                    historical record confirms this. We know now on the basis of what Egyptian
                    General Gamasy said to me later, and the book written by Heikal. The Heikal book
                    is very good in this regard in the first chapter. The Foreign Minister was not
                    brought in by his government. He did not have the information. There were very
                    few people, Mubarak knew it, Sadat and Gamasy knew it, and only a very few
                    others. So we had been given assurances. I said to Henry, “Well, I think based
                    on what we know the Israelis should be able to take care of this.” But we were
                    prudent enough, so that Henry put in a call to our intelligence people, and
                    said, “We want to have your reading as well.” We were relying on Israeli
                    intelligence. But whatever reading they gave us, they too were relying on
                    Israeli intelligence. So it was just a bad, bad intelligence gaff, on the part
                    of the Israelis as well as the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it opened a new chapter. Things began to happen very
                        fast. One of the features of the next chapter was the continuation of the
                        policy which you mentioned earlier, which was we were not giving the Soviets
                        a chance at this new one. Do you think looking back on it that that was a
                        smart policy decision?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Oh, it was the right move because we were the third party element that
                    could produce something. The strength of the United States, even to this day in
                    the area, is based on its ability, or inability as the case may be, to achieve
                    political results. Soviet diplomacy at that time was a diplomacy with one arm
                    behind its back. To some degree that is still the case. It had relations with
                    only one side, and even with that one side, it didn't have relations with all of
                    the Arabs. It was in no position to produce anything. Moreover, the Egyptians
                    didn't want the Soviets in. And even when we went on and did the Syrian-Israeli
                    disengagement agreement, despite the special relationship and all the support
                    that Syrian President Assad has been and continues to receive from the Soviet
                    Union, he didn't want the Soviets involved. And therefore, there's no doubt that
                    nobody other than the U.S. could produce anything. Moreover, the Israelis didn't
                    want the Soviets involved. None of the principal actors, in the region wanted to
                    bring the Soviets into the situation because Moscow was not in a position to
                    bring its influence to bear in order to achieve positive results.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're now approaching the shuttle period in which you
                        played a key role. I think you went on all of the shuttles. You were
                        drafting many of the positions, conducting much of the diplomacy. Let me
                        ask, Joe, just to begin with, about your impression of Kissinger as a
                        diplomat. There's much...everybody agrees he was an extraordinarily
                        effective person. There's a good deal of material that suggests that he had
                        all of these disparate Middle Eastern leaders practically eating out of his
                        hand. Was he as effective as all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was remarkable.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes, absolutely remarkable. He was able to combine overall strategy with
                    tactics. The rapport he struck with all of the Middle Eastern leaders of
                    consequence is unparalleled. King Hussein had great confidence in him. Kissinger
                    was rightly viewed as one who had influence within the administration. Of all
                    people, the people who might have been expected to be more skeptical was not.
                    Kissinger and Saudi King Fahd hit it off very well. King Fahd was taken with
                    Kissinger. Sadat had full confidence in Kissinger. The Israelis expected him to
                    press them very, very hard. With the Israelis, he tried to use the force of his
                    strategic arguments, very rational arguments. As to President Assad, two
                    individuals with great senses of humor. I can tell you dozens of stories in this
                    regard. And Assad just looked forward to seeing Kissinger on all of these
                    occasions. I've never seen in my entire career a case of better rapport that was
                    established by a Secretary of State with leaders in the area during the
                    disengagement agreement negotiating period. It was a remarkable feat. I had my
                    arguments with Henry, and my differences and agreements, but there's no
                    gainsaying: this was a man of great talent, and he applied it very effectively
                    in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw a lot of these leaders at the same time. Give us
                        your impressions of them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Assad, in my judgement, probably the most intelligent, the shrewdest,
                    toughest—negotiated every tree in every yard in Syrian-Israeli disengagement
                    agreement; was the tactician as well as the strategist; Byzantine, attractive,
                    and strong. A realist. Not anti- American. Rather scathing about the
                    Soviets.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>Sadat, as you know, you knew him well, flamboyant. Liked to think and talk in
                    terms of broad strategic sweeps. In part, I think, because Kissinger spoke that
                    way, whereas Assad negotiated every paragraph in the agreement. The two
                    disengagement agreements on the Egyptian side, Sadat was little interested in
                    what was really in the details of the substance. He left it to Fahmy and Gamasy,
                    the foreign and defense ministers respectfully, and whenever a difficulty arose
                    Sadat would break the back of the issue on political grounds rather than other
                    considerations. And both Gamasy and Fahmy were very critical, and very doubtful,
                    about Sadat pursuing the disengagement agreement between Israel and Egypt.</p>
                <p>King Hussein, is as he's pictured—courageous, straight forward, a deep friend of
                    the United States at that particular juncture. One fundamental mistake we made,
                    Mike, is that we got a first disengagement agreement with Egypt—then one with
                    Syria. We did not achieve one for Jordan. The picture would have been
                    considerably different, in my judgement. And in retrospect, both Henry and I, I
                    think, made a mistake. Hussein took out a map, and he just wanted minimally a
                    symbolic disengagement. It didn't make any difference, quite frankly. A
                    kilometer here, a kilometer there, but he needed that politically because he was
                    the number one friend of the United States, both Egypt and Syria had achieved a
                    disengagement agreement, and he had not. So we went to the Israelis, and Rabin
                    was then Prime Minister. There were two reasons why we didn't press it forward.
                    One, Rabin said, “I can't take it politically, that if I'm pressed on this right
                    now, I'm going to lose the Prime Ministership.” And we generally tended to give
                    some credence to that argument. The other was more fundamental, and certainly
                    clearer in our own minds. Namely, that we couldn't achieve a Jordanian-Israeli
                    disengagement agreement without the direct involvement of President Richard
                    Nixon vis-a-vis the Israelis. We recalled the critical concessions made by
                    Israel in the Egyptian-Israeli disengagement agreement and in the Syrian one. At
                    the decisive moments there were brought about not by Henry Kissinger, but by
                    Richard Nixon, and Richard Nixon's direct involvement with the Israelis. The
                    Israelis were very fearful of President Nixon. Henry, on specific occasions, had
                    to go to the President, and he got Presidential intervention when necessary.
                    Well, we felt that with Nixon being weakened domestically at that particular
                    juncture, that the President could not play the kind of role vis-a-vis Israel
                    which would have been required. And therefore we decided not to go ahead. It's a
                    very sad chapter. That may not have been a correct assessment. But those were
                    the two reasons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's move now. Shortly thereafter, was it 1974, you were
                        brought upstairs as Under Secretary for Political Affairs, the top job for a
                        career person. Tell me a little bit about what you felt, Joe, during that
                        period. That was about a two year period, a three year period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: '74 to '76. Just a little bit less than three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the major problems? We obviously don't have time
                        to cover everything here that you contended with in that position, but give
                        me your impression of the job itself.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>SISCO: The job itself, as Kissinger organized it, was a job that could be very
                    substantial, or it could be very limited. While I kept my eye on the Middle
                    East, there were other things—the whole Cyprus crisis came up at that particular
                    juncture, and I was involved in a shuttle diplomacy between Greece and Turkey in
                    that particular period. But candidly, Mike, the best job I ever had in the State
                    Department was the five year period as Assistant Secretary for NEA for all of
                    the difficulties, and doing, as Henry Kissinger says in his book, on many
                    occasions more negotiating between Rogers and Kissinger, than on the substance.
                    But that was by far the most satisfying five years of my entire career.</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary's job is one where the geographic bureaus are funneling
                    material through you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Secretary, you were saying that if you have a strong
                        Assistant Secretary, he is likely to establish a personal relationship with
                        the Secretary which tends to cut the Under Secretary out, and of course, if
                        you have a strong Secretary of State, it also works in the other direction.
                        You tend to be shuffling things. On the other hand, Joe, the Under Secretary
                        position had some important responsibilities. For example, intelligence
                        operations, also crisis management. You're really the desk officer for every
                        crisis that comes along. Is the job, as it's constituted...does it have to
                        be that way? It seems to me that all Under Secretaries are almost killed in
                        that job, it's so demanding. I guess you have to have somebody in the State
                        Department in that role.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>SISCO: Sure. What happens is this, Mike, in very simple language. It is seven
                    days a week, and the reason is that, if you're an Assistant Secretary and you've
                    got a problem, you have two choices. You either call the Secretary of State on
                    Saturday afternoon, or Sunday morning, or you call the Under Secretary of State.
                    And so they used to call the Under Secretary of State. After all, you know very
                    well, they knew me, I knew them. We'd been working together for twenty years.
                    There was Phil Habib in Far East as Assistant Secretary. I think Sam Lewis in
                    those days was IO Assistant Secretary. These are all people that worked
                    together. And David Newsom was on hand, Walter Stoessel was on hand. These are
                    all very, very able people. We worked together well as professionals. In every
                    crisis management, the Under Secretary for Political Affairs is involved. And
                    there are trouble shooting functions such as in Cyprus. A crisis, for example
                    like Indo-Pakistan, was one in which I was heavily involved. However, at that
                    time, I was also a member of the 301 committee dealing also with high level
                    intelligence matters as the State Department representative. I got involved in
                    the major intelligence decisions. We would sit down in the situation room maybe
                    once a week, once every two weeks, whatever it happened to be. The Pentagon
                    would be represented, Bill Clement, Deputy Secretary. The Director of CIA would
                    be there. I would represent the State Department, and there were two or three
                    others, and members of the NSC staff, and certain concrete decisions were taken.
                    There were sensitive decisions. We made sure the Secretary of State was informed
                    and the President. Or many times we didn't take a decision, but instead made a
                    recommendation to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you feel that that worked well? That mechanism
                        itself.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes it did. I think it worked very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because there have been times, as you know, when the
                        United States government has been accused of not really relating
                        intelligence operations to what the rest of the government is doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: And those were examples where the regular mechanism probably wasn't used.
                    Where you probably had a case of the CIA going to the NSC adviser without the
                    Secretary of State involved. It is a mistake to do it this way. So the mechanism
                    at that coordinating level was excellent. But I'm quite sure not everything came
                    within the framework of the 301 mechanism. I was under no illusions in that
                    regard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, looking at crisis management more broadly, not just
                        intelligence, what's your judgement as to how well the mechanism responds to
                        it? And how much does it depend on institutional arrangements, and how much
                        of that is irrelevant because in the last analysis you're really dependant
                        on the quality of the leaders that you've got in place?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>SISCO: Well, Mike, it's a combination of both. From an institutional point of
                    view, I think we're extremely well organized. We didn't always have a Crisis
                    Management Center as we do, and did, at that particular juncture. I think that
                    mechanism of monitoring, feeding the material at one central point is effective.
                    From my vantage point, and in all candor, I think I've probably been involved in
                    crisis management over the decades as most—from the Bay of Pigs to the Cuban
                    missile crisis, to the Suez crisis, the '73 war, and Cyprus, and Indo-Pakistan.
                    I was involved in every one of these, Mike. I think, institutionally speaking,
                    we are extremely well organized and many, many other countries pattern their
                    institutional arrangements on our own. It's when people try to get around the
                    established mechanisms that we run into problems. For example, take the Bay of
                    Pigs. The Bay of Pigs was handled—and this is well before your time—through a
                    mechanism where much of the Department of State was cut out. And that causes
                    difficulties. So there are occasions...there are lapses, I think, less of an
                    institutional character, but more of the individuals that are involved. You've
                    got to have people who are conscious of the need to coordinate a whole
                    government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...fast enough, for example, if you've got really a hot
                        crisis, does the mechanism allow the process of excluding all those
                        extraneous people? You know, the average day in the State Department you've
                        got to get USIA's clearance, this clearance, that clearance...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: It is rapid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does it escalate at all rapidly so that you've really got
                        a...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: But, Mike, the key is the Assistant Secretary. The key is the Assistant
                    Secretary. He is in a position to push buttons at the Secretary's level, at the
                    NSC level, and the Presidential level. Just like that. He really is, provided
                    people have confidence in him, and what he's bringing up to them. And therefore,
                    the system can work in a very deliberate, coordinating, slow sort of way, but it
                    can work very rapidly when necessary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you need good men in that job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Now I can give you an example of where the system was circumvented. Let me
                    give you an example. I was intimately involved. It was the Palestinian attempt
                    to create a Palestinian state in Jordan, so called “Black September” in
                    1970.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, we didn't talk about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>SISCO: The way that was handled, quite frankly, primarily, by three people in the
                    White House. The Secretary of State, the President, and myself, literally in the
                    White House for an extended period of time in which telephone calls in order to
                    get the Israelis to mobilize their 20,000 forces. I must have had a dozen
                    conversations with the Soviet Union right there in Washington at which we made
                    it very plain that if they didn't put a stop to this thing through the Syrians,
                    that there was no way in which we were going to be able to control the
                    situation, and that if this continued that there was definitely going to be an
                    Israeli intervention militarily. And, of course, at the same time you had the
                    wonderful conjunction of the fact that the Jordanians did well on the ground at
                    a critical point in stemming the attack. And third, there was the realistic
                    assessment of Assad. Assad took the decision for the Syrians that it was really
                    time to back off. So that there was an orchestration politically as militarily.
                    But I'm aghast as to how that was handled. Only a small part of the government
                    was involved. It makes me nervous to this day, it's the wrong way to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It turned out well, but it can turn out poorly also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes. One thing I learned in my career is that there were cases where one
                    superior may be on the margin. It doesn't help your career to be heavily
                    involved, and your superior marginally involved. I can remember during the Congo
                    crisis when President Kennedy decided to call me several times during the
                    period. He was prone to do that. I found it embarrassing to then report the
                    conversation to my superior who obviously had been bypassed. It was an
                    uncomfortable situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I got one myself.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>SISCO: And I got into trouble with my Assistant Secretary as a result of it. I
                    had nothing to do with it. Well, that happened on other occasions later on. The
                    only individual that was tolerant of that, when he knew that this was happening
                    and it was not the fault of the recipient of the telephone call, was, God bless
                    him, Dean Rusk. He really understood when that sort of thing happened and didn't
                    blame the innocent recipient. But I'll tell you, it is hurtful. President Nixon
                    used to call me, at home. And he'd say, “Well, you know, Henry is unhappy about
                    this” and so on. He said, “You know, Joe, you ought to...maybe we can do
                    this...” Amazing! On several occasions when Henry Kissinger was unhappy with
                    Bill Rogers, the President of the United States called me at home with a
                    suggestion as to how I might keep calm the situation. President Nixon did not
                    want to confront either Rogers or Kissinger. This sort of thing causes trouble
                    for the professional within the bureaucracy. I remember President Johnson in
                    this regard. Ambassador Goldberg had made a recommendation. This was only three
                    or four weeks after I had taken over as Assistant Secretary for IO. Johnson had
                    fired the previous Assistant Secretary, and I'd gone to Goldberg and said to
                    Goldberg, “You're the new United States Ambassador to the UN (I had never met
                    Goldberg before) I'll be glad to resign so that you can pick your own Assistant
                    Secretary.” And he said, “No, I would like you to continue.” Three weeks after
                    he took over, and I took over—we took over at the same time—he sent a memorandum
                    recommending that the UN Security Council be involved in Vietnam. And I had
                    tried to discourage Goldberg from doing it because, first of all, what he wanted
                    done couldn't be done within the framework of the Security Council. I did an
                    analytical memo for him. He was just hell-bent on doing it. So the Acting
                    Secretary of State, George Ball, called me and said, “What about this?” And I
                    said, “Look, I tried to discourage him, and here are the reasons why we should
                    not do this. We'll end up having to veto what is going to be produced. Here's
                    what will be produced.” It will be against us, and we will end up vetoing the
                    resolution, and it will be a great propaganda loss, let alone we won't achieve a
                    UN involvement of a positive character. Ball communicated that to Johnson
                    orally. President Johnson calls me, and he says, “Joe, we're having an NSC
                    meeting at Camp David tomorrow. I want a memorandum on my desk tonight.” This
                    was Saturday afternoon at two o'clock. “I want a memorandum on my desk by the
                    first thing tomorrow morning giving me your views on the pros and cons of moving
                    this matter into the Security Council.” So here I am, Goldberg saying yes, the
                    President not wanting to go. So I called Ball, and I said, “George, the
                    President just called me and he wants me to do a memo giving him my views. What
                    do you want me to do?” He was the Acting Secretary of State. He said, “Joe, just
                    put it down as you see it.” Which I did precisely. And then, according to Bob
                    McNamara, the next morning, Johnson reads the entire memorandum to all of the
                    NSC, including Goldberg, in which I opposed Goldberg's views. This is the third
                    week of my relationship with Goldberg. I figured a week from now he's going to
                    go to the Secretary of State and ask that I be fired. But he didn't, and he
                    respected the differing view.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>It also happened on India, and Pakistan where Kissinger and I disagreed on an
                    intelligence report. There was an intelligence report that came in which said
                    that there was a cabinet meeting in which the Indians intended to go beyond
                    separating Bangladesh from Pakistan, but also to pursue military operations in
                    order to destroy effectively the overall military capacity of Pakistan for an
                    indefinite period. I cast doubt on the memorandum, which came from dubious
                    sources. I argued strongly against it saying that's not the assumption on which
                    we should be operating. This was in a NSC staff meeting, and Kissinger carted me
                    to the President's office and, of course, what he did not tell me, and what the
                    President didn't tell me was, that they were then using the Pakistanis as a
                    conduit in opening the door to China. That was the main reason for a distorted
                    tilt towards Pakistan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...when you're not fully cognizant of...exactly, the
                        dangers of it. Well, Joe, let me take just a few moments, because we've got
                        to bring this to a close. We've gone through the historical part, but let me
                        ask you a few questions that really look back on your experience. If you
                        look back over a 40 year span of policy making in the Middle East, how do
                        you evaluate our performance in this area? And I think of it really in two
                        terms, as an old practitioner myself, one being the policy itself, and then
                        the implementation of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: One, you can't get anything done unless there's direct Presidential
                    involvement at the key points. Two, you've got to be very sure that both your
                    external, as well as your domestic position is unassailable and strong, and
                    defensible because of the close domestic-external interaction on this policy.
                    Three, I felt that in the earlier phases, in the disengagement phase, that on
                    the whole it was a sensible policy substantively. Under the Reagan
                    administration the policy has tilted too much. On occasions, the tail was
                    wagging the dog. For example, the whole Lebanese '82 episode is one that we
                    might have contributed to inadvertently; rather than being leaders on this, we
                    were being led. I feel we are still the indispensable element in the area. I
                    don't feel that since the Egyptian-Israeli treaty there have been occasions
                    during the Reagan Administration that we pursued the peace powers with the
                    required activism and persistency. For example, there was the '82 plan of Reagan
                    which was an entirely sensible plan, in my judgement. But I don't think we
                    pursued it with the kind of vigor and high level involvement which promotes
                    success. In the last decade we just haven't been willing to put sufficient
                    political capital domestically on this particular issue in order to achieve some
                    results.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you're right. Do you think the Israelis now almost
                        count on their ability to outlast our own political domestic political
                        cycle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: To some degree, yes. The differences have most often been with the
                    executive branch, much less so with the congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And is that an insurmountable problem? Or can really
                        effective leadership overcome?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: No, it's not insurmountable. Looking ahead to the decade of the '90s, if
                    this revolution of '89, and all the forces of democracy, all of these changes
                    and peaceful resolution of Central America—Angola, Namibia, Cambodia, Eastern
                    Europe, and the like continue—the Middle East is going to remain resistant
                    indefinitely. I happen to believe that the area is at a watershed today. I
                    detect that people on both sides of this issue, desire a settlement, but the
                    flexibility is lacking. I think the problem in Israel right now is the lack of
                    consensus. There are understandable genuine concerns that whatever new
                    arrangement be one that is secure. On the Palestinian side, there is the drive
                    for legitimacy and an entity of the area. I find this particular juncture
                    hopeful in the limited sense that global events are working in the direction of
                    heavier pressures on both sides to begin to find a way to resolve the
                    intractable. For example, certain Arab states will be less seen as strategic
                    allies of the Soviet Union than before. And likewise, from the point of view of
                    Israel. Will it in the long run be viewed as important strategically in a post
                    cold war environment? The strategic alliance argument with respect to both sides
                    may very well carry less weight. That's a geopolitical reality that, in my
                    judgement, becomes an added factor in this situation. There are underlying
                    political geopolitical factors that are working in favor of some kind of a
                    settlement of the Arab-Israeli-Palestinian issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting. You've seen a lot of the
                        Executive Branch, Congressional coordination problems of one sort or another
                        over the years. It's a very...I suppose its a very chaotic system of
                        government. It seems to me, Joe, even though we all live under the
                        Constitution here, that Congress in a way has become much worse in terms of
                        its intervention in international affairs, and foreign policy. Much more
                        decentralized, disorganized, and therefore irresponsible than it was in
                        earlier periods. Do you have any comments about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: Yes, I do. I've given this a lot of thought, Mike. In fact I've done more
                    study of this in the last decade than you can possibly imagine. Our most
                    productive periods historically, Mike, have been periods of strong executive
                    leadership, supported by a bipartisan Congress. From World War II to Vietnam
                    there was a consensus in our country, both on foreign policy and security
                    policy. Sure there were differences between political parties, but never a
                    fundamental difference. Vietnam fractionalized that consensus, and Watergate
                    weakened the institution of the Presidency. And since then we've been trying to
                    recapture the kind of executive-legislative cooperation that makes for a
                    consensus, predictability, and certitude as to the direction of American foreign
                    policy. We haven't recaptured that. There's been some improvement since Vietnam.
                    That's one dimension.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>The other dimension is that Congress in the past had members in it that were more
                    subject to party discipline than they are now. You have PAC money. The reason
                    why 98% of the members of Congress were reelected this last time, is simply
                    because there need not be any party discipline that one finds in a parliamentary
                    system. And therefore, in the aftermath of Vietnam, there came into being a
                    so-called resurgent Congress where there were clusters of groups on each
                    specific issue, rather than an overall strategic approach. Not only a cluster on
                    specific issues, but the enhancement of special interests, and special interest
                    issues in the Congress. And therefore you have a Congress that itself does not
                    have its house in order. And what is interesting is, that you have at this
                    juncture a Democratic House, and a Democratic Senate, and you would think that a
                    majority of the same party could find a consensus. They're not able to do that
                    because historically there has been a liberal wing of the Democratic party, as
                    well as a conservative wing.</p>
                <p>So our problem in terms of foreign affairs is that there has to be strong
                    executive leadership in order for our system to work. The nadir was under Jimmy
                    Carter because the Carter administration took a position, and the Congress, on a
                    number of instances, reversed it. And the whole Iran hostage thing really
                    brought it to the bottom. There was some slight recuperation of this under
                    Reagan, and then Iran-Contra undermined it again.</p>
                <p>Now President George Bush is giving a different kind of leadership. What people
                    don't understand is, that the objective conditions externally facing the United
                    States have changed. We moved from a unilateral dominance by the United States
                    in the immediate days after World War II to a bi-polarity between the United
                    States and the Soviet Union for a given period. And now we are developing with
                    Japan, EC-92, Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union, a multi-center world in which
                    the relative power of the United States—not the absolute power—the relative
                    power of the United States is diminished largely because of the fact that the
                    objective political-economic conditions are changed. Leadership does not mean
                    that you have to be way out in the front. What we are doing in relationship to
                    Eastern Europe right now is the most effective leadership that we could be
                    giving. Our press plays this as the decline of the United States. Some academes,
                    such as Kennedy, have written a book that says that all this represents the
                    decline of the United States. It's not the case. Even with our budget deficits,
                    even with the fact that we should be able to find, or we need to find, more
                    money resources, if you will, for Panama, for Nicaragua, for Eastern Europe, and
                    now Secretary Baker in Namibia. We are hamstrung in that regard. In the literal
                    sense, if there is political will, the money is there, or the capacity is there.
                    Our budget deficit is about 3% of our trillion dollars GNP, and it needs to be
                    addressed seriously if American leadership abroad is to be maintained.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>So that when you look at foreign affairs it's a question of executive leadership.
                    Congress is reluctant to confront a President with 70% favorable rating in the
                    polls. I am a strong believer in executive leadership. There is a propensity to
                    micro-manage foreign policy on the Hill which is not good for the country and
                    for our leadership. But again, this is part of the political process. You take
                    this Congress right now, excellent leadership in Tom Foley and Senator Mitchell,
                    but they're not able to develop an alternative strategy to what the
                    administration has, President Bush has taken hold of the center politically. My
                    own feeling is that we're going to see the constellation of political alignment,
                    as we have right now, probably for the rest of the decade of the '90s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those are very shrewd comments. The democrats have to put
                        their own house in order, and as you say, that has been terribly difficult
                        certainly. Finally, Joe, because we have to bring this to a stop, let me
                        just ask you briefly about the principle of careerism in the government. The
                        United States, compared with European parliamentary democracies, has a
                        really large shift of personnel when a new administration comes in, and
                        there's a change of leadership. Do we carry that too far in your view? Is it
                        appropriate? Is it energizing to the government? And what is your view
                        really of the balance within the Department of State—how the political level
                        relates to the Foreign Service, the career officers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SISCO: The changes of administration are energizing, there's no question about
                    it. One of the reasons why we've lost a little continuity, in terms of the
                    continuity of the professional level, is that if you go back to the 60's we had
                    a period of some fifteen years where we kicked out one President, namely Nixon;
                    we defeated another President, namely Ford; we assassinated another President,
                    Kennedy it was short lived; Carter got himself defeated; and the continuity of
                    the eight year presidency was lost for a given period of time. And therefore,
                    that tends to add far more frequent change in the professional bureaucracy than
                    even normal. Now to the degree to which, for example, you have eight year
                    presidencies, then a change in professional assignments can come about in an
                    orderly fashion. These are jobs that drain one emotionally, physically, and so
                    on. You just can't do a top job that long.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, it's a question of balance. I would like to see a situation
                    where not the entire team necessarily is cleared out at the top in the State
                    Department with every Administration change. It is understandable that a new
                    Secretary of State comes in and he wants his own people. Most of the time good
                    sense has prevailed. One difficulty has been how to move a group of political
                    advisors involved in a political campaign, into the bureaucracy and responsible
                    policy positions.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>So I have no clear cut answer and that is, that I think changes the professional
                    service have to be approached judicially, prudently, and I don't really think
                    that the assumption should be that one clears house entirely, and this massive
                    change of ambassadors all over the world takes place in the span of a few
                    months. At the moment the tilt in the direction of politically appointed
                    ambassadors, rather than professionals. But I'm confident the balance will be
                    restored. I don't want to be misunderstood. I think the mixture of professionals
                    and public figures is a good idea. I believe that it does bring new disciplines,
                    and new experiences into the Service which is all to the good. And this
                    interaction is to the good. But I think that a balance does have to be
                    maintained, and in particular this practice of bringing in inexperienced people
                    in critically important posts, I think is one where we really put ourselves at a
                    disadvantage. The role of the ambassador, as the result of modern technology,
                    has been diminished. But it is still very important.</p>
                <p>I'll tell you an amusing story. President Nixon came to me and said, “Joe, I want
                    to help you in any way I can. Is there anything I can do for you? I know you've
                    got a Ph.D. in Soviet Affairs. Would you like to become the Ambassador to the
                    Soviet Union?” And he offered it to me twice. And I turned it down both times. I
                    said, “Mr. President, I'm going to tell you why I don't want it.” He said, “Why
                    is that?” I said, “You know, you and Henry Kissinger are the Soviet desk
                    officers in this administration. And if you sent me to Moscow...” I said, “First
                    of all I won't go, but if I went, you'd have a personnel problem in six weeks.”
                    Mac Toon, who served well as our ambassador in Moscow, used to just be so
                    unhappy simply because Dobrynin had all the access, and poor Mac Toon couldn't
                    even get through the front door to see Mr. Gromyko more than once every three
                    months or so.</p>
                <p>I think we've got the best professional service in the world. And I see it even
                    more clearly now that I'm outside of government. I go see people at the desk
                    level once a week in my current work. The professionalism is just absolutely
                    outstanding. I worry about their inability to move up rapidly enough, and I
                    worry about decisions that are taken at times where the professionals are really
                    not being consulted. They have an expertise to contribute which is essential. A
                    number of the mistakes we've made historically over the last 15 or 20 years,
                    have normally been in part as a result of the people who really know not being
                    consulted. So we do move too many people too rapidly, and I think we need to
                    strike a better balance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Joe, thank you very much. It's been a great
                        interview.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
