<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001434">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with William Primosch</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>WILLIAM PRIMOSCH</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 2, 2001</p>
                <p>Copyright 2006 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an interview with William Primosch. This is being
                        done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training and
                        I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. You go by Bill.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's start at the beginning. Could you tell me when and
                        where you were born and something about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was born in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1946. I grew up in a working class
                    neighborhood and had a brother and two sisters. Three of us ended up doing a
                    kind of foreign service. I have two sisters who are Catholic missionaries, one
                    in India now and one in Hong Kong. They are Catholic nuns. Originally, I was
                    interested in being a missionary myself and spent two years at the Maryknoll
                    Fathers Seminary, which has missions in Africa, Asia, and Latin America. I left
                    there and went on to study at the University of Notre Dame political science and
                    international relations. I was interested at a fairly early time in my life in
                    living and working overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm going to stop you here and we're going to go way back.
                        Tell me something about your father and mother and the family
                        background.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: My mother, whose maiden name was Frances Held, was originally from
                    Erie, Pennsylvania, she came from a family of carpenters. The family had
                    emigrated from Germany back in the 1850s. My father's family was ethnic German
                    from what is now Slovenia. They had emigrated around the turn of the century. My
                    father was born in the United States. He worked at the county courthouse as a
                    civil servant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did either your mother or father go to college?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No. My father had to drop out of school at about 10th grade to support
                    his family during the Depression. My mother graduated from high school and
                    worked for a couple of years but was a housewife almost her entire life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they meet?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think they met through mutual friends in Cleveland. I really don't
                    know much about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to school in Cleveland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I attended Catholic schools in Cleveland. I went to Immaculate
                    Conception grade school in Cleveland, which is on the East Side in a working
                    class neighborhood, and then went to Cathedral High School, a school run by the
                    Marianist Brothers. I spent all my life in Cleveland and grew up and lived in
                    the same house the entire time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about grammar school. Were nuns running
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. We had the Ursuline Sisters. At that time, all of the teachers
                    were nuns, which is very rare these days. It was a very strict school but there
                    was good basic education and that proved to be very helpful later in life. At
                    the time I was going to school there, in the 1950s, most of the students went on
                    to high school and never went beyond high school. Many, in fact, dropped out of
                    high school in the '50s and early '60s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One hears stories about how strict the nuns would be. Did
                        you find that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: They were very strict, but they were very nice people. I've had the
                    pleasure of continuing contact with some of my old grade school teachers. Every
                    now and then when I visit Cleveland, I run into one of them. They at least
                    pretend that they remember our class very well and seem to be genuinely
                    affectionate towards their former students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in grammar school, I take it your mother
                        and father were pretty busy people. Was there much intellectual
                        backgrounreading, looking at the paper, interested in politics?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, they did not have much interest in intellectual kinds of things or
                    in politics although my father was involved a bit in local politics so I got to
                    meet councilmen and judges since he worked at the court house. That was the
                    center of a lot of local political activity. But the one difference was that,
                    even though most of the parents in my neighborhood were not well educated
                    people, they were all of an ethnic origin that stressed education. Getting a
                    good education was always very important for them. In retrospect, the cost of
                    sending their children to private Catholic schools through high school was a
                    rather heavy financial commitment. But it was just expected, and they never
                    complained about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role of Catholic Church as you saw it? You
                        were in school during the McCarthy period. Did you feel the Catholic Church
                        was there as a guide?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think what people of my generation in Cleveland felt was that the
                    Catholic Church was very much a part of their lives. All my friends were
                    Catholic. The neighborhoodCleveland was a very ethnic city and there are a lot
                    of ethnic neighborhoods tended to be divided into ethnic groups. You had
                    Slovenian neighborhoods, Croatian neighborhoods, Polish neighborhoods, etc.
                    There was a very heavy Catholic population. Anyone who was Catholic at that time
                    sent their kids to the local parish school. They were involved in some way or
                    another with the church, which was usually just a few blocks away. This was an
                    accepted reality of life growing up in Cleveland in the 1950s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did these neighborhoods fall on the political
                        spectrum?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Cleveland is a very heavily democratic time. The labor unions were very
                    strong there. It's a working class town. At that time, a very high percentage of
                    working class people were Democrat. It was unusual to have Republicans, although
                    my father-in-law was a working class person and a Republican. He didn't like the
                    Democrats.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the name of the high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The name of the high school was Cathedral Latin High School. It was an
                    all-boys high school, which was common at that time for Catholic schools. They
                    were either all boys or all girls. My wife, who grew up a couple of blocks away
                    from where I lived and went to an all-girls high school, also a Catholic
                    school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in high school, what were your
                        interests?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I didn't have any particular strong interests. I liked to play sports,
                    although I wasn't on a school team. I wasn't good enough. But I did like to play
                    sports. In grade school, we started at a young age playing football, basketball,
                    and baseball. All the kids in the neighborhood played. I got interested in
                    reading at a fairly young age and particularly in high school. For some reason,
                    I got fascinated by foreign cultures and peoples even at a fairly young age. I
                    thought it was very natural at the time, but in retrospect I guess was a bit
                    unusual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of our colleagues, myself included, found the same
                        thing. Do you recall any books or authors that grabbed you at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: For some reason, I got intrigued fairly early on, a senior in high
                    school, in Dostoevsky and some of the Russian writers. I guess this peaked my
                    interest in foreign cultures and in living overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In these areas that were strongly ethnic, were you picking
                        up ethnic politics, like the Slovaks didn't talk to the Czechs or something
                        like that or was it transmitted to your generation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It's interesting that German ethnics very quickly assimilate. You'll
                    find this if you talk to people of German origin. While we had a German club in
                    Cleveland and my father went to it occasionally, he was not terribly interested.
                    Germans don't tend to preserve their ethnic heritage as much as other cultures.
                    Just about any other European culture has a stronger sense of ethnic identity.
                    So, that kind of ethnicity did not come through in our family. I did, however,
                    note it in other kids that I hung around witfor example, the Serbs and Croatians
                    who lived in our neighborhood. Everyone knew that they didn't get along and were
                    very hostile towards one another..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Marianist brothers who were running
                        the school? Were they expanding your horizons?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. I think overall they provided a pretty good education. In some
                    respects, for example, in terms of fundamentals, my high school education was
                    better than many schools today that have a more sophisticated curriculum but
                    somehow overlook the basics of math, science, history and government. But
                    Cathedral Latin wasn't by any means an elite school. The kids going to the
                    school had rather limited ambitions. I would say about half the class went on to
                    college. By no means, however, was it expected that everyone would go on to
                    college, as it is today in most schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated from high school when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: 1964.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Cold War intrude at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was part of the background environment at that time. It's hard to
                    say in a practical way how this affected you except that you were very much
                    aware of the threat from the Soviet Union. This was kind of a reality which you
                    saw in the papers all the time. I recall rather vaguely the confrontation over
                    the building of the Berlin Wall, and more vividly the Cold War rhetoric in the
                    Kennedy administration and talk about the Cuban Missile Crisis. But I would say
                    in terms of impact on my thinking, it was more in the background.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Coming up to '64, were your parents or parish priests
                        pushing you towards being a missionary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: My parents didn't push me at all. They were very much of the view that
                    you should do whatever you were interested in doing. They didn't really push me
                    one way or the other. But it just so happened in growing up, I had over the
                    years come in contact with several priests whom I admired very much and who
                    impressed me as men and as people who had a calling and interest in serving
                    other people. Like a lot of young people, I felt very strongly that sense of
                    wanting to serve. That's what drew me into an interest in doing missionary
                    work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went from high school to Notre Dame?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, I went from high school to Maryknoll Seminary, which was at that
                    time outside of Chicago in Glen Ellyn, Illinois. At that time, the seminaries
                    were different than they are today. It's kind of interesting in contrast. There
                    are very few people who enter seminary now. But at that time, the seminaries
                    were almost overflowing with young men interested in religious work. In fact, my
                    sister-in-law, who is a couple of years younger than I, also entered a convent
                    in Cleveland. I have two sisters who entered the convent several years before I
                    graduated from high school. I think this was a rather interesting phenomenon of
                    the times that there was this great religious outpouring among a lot of young
                    people, particularly Catholics. I don't know how it was with other
                    denominations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maryknoll, both the brothers and the sisters, got very
                        much involved, particularly in Latin America, with the injustice, but found
                        themselves just by that nature to the left of a lot of the political
                        movements. Was this the sense?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: When I was there, which was only about two and a half years, the sense
                    I had was that this was an organization that was very dedicated to helping the
                    poor. I didn't sense any political ax to grind, but they did identify
                    particularly in Latin America with the Indian population, which was usually very
                    poor and politically isolated and probably discriminated against. But there
                    wasn't a political zeal. I think the politics arose out of the sense of mission
                    to the poor in these countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The political thing developed in the face of the reality
                        of being, say, in Guatemala.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. I think particularly in the '50s, '60s, and '70s, and probably to
                    a lesser extent today, these societies were very authoritarian and divided by
                    class. It was probably pretty easy to be drawn into political activism in that
                    environment if you were trying to do something to help the poor.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you getting what amounted to a continuing basic education or was it
                    moving more towards the religious side?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: They had a heavy theological curriculum, but there were a lot of
                    extremely bright people there and even though the school was small, only 400-500
                    students, it was intellectually in many ways superior to what I saw at Notre
                    Dame. It was more intellectually stimulating.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened as you went through there? Why the
                        shift?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I guess I just concluded that this wasn't for me. That's when I decided
                    to transfer to Notre Dame, which wasn't all that far away. When I transferred, I
                    went into their international affairs department following up on that same
                    interest in work overseas and foreign cultures.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the church when Pope John XXIII came on the
                        scene. Were you feeling the tremors of the change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: My recollection was that there was a lot of change in the church as it
                    tried to drag itself from the Middle Ages to the 20th century. Up until about
                    the late 1960s if you look at church practices and the church liturgy and
                    religious orientation, a lot of it is directly out of the Middle Ages. You could
                    have gone in the 1950s to a Mass in Cleveland, it wouldn't have been that much
                    different from going to Mass in 1400 in France. The Mass was in Latin. A lot of
                    the prayer services came out of the Middle Ages. I think there was a recognition
                    in the Catholic Church that it really needed to become more relevant to modern
                    times.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you went to Notre Dame, this would have put you there
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was there from '67-'69.</p>
                <p>Q: Was Father Theodore Hesburgh (the former President) still there?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here was a university that was reaching out in the
                        international field trying to establish itself as being more than a feeder
                        Catholic school for the area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I know it was aspiring to be a level of excellence which they felt they
                    hadn't achieved. My sense is that they didn't quite make it. I think part of
                    that is due to the tradeoffs they made. They had great sports teams when I was
                    there, but I think the type of environment there was not as encouraging to
                    academics as it might have been. Most of their students there came from Catholic
                    schools and maybe there is a less diverse environment. Certainly there were very
                    few minorities and very few non-Catholics. But overall, the academic level was
                    fairly high. I had a lot of very good professors there, particularly in
                    political science. What was interesting at that time was that there were, as you
                    had in many American universities, many �migr� professors who left Europe around
                    the time of World War II. One of my most interesting professors was Dr. Gerhart
                    Niemeyer, who taught political philosophy and who was a German �migr� from World
                    War II. He left under circumstances of persecution and wrote a lot about
                    communism. Another interesting professor was Dr. Stephen Kertesz, who was a
                    minister in the Hungarian government during Nazi occupation. He was a
                    distinguished professor of international law. Notre Dame's political science and
                    international affairs programs were particularly good at that time. It was an
                    interesting and stimulating group of professors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you having to play catch up to those who had already
                        been at Notre Dame? Did you find the grounding that you had put you right in
                        the slim of things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In terms of academic preparation, there was no problem. But it was a
                    different focus. But academics were not an issue.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you concentrating on any particular area?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: At that time, I was focused on Latin America and took courses in its
                    history and government. I think I came away from all the studies rather
                    frustrated with developments in Latin America. Maybe it was because that area
                    wasn't going anywhere. I didn't follow up on that as I thought I would.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For many of us, Latin America then? I'm not even sure
                        today it's changed that much. This is without lack of real knowledge. It
                        seemed to be rather stagnant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. In the '60s and the '70s, there was a heavy emphasis on leftist
                    politics and a lot of socialist experimentation which proved almost universally
                    a failure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it callerevolutionary theology?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: There was some of that. There was also the so-called “Prebisch” thesis,
                    developed by Latin American economist Dr. Raul Prebisch. He maintained that
                    multinational corporations were exploiting Latin America and the developed world
                    by perpetuating the unfavorable terms of trade between natural resource products
                    and manufactured goods. Raw materials were kept cheap while rich countries sold
                    manufactured products at higher prices. There was a lot of leftist guerrillas
                    operating in Latin America. Salvador Allende had experimented with socialism in
                    Chile without much success and experienced great personal tragedy. The
                    unsuccessful revolutionary exploits of Che Guevara also received a lot of
                    attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you reached the end, what were you going to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: This was the late '60s when I was finishing up college. What was on
                    everyone's mind at that time was being drafted and sent to Vietnam. In
                    retrospect, I can see that it was something that was very pronounced and a
                    concern of a lot of students. What was going to happen after graduation? Could
                    you get a deferment to continue studying in graduate school, which is what I
                    wanted to do but it was not possible any longer in '69? Would you be sent to
                    Vietnam? If you were opposed to the war, should you consider protesting or even
                    emigrating to another country? There was some talk of that. There were a lot of
                    protests on campus, particularly during ROTC parades. I participated in the 1968
                    March on Washington with a lot of other college students and stayed at
                    Georgetown University in one of the dorms after the protests. Later I had the
                    interesting experience as a Foreign Service officer to participate in meetings
                    with former Secretary Robert McNamara. I thought, how ironic that years earlier
                    I was protesting outside his window at the Pentagon and now I'm sitting across
                    the table with him discussing economic policy towards Asia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened? You graduated in '69.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. I had a relatively low draft number, so I knew I was going to go
                    in the Service one way or the other. I went into the Army in April of '69 as a
                    draftee enlisted man and spent a little over two years in the service. It just
                    so happened that I was sent to Germany for reasons of luck of the draw. I ended
                    up in Heidelberg, Germany, at U.S. Army Headquarters-Europe for about a year and
                    a half.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '69 was when Nixon came in and we were beginning to draw
                        down our forces. The buildup had stopped and there was a disengagement of
                        our forces.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's true, although at the time just before I went into the Army and
                    when I was in the Army, everyone was conscious of the fact that we were still
                    fighting the war and that a lot of people who were going to Vietnam. A grade
                    school friend of mine, Steve Mylant, a Marine, was killed in Vietnam. The
                    reality of the war continuing was more pronounced than the recognition that U.S.
                    forces were starting to be withdrawn. The late '60s were a very strange time if
                    you combine the war and the protests against the war and the civil rights
                    movement and the violence associated with that and then the race riots in the
                    cities. There were riots in Cleveland when I was living there and I remember the
                    National Guard being called in. This was all within a period of just a couple of
                    years. The change in social mores with the hippies and the change in culture
                    that was so different from the way our parents grew up made for quite a dramatic
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work were you doing in the military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I worked in a finance office. I was not involved in combat duty. In
                    Heidelberg, I was stationed at the U.S. Army European headquarters in the
                    administrative unit. There was nothing particularly challenging about the work,
                    although in retrospect being in the Service I found very interesting because you
                    met a lot of different people. I was an opportunity to live overseas, and my
                    wife and I traveled a lot when we were in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For many, if you don't get killed or wounded, it's a very
                        positive experience. You're getting out and it's just a different world.
                        Also being able to go overseas. How did you find Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Germany was very interesting. It struck me when I arrived as still not
                    quite being a modern country. The standard of living was not very high compared
                    with the American standard of living. This was a little over 25 years after
                    World War II. Everything was built up, but the economy was not that well
                    developed. It didn't seem very efficient. People's incomes were not as high as
                    Americans. The dollar was very strong then—over 4 marks to the dollar. Even on
                    an enlisted man's salary, we were able to travel and go out to restaurants and
                    do a lot of interesting things.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the finance unit, so you weren't going to be
                        on the front line, but was there the feeling that the Soviets might move at
                        any time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, there wasn't. There were, however, exercisethey called them
                    “alerts” every month on a date that was not known in advance. We would get a
                    call that said, “This is an alert” and you would simulate what you would do if
                    there was an invasion. For the people in the administrative unit, you would just
                    to go your office. But the combat troops would get in their tanks and trucks and
                    go out on maneuvers for two or three days to simulate a response to a Russian
                    attack. However, everyone was more focused on what was happening in Vietnam than
                    the possibility of a Soviet invasion.</p>
                <p>The military at that time was very different than the military now in terms of
                    morale and professionalism. The morale was terrible. The enlisted men for the
                    most part didn't want to be there. There was strong opposition to the war.
                    Racial tensions were very high. There were a lot of fights between black and
                    white soldiers and just a sense of palpable tension.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On this black-white thing, were there black areas,
                        gasthauses where one went and there were white areas? Were things pretty de
                        facto segregated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think there was pretty much de facto segregation. I was married at
                    the time, so I didn't go out to gasthauses (i.e., local bars). But I think the
                    Army reflected society at large. People tended to congregate racially among
                    themselves. Of course, it wasn't much different than growing up in Cleveland,
                    which was is a very segregated city. That's the way people lived then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned you were married. You and your wife grew up
                        together?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. In fact, we went to grade school together and knew each other
                    since then, although we didn't date until college. We have very similar kinds of
                    backgrounds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was she able to come to Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. She came to Germany shortly after I got there. She was at Kent
                    State University and had left to go to Germany just a couple of weeks before the
                    shootings there. She is a teacher by training and did some teaching at the
                    University of Maryland's extensions on the bases.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the military until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Until 1971.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any feel for what you're going to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I knew I was interested in international work of some kind. I had only
                    a very fuzzy notion about what the State Department did. At that time, I had
                    more of an interest in AID doing development work, which was more aligned with
                    my original interest. So, I was toying around with the idea of doing some
                    graduate work in Europe in international affairs and ended up going back to
                    George Washington University and doing graduate work in their international
                    affairs program there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at George Washington from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: From '71 to '73.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a master's?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I got a master's degree in international affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find George Washington as a place to go for a
                        graduate degree?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Overall, I thought it was a good program. They had several very good
                    professors. One of the things that they stressed in the courses that I took was
                    research and writing. So we did a lot of papers and that was a great opportunity
                    to refine my writing skills. Acquiring good writing skills really helped me
                    later on in the State Department. Several of the courses I took I also found to
                    be very useful later on at the State Department. I took courses in international
                    trade and economics, and some courses in international communism. We did a lot
                    of reading on China, Russia and Eastern Europe. As it turned out, my first
                    assignment at the State Department was in Belgrade, Yugoslavia. I found myself
                    very well prepared academically for that kind of work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you had any real contact with the Foreign Service? Did
                        you have any idea what it was about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Not really. I had just the vaguest sense of how the State Department
                    works overseas. My original interest was in the Agency for International
                    Development. I can't quite remember why I ended up taking the Foreign Service
                    test and not pursuing an interest in AID, but I did take the test and passed it
                    and had the interview shortly thereafter. The timing was fortunate as there was
                    a big turnover at the State Department. It was hiring a lot of junior officers
                    so I came in fairly quickly after taking the test.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In June of '75.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall anything about the oral exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was very different than the oral exam now. It only lasted about 50
                    minutes. There were three examiners. They asked some rather general questions
                    about international events. I read “The New York Times” daily a couple of weeks
                    beforehand, so I felt I was up to date on current events. I recall the examiners
                    asked me several questions about literature. I had read a lot of Russian and
                    German literature, so I was able to converse about literary and cultural
                    developments in foreign countries. But I got the impression that it was a kind
                    of examination that was intended to confirm what they thought—t hat you passed
                    the test and you're okay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: See if you could talk.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. To see if you could talk and if any obvious problems would emerge
                    from the person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you came in in '75. What was your A100 course
                        like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think fairly useless except as a social event. We had a very big
                    class. I think it was the biggest class ever to have entered—about 120. Henry
                    Kissinger came to our graduation ceremony. But I must say that I don't think it
                    was very useful in terms of what I thought would have been helpful as a junior
                    officer to prepare for a first assignment overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When in '75 did you get in?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: My recollection is that I entered in the junior officer class in June
                    and went into language training at the end of August/early September for
                    Belgrade, studying Serbo-Croatian course at FSI. I then was assigned to Belgrade
                    that following summer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any choice in where you wanted to go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I did have an interview to discuss assignments. I think that because I
                    was a little bit older, that I had been in the Army, and that I had graduate
                    work, there was a readiness to consider me and people who had similar
                    backgrounds for more responsible and demanding first assignments. At that time,
                    they were still assigning people to the State Department as a first assignment.
                    I don't think they do that anymore. Usually a first assignment is overseas.
                    Based on a bit of work experience, a couple of different options were suggested.
                    I said I was interested in Belgrade. I don't know whether they assigned me there
                    because I expressed an interest or because that just happened to work out that
                    way in terms of what was convenient for the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you picking up any reverberations from the collapse
                        of South Vietnam in April of '75?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think there were reverberations in the sense that the confrontation
                    or the conflict with the Soviet Union was still very much alive. This was part
                    of a worldwide problem. Vietnam was one symptom of this global challenge of
                    trying to deal with communism, which was very much embedded in U.S. foreign
                    policy strategy at the time. For Foreign Service Officers in the State
                    Department in the 1970s, this was a foreign policy issue that was on everyone's
                    mind no matter where you were serving. Even in Latin America, there was a
                    concern that the communists were going to take over, that they had Cuba and were
                    going to gain control in Central America too. There were communist guerrillas in
                    Bolivia and Salvador Allende in Chile. There was very much that sense that
                    communist groups were on the move, and that this was a confrontation that was
                    global, whether it was in Central Europe or Yugoslavia or Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Chile had a revolution and the communists for a brief time
                        were in power.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: And even in France, the leftists and Communist Party were very strong
                    and in Italy as well. So, there was this sense of a real global struggle that
                    was very prominent on the foreign policy agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When one takes a language before going to a country, one
                        often picks up quite a bit of a feel for the culture through the teachers.
                        How about before going off to Belgrade?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: We had very good Serbian teachers. I don't know, however, that I
                    necessarily agree with the FSI method even to this day. I think it might be
                    better to just throw people in the water and have them start speaking the
                    language more in country. You might learn more effectively. But I did end up
                    speaking Serbo-Croatian fairly well by the time I left Belgrade, although I
                    really applied myself when I was in country. I think you pick up a bit of the
                    culture through the teachers. But if you haven't actually lived in Yugoslavia,
                    like many foreign cultures, contact with �migr�s is no replacement for actually
                    being in the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were your teachers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: There was Father Milosevic, who was an Orthodox priest. I can't
                    remember the other two teachers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Belgrade from '76 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was there from 1976 to 1978.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was a commercial officer. At the time, the State Department had the
                    commercial function in the Foreign Service. It turned out to be an interesting
                    job for a first tour officer because it got you out of the embassy a lot. You
                    interacted a lot with the local businessmen and traveled throughout Yugoslavia.
                    I also participated in a lot of different kinds of business events, which I
                    found unusually interesting for a first tour.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It started off with Lawrence Silberman, who was a political appointee,
                    a former senior Justice Department official. He was there a year and then he
                    left. Larry Eagleburger, the former Under Secretary for Management, came out
                    from the Department and was there my second year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have interviewed Silberman. What was your impression of
                        him? Was he pretty far away from your?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was a pretty small embassy, so even as a junior officer, you did
                    have a fair amount of contact with the ambassador or at least observing the
                    ambassador and being involved in meetings with him.</p>
                <p>My impression of the ambassador was that he was a very smart professional. I
                    think he was trying to pursue some very specific objectives. He was rather tough
                    on the Yugoslav government. In retrospect, I think that was perhaps the better
                    strategy. In all of Eastern Europe and in Yugoslavia, the overall approach was
                    to try to win over friends and governments. The idea was that somehow we were
                    going to encourage more independent policies that would be more favorable to the
                    United States. In particular with Yugoslavia, the government under President
                    Tito was more independent than the other communist satellites. Yugoslavia didn't
                    consider itself to be a “satellite.” It was thought that somehow we would be
                    able to break Yugoslavia away from its close ties with the USSR or at least get
                    it to lean toward the United States in some of our confrontations with the
                    Soviets and the other communists. There was also a belief that from the
                    commercial and economic perspective if you could show them the benefits of
                    capitalism, bring the Yugoslavs into contact with Western businessmen and
                    Western business practices, and Western investment, that this would accelerate
                    the change and that Yugoslavia would evolve away from a communist system and
                    become more independent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of Silberman, how did you find the Yugoslav
                        economy and opportunity for commercial American interests there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: There was a coincidence of interests in Yugoslavia. As I noted, we
                    believed that if we could get more Western and American businessmen involved in
                    Yugoslavia, that would support our foreign policy goals in encouraging a more
                    westward leaning government and people. At the same time, in the 1970s not only
                    in Yugoslavia but in Central Europe and even in the Soviet Union, there was a
                    greater interest in doing business with the West because of all the problems in
                    their state-controlled economies. They didn't have modern technology. They
                    needed foreign investment, and they were also trying to generate hard-currency
                    exports. So, we had a very active commercial program in Yugoslavia to try to
                    encourage U.S. businessmen to come. Some were interested. They saw these as new
                    markets. At a time when western commercial efforts in Western Europe may have
                    reached their limit, Yugoslavia, Central Europe and the Soviet Union were seen
                    as new potential markets, not necessarily large but significant enough that
                    companies could make some money there. In reality, the business opportunities
                    were quite limited. There were some U.S. companies who were doing a significant
                    business there but not a lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there at the time when this American businessman
                        was arrested on charges of spying?? Could you explain what that was and how
                        this operated?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: He was an American businessman of Hungarian extraction. His name is
                    Hungarian, but he might have been a Hungarian from Yugoslavia since there is a
                    large Hungarian minority population in the Vojvodina area of northern
                    Yugoslavia. He went to a factory, allegedly was taking pictures of sensitive
                    equipment in a sugar factor, and was arrested as a spy. That part of the country
                    has a lot of beet sugar production. He was arrested as a spy and they had kind
                    of alleged he was working for the CIA or Western intelligence. The Yugoslavs
                    were rather paranoid about the United States' intelligence seeking to penetrate
                    Yugoslavia at that time. It got to ridiculous levels where you would go to a
                    factory and ask someone, “How many people work here” and they wouldn't tell you
                    because they apparently thought: “Well, I might get in trouble because I told
                    this person from the U.S. embassy who could be working for the CIA, something
                    that someone is going to blame me for giving away secrets.” Even the most
                    innocuous information was considered secret. I don't think the
                    Hungarian-American who was arrested had any connection with any Western
                    intelligence. He might have just pissed some Yugoslavs off, and they picked him
                    up. They were going to put him on trial. Ambassador Silberman took a very hard
                    line that this had to be resolved. He talked very tough, including making some
                    very tough public statements that got a lot of Yugoslavs mad. Reportedly his
                    comments angered President Tito himself. I think the Yugoslavs came to the
                    conclusion that keeping this guy was more trouble than it was worth and they let
                    him go. But what really set the Yugoslavs ofand I had heard that this went all
                    the way up to Tito himself is that at the time he was released, Ambassador
                    Silberman went to the train station to see the man off as he left Yugoslavia and
                    made a statement to the press, something to the effect that: “This shows that
                    you can't do this to an American.” I believe that immediately after that
                    happened, he was considered persona non grata. He couldn't get any senior-level
                    appointments. I think that was when it was decided that he ought to leave. It
                    also coincided with the change in administrations in Washington (i.e., in
                    January 1977).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this have a dampening effect on business people coming
                        to Yugoslavia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That wasn't a problem. I think a lot of U.S. business representatives
                    who did travel to Yugoslavia were from either Western Europe or Greece. I don't
                    think that was a big problem for American business representatives, but there
                    was always this overlay of suspicion about Americans, particularly among
                    unsophisticated government bureaucrats, that rose to rather ludicrous levels.
                    This diplomatic problem probably didn't help. But it wasn't so damaging that we
                    couldn't get out and do things and meet with people. I think particularly people
                    like myself who were clearly commercial trade officers were not effective in a
                    major way, but Ambassador Silberman was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the DCM?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The DCM was at the time of Ambassador Silbermahe brought out his own
                    DCM, a political appointee. He was a very nice guy, very bright, but was not in
                    the State Department culture. He left with Ambassador Silberman. Charlie York,
                    who was the economic counselor at the time, was the senior Foreign Service
                    officer and became charg� then for a period of time until Ambassador Lawrence
                    Eagleburger came with his DCM. We had a really outstanding team of officers.
                    Bill Montgomery, who is now an ambassador to Yugoslavia, was out there at the
                    time. So was Mark Palmer, who later became a very distinguished ambassador to
                    Hungary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yugoslavia is attractive. When I took Serbian, it was with
                        Larry Eagleburger. We went out there in '62 together. Was there a change
                        when Eagleburger took over?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In a lot of different ways there was a change. Personally, Larry
                    Eagleburger was a fine man. He was very nice to everyone. I was at a fairly low
                    level in the embassy, but I do remember him treating everyone well, as
                    professionals. He had a great sense of humor. There was a sense of a steady
                    helm, of someone who knew what he was doing. He had a lot of enthusiasm for
                    trying to advance the strategy of encouraging Yugoslavia's independence and its
                    ties with the West. He looked particularly on trade and business as a way to try
                    to influence Yugoslavia and encourage internal change, which all of us at that
                    time had hoped would accelerate with contact with the West. We thought that this
                    could be an evolutionary kind of change as opposed to a very abrupt falling
                    apart, which is what happened after Tito died.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking back on it, an interesting thing is how much there
                        was a Yugoslav establishment within the Foreign Service. A good number of
                        people who did rather well in the Foreign Service went through Yugoslavia,
                        which was both a challenging but also kind of a fun place to be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's right. I think at that time in the '70s and even into the '80s
                    as well, there was a sense that being involved in issues involving the Soviet
                    Union and Eastern Europe and the East-West struggle was at the cutting edge of
                    diplomatic work and was some of the most challenging work in the State
                    Department. There always seemed to be a crisis of some sort that you were
                    involved in. As it turned out later, I was also in the Office of East European
                    Affairs when the Polish labor strikes broke out, and there was concern about the
                    Russian invasion. There was a continuum through the '70s and '80s of intense
                    diplomatic activity and challenge in that part of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the workers management system
                        in Yugoslavia? It was supposed to be the Yugoslav way, which is different
                        than the central planning system in the Soviet bloc.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The “worker self-management system” was considered by some the middle
                    way between a state planning system that existed in Central Europe and the
                    Soviet Union and Western style capitalism. It struck me that the economy at that
                    time had significantly more and better consumer goods than economies in the
                    Soviet Union and Central Europe under the central planning system. But at its
                    core it wasn't that much better. The enterprises had a little more independence.
                    There was maybe a little more incentive among the workers to produce a higher
                    quality product. But in the end, there wasn't a dynamic that encouraged
                    innovation or competition or quality like you have in a market economy. It
                    really was in the end a failure that Yugoslavia is still living with because
                    they tried to continually adopt that system even after Tito died without
                    success. On the other hand, in Central Europe and Russia, the post-USSR
                    governments made pretty much a complete break and tried to create a market
                    economy. Some such as Poland, the Czech Republic, and Hungary have done fairly
                    well, but Yugoslavia, even though in many respects it has some advantages in
                    terms of skilled workforce and level of technological development under their
                    system, couldn't get much more out of this hybrid market system. There was an
                    expectation when I was there that somehow the worker self-management was going
                    to work and that it was also compatible with foreign investment and more trade
                    with the West. To some extent, it was but only to a very limited extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As far as our looking at it and reporting, do you think
                        that we were trying to put the best face on the economy and the
                        opportunities there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think we were and that was a mistake. I don't think we were as
                    critical as we could or should have been and that wasn't just in Yugoslavia.
                    That was in Eastern Europe as well in countries where we thought that we sniffed
                    change in the air. Hungary was certainly one of them where there was a sense
                    that it was one of the “nice” socialist countries because the government wasn't
                    so brutal, at least not that we were aware of, and government officials and
                    business executives were more polished and more Western oriented, at least in
                    their outward demeanor. There was a similar view of the Poland and the Polish
                    government, which always had very sympathetic support from Polish �migr�s, U.S.
                    policy was to give these countries special privileges in terms of access to
                    Export-Import Bank credits and most-favored-nation (MFN) tariff treatment (i.e.,
                    normal U.S. tariff treatment as opposed to special high rates for most communist
                    countries). But in retrospect, we were too uncritical and too optimistic of what
                    the limited liberalization of their systems would permit in terms of economic
                    change. In the end, we were too hopeful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today we're looking at four or five Balkan wars in the
                        last few years. Could you see at that time the dissolution of Yugoslavia
                        into a bloody mess?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I certainly could not have envisioned this when I was in Yugoslavia,
                    and there was no one talking of that either. Anyone who went to Yugoslavia
                    serving in the political-economic area had done reading on Yugoslavia's history.
                    You don't have to dust off too many book covers to learn of the terrible, bloody
                    events of the 20th century that had left so much enmity between the different
                    ethnic groups, particularly between the Croatians and the Serbs, more so than
                    with the Muslims. No one was talking about the possibility this would occur
                    again. The action plan was focused on what do we do when Tito dies. There was a
                    very thick book which we updated in the State Department every year on the
                    action plan for a whole series of steps that we were expected to take in terms
                    of military precautions, in terms of diplomatic communication, when Tito died.
                    There was concern that the Russians would immediately try to exert their
                    influence, maybe even invade and try to bring Yugoslavia back into the Soviet
                    Bloc. So, that was a very myopic view of the threats to Yugoslavia and what
                    would happen in the future, even though people were aware of the history. Most
                    Americans and I personally find it even to this day hard to believe that the
                    Yugoslav people could do such brutal things to one another, particularly people
                    who in many cases have lived right next to each other, but just happened to be
                    from different ethnic groups. That kind of brutality is just hard to understand.
                    I think it should be a lesson learned for any place in the world where we're
                    trying to promote our diplomatic objectives. We need to be continually aware of
                    how ethnic tensions can very quickly intensify and become very violent. We can't
                    be too optimistic about finding peaceful solutions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have much more understanding of the whole of events that
                        happened during the Hitler time in Germany. When looking at Yugoslavia, you
                        thought, “Well, they don't get along, but these are civilized people.
                        They're not going to go out and slaughter each other.” Of course, we all
                        watched in horror what happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: When I was there, I cannot recall any or perhaps just a couple of
                    ethnic incidents where the police beat up someone, there was a fight, or someone
                    got killed. But this was shortly after we had riots in American cities for three
                    or four years and where you saw racial tensions in the U.S. just at a fever's
                    pitch coming and going and people were getting killed. Then you read about the
                    history of Yugoslavia, and you look at what you see. But you don't see that kind
                    of tension that you saw even in the U.S. I think the natural conclusion is,
                    well, that's all in the past and these people now are more civilized and more
                    understanding and it just couldn't happen again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go in 1978?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I went to the East European Office.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is May 17, 2001. In 1978, you went to the East
                        European office. What did that consist of?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: At the time I went back for a short stint in the East European office
                    working with Carl Schmidt and Harry Gilmore, who were old hands in the region,
                    prior to going to the economics course at the Foreign Service Institute. Things
                    worked out well during those months and I was offered a job the following summer
                    as the economic officer for Hungary, Bulgaria, and Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk a bit about in 1978 the economics
                        training.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was a very rigorous training. In retrospect, it was a bit too
                    academic. I didn't find that I used a heck of a lot of it later on, although
                    there were some good parts to the course and it reinforced some of the economics
                    courses that I had had at the graduate school level. Overall, it served its
                    purpose, but it was a bit too academic. We spent a lot of time learning
                    statistics, which was excruciating for those who were not mathematically
                    inclined. I never used that later on at the State Department or overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to what bureau?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The European Bureau in the Office of East European Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: From '79 through '81.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you had what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: We had two economic officers in the Office of East European Affairs. I
                    was the economic officer for Hungary, Poland, and Bulgaria. Bob Bradtke, who has
                    had a very distinguished Foreign Service career, was the economic officer for
                    Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>Q: Is he still in?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: He was at the NSC as the executive secretary there. He may still be
                    over there. (Later Deputy Assistant Secretary in EUR and Ambassador-designate to
                    Croatia.)</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were our interests in Hungary, Poland, and Bulgaria
                        from '79-'81?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Our strategy toward Eastern Europe at that time was very well defined.
                    It was trying to encourage more independence among the countries of Eastern and
                    Central EuropHungary, Poland, Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Yugoslavia, and
                    Romania. The economic strategy was one to find new markets for U.S. business,
                    which seemed timely since these countries in the late '70s were turning more to
                    the West for technology and investment in an effort to catch up to capitalist
                    countries. In retrospect, it was the final phase of deterioration of the Soviet
                    Bloc. Economically, it was exhausting itself because it couldn't generate the
                    kind of technology, investment and efficiency that existed in market economies.
                    Our role was to try to encourage more contact with Western business and to
                    encourage more of a market orientation in these economies. We had a very active
                    economic program in all the countries, including bilateral economic commissions
                    or committees which brought together the U.S. government as a team with their
                    counterparts in these countries to discuss investment and trade issues and
                    encourage more economic contact with the West and particularly with the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In December of '79, the Soviets moved into Afghanistan.
                        The Carter administration really turned against the Soviet Union. How did
                        that reflect itself on your particular area of concentration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It did complicate our effort somewhat, but in all of these countries in
                    Eastern and Central Europe, you could even at that time see the yearning for
                    more connections with the West. So, that continued even though relations with
                    the Soviet Union were more tense after Afghanistan. But there was still this
                    desire, and you saw it in Poland, Hungary, and Czechoslovakia, of having more
                    ties with the West, a recognition that the Russians really didn't have much to
                    offer in terms of technology and business opportunities and that if they were
                    going to raise their standard of living they had to have Western investment and
                    technology. These countries also wanted to also have more trade with the West
                    because they needed hard currency (i.e., dollars). That could help them import
                    consumer and industrial goods from the West that would make life better.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any concern on our part about helping the
                        investment to these countries, all of which were part of the Warsaw Pact,
                        supposedly potentially our mortal enemy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, that was a key issue in our economic and trade relations. Export
                    controls were a very important issue in trying to develop our economic
                    relationship with these countries. There was in the Economic Bureau an Office of
                    East-West Export Controls that was trying to find the balance between offering
                    them advanced technology and protecting national security. We didn't offer them
                    any military technology, but a lot of advanced technology has dual uses and
                    required close scrutiny through the export licensing system. Particularly in the
                    computer area, there was a great sensitivity and some differences within the
                    government as to how much advanced technology and the kinds of advanced
                    technology that we should offer. For example, the Romanians had started to
                    develop their own computer industry and were always seeking greater access to
                    computer technology and maintained in their presentations to us that this was
                    strictly for civilian uses. Then we would have an interagency process of trying
                    to decide what level of technology we should offer. It was a rather contentious
                    process. I think the State Department tended to push for perhaps a bit more
                    liberalization there in line with our strategy of trying to build greater ties
                    with countries than the Defense Department found acceptable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we view the economies and technical abilities of
                        Hungary, Poland, and Bulgaria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: We saw Hungary among the Soviet bloc countries as the more advanced
                    just because they were more Western oriented. Some of the Hungarian companies
                    seemed to be doing a little bit better in terms of exporting and seemed to be a
                    little savvier. It was probably more marginal than we had thought. Poland might
                    be next on the list. Bulgaria was at the bottom. Bulgaria considered itself
                    almost at that time as another republic of the Soviet Union in terms of their
                    relationship with the Soviets. They were rather cool and distant toward the
                    U.S., but still made somewhat of an effort to develop their trade ties because
                    they were getting so little from the Soviets in terms of advanced technology.
                    But that gets back to the issue of to what extent this technology might be
                    migrating to the military sector. There was a lot of concerns there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the Poles and the Hungarians rather aggressivthe
                        people at their embassy and trade delegations? Was there the sense that they
                        realized they were tied to a sinking ship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, I don't think so. There was a recognition, more so with Poland and
                    Hungary, that there were real limits to what they could attain from their
                    relationship with the Soviet Union. With Bulgaria you sensed more of a
                    comfortable relationship but certainly not with Poland and Hungary. Of course,
                    you had in Hungary the 1956 rebellion and the residue of that was evident.
                    Poland has always been Western oriented. It was during my stay on the desk when
                    we had the Polish labor strike and Lech Walesa came to prominence at that time.
                    There were already tensions between Eastern European countries and the Soviets
                    and particularly with Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we see economics as a weapon of prying these countries
                        loose from the Soviets to a limited extent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Definitely. That was part of the strategy. We were perhaps a bit naive
                    as to the extent to which that was real leverage and that we could leverage
                    political change through more economic contacts. It was only when the system
                    literally collapsed that you saw real political change in the country. You saw
                    some change around the edges perhaps from contacts with the West. For example,
                    there was a certain relaxation of their own internal policies although I don't
                    think ever as much as we wanted. Even in Romania, where we made very strong
                    efforts in terms of developing our economic relationship and courting Ceausescu,
                    the toughest of all the Eastern and Central European communist governments, and
                    the government never really loosened its internal political and economic
                    policies until the very end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any pressures from Congress, congressmen from
                        Chicago, which is the largest Polish city after Warsaw? Did this translate
                        into pressures on you all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Certainly with Poland in particular, there was a lot of congressional
                    support which was derived from the large Polish-American population to do
                    whatever we could to develop our bilateral relations. Poland got a lot of
                    special treatment because of its political support within Congress. It was the
                    only East European country that got MFN tariff treatment very early on. The
                    others got it on the basis of an annual waiver review countries' willingness to
                    permit Jewish emigration under the so-called Jackson-Vanik amendment. Poland had
                    it on a permanent basis. Congressman Charles Vanik, who just happened to be from
                    the Cleveland area where I am from, was active in trying to encourage relations
                    with East European countries.. I think his background was Czech or Slovak. He
                    supported initiatives to advance that goal. I wouldn't call it pressure, but as
                    it turned out for those who were trying to implement our strategy for Eastern
                    and Central Europe, it was helpful support generally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you getting from your colleagues? You were
                        dealing with the economic side. What about the ones who were dealing on the
                        political side? Was there a cause and effect of more liberal economic
                        policies?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: My recollection was that we worked well together. The political and
                    economic strategy tended to complement one another. There were some difficult
                    issues usually involving political dissidents. People tend to forget the arrest
                    of political dissidents at that time and Jewish emigration, particularly from
                    Romania more so than from other countries, were very big issues in our
                    relations. Defectors were also a big issue, particularly senior level political
                    defectors, and there were a number of them, including the former ambassador to
                    Washington from Poland. He is a nice guy, Ambassador Romuald Spasowski, a very
                    intelligent guy. He later wrote an interesting autobiography. He had defected
                    shortly after I left the desk, but I had met him many times. My political
                    officer colleague who dealt with Poland and I would go down to meet him and we
                    would chat in the elevator coming up to the seventh floor. The ambassador's wife
                    was a very fervent Catholic. Apparently, even the ambassador was trying to
                    reconcile himself with his Catholic roots. He would lecture my fellow colleague
                    from the desk about how he needed to go back to the Church. We found this rather
                    bizarre, getting a lecture from the communist ambassador from Poland that we
                    needed to be better practicing Catholics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am told by people who were serving in Poland at the
                        timsome of them said that they were convinced that there were at least three
                        communist believers in Polanothers disputed this down to one. Was it pretty
                        obvious that the intellectual support for the communists had pretty well
                        disappeared or were dissipating?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I wouldn't put it in those terms. Looking back, you can see in so many
                    different ways that it was dissipating in the '70s and by the '80s it was just a
                    fragile hallow chamber that was waiting for something to knock it to pieces. But
                    at the time, I don't think anyone had an expectation that there would be radical
                    political change in these countries. We knew that East European countries were
                    Western oriented. Many of the people we dealt with clearly liked you and the
                    United States. But there was nothing that indicated imminent demise of the
                    system. Until the labor strikes in Poland in 1981, it was hard to recognize
                    cracks in a dictatorial regime where you see police out in uniform and armies at
                    the borders. One of the things that always struck me and probably anyone who
                    traveled to that part of the world was crossing a border and seeing armed guards
                    with automatic weapons and the barbed wire and the dogs trying to keep people in
                    and undesirables out. You look at that very impressive physical police and
                    military presence and it's hard to see where the weaknesses are, even though you
                    know the people are dispirited. You know perhaps a majority of people don't like
                    the regime, but you don't see a means for change. The Hungarians tried it and in
                    '56 were brutally crushed. The Czechs tried it in '68. They failed. It didn't
                    look like a regime that was dissipating and about to collapse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had this job during the initial strikes in
                        Poland.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we getting on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It began at the Gdansk shipyards. There are major shipbuilding
                    facilities in Gdansk, and shipbuilders were some of the more radical trade
                    unionists. Lech Walesa, as I recall in a scene that is almost out of a Russian
                    melodrama of how the October Revolution started, got up on a platform outside
                    the shipyard gates and rallied the workers to defy management and go on strike.
                    It resulted in massive strikes throughout the country. At the time, the
                    perception was not so much “Is the regime going to fall apart” but “Are the
                    Russians going to invade?” That was very much a concern. I didn't have access to
                    all the intelligence reports, but there were some that seemed to indicate some
                    mobilization, some indication that the Russians were ready to move in. This is
                    what General Wojciech Jaruzelski, who was the Polish general who emerged as the
                    government leader after the strikes and declared martial law, said he was trying
                    to prevent by declaring martial law and cracking down on the dissidents. He
                    said, “This is necessary to prevent Soviet invasion.” That's indeed what we were
                    fearful of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the Eastern European section, how close were you to the
                        Soviet desk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Actually, not that close. We had some contact, but on the working
                    level, there was not that much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're asking now in 2001. All of us are looking back to
                        '89 and what happened. While you were there, was there any intonation that
                        the Soviet Union's economic policy was sort of a dead end, that eventually
                        this was going to bring everything down? It really was the economics that
                        did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I agree. I think there was a growing realization that the Soviet system
                    couldn't keep up and couldn't produce. There was a sense that East Europeans
                    because they were a little more open to foreign investment and trade, had
                    perhaps somewhat more motivated workers, were more accustomed to Western work
                    habits, that they were a little bit better off. In fact, the visible standard of
                    living in places like Budapest and even Warsaw were noticeably better than in
                    much of the Soviet Union. But where this was going to lead, at that time, you
                    kind of had a sense that the Soviet government couldn't get itself out of this
                    dead end, but no one expect collapse to happen anytime soon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've had people who've said that they were either German
                        experts or Soviet experts or what have you and by the early fall of '89,
                        they had no intimation that this thing would come falling apart the way it
                        did. Of course, this is the thing with a dictatorship. When the powers that
                        be lose the will to enforce it, it does fall. You just don't know when that
                        will will be lost.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It's not only the leaders, but it's also the troops. At some point,
                    they don't believe that the orders will be carried out and at that point the
                    game is over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '81, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In '81, I had a transition to the mid-level economics course and from
                    there out to Thailand in January of '82. This mid-level course was for people
                    who had been in five or six years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I thought it was pretty good. We had more economic training, and the
                    program was better focused there. There was public speaking training and
                    leadership training. Overall, it was pretty good. Others felt differently about
                    it, but I drew upon some of the training later on, so I thought it was
                    useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Thailand from '82 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: 1982 to mid 1985</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job when you went out there in '82?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I had a rather unique position within the embassy. There is a UN
                    regional economic commission located in Bangkok called the Economic and Social
                    Commission for Asia and the Pacific (ESCAP). It is a regional UN center whose
                    purpose is to promote economic and social development mainly in the developing
                    countries. Following World War II, the United States along with Britain, France,
                    and Japan were the founding members. Half to three quarters of the time was to
                    attend meetings at the UN body there and to meet with officials and try to get
                    U.S. agencies involved in some of their activities. I did have some contact on
                    internal Thai issues. I picked up a number of different portfoliothings like
                    minerals and some of the oil industry development, which were important for
                    Thailand's economy at the time. But I spent much of my time involved in the UN
                    activities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the UN activities, how did that mesh with ASEAN?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Really the two didn't mesh much and that was another area which I was
                    also following while I was in Bangkok. The ASEANs within the UN were usually
                    acting together on a lot of different issues. To that extent, there was an ASEAN
                    component, but it was more in terms of their voting within the organization and
                    organized activities.</p>
                <p>We had some economic activities out of the embassy involved with ASEAN and trying
                    to promote ASEAN as a forum for Asia, as a forum for promoting economic
                    development. We helped found ASEAN after World War II.. The United States still
                    attended a lot of ASEAN meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel at least that you were an adjunct of our
                        International Organizations Bureau?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, because the International Organization Bureau was the bureau that
                    backstopped the regional UN economic commissions. Some of their people would
                    come out to the meetings and provide support for that particular function at the
                    embassy. It was a unique economic section function. I found it interesting in
                    many respects because you dealt with all the countries of the region and had an
                    opportunity to meet a lot of different people?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the issues that you were dealing
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The overall thrust of our participation was to try to project a
                    presence within the region, try to use this to enhance our presence and interest
                    in the region. My impression of the UN is not very high as a result of that
                    experience. There is a lot of talk and a lot of paper. It doesn't tend to
                    accomplish all that much. I viewed my role as trying to project in statements at
                    the meetings the U.S. perspective on particular development issues and
                    occasionally some political issues came up. We were trying to encourage these
                    countries, which at that time were still flirting with socialism and a more
                    statist approaches to economic development, to recognize the merits of a more
                    market-oriented approach as we had in the United States.</p>
                <p>Q: Some of the countries one thinks of would be Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore,
                    Indonesia, the Philippines? Vietnam wasn't? I don't know whether Australia was
                    in there.</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: They were in the UN organization, not in ASEAN.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a very dispirited group of countries going off in
                        different ways. Were they at least under UN auspices working together?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: For ASEAN countries as a group, the UN didn't help them very much.
                    ASEAN members, though, clearly had a political sense of identity as a regional
                    grouping. The Thai certainly felt that way. Their strategy was to act as a group
                    because they could get the attention of the United States and Japan and even
                    Europe. Politically it was thought that they would have a much more powerful
                    voice if they spoke together, if they acted together on some of their foreign
                    policy positions. In fact, they were effective in that respect. One of the
                    forums that worked well for them and that they still have is the ASEAN
                    Post-Ministerial Meetings. The ASEAN foreign ministers met together and then
                    they invited the United States, the European Union, and Japan to attend a
                    post-ministerial conference. If any single one of those countries had invited
                    the foreign ministers from the West to attend, they wouldn't bother. But the
                    opportunity to meet all five or six (with Brunei) foreign ministers of the ASEAN
                    countries and talk about regional issues did attract the EU at a senior level
                    and the United States. Secretary of State George Shultz came out to a couple of
                    meetings in the region when I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The U.S. normally made a point of going to that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's right. That was an opportunity to have contact with all
                    Southeast Asian governments at a very high level. It served both our and their
                    interests. We needed an excuse to get out there to the regional but just to go
                    out and visit one Southeast Asian country, secretaries of State aren't going to
                    bother.</p>
                <p>Q: Was Burma sort of an outcast?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, it was still an outcast. We had some Burmese friends in Bangkok;
                    they were kind of political �migr�s. There was a significant community in
                    Thailand of Burmese. The Thais didn't like them. This dislike for Burmese
                    probably goes back hundreds of years. The Thais are polite to everyone, but they
                    really didn't like the Burmese. But Burma was considered an outcast country.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>The other big issue that was somewhat coming to an end but was still significant
                    to us with Thailand was a huge border population of refugees, mainly Cambodians,
                    some Vietnamese. There were also a lot of Vietnamese “boat people,” people who
                    escaped from Vietnam on rickety boats and ended up on Thailand's southern
                    coast.. Many refugees, however, were on the Thai border with Cambodia. There
                    were also camps in southern Thailand where the boat people tended to end up. how
                    the Thai government treated refugees was a big issue. Thailand really didn't
                    like having all these refugees in their country. Initially, they were very
                    hostile and uncaring. I understand that when Mort Abramowitz was ambassador to
                    Thailand, he took this on as a key policy issue. People have said that if it
                    wasn't for his direct intervention, there would have been thousands who would
                    have starved to death because the Thais just weren't going to do nothing.
                    Ambassador Abramowitz finally shook up everyone, including our own government,
                    to intervene and provide what was needed for the refugees. When I was out there,
                    there were several hundred thousand refugees in camps on the border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role that China was playing, particularly in
                        the economic sphere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: China was trying to project more influence in the whole region at the
                    time. My impression was that they were rather clumsy at it. The Chinese did
                    participate in the UN regional organization. They were rather friendly to other
                    representatives there. The Russians were also there. But I didn't get the
                    impression they were all that effective. The Thais, however, are very astute at
                    judging power relationships and had launched a number of initiatives to try to
                    improve relations with China. They were very wary of offending the Chinese in
                    any way. Even when we pushed them to take some hard stands on issues, you could
                    tell they were reluctant to do that because this was a small neighborhood and
                    the Chinese were the big boys in the neighborhood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure you were dealing with the UN bureaucracy there.
                        What was your impression of the international bureaucracy, the UN, as it
                        projected into where you were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I did not a very high assessment of the UN bureaucracy. They were
                    usually very nice people. A lot of them were from South Asia or some from the
                    region there. I got the impression that they valued their UN employment as
                    exceptionally good jobs and they were going to hang on to them. They didn't do a
                    lot as far as I could see except organize meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're talking about Indians and Pakistanis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes. A lot of the UN employees were nationals of these countries. The
                    UN employees were very nice and professional in some ways, but they didn't get
                    very much accomplished.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find living in Bangkok at this particular
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Overall, it was an interesting experience. It takes a while to get used
                    to the tropical heat. In Thailand, you can never get away from it. In Malaysia,
                    you can go to the mountains.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can go North, yes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's one of the things that for a while is enervating, the heat and
                    the sense that there is no place you can go to get away from it. In Thailand,
                    you could go way north into the mountains around Chiang Mai, but in most of
                    Thailand, it was very hot most of the year. There was about six weeks where it
                    was very pleasantly warm. But the heat really saps you. I got used to it over
                    time. Some people never get used to it and never really like it. Compounding
                    that, Bangkok is a bit of a mess of a city and very congested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's worse now.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's what I hear. Traffic is bad. I know the traffic is much worse
                    now. It's a bit of a dirty city, too. There were some very nice hotels and
                    restaurants, but there were some very trashy parts of the city, too. Overall,
                    the combination of the heat, the traffic congestion, and aesthetically the city
                    not being very nicely built could get to you over time. But the Thai people are
                    very nice. They are generally nice to all foreigners, but they really like
                    Americans and were generally very easy to deal with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the head of the economic section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: During most of the time, it was Paul Stahnke, who is retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you off to one side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I worked under Paul. He was technically the permanent representative to
                    the UN, but he didn't attend many meetings. I attended most of them. Then I
                    would work under his direction for other parts of my portfolio.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a feel for the Thai economy as it contrasted
                        to Singapore or Malaysia? How did you see it adjusting to the changes in the
                        world economy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Thailand was generally considered even at that time to be one of our
                    success stories for economic development. After World War II, it was a
                    rice-growing economy. There was no industry there to speak of. The Thais were
                    generally very pro-market in terms of their approach to economic development.
                    The government didn't get involved in a lot of things. You saw a lot of very
                    interesting dynamic economic developments in Thailand as a result. Thailand had
                    a very well developed agricultural sector. It used to be just rice. But Thai
                    farmers were so flexible and responsive to the market that they began growing
                    many different types of crops. Anything they could grow in a tropical climate,
                    they would grow. All kinds of interesting fruits and vegetables and corn, and
                    other crops that we grew in the West. They were very entrepreneurial. It helped
                    that Thailand had a strong Chinese immigrant presence. Many Chinese immigrants
                    has been there for 100 or 200 years, so it's not as if they were recent �migr�s.
                    Most of the business sector, as it is in much of Southeast Asia, is controlled
                    by Chinese immigrants. They're very entrepreneurial. Thailand was considered to
                    be a strong and growing economy at the time, although there were still a lot of
                    poor people. Most of the farm sector consisted of poor farmers, but you could
                    also see very visible growth there. The Thai economy was considered rather
                    successful, although not as successful as Singapore, which was the premiere
                    economy in the region. Malaysia was also considered to be very strong. Then
                    probably Thailand after that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have family there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, I had my wife, who gave birth to our third child there. I had
                    three children in Thailand with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How old were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think they were six, four, and then my youngest was born over
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't really have to worry then about the pernicious
                        influences of Thailand which hit some of the teenage kids.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No. That wasn't a problem. I understand that drugs had been a big
                    problem, particularly before I had arrived. Someone told me that a couple of
                    teenagers had died from drug overdoses at the international school. Even after I
                    had left, one family had to be sent back because their teenage children got
                    involved in drugs. The drugs and the sex, massage parlors and bars, was pretty
                    wide open. So, if I had teenage children, I'd be very concerned about the
                    influence of that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '85, you left Thailand. Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was initially supposed to go back to Romania. I started language
                    training, but we had a family medical problem, so I had to terminate that
                    assignment. I picked up eventually in the Office of Monetary Affairs, which at
                    that time was dealing a lot with Third World debt problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the Economic Bureau from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I started there in the summer of 1986 and went on through '88.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Third World debt was an issue that really concerned the
                        U.S. It concerned everybody, but? It was a north-south issue for the most
                        part. What aspect did you have of this? This was during the Reagan
                        administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: People forget what a big issue that was back in the late 1980s for
                    developing countries around the world, particularly in Latin America and some of
                    the Central European countries (e.g., Poland), some of the North African
                    countries, too, and Nigeria and Sub-Saharan African countries. Asian countries
                    had less of a problem. Basically, these countries had borrowed too much.
                    International banks made credit too easy, and the countries never developed the
                    export capacity to service the debts. We spent a lot of time trying to figure
                    out how to deal with the problem. The Treasury Department had the lead on that,
                    but it was such a big foreign policy issue that the State Department felt that
                    it had to get involved. At least we tried to stay involved, but this was a
                    source of bureaucratic fiction with the Treasury Department because it
                    considered Third World debt to be its issue. The office spent a lot of time on
                    debt issues involving Central Europe, Poland and Yugoslavia being the two
                    countries of greatest concern. Much of the debt these countries owed the United
                    States was U.S. official debt. I often jokingly said when I was on the Polish
                    desk, I recommended that we give two billion dollars in agricultural credit so
                    the Poles could buy U.S. grain and then I went to the Office of Monetary Affairs
                    and tried to figure out how to collect it when they couldn't pay.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were mainly working on the Eastern European side?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was on Eastern Europe, but there was also one kind of unique issue
                    which I spent a lot of time on. It involved Foreign Military Sales (FMS) debt.
                    The United States in its effort to help countries build their defenses against
                    the communists, the threats of communism, had lent a lot of money to countries
                    all over the world, particularly the Middle East, to buy weapons. But it was
                    awful the way it was provided, with commercial interest rates as high as 10
                    percent or more. Basically, we provided the credit at market rates over long
                    terms. Some of these countries, particularly Egypt, had borrowed billion dollars
                    to buy arms. Of course, Egypt is a poor country to begin with. You don't create
                    any economic capacity when you borrow to buy tanks and weapons. Then lo and
                    behold, we're surprised that they can't pay it back. What do we do? The U.S.
                    Congress, being very cheap, didn't want to write it off. They had borrowed,
                    which today seems like extraordinarily high rates, 10 year loans at nine to 11
                    percent. By the late 1980s, the interest rates had started to decline and these
                    countries were complaining 1) we've got this huge debt and 2) it's at very high
                    interest rates. How can we possibly pay it back? Can't you help us? We did an
                    awful lot of running around in circles trying to figure out how to lower the
                    interest rate payments on that debt. In the end, the solution was provided by
                    the Gulf War. All the countries that had supported the United States or
                    participated in the allied force that went into Kuwait were forgiven their debt.
                    That was the one of the greatest financial benefits offered to Egypt. In one
                    fell swoop, they had billions of dollars of debt written off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As one was working on this, in one way or another, you
                        were going to have to write this off. One can talk tough, but you're not
                        going to drive a country to its knees when you've persuaded them to buy
                        military equipment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It seemed pretty evident to me that that was the only outcome, but at
                    the time the Congress was being very hard-nosed that they would just not accept
                    debt write-offs, particularly of this scale. There was a fear of setting a
                    precedent that would migrate over to the commercial debt owed. The Export-Import
                    Bank had also had a lot of loans to these countries that they were having
                    difficulty servicing. Commercial banks were worried about the problem because if
                    you started encouraging countries to think that you could write that off then
                    they would want their civilian private bank debt written off. So there was great
                    resistance to this even though it seemed pretty evident. Egypt is a perfect
                    case. They had billions of dollars in military debt which had very high interest
                    rates and an economy that's not producing much. They were just not going to be
                    able to pay. But when you write off debt, you have to adjust the budget to
                    account for lost income and that means Congress had to cut spending in some
                    other domestic area or in the defense area. At the time Congress was just not
                    willing to do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When there was a big debt crisis that involved Brazil and
                        Mexico, did that come at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Brazil was undergoing debt problems at that time. I think the big
                    Mexican crisis came later. It wasn't something I was focused on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel that Shultz was personally engaged in
                        the economic side of things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: He was interested and was very knowledgeable and took a personal
                    interest in Third World debt as a policy issue. He probably was the only
                    Secretary of State who, because of his experience and academic qualifications,
                    could interact on a peer basis with the Secretary of Treasury. So he was
                    actively involved and probably energized the State Department to be more
                    actively involved on these issues than another Secretary of State might have. He
                    wanted to keep up on both the policy and economic analysis. He met fairly
                    regularly with the Secretary of Treasury to discuss these kinds of issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left in '88. Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Then I went over to the Asian bureau. I got a surprise call from the
                    China Office asking if I would like to serve as their deputy for economics and
                    trade. I didn't know much about China. I had served in Thailand. They wanted
                    someone who knew something about the economy, international economic policy and
                    trade and debt. So, I was asked to serve there in the China Office of the East
                    Asia Bureau. At the time, Stapleton “Stape” Roy was the Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary for China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did this from '88 to '91.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I was there for three years, including the Tiananmen Square
                    massacre.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's do it prior to Tiananmen, which was June '89. What
                        was our stance economically towards China?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was very similar to what it was toward Eastern and Central Europe a
                    decade earlier. The strategy was to try to encourage China to have more contacts
                    with the West. There was almost a missionary fervor in thinking that if we could
                    just bring the Chinese at all levels into greater contact with the West, if we
                    could expand trade with the West, that this would stimulate internal change that
                    would be more liberalizing and might encourage democratic yearnings and a
                    democratic transformation. This was very much the thinking that we had in
                    Eastern Europe in the '60s and '70s. It was a very similar kind of policy only
                    it was much more comprehensive because we were trying to deal with the Chinese
                    at almost all levels. For example, I was also involved in trying to promote the
                    science and technology cooperation. This was also a major effort. There were a
                    lot of U.S. scientists visiting China, and a lot of Chinese scientists coming to
                    the States under a joint science program. We negotiated a new science agreement
                    when I was on the desk. We also had a big joint economic commission with China
                    where we met at a high level. The Secretary of Treasury was involved and the
                    Secretary of Commerce. It was very similar to what we did with Eastern Europe
                    only on a much bigger scale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: China has the potential for being such a major economy
                        that it would do to us what the Japanese had done to us, use us as a market
                        and there wasn't much of a return for us?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, I don't think it was so evident at that time. Actually, it was
                    looking the other way in which many American corporations are still optimistic
                    about the potential of the Chinese market. “There are 1.2 billion people who
                    need to buy Cokes and hamburgers and tractors and machine tools, and if I can
                    just get into that market, I'll be on easy street.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was a book that came out in the '30s called “Oil for
                        the Lamps of China.” If we can only do this? I recall someone wanting to
                        sell caskets. He thought, “Wow, what a market for caskets.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think that in essence was the mentality of a lot of American
                    businesses at that time and still is. If somehow they could crack that market,
                    they would have enormous sales opportunities. The China market has developed
                    much faster than we had thought it would 11 or 12 years ago. When I visited
                    there, you could see the beginnings of market economy develop, and the Chinese
                    had a great interest in Western technology. A lot of companies were starting to
                    go there. But China was still also a very backward place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in either backstopping or dealing at
                        any level in negotiations with the Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, we were involved in a couple of different negotiations. One
                    involved China's membership in the WTO, which started back in the late 1980s. We
                    had two or three rounds with the Chinese before Tiananmen Square. It's rather
                    interesting that because of the desire to have better relations with the China,
                    the Chinese at that time could have gotten had a very easy deal that required
                    few concessions. We were making almost minimal demands. The Chinese, though,
                    were smart by a half. They always thought that they could get a better deal with
                    even fewer commitments. Ten years later when the Chinese finally resumed
                    negotiations, they had to make extensive, comprehensive commitments to reform
                    their economy and open up markets. If they cut a deal back in the late 1980s
                    along the lines that USTR was proposing at the time, it would have had to make
                    very little in the way of commitments. So, their delay was costly in some
                    respects, although their commitments are going to help promote the kind of
                    reforms that they want to do anyway. However, it's going to be very painful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a taste of the Chinese as negotiators?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, a little bit. I traveled three times to China when I was on the
                    desk. A couple of times we had to cancel out. I was supposed to go there a week
                    before Tiananmen, but it looked like situation was going to worsen, so we
                    decided not to go.</p>
                <p>But there are a couple of interesting things about their negotiating style. Their
                    overall approach to dealing with foreigners was to win friends. The Chinese can
                    be very charming to deal with. If you ever go to dinner with the Chinese, you're
                    going to have fun. They're good jokesters. They're friendly. And they like to
                    tell stories. They're a lot of fun to be around. We went many times to the
                    Chinese embassy for dinner. They're very good entertainers. They treated
                    everyone well, from the lowest person on the office staff up to the ambassador.
                    Their approach was to win friends. Their thinking was: “We want to have people
                    all over who are friendly to China.” Of course, they're going to try to use that
                    friendship. It's a very clear strategy of trying to win friends, and they can be
                    very charming at that.</p>
                <p>The other thing I found very strange in the Chinese mentality is, they have this
                    notioand I saw this in the newspaper recently with regard to the downing of the
                    U.S. spy plane in China which they repeatedly referenced and which just sounds
                    so bizarre to Americans. If we did something the Chinese didn't like, their way
                    of trying to put us on the spot was to say, “Well, you have to understand, this
                    hurt the feelings of the Chinese people.” I don't know how many times I heard
                    that. I think it was the Chinese ambassador who said almost the exact same thing
                    about the aircraft. “You hurt the feelings of the Chinese people and now we have
                    to make amends.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, our mantra is, “We'd love to help you, but we
                        have Congress to deal with.” After Tiananmen, what did you do, just fold
                        your tents and twiddle your thumbs?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In some respects, while there was a huge amount of work to do after
                    Tiananmen, mainly just to preserve the relationship because there were those in
                    Congress who wanted to retaliate in various ways against China, most importantly
                    by trying to take away their most favored nation (MFN) trade status. This had to
                    be renewed every year for communist countries under the Jackson-Vanik provisions
                    (of the Trade Act of 1974). The requirement stays in effect until China becomes
                    a member of the World Trade Organization (WTO), in which case we have to provide
                    it on a permanent basis. We spent a lot of time trying to manage the
                    relationship, prevent further damage and get the Chinese to do something to show
                    that they weren't brutal dictators. We also had an incident at the embassy
                    Beijing. There was a Chinese physicist, Fang Lizhi who was an outspoken human
                    rights advocate and who had secretly sought refuge in the ambassador's residence
                    during the Tiananmen Square protests. A very delicate negotiation went on for
                    months to get Chinese permission to have Fang Lizhi leave the country. There was
                    also some concern during that time that the Chinese might even try to break into
                    the residence and snatch him. So we also had in mind the potential threats to
                    the security of the ambassador that such an occurrence might involve. The two
                    years after Tiananmen were very busy and very difficult in terms of dealing with
                    the Chinese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself going over and explaining to
                        particularly the congressional staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Not so much me. That was more done at the senior level. But the
                    congressional dimension took a lot of time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '91, what did they do with you? It was about time to go
                        out again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I had a year at the National Security Council. That was in '92-'93. I
                    was at the NSC working in their Economic Office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One always thinks of the National Security Council as
                        politics. Was this the end of the Bush administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I straddled the two administrations. The Bush administration was
                    winding up and Brent Scowcroft was the National Security Advisor at that time. I
                    worked for Eric Melby, who was the senior director for International Economic
                    Affairs. There were a few issues that were still percolating. We were trying to
                    wrap up NAFTA as an agreement. President Bush had launched the initiative for
                    the Free Trade Area of the Americas [FTAA]. That was back in '92 and President
                    Bush had hoped to follow that up in the second administration. We had some
                    difficult trade problems with the Japanese and with the European Union that we
                    were dealing with at the time. So, there was a fair amount of activity during
                    the final year of the administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling about NAFTA? It became an issue
                        during the election of '92. Ross Perot was running on the independent ticket
                        and he was talking about “Mexico is going to absorb all our jobs.” It got to
                        be very populist. What did you all do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Still in '92 the United States was just wrapping up the negotiations, a
                    very complicated set of negotiations. Part of the complications involved issues
                    like labor rights and the environment that are still active issues. The issue of
                    having Mexican truckers being able to drive into the United States was also
                    prominent in the negotiations. That was something that was handled rather late
                    in the negotiations. The agricultural negotiations were very complicated as
                    well. There is a very complicated system of controls to limit the importation of
                    Mexican fruits and vegetables. California and Florida farmers were concerned. I
                    think the Republican administration and President Bush were just convinced that
                    NAFTA was a good deal for the U.S. and that this would be obvious to everyone.
                    Mexican tariffs were very high. Our markets were relatively open. This large
                    tariff differential continues to be a reality in almost all our negotiations
                    with developing countries. Our markets are already open. When the U.S.
                    negotiates a free trade area, it is basically lowering the other country's
                    tariffs and providing only a marginal lowering on our part. But still there was
                    a sense among the labor unions that, well, this is going to open the flood gates
                    to cheap foreign manufactured products. I don't think the Bush administration
                    fully grasped how sensitive the issue was. Officials were just convinced that
                    this was a good deal, that when you lay it on the table and you point out some
                    of the obvious benefits like lowering these very high Mexican tariffs, that
                    people will see that this is in our interests. Of course, the unions looked at
                    it from a different perspective and saw more risk and threat.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the transition, the NSC is so much a creature of
                        the President and it changes, the way it operates with each new
                        administration. How did that affect you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It did affect the way the NSC operated. (end of tape)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were talking about dealing with Brent Scowcroft.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The way the system was set up in the Bush White House, you had pretty
                    direct access to the National Security Adviser. If you knew an issue needed to
                    come to his attention and maybe to the President's attention, you had latitude
                    to raise it. Brent Scowcroft was very close to the President. There is a big
                    difference between an organization like the NSC and the State Department. You
                    would literally go into Scowcroft's office and brief him on an issue, and he
                    could either deal with it or bring it to the President's attention. Then we went
                    into the Clinton administration. The NSC was hived in two, the regular NSC and a
                    newly established National Economic Council [NEC], which Bob Rubin headed
                    initially before he went on to become Secretary of the Treasury. That was an
                    attempt to do for national and international economic policy what the NSC did
                    for more political foreign policy, that is, effectively shape policy issues, the
                    presidential decisions and communication on economic issues, like the NSC did on
                    foreign policy issues. I think initially, at least, President Clinton had a much
                    more ambitious economic agenda starting with the comprehensive health care
                    reform plan. He originally also had very ambitious plans on energy policy. So,
                    the idea was to provide that same kind of structure for decision making on
                    economic issues that the NSC had traditionally provided on foreign policy. But
                    It didn't work out that way.</p>
                <p>So, the end result was that the international economic side of the NSC had less
                    influence and less direct contact with the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When the President came in, President Clinton, his focus
                        was very much on the domestic economy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's right, and trying to at least “revive” the economy, which
                    looking back was already reviving itself. But that was the thinking, that there
                    needed to be more government intervention. The focus of the NEC at that time was
                    more on the domestic economy.</p>
                <p>Q: In '93, you did what?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: In '93, I ended up going back to the Department for a short time in the
                    Asia Bureau. I was working on China's most- favored-nation trade status renewal
                    and spent a short time working with Winston Lord, the Assistant Secretary for
                    Asia and Pacific Affairs, on that issue. We were still dealing with the fallout
                    from the Tiananmen Square massacre, and relations with Congress over China's
                    trade status was very sensitive. There were expectations, which proved to be
                    unrealistic, that China would make some gestures towards human rights and
                    internal relaxation as a condition for MFN approval. The Chinese, however, were
                    very resistant to that. In the end, we had to try to convince the Congress that,
                    “Even though we told you we thought the Chinese were going to do certain things
                    internally on human rights, they're not going to do it, but it's still worth
                    renewing China's trade status.”</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is August 6, 2001. NSC. You were with the NSC from
                        '93 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I spent a little over a year there. I started in the late spring of '93
                    and that was the last six or seven months of the first Bush administration, Bush
                    Sr., and then continued through midway through the summer of the Clinton
                    administration in which we brought in a lot of new people. I worked in what was
                    called the International Economic Directorate. Eric Melby was the senior
                    director. He had worked at the State Department, although he was not a Foreign
                    Service officer. Brent Scowcroft was the National Security Advisor. There wasn't
                    a lot of activity at that time. The Bush administration was winding up. A lot of
                    focus was on the campaign. But there were some issues, particularly trying to
                    bring the NAFTA negotiations to a closing and also the Uruguay Round, where the
                    NSC was brought in a few times to try to be helpful. Brent Scowcroft was a very
                    smart man and a real military strategic thinker. He did not have a great
                    interest in international economic issues, but one of the things we always
                    appreciated was that at least he was prepared to help if we made a request. If
                    we said, “We think the President ought to raise this with a particular leader,”
                    Brent would make a point of being helpful and trying to get it on the
                    President's agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the international economic directorate at the
                        NSC?.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was the directorate in economics and trade at that time. There was
                    also some environmental work going on. But the focus was on winding up NAFTA and
                    the WTO negotiations. There were also some problems with Japan relating to its
                    implementation of a bilateral semiconductor agreement that set targets for U.S.
                    semiconductor sales in Japan. This concern seems rather odd now that Japan's
                    economy is in the dumps and is not seen as much of a threat to the U.S. in
                    economic terms, but in the early '90s, the Japanese were riding high on their
                    horse and everyone looked up to them with admiration for their manufacturing
                    successes. Particularly in the information technology area and semiconductors,
                    they were considered to be the real threat to the U.S. industry. So the United
                    States had an agreement with the Japanese that tried to guarantee access for
                    U.S. semiconductor companies in Japan and had some limits on what the Japanese
                    companies could do here. In retrospect, it doesn't seem terribly significant,
                    but at the time that was a rather important political issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the NAFTA? The Bush administration had brought
                        this up almost to fruition and then it left.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's right. U.S. trade officials had really done all the
                    negotiations. They were done principally at USTR. There wasn't a lot of White
                    House political intervention to try to close the deal. Carla Hills was the U.S.
                    Trade Representative at the time, a very able negotiator. A few times, we were
                    asked to become involved, but it was done mainly at the U.S. Trade
                    Representative's office and it was almost concluded at the end of the Bush
                    Administration. The negotiations then spilled over into the Clinton
                    administration, and two new issues emerged that have now become more prominent
                    in international trade negotiations: labor and the environment. The Clinton
                    administration under U.S. Trade Representative Mickey Kantor went back to look
                    again at the Bush NAFTA agreement and renegotiate certain provisions that dealt
                    with labor and environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were with the NSC during the transition?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it a friendly transition?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It's rather interesting when you're in a political environment. There
                    is kind of “our guys versus the outsiders” mentality. With Bush, I think because
                    I had known some of the people on the NSin fact, there were several State
                    Department officers who were assigned to the NSC at that timI had a rather
                    smooth transition. When the Clinton team came on, I think it was very clear that
                    “This is our team and we want to assemble our own people. You're just a State
                    Department guy. You didn't work on the campaign, so you're really an outsider.”
                    They weren't unfriendly, but it was very clear who was an “insider” and
                    “outsider.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So did you go looking around for what to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I wasn't sure for a while whether they would want to keep me on. I got
                    a fateful call from Tony Lake, who was the National Security Advisor at the
                    time, on a Saturday afternoon saying that they had decided that they were going
                    to bring in new people and that I would not be kept on. I was not terribly
                    surprised at that. I was hoping that I could stay on because it was interesting
                    work, although they had changed the structure of the NSC at that time. When I
                    had started under Bush, the International Economic Division was part of the NSC
                    structure and then Clinton decided that they wanted to have a separate National
                    Economic Council. So, our office was broken off from the NSC. We were considered
                    a combined office, but effectively we were outside the NSC. Bob Rubin was the
                    national economic advisor, a very interesting person, obviously very smart, but
                    extremely atypical for Washington. He was low key, understated. Even his manner
                    of dress was. Where everyone else on the White House staff had the latest style
                    of suits, he looked like he got his off the rack from a rather low budget store.
                    He didn't carry fancy leather briefcases, but had an inexpensive little
                    collapsible folder that carried all his papers. He was a very nice person. He
                    obviously he felt confident enough that they knew what he was doing and didn't
                    have to impress anyone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened? Were you doing much work for them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was kind of slow. Again, I think it was the sense of the political
                    team wanting to keep control of the important work. I didn't have a heck of a
                    lot to do at that time. One issue that I helped to negotiate that actually
                    turned out to be rather significant had to do with Russia's interest in using
                    their former military rockets to launch U.S. communications satellites. At that
                    time, the U.S. was the only country that made the whole range of communications
                    satellites. Satellites happen to be on the U.S. Munitions List, which means it's
                    a militarily controlled item. So, any country that wanted to launch a U.S.
                    satellite had to get a license from the State Department. The Russians came to
                    us for help. This was at the time of their political transition. The hard-line
                    communists had fallen from power. The new government asked, couldn't we help
                    them by allowing them to use their rockets to launch our satellites, which made
                    perfect economic sense. From a foreign policy sense, it would have helped the
                    Russians. But our rocket launch industry was much opposed to that because it
                    turns out that we had expensive rocket launchers which are geared mainly to
                    military uses. They were the “gold plated version” of what it takes to put a
                    satellite up. We had to negotiate an agreement with the Russians that would
                    enable them to launch only a limited number of satellites a year. We had a
                    similar agreement with China that I also helped to negotiate. So successfully
                    concluding those negotiations and the interagency deliberations involved was one
                    of my concrete accomplishments at the NSC. I was the intermediary for
                    negotiating the position among the agencies as to what the terms of this
                    agreement were going to be. It was eventually signed before I left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they deal with the fact that our commercially
                        launched people were not happy with this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Basically we addressed U.S. industry concerns by putting a quota on the
                    number of satellites that Russia could launch. Our industry was concerned
                    because these Russian launches could be done for a couple of million dollars.
                    U.S. companies were charging $40-50 million. The whole U.S. industry was
                    concerned. I don't know whether the civilian launch industry would have
                    collapsed, but it would have been under severe stress if we allowed unlimited
                    access. There was no real national security reason why we needed such an
                    agreement. Some arguments were made that the satellites could be misused for
                    military purposes. Therefore, we had to control the satellite technology itself
                    and be sure the application was for civilian telecommunications use. Eventually,
                    Russia did sign the agreement, even though it kept a rather low cap on what the
                    Russian could launch. I think that agreement remains in place although it might
                    have been modified.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see a change in the outlook in the people who came
                        into the new NSC, the economic people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think they were rather inexperienced. Of course, Bob Rubin is not
                    inexperienced in the sense of someone who knows international finance, but he
                    was new to government. The people he brought in under him were new. Sandy Berger
                    at the time was the Deputy National Security Advisor. He was a lawyer who did
                    some international practice which mainly, I think, was dumping cases. He didn't
                    have a lot of experience with government, but I think he proved himself to be a
                    very able person in that position. Eventually, he took over from Tony Lake. I
                    sensed a lot of learning during that first six months and a lot of distractions.
                    I remember walking into Sandy Berger's office. This was within weeks after the
                    new team was there. They were talking about gays in the military and trying to
                    figure out how to change the policy and deal with the press. They were spending
                    a lot of time on that particular issue and not on more important international
                    issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you start looking around or let it be known that
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Yes, I looked around a little bit. I ended up working for Tom Simons,
                    who was a former ambassador to Poland and then was a coordinator for our
                    assistance programs for the former Soviet Union, that is, Russia, the Ukraine,
                    and the other New Independent States (NIS). That proved to be interesting. I
                    took several trips to Moscow and to other countries in the region. We had at
                    that time a huge aid program for Russia and the NIS. I think that when the
                    program started, $800-900 million a year was going to Russia and all told almost
                    $2 billion a year for all the NIS, mainly for technical assistance, although
                    there was some commodity assistance that we gave to certain countries. For
                    example, Armenia and Georgia right after they became independent had no access
                    to energy. The Russians had given them subsidized oil and gas as long as they
                    were part of the Soviet Union. They couldn't pay for Russian energy at market
                    prices. They had no hard currency exports. The Russians cut them off. People
                    there, particularly in Armenia, would have froze to death had the U.S. not
                    provided everyone in Yerevan, the capital, with a space heater and kerosene oil
                    to get through the winters. The people in Georgia received a lot of fuel
                    assistance too as well as food assistance.</p>
                <p>It was a real challenge to try to provide political direction to these programs,
                    which were carried out mainly through the AID. I think the programs all had good
                    intentions. But a lot of the assistance was, looking back, not very effective.
                    Either the governments weren't ready for it or it was delivered in a way that
                    didn't take into account the political realities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was such turmoil there that it would have been
                        almost impossible to have a well reasoned, rational program. There wasn't
                        anything well reasoned or rational on the other side to absorb it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think the aid programs generally had a sound rationale. There were
                    some elements and some individuals who were capable of using the assistance. For
                    those there was a lot of good that came out of it. One of the things that AID
                    did very quickly, within two to three years after the Soviet Union fell apart
                    and a new more private market-oriented government come in, was to privatize
                    Russian state enterprises. AID moved very quickly and spent a few hundred
                    million dollars within a year's' time to provide technical assistance on
                    privatization. They did it through a voucher system. Millions of vouchers were
                    printed. The idea was to give all Russian citizens and workers a voucher that
                    they could feel that when the enterprise was sold they would have a stake in it
                    as a shareholder. As it turns out, the big Party bosses took over many of these
                    companies and still run them. So while the privatization occurred quickly, you
                    never really had a stockholder-based private enterprise develop. You certainly
                    didn't have the free-market culture develop. Nonetheless, it helped to get
                    Russia get over that hump quickly. So while not perfect, at least it laid the
                    groundwork for the future. It was very effective in that sense.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Another notable example I remember was, in Moscow we visited a group of teachers
                    who were going to the United States to participate in a curriculum development
                    program at an American college. They had been recruited from all over Russia.
                    They were going to a college someplace in New England for the summer to try to
                    develop a civics curriculum for Russian schools, one based on more democratic
                    principles and a more objective look at Russian history. That was a very good
                    use of money. We talked with the teachers who were participating and they were
                    all delighted to be part of the program. They seemed so sincere and had such a
                    strong feeling and desire that they wanted to help Russia make that transition
                    and they wanted to be a part of that. So, those were a couple of examples where
                    I believe the aid programs made a difference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find working with this dealing with the Bureau
                        of European Affairs and the old Soviet structure within the State
                        Department, the SOV group? They were having to reinvent their own
                        representation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I didn't find that to be an issue. I knew some of them from my earlier
                    assignments. I had worked in the European Bureau for many years. At that time,
                    the new Russia team was part of what was called the Office of the Coordinator
                    for Former Soviet Union. Jim Collins was the director. Later he went out to
                    Moscow as the Ambassador. Tom Pickering was the ambassador to Moscow at the time
                    I was working in the aid coordination office.. I don't think that coordination
                    with the Russian affairs office was a problem. The bigger issue had to do with
                    trying to get a handle on AID. The AID and State Department people are very
                    similar going into the system, but they have a very different culture at AID. I
                    found AID to be very bureaucratic even by State Department standards. We had a
                    lot of bureaucratic friction between our office in the State Department and AID
                    trying to give the assistance programs overall political direction. It's such a
                    cumbersome process to start a new AID program. To develop a technical assistance
                    team, they have to put out bids. It's a very cumbersome paperwork process to get
                    proposals. They have to be evaluated as well as the credentials of the experts.
                    Then the contractor would send “experts” to the field, and some of them weren't
                    all that qualified. A lot of the people assigned had no foreign experience at
                    all. They were only experts in a particular area. So, I think to the extent that
                    there was a friction and a clash, it was more with the State and the AID culture
                    and their sense of not wanting to accept any kind of political direction or
                    guidance. They really needed it because they didn't in many cases understand
                    what they were getting into.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there the equivalent of bull sessions or staff
                        meetings? Here is a system we've been opposing for more than 30 years and it
                        falls apart and instead of trying to stick it to them, we're trying to help.
                        There must have been an awful lot of discussion among our own people,
                        including you, as to what the hell was happening and what could be
                        done.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: At the time, there was great expectation that both the Russian
                    government and the Russian people and even Russian businesses really wanted to
                    change and that they would readily receive our assistance and follow what we
                    thought was a very practical and logical course for transforming and
                    transitioning their government and economy. We underestimated the challenge at
                    all levels even within the State Department and certainly within AID, which had
                    overblown expectations of what they could achieve, how difficult it would be and
                    how entrenched certain interests in the old economic systems were. The
                    corruption element became very quickly embedded in the new system and prevented
                    change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were all sorts of missions and various universities
                        and think tanks going out there as so-called experts. They talked a great
                        game, but when coming up against it, it really wasn't very helpful, was
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The bottom line is, no, it wasn't. The changes didn't occur that we had
                    proposed and that we were paying people to try to achieve. This is probably not
                    unique to Russia. There are probably a lot of AID people who went to Africa
                    25-30 years ago who thought Africa would look a lot different today than it does
                    now. There was a real lack of appreciation of the difficulties in promoting
                    change in the former communist states. There was also a lack of expertise.
                    Certainly AID didn't have any expertise in the former Soviet Union. Our State
                    Department did, but technical assistance is not the kind of thing even we were
                    doing years ago. Perhaps these programs had to be tried. But they should have
                    been reassessed more quickly as to their effectiveness and readjusted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were with Tom Simons from '93 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: '93 to '94. Then I went off to London. I was the economic counselor
                    there. But I was only there a short time. We had an illness in the family and I
                    had to come back after five months. It's a lot of fun for five months. A very
                    interesting place, although I must say, in Europe, most of our economic sections
                    don't have a lot to do because so much of the real economic and trade policy
                    work is done in Brussels. The European Commission and European Union is the
                    center of most of the trade policy and a lot of the economic policies in Europe
                    today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also a lot of the ties between treasury departments.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Actually, we had a Treasury Department office at the embassy in London,
                    which was eventually closed. The person in that office didn't have much to do.
                    In European capitals, there are a lot of senior-level ties with U.S. cabinet
                    secretaries and other senior officials, so there is a tendency to bypass the
                    embassy because they have pals in Washington or particular agencies at very high
                    levels. The feeling was they didn't really need to deal with us at the embassy.
                    They would go directly to the responsible official.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came back in '95.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That's right. When I came back, I didn't have any assignment
                    immediately. Initially, they were going to send me to some program at the War
                    College. I called Bill Montgomery, who had just come back from being ambassador
                    to Bulgaria and was working on Bosnia. The Bosnian peace accord had just been
                    signed at Dayton. The State Department was assembling a team to monitor and
                    assist with implementation of the peace agreement. There were two sides to
                    implementation. DOD was handling the military implementation. The State
                    Department was responsible for the civilian implementation, including elections
                    and aid programs. That brought me in touch with AID again. Bob Gallucci was
                    initially the coordinator for our peace implementation. But he had a bit of a
                    clash with John Kornblum, who was Assistant Secretary for the European Bureau at
                    the time, over who should have the policy lead on Bosnia. John Kornblum, being
                    an old experienced State Department bureaucrat, was not going to have someone
                    within his bureau whom he had no authority over. So, Bob Gallucci said, “I'm not
                    going to accept an appointment on these terms.” He left, went to Georgetown, and
                    Bill Montgomery then became the coordinator for the office. We spent most of our
                    time then overseeing elections and aid programs and coordinating with the
                    military on trying to be sure that the two aspects of the implementation were
                    complementary. While I was in the office there was some discussion of catching
                    senior war criminals (e.g. Radovan Karadzic and Ratko Mladic). I got involved in
                    coordinating with DOD on this but the issue was not resolved. Later on, there
                    had actually been several war criminals that had been sent to The Hague. Former
                    President Slobodan Milosevic was eventually handed over. I'm flabbergasted that
                    they finally got him to go. That was a very interesting period.</p>
                <p>It reflects well on the State Department that when we had crises of this nature
                    which really didn't fit into the established offices or bureaucratic structures,
                    we were able to assemble a team and to bring people to work on the problem. In
                    this case, they were all experienced officers, people with different
                    backgrounds, including several who had Balkan backgrounds. We succeeded in doing
                    something different from what you normally do within the existing structure. I
                    think this is increasingly the kind of thing that the State Department will be
                    called upon to do when crises emerge. The fact that we showed we were able to do
                    this reflects well upon the people and the system.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What piece did you have of the Bosnian action?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was a little bit of everything, a little bit of coordinating aid, a
                    little bit of helping to prepare for the elections. There was some de-mining
                    issues which came up. It turns out that during the fighting they had spread
                    mines all over the fighting area and no one knew where they were. It is even to
                    this day extremely dangerous for anyone walking or riding through that area.
                    They could get blown up. It happens every now and then, although they've charted
                    certain safe zones and safe pathways that people can travel on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was an election observer twice. Near Tuzla, up in the
                        Serbian area, there was a lady from the OSC talking about mines and saying,
                        “Okay, fellows and ladies, if you have to relieve yourself, piss on the
                        pavement and don't step on the side.” But it did bring home to you. You just
                        didn't mess around.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the last couple of years, almost criminal elements within the Bosnian
                    government or at least the establishment have? There are a lot of questions
                    about where money went. Did you get involved with this?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: It was an issue that emerged in our work. Corruption was prominent in
                    the region very quickly after the war. Even when we made “clean” government
                    practices a condition for receiving aid, senior people in the Bosnian
                    governmenand these were from all factions, but the Muslims were certainly as bad
                    or worse than the other groupkept haggling. The conclusion was that they would
                    just not agree to accept the aid unless there was a way that they could steal
                    part of it. I recall seeing not too long ago an article in the paper noting the
                    problem when an audit was done. I don't think it was USAID programs so much as
                    some of the other foreign aid programs where there was massive fraud in stealing
                    by government officials. It surprised us at the time that even though there was
                    such a dire need for aid and people were hungry and cold and needed all kinds of
                    material assistance, the government officials would insist on getting their cut
                    before they were willing to receive or distribute aid. That problem continues in
                    the region. It was interesting that even at a senior leveJohn Kornblum went out
                    many times and beat up on the president of Bosniit didn't seem to have any
                    effect. It was all nice words, but then when it came time to try to develop the
                    terms for receiving the aid, someone in the government would insist, no, it had
                    to be done this way, which of course would mean they were going to get part of
                    it. So, this was a big issue and it was never satisfactorily resolved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a big European effort, too. How about the
                        various? Was aid pretty well coordinated at least between the various
                        governments?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: That was always a challenge. The U.S. and EU aid systems are very
                    different. AID is by all measures a bit slow in getting aid out, but the
                    European Union system, which is administered out of the European Commission in
                    Brussels, is awful. They're very slow and there is a lot of political bickering
                    over which country gets which contracts. Part of the slowness of the process is
                    that certain countries insist on getting their cut of the contracts and they
                    won't agree to the program unless they do. So a way had to be found to spread
                    around the contracts to different EU countries and that took time. We had a
                    special coordinator for reconstruction assistance. He was the president of a
                    construction company who had no diplomatic experience who went out to Bosnia and
                    did a pretty good job. We all thought he was a bit brusque and obnoxious, but
                    apparently it was just what was needed to knock heads out there and get people
                    to cooperate. In that respect, I don't know if you've talked with Jock Covey. He
                    was the senior U.S. diplomat who was the deputy coordinator for civilian
                    implementation in Bosnia. It was an international position that was created
                    after the Dayton Accords and that we paid for. The civilian implementation
                    organization was not really part of the European Union or the U.S. government
                    but a separate entity. Jock said something about international coordination that
                    stuck with me. He said that one of the things that the Europeans really
                    appreciated about U.S. diplomats is our ability to organize staff and implement
                    programs. They're not used to getting together in a meeting, setting an agenda,
                    doing a decision paper, and then coming to a conclusion and then taking an
                    action. They really appreciated what comes natural to a lot of Foreign Service
                    Officers if you spend time in Washington and even overseas—this methodical
                    ability to bring people together, talk an issue through, staff it out, do your
                    decision paper, and then reach a decision, and then implement it. He said that
                    our U.S. diplomats were very much appreciated for this ability that just comes
                    pretty natural to people who have been in the system for a while. U.S. diplomats
                    were considered a real asset to the operation over there. It was easier for
                    Americans to bring Europeans together and go through that process than it was
                    for a European national who would seen as a rival to others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing this from '95 until about when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Through '96. Then I took over as director of the European Union office,
                    which was called the Office of Regional and European Union Affairs, better known
                    in the old days as EUR/RPE [Regional Political and Economic Affairs]. The office
                    had two responsibilities, overseeing the U.S. OECD mission in Paris and then
                    directing relations with the European Union and the European Commission in
                    Brussels. At the time, I didn't know much about the European Union. I had to do
                    a lot of quick reading. It's a rather complicated organization with a lot of
                    different institutions. The European Union is a quasi-federal system, but really
                    the 15 members states (at that time), most of Western Europe, still want to keep
                    their national prerogatives, particularly over foreign policy. The members are
                    always limiting what Brussels is trying to do. But just shortly before I
                    started, the U.S. had launched with the European Union something called the “New
                    Transatlantic Agenda.” This was an attempt to reinvigorate the U.S.-European
                    partnership which had lagged over the years, particularly as the Cold War ended.
                    The Cold War threat had encouraged European unity and kept the Europeans working
                    with the United States, but it was no longer a compelling force. The New
                    Transatlantic Agenda established a variety of areas in which we would try to
                    interact in a formalized way to see if we could build up a greater sense of
                    partnership in trade and political issues, foreign policy issues, and areas like
                    law enforcement and drugs trafficking, There was also a belated attempt to
                    somehow build “people to people” relations, which didn't really do very
                    much.</p>
                <p>Under the New Transatlantic Agenda, we had a formalized process of consultations
                    with the European Union that involved the European Commission in Brussels and
                    the EU “presidency” country. Under the European Union system, there is a
                    rotating presidency,. Every six months one member country serves as the “chair”
                    of the European Union. So, we would have these joint meetings with the European
                    Commission and the presidency country of the European Union to discuss trade and
                    international cooperation on issues like aid to Russia or crisis issues in
                    Africa. We spent a lot of time trying to find a way of managing a relationship
                    which had often deteriorated into a lot of spats over trade issues. To some
                    extent, we succeeded. The idea of this kind of partnership was a good one at the
                    time and it remains a good one. The European Union as an organization and a
                    political and trade body is going to be even more important as it expands its
                    membership. The EU will soon include all of Western, Central and Southern
                    Europe—27 countries in all. So, we have to find a more systematic way of dealing
                    with this group. This is a good initiative, and I think it's going to
                    continue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started with this in '96 and-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Through '98.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived on this, could you state your prejudices
                        at that time? Was this a good thing or a bad thing? Whither the European
                        Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: When I first started, I was appallingly ignorant of what the European
                    Union was all about and really had to go out and read two or three books within
                    the first month to just understand the institutions. I think my prejudices were
                    that Europeans were a bit feckless and always complaining and not really
                    appreciative of all the things the United States had done. In the end, I don't
                    think it was dispelled. But I can see now how the Europeans see Americans as a
                    bit arrogant. We pride ourselves in being very creative and coming up with a lot
                    of new ideas, but what they always laugh and cry about is, “You come up with all
                    the great ideas and then you want us to pay for them,” which isn't too far from
                    the truth. We certainly didn't have in the European area any extra cash to spend
                    on new ideas even in aid programs in other parts of the world where we thought
                    more money should be spent. We didn't have a lot of money to put in. From their
                    perspective, there is some validity to their criticism of us. But our biggest
                    challenge with Europe is we're two trade competitors in the global marketplace.
                    The Europeans perhaps see themselves as more of a competitor to the U.S. than we
                    see the Europeans. We just want market access everywhere. They see every
                    initiative by the United States as just one more effort to try to prevent Europe
                    from becoming competitive or to continue our economic dominance. The French
                    particularly have this perspective. That psychology did have practical
                    consequences. There were trade conflicts that we had a hard time solving because
                    the French, in particular were very suspicious of the United States and didn't
                    want to compromise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel? Looking at this, watching the
                        European Union and all, an American can sit back with a certain amount of
                        satisfaction by saying the fact that you've got this outfit in Brussels and
                        Strasbourg putting together all these laws and regulations and then you have
                        to make sure that every nation in the Union gets its cut, plus the socialist
                        overlay, the social net, so you can't cut jobs, you can't move things
                        around. But this gives us maybe a good five percent advantage in dealing
                        with them. It's an inhibitor rather than allowing the real competition to
                        develop.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: European officials recognize that they have this heavy burden of the
                    European approach to economic policy and social programs. What that makes them
                    is all the more paranoid and all the more concerned that no matter how hard they
                    try, given their approach to social welfare programs and labor laws, they're
                    never really going to catch up with the United States. That concern remains. It
                    affects their attitude towards problem solving. There are certain American
                    extraterritorial laws, for example, dealing with Cuba or Iran, that allow the
                    United States to sanction any company in the world even if they are not a U.S.
                    company, if for example they invest or trade in Cuba or Iran. This drove the
                    Europeans crazy to think that Americans would pass a law that could punish their
                    companies in other countries when their own foreign policy decided that this was
                    totally acceptable. Because of this sense of being behind the United States
                    economically, they were always on the defensive and tended to overreact. This is
                    a problem in managing relations with the Europeans. On the one hand, Congress
                    blithely passes these sanctions laws, even though the laws don't have much of a
                    practical consequence. For Europeans, their reaction against U.S. unilateral
                    policies is a matter of principle, but what stirs the matter of principle is
                    this gnawing paranoia and fear that the U.S. is always going to be above them.
                    They tend to overreact. It makes it more difficult to solve the problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find in our looking at Europeans that, say, the
                        Germans and maybe other countries were allowing the French to be the point
                        person to be difficult and they were happy the French were carrying the
                        burden of protectionist policies but they were really supporting the
                        French?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: We've often talked among ourselves about the dynamics among the
                    different countries. I think for some countries that may be the case and perhaps
                    for some companies within countries. The Brits were generally always well
                    disposed to try to be helpful and try to broker compromises and deals so that
                    we'd get out of these disputes, although not always. They could be very hard
                    headed on their own trade interests, too. But the Brits didn't have much
                    influence on the Continent. They were considered a late joiner of the EU and
                    even today are the least enthusiastic about the EU among the member countries.
                    Brits and even some of their politicianare always making snide remarks in the
                    press to the effect “We really don't like being in the European Union.” So as a
                    result they don't have much influence in the EU. Germany, the big elephant in
                    the room, is a victim of its history in that its goal is to be integrated into a
                    Europe where they don't stand out and their historical misdeeds don't become
                    prominent in relationships. Its primary goal is to have good relations with
                    France. When we had these problems and we'd go to the Germans and say, “Can't
                    you be helpful on this? Can't you try to work this out within the European
                    Union,” they'd always say the right things, but as far as we could see, they
                    never did anything. Our interpretation was that they deferred to the French. If
                    it was a huge strategic issue with the United States, they'd probably side with
                    the United States. But on your day-to-day disputes and even fairly significant
                    ones, they felt that the most important thing is not to be out of step with
                    France. “We have to have good relations with France and if that means the French
                    are being obnoxious with the Americans, and this is causing problems, that's
                    okay. We'll live with that. But we're not going to do anything to upset our
                    relations with France. We're not going to pressure them.” The French are pretty
                    hard to pressure anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's been a cornerstone of our policy, and really a very
                        successful one? The whole idea was to stop one of these European civil wars
                        between the French and the Germans. Two world wars is sort of enough. That
                        was our policy. It's working. But were we beginning to say, “Well, let's try
                        to do a little unknitting to bring a little pressure, to draw a line between
                        the Germans and the French?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: No, that never came up in any discussions. We had a very firm and clear
                    policy of support for European unity and for the European Union as a community.
                    And we were also pushing Western European countries to expand the European Union
                    to include Central Europe. A united EU trade community, combined with NATO,
                    would be the mechanism for ensuring stability throughout the European area.
                    That's still a very sound policy. Trying to play in European politics and play
                    one off against the other, I don't know that we ever tried that. We tried to use
                    our friends like the Brits and the Germans, and even the Dutch occasionally, to
                    mediate or be helpful in resolving disputes, but we never tried to play one off
                    against the other.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a very dangerous game to do. The whole idea is to
                        keep the Germans and the French from going at each other. How about what was
                        coming out of Brussels and Strasbourg? You have an awful lot of very highly
                        paid politicians and bureaucrats coming up with unified economic rules which
                        seem like part of a sclerosis of the system. They're over regulating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: The trade issues that came up that we spent most of our time related
                    more to regulatory policies and standards. There were relatively few trade
                    issues that were strictly speaking protectionist. Some companies complained
                    about difficulty of doing business in Europe because EU technical standards are
                    set in ways that favor European companies. We had a few big regulatory issues
                    that came up because of their major impact on trade that we spent a lot of time
                    on. One of them involved new products based on biotechnology. U.S. grain
                    producers have developed these genetically modified grains. The jargon is
                    “genetically modified organisms [GMOs]” that trigger certain qualities in seeds
                    and make them resistant to bugs or have other qualities that are overall very
                    beneficial for growing. But the European publics haand I think it was genuine,
                    although there could have been some protectionist sentimenstrongly opposed
                    development of these GMO-based products, saying “This is 'Franken food.' This is
                    going to be terrible. We'll have mutated babies.” None of this was ever proven.
                    The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and other scientific groups have
                    done studies and concluded that there is no harm to humans from GMO-based
                    products. There was probably some protectionist motivation among some groups,
                    but this was basically a public perception issue. “Even though there is no
                    scientific evidence, we don't want these products coming to Europe.” So, with
                    U.S. farmers going whole hog growing this grain with genetically modified
                    organisms, we had a situation where we thought we'd have to shut down the grain
                    trade to Europe. The Europeans seemed initially to indicate that “Even if there
                    are trace amounts, we won't accept grain shipments.”</p>
                <p>Q: What would that mean?</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: You could have ships on the sea with grain that are just stuck there. A
                    major disruption in agricultural trade with Europe. We reached a temporary
                    compromise, but this is a continuing issue. I think this shows the importance of
                    having clear internationally recognized technical rules on what are acceptable
                    products. Given the massive flows of commodity and product in global trade these
                    days, even small changes in technical rules can have huge impacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I live in Northern Virginia and can see French TV every
                        night. You can see Joseph Bove and all these guys running around having a
                        wonderful time. The French and the Germans go for a sense of dramatic. It's
                        a lot of play acting. They're treating this like a nuclear disaster. Let's
                        say they did say, “No, we won't accept your grain.” Were we thinking in
                        terms of “Okay, screw you. If you won't accept your grain, we will retaliate
                        by not accepting major exports to the United States?”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I'm sure there would have been some kind of retaliation along those
                    lines. The threat was out there. I don't think we had gotten that far. But we
                    did have some trade retaliation on a couple disputes. There was another case
                    involving beef that Americans had been exporting to Europe that was grown with
                    growth hormones. The Europeans said, “We don't want that beef,” even though
                    there was no scientific evidence saying that cattle raised with
                    hormone-containing feed was harmful to humans. Increasingly, this is a category
                    of trade problems that we're going to have to address, particularly with Europe.
                    European consumers have a certain kind of preferences on acceptable foods and
                    they don't care if there is no scientific evidence supporting their preferences.
                    Either they feel it's unhealthy or there is some perception that this is not
                    good for them. What do you do? It seems to me a bit unreasonable on the part of
                    the U.S. government to say, “Well, you have to accept these foods even though
                    your publics don't want them.” On the other hand, if you allow this to continue,
                    that is, allowing trade restrictions without scientific justification, this
                    would be an open invitation for protectionism.</p>
                <p>Q: One can see that people feel very strongly about this, but behind some of this
                    is a certain amount of sticking it to the Americans on the part of the
                    public.</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Sticking it to Americans may have been part of it but not necessarily
                    in a protectionist sense. My impression of Europeans is that they have a rather
                    low opinion of Americans and that there are all kinds of prejudices out there
                    that Americans don't have about Europeans. We have stereotypes, but I don't
                    think it's so much in a negative way. I think they look at us as too
                    capitalistic and lacking in culture. The French think we don't know good food
                    when we see it. So, I think that there is that overlay that does affect public
                    attitudes and has practical implications in terms of trying to solve problems
                    that arise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said there are a couple of issues. One was the
                        modifications of grains. Any other major ones that you were dealing
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: There were a lot of unique kinds of trade issues. One involved the
                    merger of Boeing with McDonnell Douglas. Even though they are two American
                    companies, because they sell their products around the world, including Europe,
                    the European Union claimed jurisdiction over the merger under EU law. The
                    European Commission was going to block the merger. In fact, the Commission did
                    this with Honeywell and General Electric just a few weeks ago, flexing its
                    muscles on regulating mergers and acquisitions. This had all of a sudden come
                    from being a routine regulatory issue to one that went to the White House very
                    quickly. McDonnell Douglas was going to go bankrupt if they didn't merge with
                    Boeing because they couldn't make it in the jumbo jet market. So, we very
                    quickly scurried around. There wasn't too much we could do. The Justice
                    Department was managing the issue and told us to butt out. Nonetheless, it was a
                    foreign policy issue. We had to somehow try to become involved. In the end,
                    Boeing agreed to concessions that involved selling off certain subsidiary
                    product lines of McDonnell Douglas so that they would be less dominant in
                    certain areas and that solved the problem. But for a few weeks, this had gone up
                    to the President and was probably would have caused a very serious reaction,
                    particularly since there had been a lot of workers who would have been let go at
                    McDonnell Douglas if the merger failed.</p>
                <p>Q: It sounds like somebody must have been thinking, “Okay, there goes the
                    European Airbus.”</p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I'm sure there were some who probably thought that this was really the
                    French and Airbus behind the scenes trying to make it difficult for Boeing.
                    Boeing went downhill after the merger with McDonnell Douglas. I don't know
                    whether that was part of the cause. I think it might have been. The European
                    Commission had a very strong Commissioner for competition policy, Karel Van
                    Miert. I think he was sincerely interested in competition issues and did not see
                    this as a protectionist measure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we developing a comparable thing to look closely at
                        European mergers?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: U.S. authorities do look at European mergers, but the Justice
                    Department and Federal Trade Commission have a much more flexible approach. For
                    example, with General Electric and Honeywell, they had approved that merger and
                    then it went over to the European Commission. Commission officials took a
                    different analytical view that had some validity, but it was not one that our
                    experts would have taken.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>Another set of issues that we spent a lot of time on had to do with Iran and
                    Cuba. We had two laws on the books that would have punished European companies
                    for doing certain kinds of business in Iran and Cuba. We had something called
                    the Iran-Libya Sanctions Act (ILSA), which Congress just renewed for another
                    five years. ILSA says that any company that invests more than $20 million in
                    Iran in the energy sector can be subject to certain penalties in the U.S. We
                    were in a situation where a Malaysian oil company, a Russian oil company, and a
                    French oil company had signed a contract to invest several hundred million
                    dollars in Iran and clearly violated the law from the U.S. perspective. But the
                    President did have a waiver authority. What we had to do was try to extract from
                    the Europeans some kind of commitments that they would work with us to promote
                    positive change in Iran. It was touch and go for an extended period. But it was
                    as much a negotiation with the Congress as it was with the Europeans. The
                    Congress kept saying, “Why aren't you enforcing the law? Why should the
                    President waive? This is what we wanted him to do. We wanted him to sanction the
                    Europeans.” There was a similar problem with Cuba and the Helms-Burton Act,
                    which involves sanctioning companies that trade in U.S. property in Cuba that
                    was nationalized after Castro took over. That happened to several big U.S.
                    companies down there. That property had been transferred from one party to
                    another and was eventually sold by the Cuban government to some European
                    investors. Under the U.S. law, the European companies would have had to have
                    been sanctioned because they were trading in U.S. confiscated property. So, we
                    had a rather elaborate negotiation with the Europeans which Stu Eizenstadt, who
                    was Under Secretary for Economic Affairs at the time, coordinated. I was
                    involved with that along with a few other people trying to develop a face-saving
                    statement that we could use with the Congress and with the Europeans saying that
                    “The U.S. and EU are cooperating for positive change in Cuba and Iran and
                    because of that, you should overlook violations or what were in effect
                    violations of the law and allow the President to waive the Helms-Burton
                    sanctions.” We had Secretary Madeleine Albright raise it when she was at the
                    U.S.-EU summit in London in June 1998 which I attended. Secretary Albright had
                    to weigh in with her European counterparts to try to get them on board. Finally,
                    the French did agree and we concluded a statement that had virtually no
                    operative impact on anything but it provided the cover we needed to do what
                    everyone knew we were going to do anyway, i.e., waive the sanctions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've had the feeling for a long time that the French are
                        way out in front in trying to? For example, we have a real problem with
                        Iraq, which is still a hostile state no matter how you slice it. It is a
                        threat. We're trying to keep it down through sanctions. But the French can
                        hardly wait to get in there and sell whatever they can to Iraq, including
                        military equipment. Was this your perception?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: When I was working on these issues, the concern was mainly Iran. I
                    don't recall whether there was much activity with Iraq. But we had a number of
                    discussions with the Europeans to talk about Iran and why we thought the
                    Europeans should be tougher on their trade with Iran. We never really convinced
                    them. This raises a very good question with regard to Europe and the French and
                    the Germans. They all wanted to get into Iran to do business. A lot of them were
                    active in Iraq already at that time. I don't know the Europe's level of trade
                    with Iraq, but I know with regard to Iran, all the major European companies had
                    been there. The Japanese had sent a major trade mission there. It raises a
                    question about their real intentions. Our European counterparts said that they
                    saw transition happening, particularly in Iran with the election of President
                    Mohammad Khatami. When he was first elected in '96 or '97, Europeans said,
                    “Well, we're going to see a lot of change in Iran, so we need to be nicer to
                    them.” There probably has been some change, but I think both Iran and Iraq are
                    still threats. They're as much a threat to Europe as they are to the United
                    States. So the question is, what is their strategic thinking or do they have any
                    strategic thinking? Are they just assuming that if things really get bad, the
                    U.S. will take care of it and, in the meantime, Europeans can just go and make
                    some money? Or are they really deluding themselves to think there's no problem?
                    I've often wondered how the Europeans see a lot of these issues where we see
                    strategic threats and they just see commercial opportunity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Cuba? Many people have said that we made a
                        terrible mistake in Cuba in that if we had opened up our trade and not put
                        this tremendous embargo, it probably would have helped destabilize Castro as
                        it did in other places. Was this one of those things where because of the
                        politics of the Cuban-American votjust like Israeyou don't talk about
                        change?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: I think you hit it on the head. There was an assumption that the trade
                    embargo was a given, that this was what Congress wanted and that you weren't
                    going to change the minds of people on the Hill. You had some influential
                    Florida representatives who were very active and were willing to weigh in
                    heavily on Cuba policy. The assumption was, this is what we have to live with
                    now, so let's make the best of it and try to get our Europeans to come along as
                    best we can. This says a lot for Stu Eizenstadt, the Under Secretary for
                    Economic Affairs at the time. Stu had to deal with the Congress directly on this
                    issue and got beaten up a number of times for not being as tough with the
                    Europeans as they thought he should have been. His approach was to show that the
                    Europeans were helping to encourage positive change in Cuba and at the same time
                    to try to encourage the Europeans to do more. He was successful at this. He
                    defused a huge problem over European companies' violation of the Helms-Burton
                    amendment. His approach was to say something along the lines of: “You don't like
                    our policy but you do share our interests. You want to promote human rights in
                    Cuba—the Spaniards in particular were very committed to that, and a few other
                    countries as well—so why don't you just work with us? You can do a few extra
                    things and then we can use this to help on Helms-Burton. You can have some
                    seminars on human rights. You can speak out on human rights. This will help to
                    defuse the problem of Congress.” He took a lot of relatively small actions and
                    put them all on a big list and said, “Look at all the things that the Europeans
                    did. The Dutch held a seminar. The Spaniards made this statement. They sent a
                    delegation here. There was this and there was that.” There was this whole long
                    list of things that the Europeans had done which if you looked individually at
                    each one, they were really of relatively minor significance, but overall, it
                    looked like the Europeans were finally cooperating. So, by taking that approach,
                    he defused a problem with the Europeans and satisfied the Congress. Everyone
                    just accepted that Cuba policy was there and you weren't going to change it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '98, what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: When I finished in the Office of European Union Affairs, I went into
                    the retirement seminar, concluding an interesting 23 years in the Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly looking at your last job with the OECD, with
                        the European Union and all. This is going to be with us for a long time.
                        Having a bit of work on how we deal with this problem? It's not earth
                        shaking in that it will be there for a long time, but it's trade and not war
                        and that's the way it should be.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: There is a general ignorance of what the European Union is and how it
                    functions within the State Department. There aren't too many people who really
                    understand how we need to interact with them. I hope that in the next few years,
                    we come to a better understanding of how to interact in an effective way. When
                    you look around the world, Europe is our only potentially effective ally to deal
                    with a whole range of global and strategic issues. If we can't do this well, the
                    United States will be at a loss because of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's stop at this point then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>PRIMOSCH: Thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
