<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000642">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Donald A. Kruse </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>DONALD A. KRUSE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: March 17, 1997</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: Today is the 17th of March 1997. This is an interview with Donald A. Kruse.
                    This is being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and
                    Training and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. Let's start at the beginning. Tell me
                    when and where you were born.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I was born in Philadelphia in 1930.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me a bit about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We were quintessential Philadelphians, I guess. My father and grandfather
                    had lived in Philadelphia. I was raised in the city for the first 12 years of my
                    life and then we moved out to the suburbs in Media. I graduated from Media High
                    in 1948 and then went onward to other places. My family continued to be based in
                    Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your father and mother have occupations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: In those days, of course, my mother was mostly at home. I had one brother.
                    My father was trained as a Presbyterian minister, but he had left the ministry
                    by the time I came along. He was a bank officer for most of the time I was
                    growing up.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went to Media High School. What was that like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It was a nice little high school. I must say, back in those days, I felt I
                    learned in a rather peaceful environment. I thought that the education I got
                    there was decent. It prepared me for my college. We had a sense of community. It
                    was a small high school. It had not yet been overwhelmed by the suburbs, which
                    were gradually encroaching then. In fact, the high school no longer exists. It's
                    been amalgamated into some bigger one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated from high school about 1948?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Then I went out to college in Illinois at Wheaton College and majored in
                    history. Those were the years—I was interested in foreign affairs. I was
                    recognizing the aftermath of World War II. I think, probably, that began to get
                    me my interest in the Foreign Service, just events that were going on around the
                    world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In history, did you have any particular field of
                        concentration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Not essentially, although my interest was deeply in American history. I
                    did take a lot more courses in that than I did in European or others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the foreign affairs raise any interest at Wheaton?
                        You're ithe middle of Illinois.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's a good question. I think I was about the first in the post war era,
                    except for one other officer that I discovered later on who took the Foreign
                    Service exam. It's true that we had one earlier graduate of Wheaton, who many
                    years before I got there had gone out as a missionary to Thailand. Ken Landon,
                    husband of Margaret Landon who wrote “Anna and the King of Siam.” He was the one
                    graduate that we knew had been in the Foreign Service. In fact, when I first
                    came to Washington in 1951 just to kind of look around, he was the person that I
                    first saw. So, we had that kind of a connection. But you're right. There were
                    not many people into foreign affairs, not many who were anything else but
                    conservative Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you would have graduated from college in 1952. Then
                        what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, the Army was beckoning. So, I stayed it off for a year as I got my
                    graduate work at the University of Pennsylvania. I got a masters in political
                    science. Within a year, I was in the Army for a two year stint which did not
                    take me overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in the Army?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>KRUSE: The Army in its wisdom decided I would make a wonderful psychiatric social
                    worker. My friends jokingly say that was one way for a psychiatrist to keep an
                    eye on me. But I learned things about Rorschach tests and that kind of thing,
                    which was elucidating. I'm not sure how much of it ever stuck with me. But the
                    Army gave me something that I wouldn't have done otherwise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you doing that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Mostly in the south. I had a succession of places from South Carolina to
                    Texas. Eventually, I actually got married in the stint in the Army. I took my
                    bride to the unlikely sounding town of Ozark, Alabama. We then moved over to
                    Enterprise, which probably sounds a little better. It was an interesting town.
                    This is the town that has a statue to the boll weevil. That's its distinction.
                    The boll weevil made them switch from cotton to peanuts, some have been
                    millionaires ever since.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you're out of the Army about '55? KRUSE: Yes. It was
                        '53 to '55 that I served.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I came back to Philadelphia. As soon as I got out of the Army, I wanted to
                    take the Foreign Service exam. I took it in '56. In the meantime, I had gotten a
                    job with a municipal research institution in Philadelphia called the
                    Pennsylvania Economy League, a taxpayer supported group that was for good
                    government. I have to say that, although it wasn't unpleasant, I don't think I
                    could have stayed at local government very long. It just seemed not interesting
                    enough, not broad enough based. Actually at that time, it was very interesting
                    in Philadelphia. Finally, the reform people had come in of Joe Clark and Dicky
                    Dilworth and thrown out what had been called the corrupt and contented
                    government of Philadelphia. So, it was an exciting time. But even with the
                    excitement, I didn't think this was for me.</p>
                <p>Q: Before you took the Foreign Service exam out of the Army, did you run across
                    any more people connected or reading about the Foreign Service?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think maybe a few more, yes. In fact, I guess one or two of my
                    colleagues did take it, but I don't think any of them came in. I have not seen
                    them since.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you pass the written exam?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, I passed the written and then got myself set up for the oral, which
                    was an interesting experience. In those days, they gave you a two hour oral.
                    There wasn't any “in box” business. It was just straight interviewing, as you
                    know. There was another fellow with me. We came up from Philadelphia to New York
                    for the afternoon they were giving it. The other fellow had gone first. I didn't
                    know him, except talking outside as we waited. He came back out and he indicated
                    that he had not really known a lot of the subject matter that he was being asked
                    about, but that he had attempted to kind of talk around it. I thought to myself,
                    “That doesn't sound like the way to go.” I think you're better off if you simply
                    go in and tell them you're dumb. I followed that scheme. It turned out when they
                    called him in, they told him that they didn't pass him for the very reason that
                    he seemed to be devious. In my case, they figured I may be dumb, but at least
                    I'm honest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you recall any of the questions you were asked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I do. They said, “You're from Philadelphia. Tell me something. Who do you
                    think is the most important Philadelphian that ever lived?” I had never thought
                    about it before, but I think I made a good choice in that I said, “Ben Franklin
                    probably would qualify, even though he never was President. He seemed to do a
                    pretty good job of everything he turned his hand to.” They always asked you in
                    those days why you were coming. I guess I did say something about public
                    service. But it was clear that this was more a psychological test than it was a
                    test of knowledge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came in when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Actually, they called me the last class in the fiscal yeaending in 1957. I
                    came in in July of '57.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You took the basic officers course, A-100. Could you give
                        me little description of the type of people in your group?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Because it was the end of the fiscal year, it caught a whole lot of
                    people. It was a larger class. There were about 40. Surprisingly enough for that
                    year (We're talking 1957.), there were about six women, which is probably a
                    higher average than certainly was in the Service in those days. I was impressed
                    that so many of these other candidates or other young officers had not majored
                    in political science or history, but had just gotten a general college degree.
                    Maybe that gave me a certain hope that, even though I didn't think I was an
                    expert in political science or foreign policy, maybe the Service would allow you
                    to learn a little bit as you went along. It was a good class of fellow officers.
                    I guess my age at that time, being 27, was kind of median, although there
                    weren't any over 31 because of the age limitation then. I think there were some
                    as young as 21.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how the class was taught?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We had some good people that they brought in to brief us. I guess you felt
                    kind of that here was a class that you really couldn't flunk. They simply were
                    trying to give you a little orientation. I thought, aside from the foreign
                    language requirement, that it was a decent preparation. It gave us a sense of
                    collegiality amongst us. The foreign languages turned out to be one of my, I
                    won't say bitter disappointments, but I discovered that I really wasn't very
                    good in foreign languages. I had a difficult time getting off probation, even
                    learning French. My MLAT must have been very low. They didn't test your MLAT in
                    those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. MLAT was your language aptitude.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It must have been down in the single digits, I guess. I learned later in
                    life that if you were up in 60-70, you were probably well endowed for learning
                    languages. So, the language was a problem. It turned out in my first two
                    assignments that it took me actually a year over in Europe to get off
                    probation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I had my problems, too. So, you started in July '57, about
                        simonths in Washington. Was it all training and language?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. Q: So, we're talking about the end of '57. Where did you go?</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>KRUSE: We took a railroad train to our first Foreign Service post. We went to
                    Toronto, Canada. In fact, we took the Black Diamond Express from Philadelphia,
                    where our parents saw us off like we were going on a steam ship. In the dark of
                    night we left because it travels all night. You wake up and you're in Canada. We
                    had a six month old baby. We had two berths up and down. But we did have three
                    human beings, inconveniently. My dear wife had the baby and professed the next
                    morning as I awoke from a fairly decent night that she had not slept too much
                    because the baby had been all over the place. I don't know what you could call
                    that. Her first sacrifice for the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Only one of many. You were in Toronto when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: From '57 to '60.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I was the administrative officer. In fact, I tried hard to stay the admin.
                    officer all the three years because the only alternative was the visa mill,
                    which is essentially what Toronto was in those days. Out of the 20 or so
                    officers, I would say 15, were doing visa or consular work. All of my
                    predecessors had been rotated out of the admin. to consular at a certain point.
                    Having observed that visa mill, I thought to myself, “You know, this is not a
                    bad job up here as admin. officer. Let's just see if we can't stay there.” So, I
                    spent my three years doing admin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Consul General?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We started with Ivan White, who eventually became quite a senior officer
                    as the Deputy Assistant Secretary for EUR in the late '50s. I'm not sure if he
                    did get an embassy, but he got his own post, whether it was a consulate or just
                    what. He was favorably looked upon by the Washington establishment because
                    Livingston Merchant was the ambassador in Canada and when he left Canada took
                    Ivan out and back to be his deputy in EUR. So, that was my first consul general.
                    He was a good boss for younger officers. He paid some attention to us, gave us
                    some good advice.</p>
                <p>He was replaced by Bob Memminger, who was a different kind of officer, mostly a
                    consular officer, kind of a southern, laid back fellow, who was pleasant to work
                    for, but a totally different kind from Ivan, who was a political officer.
                    Memminger was very helpful to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work were you doing? You say admin., but what
                        doethat mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>KRUSE: It was everything combined, the GSO, the security. I was it. We had three
                    Canadian FSNs working in the section with me. But I was the officer for signing
                    everything. The only thing that, I think, may be remembered 40 years later is
                    that we put air conditioning in the building in Toronto. This apparently took a
                    great revolution in Washington's thinking that any place in Canada would need
                    air conditioning. They kind of think you can keep that winter air all year long
                    without recognizing that it's a pretty warm summer. So, we managed to install
                    air conditioning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for what relations were like with
                        Canada athat time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. I guess this was my interest and I could do it kind of on the side.
                    They sent me out to speak at a couple of Rotary Clubs. There were Canadian
                    elections. In fact, it was rather exciting if you can think of U.S.-Canadian
                    relations as ever being exciting, at least from the American standpoint. Every
                    day it's exciting for Canadians, but very seldom is it for Americans, it seems.
                    This was the time that John Diefenbaker was Prime Minister, who kind of made it
                    his forte to put the jab in the Americans when he could. He had won a landslide
                    victory. So, it was something that Washington became interested in. How are you
                    going to deal with John Diefenbaker? Basically, that's what the consul general
                    said: “Give me your impressions?” So, I wrote him some things. He seemed to
                    think they were well-done. I guess he put some good words for me in Washington.
                    I think my next assignment was really attributable to his reporting favorably on
                    my progress.</p>
                <p>Q: What did Diefenbaker think? What was our thinking at that time, that you were
                    getting sort of internally, talking to your fellow officers and all, about this
                    nationalistic anti-American stance? How did we react?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: As you could imagine, we expected loyalty of allies in those days. It was
                    the heart of the Cold War and we didn't like some of the Canadian rhetoric. We
                    understood that the Canadians may have some gripes about our foreign policy and
                    our actions, but when it came to defense and security arrangements, we thought
                    that allies should be allies and it was exactly on nuclear issues that we had
                    our biggest problems. Walton Butterworth was the ambassador at that particular
                    time. It became publicly known that he was carrying critical messages to
                    Diefenbaker about American unhappiness. The Diefenbaker-Kennedy relationship was
                    not a happy one at all. So, I would say those were not easy years, not that
                    later years with Trudeau were that easy as well. I think it's necessary for
                    Canadian leaders at some point to show their own electorate that they're
                    standing up to the Americans. But when it came to these defense issues, we
                    really thought that the Canadians and Diefenbaker were unnecessarily tough on
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about in Toronto, was this an Ottawa-Ontario
                        manifestation,too, or was this more from elsewhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I always think Ontario has the quintessential Canadian attitude toward us
                    because they think of themselves as one of the reasons that Canada is separate.
                    If you try to define a Canadian, it's not often easy to do that as an American.
                    The Ontario situation is usually where there is perhaps the most intellectual
                    argumentation against American foreign policy. I'll never forget seeing the
                    Canadian protestors outside the consulate. I don't know what in particular the
                    issue was, but one day the first fellow came with the sign “Dull.” The second
                    guy came with a sign that said, “Duller.” The third one said, “Dulles.” That was
                    a fairly good imagination for a Canadian to come up with that, not that
                    Canadians don't have good imaginations. But they tend not to be too
                    demonstrative. They don't like to dramatize their problems with us because in
                    the long run, they recognize that the ties are too close. Of course, in Ontario,
                    Diefenbaker won very handsomely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1960.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Off to Europe for my first European assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We went to the little country of Luxembourg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Luxembourg from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '60 to '62. KRUSE: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Luxembourg?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Having done my administrative swing, they gave me the Economic/Commercial
                    office. This was a very small embassy in those days. We had an ambassador and a
                    DCM and another agency type. Then we had an admin. officer, a consular officer.
                    I don't think we even had more than that one consular officer. So, we're talking
                    about something like five American officers. This was the start of the Kennedy
                    era. Within a few months of my arrival (We came in the summer of '60.), we knew
                    Kennedy had won the election and we expected a “New Frontier” ambassador, as we
                    got in early 1961. He was a very charming and serious-minded man named James
                    Wine. His claim to fame with the Kennedy troupe was that he put on that meeting
                    in Dallas, where Kennedy faced the Protestant ministers.</p>
                <p>Q: Kennedy being a Catholic. At that time, it was considered that the Baptists
                    and others in the south would never vote for him. Wine was able to arrange a
                    meeting with 50 religious ministers and answer their questions. It helped
                    diffuse the issue.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It did lay it to rest. I don't know how many votes it got, but it
                    certainly laid to rest the public issue. As a result, Jim Wine came out to be
                    the ambassador. I must say, he turned out to be a good ambassador, certainly in
                    wanting to make use of me. He had some problems with the DCM. I have to say, I
                    think it was the DCM's fault. So, I got a little bit in the middle there between
                    the ambassador and DCM. But the ambassador wanted to use me whenever he went to
                    the Foreign Ministry. We negotiated a treaty of friendship and commerce with the
                    Luxembourgers, which may sound like walking through an open door, but we never
                    had one before. I got experience in doing negotiations.</p>
                <p>Q: Anything like that gets very technical and time consuming. To get a feel for
                    this, because I think relations at an embassy are always important- I take it
                    our DCM was a professional career Foreign Service officer?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: He had had previous career assignments, but I think, to be honest, his
                    claim to fame was some very good family connections. He was, as I learned later,
                    not held in great regard by most of his colleagues in the Foreign Service. In
                    fact, there were those who said that he shouldn't have been sent to be a DCM. He
                    had some problems in previous posts. I think probably providence was keeping me
                    in its favor here because he could have done me a lot of damage. I don't think
                    he felt very good about my role there. But again, the ambassador was able to, in
                    effect, make Washington understand that what I was doing was what the ambassador
                    wanted to do. I did my best to keep the DCM informed. That was probably the most
                    tricky interoffice relations I ever had.</p>
                <p>Q: This is one that occurs again and again of particularly a relatively junior
                    officer being picked by an ambassador and sort of bypassing the system, maybe
                    for perfectly good reasons. Resentments had be built up and the junior officer
                    is sort of hostage to fortune. There's not a hell of a lot you can do.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right. You're the guy in the middle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you describe Luxembourg in the early '60s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I'm not sure it's changed all that much, except it's probably gotten a
                    little wealthier. They often say it's like the mouse that roared, that although
                    in the case of the Luxembourgers, they didn't get help from the United States
                    because of being difficult, but basically had an almost embarrassing love for
                    the United States. This was only 12 or 15 years after World War II. Although it
                    may sound like a lot of years Luxembourgers still remembered and appreciated
                    what America did in coming back and liberating the continent, they acted as
                    though we came only to save Luxembourg. There is an American military cemetery
                    in Luxembourg where General Patton is buried. That became a virtual shrine to
                    venerate the American effort to liberate Europe. They were not embarrassed at
                    being absolutely grateful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were ceremonies at Bastogne?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: The Belgians, of course, had their effort. Bastogne is just across the
                    border. But that whole Battle of the Bulge did encompass the northern part of
                    Luxembourg and the eastern part of Belgium. I would go up to that area 15 years
                    later and the foxholes were still there. You could run across a grenade if you
                    were unlucky or not careful. In fact, Luxembourg would have escaped almost any
                    damage from the war because in our initial invasion, we swept right through
                    Luxembourg and the Germans retreated. But this, as you know, December offensive
                    in 1944 brought the Germans back in. Lots of bombardment, lots of fighting going
                    on in northern Luxembourg. Luxembourg City escaped it. One of the great
                    institutions in Luxembourg in my days was the American-Luxembourg Society. They
                    got very close to the embassy. They were very kind to us all. We certainly had
                    many good dinners and banquets. Luxembourg wine flowed.</p>
                <p>Q: Were there any stories still circulating about Perle Mesta, who had been
                    Truman's ambassador? A very good musical was made called “Call Me Madame.”</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>KRUSE: That was all well-known. Of course, they didn't understand why it would
                    have been funny that they had such an important person come. There were jokes
                    that never ended. They told one, for example, that a French general had just
                    come back from Indochina and was talking about how difficult it was out there
                    fighting the guerrillas. This took place at the dinner table of Mrs. Mesta at
                    the embassy. She listened very carefully. She was quite surprised to hear all
                    this and said, “You know, that is really just terrible, mon general. I'm going
                    to report that to Harry tomorrow.” As though this might be the first time Harry
                    would have heard about it. Of course, Harry was Harry Truman. The first time
                    that she left the post, she thought it was perfectly appropriate if her brother
                    could just take charge while she was gone. She found it a little difficult to
                    accept Washington's view that that really wasn't possible. She did do a good
                    representation job for Americans in those days.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, she helped put Luxembourg onto the American map. It probably would have
                    stayed with Liechtenstein if Perle Mesta hadn't gone there.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It's a tiny country of 300,000 people. One ward in Chicago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for NATO while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Just a little. The Luxembourgers' entire military, the size of about 500
                    men, was totally committed to NATO and would join up and had exercises with
                    American troops in Germany. Their duty would be to just get enveloped into an
                    American outfit and assume their duties. So, there was just the beginning of a
                    NATO connection. What was even closer to us in those days was the European
                    economic communities. The European Iron Steel Community had its first
                    headquarters in Luxembourg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As economic officer, you must have been up to your neck in
                        that,weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We didn't do so much with the European communities. Remember, we had a
                    separate mission to the European Community also. What I was doing was trying to
                    help American businesses come into Luxembourg. The Luxembourgers were actively
                    recruiting American companies like Dupont and Monsanto. That was kind of fun.
                    The idea of being good for Americans to get inside the Common Market with their
                    production facilities so they would escape any kind of an external tariff. But
                    you see, the big business of Luxembourg then and, I think, even still today, is
                    iron and steel. That's the one industry that kept them alive for decades.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about banking?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>KRUSE: That was just beginning. As I suspect, that would probablaccount for a lot
                    of their prosperity today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems getting data, information and
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, they were helpful. Iron and steel, china, and a certain amount of wine
                    and agricultural products. So, it wasn't a very diversified economy. The only
                    problem would be often that the government itself was slow in collecting data,
                    but they were very cooperative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling about the Luxembourger's relations
                        to thGermans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Certainly in front of us, they were very anti-German. They wanted it to be
                    very clearly understood that they were Francophile, although their language or
                    their patois was mostly Germanic. (You had these kinds of “Bonjour, mein Herr”
                    combinations of French and German that they put together.) Even though this
                    patois was mostly German, they were always with the French against the Germans.
                    Of course, culturally and linguistically, they tried to stress as much as
                    possible the French side. The interesting thing was, of course, that they had
                    both French and German as official languages. I think they realized that they
                    had to get along. They were, as were the other Benelux countries, very loyal to
                    the concept of the Common Market. English became basically a third language.
                    Luxembourgers were very, very good at learning languages.</p>
                <p>Q: What about relations with Belgium?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Of course, they had these jokes about the Belgians, that to be a Belgian
                    is not a nationality, it's a profession. They see in Belgians an unerring
                    instinct for money. I think a little bit of that might be kind of projection.
                    Luxembourgers weren't too bad at it either. They recognized that they were tied
                    in the economic union with the Belgians. Belgian money was legal tender in
                    Luxembourg. They just recognized it was a fact of life. They had to get along
                    with the Belgians. Sort of like the Canadians and us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about France under de Gaulle at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I would say, officially, the Luxembourg government would be a little
                    nervous about too much anti-Americanism from de Gaulle because Luxembourgers
                    would never forget the fact that the most important Western power was the United
                    States. They would not like to have seen the United States react in a huff and
                    leave Europe or retreat into isolationism. That was always a fear that the
                    Luxembourgers had. I think there was a certain satisfaction that de Gaulle stood
                    for French pride. But I think they did feel that he went too far, particularly
                    when our troops had to leave France, which would be a later chapter in my life.
                    I wound up in France to help work on that issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you leave Luxembourg?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We left in the fall of '62.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the Cuban Missile Crisis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Actually, it happened just when I got back to Washington. I was assigned
                    to work for Alex Johnson, who was then the Deputy Under Secretary. The very
                    first issue that the office faced was this Cuban Missile Crisis when I got in
                    the job in October of '62.</p>
                <p>Q: You came back and were staff assistant to Alexis Johnson. Was he number
                    two?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, he was under Ball.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Number three.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: His designation was G, Deputy Under Secretary for PoliticaAffairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '62 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I stayed two years. I left in early '65, so it was just little more than
                    two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come to the Missile Crisis in a minute. What was
                        youjob? Staff assistants do different things.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. Alex Johnson, I think, had a very formal view, though not
                    unpleasant. His idea was that I was there to get the paper passed to him and
                    serve basically an office function, not a substantive function. I think he was
                    quite right. Not that I couldn't have learned things, I'm certain, but I
                    accepted the fact that myself and the senior assistant were basically there to
                    keep his paper flowing. In my case, I rarely sat in on the substantive meetings
                    that he held with colleagues from other departments or other bureaus. But it was
                    in many, many ways a great education for me because I was reading global
                    traffic, very sensitive stuff, as well as listening in on phone calls, as he
                    asked me to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you listened in on phone calls, what was your
                        role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Simply to take notes. Rarely would he call us back and check on something.
                    But it was mostly to keep us informed of what he was doing. Alex Johnson was a
                    superb officer, almost indefatigable. At eight o'clock at night, he was as on
                    the ball as he would have been at eight in the morning. He never tired. He
                    needed reminding sometimes to keep his staff posted on what he was doing. He
                    tended to think that we'd just get it by osmosis. I remember, I was in the job
                    about two weeks before I met him. He was in the middle of this Cuban crisis. At
                    that point, he couldn't even say what the crisis was. But everybody and my
                    predecessor, who was still in the first week of overlap, would say, “We all
                    figure it's got something to do with Cuba, but we don't know anything about it.”
                    Alex Johnson was a member of the famous Ex-Com, which was meeting with the
                    President regularly. But he could not, of course, brief us on that. So, I
                    learned about the crisis and met him sometime soon after the crisis had become
                    public.</p>
                <p>Q: As time went on, what was the role of Johnson's office, Deputy Under Secretary
                    for Political Affairs? Each administration has its own dynamics. What were the
                    dynamics there?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: His job was very much the interagency coordination with CIA, with DOD,
                    with the other foreign policy establishments. We had a staff unit, G/PM, which
                    was the predecessor to the PM (Political/Military) bureau. That was run by Jeff
                    Kitchen, which had a whole group of, as we called them, the prima donnas, or the
                    experts on various things from nuclear energy to nuclear weapons to DOD budgets.
                    Actually, the Secretary, Dean Rusk, depended on Johnson to do the day to day
                    coordinating with these other agencies. So, we'd see, often, Dick Helms and
                    others who would be coming in from the Agency and others like Bill Bundy from
                    DOD.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that you or your office would be tasked with
                        makinsure that EUR and EA did what they were supposed to do or
                        coordinated?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, we did. There would be times if they didn't act or coordinate that we
                    would either go to S/S, the Secretariat, and tell S/S, “Look, the boss has asked
                    various things.” So, we would often use S/S to be the ones to remind the bureaus
                    of what their responsibilities were. At my level, we'd be dealing with the staff
                    assistant in EUR. We'd very easily be able to talk about what he would like to
                    do or even what he had done. It was always helpful for the bureaus to know what
                    the principals were up to.</p>
                <p>Q: So, in many ways, the staff assistants represented a sort of a supporting but
                    non-egotistical thing of saying, “Look, we've got to get this. My guy is a
                    little bit ticked off at that. Can you get your guy to do this thing?” Was this
                    kind of a role?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's what Alex Johnson wanted. The other principal, George Ball, I
                    think, had some people with him that were kind of egos in their own right.
                    Perhaps he would give a task to them on a certain question. The whole business
                    of appointing ambassadors and senior level appointments was handled out of
                    George Ball's office and the Under Secretary. So, one of his staffers (George
                    Springsteen) was, in fact, his alter ego. In that sense, basically, the
                    principal had delegated authority. I was not delegated any particular authority.
                    It was mostly just to keep paper flowing.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you have any feel for, I won't say the “ranking,” but the esteem that the
                    various bureaus had? How would you rank them? A staff assistant sort of picks by
                    osmosis.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It's kind of a reflection, although it's a little subjective, depending on
                    your boss. In the case of Alex Johnson, he was an East Asia person. In fact, he
                    confessed to us that he had only been in Europe once in his life. So, there,
                    clearly would be a man who would see the Asian side of things as being very
                    important. But, yes, as far as bureaus themselves, reputation—clearly FE, (now
                    EAP), was considered a solid one with career Chinese and the Japanese language
                    officers. These were solid countries whether they were problems or not. Of
                    course, in the Department as a whole, Europe continued to be considered the most
                    important bureau, the “primus inter pares”. ARA and AF would be down the line.
                    This was the days of Soapy Williams when African countries were just becoming
                    independent states. Everybody was hoping that this would lead to better things
                    for African peoples. You could almost say there was a certain reverse
                    compensation going on for AF to make up to them. ARA was, I suppose, considered
                    the weakest.</p>
                <p>Q: With Soapy Williams, in many ways, he was sort of a one of a kind character in
                    that, unlike other bureaus, he personified this African centric focus that he
                    had. Because of his political ties (He had been governor of Michigan and a
                    strong supporter of Kennedy.), it gave Africa an extra clout. What was the
                    impression of the African bureau as far as you were dealing, and Soapy
                    Williams?</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>KRUSE: You really go back to World War II, don't you, with President Roosevelt
                    assuming that this would be the end of all colonization. By and large, we worked
                    hard to do that. We had troubles with the French in Algeria, as you know. The
                    Brits were slow in some ways to give up theirs. Of course, there was a
                    continuing problem with the Portuguese that lasted on into the '70s. But, I
                    think, there was that feeling that this is one of the great outcomes of World
                    War II, that we will now end colonialism and all its attendant evils. So, Soapy
                    Williams, if he cried “Hey, you're not moving this fast enough,” I think he'd
                    get a lot of attention, especially in the White House.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying that you didn't think the Black Caucus
                        existed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, we were having our civil rights movement in our own country. I think
                    the Black Caucus was significant for black members of Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what the Black Caucus was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Back in those days, I'm not sure they even had a caucus. You had
                    individual black people like Adam Clayton Powell of New York. But they were not
                    in an organized way. What I'm saying is that our attitude toward African
                    countries was very much based on “Let's get away from colonialism, let's have
                    one country, one vote. We ought to have democracy.” I think that's why Soapy
                    Williams got support. There was a feeling of let's do what we can to reverse
                    what's been done to Africans.</p>
                <p>Q: What about George Ball? Sometimes if you're working for number three as a
                    staff assistant, you pick up vibes of your guy against their guy or something
                    like that. What was your impression of Ball and Johnson and Rusk and how they
                    worked together?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: All three worked pretty well together, I thought, from all I saw. They
                    played cards together, although it was more golf with Ball and Johnson on
                    Saturday. There was a collegiality there. My boss, Alex Johnson, had known Dean
                    Rusk since World War II and from Rusk's earlier stint in the Department.
                    Harriman was another Under Secretary. He was a bit apart. He had his political
                    connections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Far East Asia.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>KRUSE: He got involved in the Near East often also because of political
                    connections. But I had great respect for him. Despite the fact that this team
                    (Johnson, Ball, Rusk, and even Harriman) and all the foreign policy
                    establishment was moving fast into the great crisis of Vietnam, by the time I
                    left in 1965 that had not really overwhelmed the country yet. I left in early
                    '65. Johnson himself was off to be the deputy ambassador in Vietnam. As he left,
                    he said that he didn't consider this a career enhancing assignment. I thought
                    that Dean Rusk was a tragic figure. I think he was an honorable, brilliant man
                    who was wrong in some of his perceptions. He apparently felt that the Chinese
                    and the North Vietnamese could work together and that, in fact, they represented
                    a combined communist force, whereas I've learned subsequently that most people
                    who knew anything about Vietnam know that you don't have Vietnamese and Chinese
                    getting along very well together. I think he was a wonderful human being, Rusk,
                    and Ball, too. Ball, of course, was the in-house devil's advocate against
                    Vietnam. I didn't have any background in Southeast Asia history or politics, but
                    I remember saying to a colleague as our Vietnam involvement accelerated that I
                    couldn't believe that Vietnam was worth 500,000 American troops.</p>
                <p>Q: You did have with Johnson and Rusk a heavy emphasis on the Far East, whereas
                    Ball was Mr. Europe and Mr. European Integration Personified.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any of that feeling, that something would
                        happen anboth Rusk and Johnson would turn to Ball and say, “You take care of
                        it?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Ball had Europe, even if it was messy things. In those days, Cyprus had
                    just become part of the European Bureau. That was George Ball's problem. Of
                    course, handling de Gaulle was George Ball's issue, and all of the other things
                    in Europe. I had a deep respect for George Ball. Frankly, his views on the
                    Middle East, even though they were not ascendent in his time, were much more in
                    our interest than our policy has been most of the time.</p>
                <p>Q: What was the general feeling when the Cuban Missile Crisis became known? At
                    one point, there was about a week there where everybody was sort of sitting and
                    waiting for something. We thought World War III might start.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>KRUSE: We staffers were all in the vacuum of not knowing any of this. Alex knew
                    it, but didn't pass it on. I remember when that week finally broke and, in
                    effect, Khrushchev's message indicated that, as Dean Rusk said, “the other side
                    blinked,” I was (It was a Sunday.) up in Philadelphia and I heard about it on
                    the radio. It looked as though the Soviets were taking the missiles out. But the
                    texts of all the messages that had gone back and forth, of course, I knew
                    nothing about until much, much later. I guess for all of those who were in the
                    know, you're exactly right. They started the week without knowing where this one
                    was going to wind up. The one diplomatic principle I learned from the Cuba
                    crisis was to take the positive points from the adversary's message and ignore
                    the unfavorable portions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working for Johnson when Kennedy was
                        assassinated. Hodid that hit your office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It was just absolute shock. I remember particularly that it becomes a
                    function of the State Department to notify and do certain things at the time of
                    a presidential succession. George Ball was Acting Secretary because Dean Rusk
                    was out in Asia. He sent out the flash message. It started, “It is my painful
                    duty to inform you that President John F. Kennedy died.” It was a colossal blow.
                    I have to say that, looking back on my own, those two years of Kennedy were the
                    most exciting of all my years in Washington, partly because we were still coming
                    out of the second world war, we were establishing our dominance with our
                    military and with other things, and yet Kennedy was trying to project an image
                    of an America that wanted the best for the whole world. His American University
                    speech on “Making the world safe for diversity” had words I never forgot. As a
                    young officer, they were thrilling times. We may have all gotten caught up in a
                    certain “Camelot” euphoria, but those years with Kennedy were fun. I've often
                    thought that Kennedy, maybe, in terms of his place in history, benefitted from
                    not being on for the full tour given what happened in Vietnam thereafter.</p>
                <p>Q: One always thinks of Lincoln. Lincoln did not have to face the forfax of
                    Reconstruction. Did you get any feel for Middle Eastern affairs during this
                    time?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Not very much at all. The first thing I remember reading was a dissent
                    piece written by Ed Djerejian. I knew Ed very well. We were junior officers
                    together. He had finished his Arabic training. I guess. I guess it was the
                    Kissinger era when the dissent channel was established. Ed's message was that,
                    “We're not going to solve the Middle East problems until we do something about
                    the Palestinians.” That was just something that I had never focused on. That
                    would have been in the early '70s when I was back in a different job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had de Gaulle made his move to get France out of
                        NATO?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>KRUSE: No, it was my next assignment after I left Johnson in the spring of '65. I
                    went to Paris to be the deputy POLAD (political advisor) at the U.S. European
                    Command in suburban Paris.</p>
                <p>Q: Still sticking to the '62 to '65 period when you were with Johnson, did you
                    get any feel for relations with France and particularly with de Gaulle at that
                    time?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, partly because of the traffic that we got to read. I think it's
                    characterized by Lyndon Johnson's public comment. He said, “Whenever de Gaulle
                    gets on the pitcher's mound, I step out of the batter's box.” That clearly was
                    what we were doing. We chose not to go to the mat with de Gaulle on our
                    differences. We were not happy at his actions, but I think, as I then discovered
                    in my next assignment in Paris, Ambassador Chip Bohlen felt strongly that, “What
                    are you going to do? Are you going to fight France to keep our forces in here?”
                    However much we tried to get our allies and others to convince de Gaulle and
                    maybe isolate de Gaulle (and indeed he was isolated in the Alliance), we were
                    not going to go to war. Congressman Mendel Rivers of South Carolina, the
                    Chairman of the House Arms Services Committee, expressed American anger by
                    saying something to the effect that, “Okay, if he's going to force our troops
                    out, we're going to take the graves of American troops who died there for
                    France. We'll show him.” But of course in the long run we had to accommodate
                    Gaullist thinking.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that was proposed, not seriously.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, the Congressman wasn't serious but he was mad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get anything about Canadian-American relations
                        while you were there? This is the time when Diefenbaker was riding high.
                        Kennedy had had a meeting with Diefenbaker and found him impossible.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: There was even that leak in the Canadian papers about Kennedsaying, “When
                    is that bastard coming” or something like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Actually, I think it was Kennedy who claimed, “I didn't
                        writ'bastard' because I didn't know he was one at that point.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>KRUSE: This was not an easy relationship. Diefenbaker was a prickly guy. I think
                    it was a total difference in character. Here is the glamourous young President
                    and here was the kind of crusty old Canadian from the mid west provinces in
                    Canada. I suppose, to be honest with you, I haven't thought back to why
                    Diefenbaker was the way he was, except there is that strain not of
                    anti-Americanism, but it's that standing off from America. There is that fear
                    that some Canadians have that, if they go along with the Americans too much,
                    they're all going to wind up being Americans some day.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, they have a real problem. I mean, they still have it. They keep having
                    editorials that I follow with a certain amount of amused interest, where they
                    try to figure out what is a Canadian? I have never really seen it, except for
                    the fact that they're not Americans.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: As the French Canadians say in Quebec, “We're the only ones that have no
                    problem telling you how we're different. We don't speak like those Americans.”
                    But for the English-speaking Canadians, it is difficult. It was Trudeau, who
                    said something like, “Living next to the United States is like sleeping next to
                    an elephant. Even if it doesn't want to hurt you, you can't be sure that it will
                    not.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1965, you went to France. You were a political
                        militaradvisor to NATO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Actually to the U.S. Commander in Chief in Europe—EUCOM, awe call it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '65 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I stayed in Paris and moved down to the embassy to take a Pol-Mil job in
                    the fall of '66 and then stayed on in Paris essentially doing pretty much the
                    same thing, although it's a little different down at the embassy where you are
                    really back to a State Department operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk first about the '65 to '66 period and EUCOM.
                        Who wathe commanding officer at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: General Lemnitzer was the overall Supreme Allied Commander. At his EUCOM
                    headquarters, the American-only command in St. Germain-en-Laye, he had a deputy
                    who was a four star Air Force general, Jake Smart. On a day to day basis, we
                    worked with Smart.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did this command fit into the overall...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>KRUSE: EUCOM was the overall joint command that oversaw our Army, Navy, and Air
                    Force in Europe. It is currently in Stuttgart, as all of our forces moved out of
                    France in 1966. In that sense, it comes right from the JCS to EUCOM and then out
                    to these subordinate service commands. It was at this time in my career, after
                    my stint with Alex Johnson, which got me very much into political-military
                    subjects. This was a desirable assignment for me to get out to Paris and to be
                    able to continue to work on what was essentially NATO-related issues. EUCOM was
                    U.S.-only forces. As you know, there are times when we use our forces in Europe
                    not to do NATO things, but to perform unilateral tasks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would be an example of a non-NATO thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: A recent example was when our forces assigned to the Sixth Fleet attacked
                    Qadhafi, that was clearly an American-only thing—not under NATO
                    authorization.</p>
                <p>Q: As the reaction to the Czech invasion by the Soviets and their allies, was
                    there any sort of cranking up or was it just a feeling that this was something
                    we couldn't do anything about and we just watched to make sure that something
                    else wouldn't happen?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: My recollections are that the NATO military asked for guidance, what to
                    do. I think NATO authorized some minor steps, maybe more intelligence
                    information collection and moderate increase in readiness, but certainly no
                    alerting. Again, the Alliance looked to the United States for what lead we were
                    going to give. It wasn't too long before it was clear that the United States was
                    not going to engage militarily. It was not a close call. The Alliance did not
                    want to go to war with the Soviets over Czechoslovakia however sympathetic
                    allied countries were to the Czechs.</p>
                <p>Q: At that time when you were dealing with NATO, what was the general feeling
                    about Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Romania, East Germany? Where would they
                    go?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: There was a question as to how loyal their forces would be if there was to
                    be a real encounter between the Warsaw Pact and NATO, how much real fighting
                    we'd encounter from some of the Warsaw Pact nations. But given the examples of
                    East Germany and then Hungary being crushed earlier by the Soviets, most people
                    in the Alliance were feeling that as long as the Soviets were calling the shots
                    the Warsaw Pact would follow their lead. It would not be possible to free the
                    Czechs from the Soviet Empire.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You weren't expecting a dissolution of this Alliance?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>KRUSE: No. I think we still were pretty much of the feeling that the Europeans
                    had come to terms with communism in the East and that was probably the way it
                    was going to stay. Subsequent to the fall of the Soviet Empire, even West
                    Germans told me that when they finally got to East Germany for the first time,
                    they were appalled at just the mediocrity of everything, if not worse. They
                    said, “We thought we knew our brethren. We thought we knew East Germany. We were
                    just abysmally wrong in knowing how bad it was.”</p>
                <p>Q: Did you ever find yourself while you were with the Secretary General's office
                    having a problem wearing the NATO hat rather than the American hat?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: We tried hard to wear the NATO hat. Jokingly, you were called “the
                    American spy.” This has been typically a job that Americans handled. There would
                    always be a person in the private office of the Secretary General. George Vest
                    and other officers had been assigned to previous Secretaries General. I guess
                    you do your best to serve the Secretary General. He knows that you're a career
                    Foreign Service officer. He knows that the American must write an efficiency
                    report on you. He knows you've got to show that you're doing things the
                    Americans want. Everybody that works at NATO is seconded, if you will. There
                    isn't any NATO nationality. Everybody has their national biases. But, sure,
                    being the American and being in a strategic office, you do try to talk a more
                    NATO line and understand the European situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the Norwegians and Danes within the NATO
                        context?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Not very strong militarily. We were always battling the Danes to keep
                    their standards and equipment up. The Norwegians were maybe not quite so bad.
                    The rhetoric was that they were strong allies. It's just that they didn't have
                    much to contribute militarily. They had their particular views on nuclear
                    weapons. Norway wouldn't allow nuclear weapons on their soil. That made them a
                    little bit of a second class citizen. After all, the Alliance was based on
                    nuclear deterrence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about those two foreign friends, Greece and
                        Turkey?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, they both liked NATO better than each other, that's for sure. There
                    was a lot of question about whether they should ever have been allowed to come
                    in—their aversion to democratic ideals. The Greeks have their great democratic
                    traditions but during those years—the '60s—Greece was a military
                    dictatorship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this thing, the colonels were in the whole time you
                        werthere.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. I often cite the examples, that both in Portugal, where a
                    dictatorship was in force, and in Greece with the colonels, there was no doubt
                    that the pressures of being within the Alliance helped eventually to destroy
                    these dictatorial regimes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the attitude towards the Greeks and the Turks
                        when yowere there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That they contributed to extraneous problems. I came to see that more in
                    my later job when I was in Naples because we clearly could not conduct a regime
                    of sensible exercises in the Aegean because of the Greek and Turkish views of
                    what you can do there. So, it was a nuisance to us. More than a nuisance,
                    militarily, it certainly meant we couldn't do things that we wanted to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular tensions at that time or were
                        sort othe Turks and the Greeks treated with a certain (inaudible)?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: The Turks were admired for their tough military. They contributed a lot of
                    forces. Of course, it was essentially to protect their own country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They bordered the Soviet Union.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. The Greeks were not as formidable a fighting force.</p>
                <p>Q: I don't think Cyprus did. It blew up in July of '74. The colonels came in in
                    April of '67 and kept the lid on for that period of time. I was thinking that
                    this might be a good place to call a halt for today. We've covered an awful lot
                    of your NATO business at this point. We've covered really from '68 to '70 when
                    you were assistant to the Secretary General. We'll pick up when you moved over
                    from '70 to '73 at the U.S. Mission to NATO and talk about the differences there
                    in your job and perspective and all that.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Today is April 10, 1997. Let's go into NATO. You were there fro'70 to '73. What
                    was your job?</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I was involved in this initiative that President Nixon took to get NATO
                    involved in the “challenges of modern society.” These would be environmental
                    issues, quality of life issues. It had high White House support because
                    President Nixon felt that we had to keep NATO active. It was kind of a strange
                    idea to many people that NATO, which was seen as a mostly political and military
                    organization, would get involved in what you might say were softer issues,
                    issues maybe most people thought would be more for OECD or some economic
                    organization. At this time, there was no UN body dealing with the environment to
                    speak of. So, I was asked to take the job of being the action officer in the
                    U.S. delegation to NATO for this Committee on the Challenges of Modern Society
                    (CCMS).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was this, in Brussels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: In Brussels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were you received when you appeared with this new
                        portfolio?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I was received with some skepticism even within the U.S. delegation
                    because there were lots of traditional people who wondered what in the world
                    NATO was getting involved in. The other delegations probably had even more
                    questions about what the U.S. was up to. But frankly, it did make a certain
                    amount of sense, the way we did the projects. Our first representative to the
                    plenary sessions of the committee Pat Moynihan, who was, of course, right in the
                    White House at that time serving for Nixon. Continuing after Moynihan, the next
                    several chief delegates were all very high level appointees such as Russell
                    Train, the chairman of the Council on Environmental Quality. So, it was clear
                    with that kind of high-powered delegation head that the U.S. wanted to make this
                    thing work. So, we got into projects like oil spills, air pollution, road
                    safety, disaster assistance. The idea would be to take advantage of NATO's
                    ability to do things and to have a certain amount of technological know-how and,
                    instead of burdening the NATO bureaucracy with a whole new staff, that most of
                    the work would be done by individual nations. We called it a pilot project kind
                    of organization where a nation or several nations would agree to be the pilot
                    project leader and they would do most of the research and the work back in the
                    home countries and then bring their results together for meetings with other
                    NATO countries. But it would all be done with a very minimum of additions to the
                    NATO staff. In fact, I suppose we had only one CCM(Committee on Challenges of
                    Modern Society) officer in the NATO staff for the first 10 years.</p>
                <p>Q: Some 20 years later, seeing the absolute disaster that the Soviet army and its
                    satellites, the effect that they had on the environment where they were...
                    Anywhere where they were, there were sort of vast cesspools of pollution from
                    the motor pools on. Did this have a military component in it at that time?</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Not a whole lot actually because these were conceived as projects that
                    were good for the entire society and we would have mostly civilian experts
                    working on it. But there was no exclusion of the military of certain countries.
                    In a small country like Portugal, most of the technological expertise was found
                    in the military. So, they would sometimes send to certain projects (air
                    pollution or water pollution) military people. But by and large, the larger
                    countries like Germany and France and England and Italy had civilians working on
                    these projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was our army looking at the environment as it worked
                        around, thmotor pools and so on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. I'm not so sure it was a result of CCMS necessarily. At that time,
                    the French were getting very green. They had just become aware of the need to
                    start doing a lot more in terms of environmental protection. The Canadians, who
                    were always very strong on the environment, were probably our best supporter in
                    CCMS, thinking that this was a good thing for NATO to do. But other countries,
                    the British, for example, were not terribly interested in seeing NATO do some of
                    this business. But over the years, they became accustomed to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you go about your tasks?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Essentially, I got the instructions from Washington of what we were trying
                    to do and would prepare the agenda along with the Secretariat for these meetings
                    that we had every six months. Delegations came from capitals. There was always a
                    big effort to get high level people to match our high levels. Sometimes we were
                    dependent on our embassies in London and Paris to produce big name people. But
                    my job was very much a bureaucratic job. It was nothing to do with the research.
                    Our experts came to the meeting on their agenda. I didn't present their
                    business. The idea was that there would be action recommendations for the NATO
                    council to take on oil spills or air pollution. To a certain extent, it got
                    government awareness of many of these problems. For smaller countries, they got
                    the best of U.S. expertise. For example, in road safety, at that time, the
                    airbag was very new. Of course, for some countries, they saw it simply as
                    another economic issue. Can we afford to put airbags in our cars if the
                    Americans want to do it? But it certainly got a lot of attention, the idea of
                    airbags. There were a lot of other technological things. Back in those days
                    (It's hard to believe.), there were still little French deux chevaux cars
                    traveling around with not even safety glass. All these new improved safety
                    standards were a way for members of the Alliance to be aware of the way the U.S.
                    was going in these subjects. So, I think CCMS had a value.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, there's no doubt about it. This was a case of
                        realltreating NATO as something other than a military Alliance.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right. I would contend that, as we might have talked about last
                    time, one of the great values of NATO beyond its military capabilities was its
                    ability to get high level attention in Alliance countries on political issues,
                    whatever was going on. I always think of the arms control issues, with us
                    dealing with the Soviets in SALT and in START. We truly kept the Alliance
                    completely up to date on how these negotiations were going. There would have
                    been no other forum that we could have presented the kind of sensitive, highly
                    classified material than we could in NATO. While it was very much related to
                    defense and security, it had nothing to do with improving NATO's hardware as
                    much as it did in improving our allies' understanding of our political goals in
                    arms control.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were the Germans responding to the environmental
                        programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: They came along later. Once they got on board, they were pretty good. But
                    I think at the time CCMS started, the French were the best on the Continent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Greens became a big thing in Germany later on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's true. In terms of German cooperation with this committee, it was
                    good, but it came along a little slower than the French did. They may have had
                    the question of their federal system. On some of these issues, the Lander didn't
                    want the federal authorities to enforce standards.</p>
                <p>Q: Was there any effort that you know of to reach out to the Soviets and the
                    Soviet bloc and say, “We're trying to do something of this nature. Maybe it
                    would be a good idea if you did, too.”</p>
                <p>KRUSE: There was maybe a little bit of language in that direction. But you do
                    raise a good point in asking. We did have other countries that were not NATO
                    members joining us. This was in 1970 when it was quite a change to think that we
                    could work with neutrals. The Swedes came to some of our meetings. Of course, it
                    was as big a thing for the Swedes to get involved with NATO as it was the other
                    way around for us to have the Swedes. Eventually, we would have other non-NATO
                    countries coming to these pilot project meetings.</p>
                <p>As far as the East Bloc is concerned, we knew that many of the Eastern European
                    countries were interested in what we were doing, particularly air pollution and
                    water pollution. But they were not free to join. The Soviets, as long as it had
                    the NATO label, were not going to get involved in CCMS.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was your ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>KRUSE: We had several, starting with Harland Cleveland. Then we had Bob
                    Ellsworth, and the former Secretary of the Treasury, David Kennedy. The last one
                    when I left was Rumsfeld.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was there such a turnover in NATO ambassadors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Ellsworth was there at least two years, maybe three. Cleveland was
                    leaving. He had already been there quite a few years. I think the most unusual
                    appointment was David Kennedy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were saying Kennedy was really an economic man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. It was an unusual appointment as he was never personally associated
                    with military issues. I'm not sure what was the reason for that. But he stayed
                    by my recollection not much more than a year or a year and a half. Most
                    countries will send an ambassador for at least four years. We had the Belgian
                    ambassador, Henri de Staercke, who had been there almost since the start of the
                    Alliance. Some of these had tremendous continuity and wouldn't mind letting you
                    know that, too. The Dutch also had a very longstanding ambassador. They were all
                    high quality people. The Turks had Ambassador Burgi, who had been there for
                    decades. So, for other countries, it was very much a continuity job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your work, did you feel a little bit like the
                        stepchild,trying to raise your agenda items when there were other things
                        afoot?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I would usually in the staff meeting introduce CCMS items by saying, “The
                    White House wants to do this or that.” If they asked me who in the White House,
                    I would say, “Pat Moynihan.” So, that got you a fair amount of attention. But
                    there were usually a certain amount of quizzical looks as to what this CCMS
                    thing was, especially on the part of some of the uniformed military folks in the
                    mission. You would have to ask Henry Kissinger. I don't know that he ever has
                    revealed that in his memoirs, what was all behind this initiative. But it had
                    something to do with, here we are in the middle of Vietnam, the fear in Europe
                    that maybe we are really getting tired of NATO and maybe our attention was going
                    elsewhere. The idea of the “Year of Europe,” which was one of Henry's slogans.
                    All of this was meant to somehow show that the old dog of NATO was still up to
                    good new tricks. This, while half a million American troops were half-way around
                    the world in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the American military? This didn't have much
                        resonancwith them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>KRUSE: No. You know how the mission of NATO was organized. You actually have a
                    military office of fairly large size with uniformed military people dealing with
                    the weaponry and personnel and all the other things of NATO military
                    commitments. Then you have a political section, which does all the political
                    consultations. You had a Pol-Mil section, which was mostly having to do with
                    arms control. Then you had an economic section because there was an economic
                    committee in NATO. Then there was the usual admin. section, etc. But the defense
                    staff (We called it the third floor because that's where all the defense
                    uniformed people were.), had a lot of work. They went through these annual
                    exercises of the U.S. responding to NATO questionnaires about force commitments
                    and all that. So, it was a big, big job. Lots of subcommittees, lots of things
                    going on to keep the military busy. That was certainly still the guts of the
                    Alliance. The American commitment was obviously what made it all stick together.
                    So, I would not presume to say that, within the delegation, my CCMS activity was
                    really much of the work of the delegation, except when it came to these meetings
                    every six months when the gang from Washington came in and then everybody paid a
                    little more attention.</p>
                <p>Q: Where was your allegiance back in Washington? Was it to Pat Moynihan's office
                    or to an office in the State Department, both in fact and also in reality?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Moynihan had a small staff to work on this. In State, the NATO office, the
                    old EUR/RPM office, was where it was housed. They did put one of their officers
                    on this job. But I think it was about the same order of priority there as it was
                    out in the delegation. We bowed to the fact that this was a presidential
                    initiative. We weren't going to let it fail. We were going to work at it hard.
                    But 90% of the work of the office in RPM was something else. It was either
                    political or military. You asked me where the power was. It was throwing around
                    the name of the White House and Pat Moynihan and presidential initiative and
                    that kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular issues that you recall in this
                        durinthis three year period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Because of CCMS or elsewhere in the Alliance? There was an awful lot of
                    stuff going on in the Alliance because it was just the beginning of detente, the
                    whole idea of the Harmel report (the Belgian Foreign Minister) that NATO had to
                    be more than just defense, it was to be emphasize detente also. So, there was
                    really a lot of political activity keeping the delegation busy. In my case, we
                    got a little bit of publicity, when we put forth this Oil Spills Resolution,
                    which was to commit all NATO countries to cease deliberately spilling oil from
                    tankers into the open sea. A noble goal, but it had some economic consequences
                    which meant you had to build a different kind of tanker or you had to provide
                    different ways that you were going to clean out the tanks of an oil carrier.
                    Those were the kind of CCMS type things that kept us going. But in the Alliance
                    itself, clearly, it was a very busy time. This was the early '70s. I have a
                    feeling that the competition of the Cold War up until about this time, left us
                    wondering how the Soviets were really going to do. Was this experiment in
                    socialism going to improve the life of the Soviet citizen or was the Socialist
                    just not going to make it at all? It certainly had some appeal to many
                    Europeans. So, when we finally got into this engagement with them in detente,
                    negotiations on security cooperation, on the question of confidence building
                    measures and all the other things, many Western leaders were fearful that the
                    Soviets could beat us. Secretary General Brosio often expressed to me his
                    concern that the West, with its free democratic system and free expression of
                    public opinion, might not be tough enough to face down the Soviets in a time of
                    relaxing tensions. Militarily, the Soviets continued to grow stronger. But I
                    think this was beginning to be the other side of the hill for them and that the
                    West finally was getting to demonstrate the superiority of our way of life.
                    Although at that time, I don't think we felt that. I know that many in the
                    Alliance didn't want to have detente very much. They thought that to deal with
                    the Soviets, you just simply had to stay tough and either make them collapse or
                    let them collapse on their own. You had the French playing their separate game.
                    So, it was a time of a whole lot of important turning points, I think.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '73, you left NATO for where?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I came back to Washington to work in Canadian Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: From '73 to '76, for three years.</p>
                <p>Q: I've often heard people I've interviewed say that dealing with the Canadians
                    and perhaps dealing with the French is certainly as difficult as dealing with
                    the Soviets. Could you describe the Canadian Desk, where it was and how work was
                    divided? Then we'll talk about the issues.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Of course, to start with, there is kind of an anomalous thing about
                    Canadian Affairs. That is that we were dealing with them under the rubric of
                    European Affairs. That had a history all its own. Suffice to say that there were
                    those who felt that we ought to deal with Canadian Affairs more separately from
                    Europe because they really weren't European. I guess the Canadians were among
                    those who pushed that idea, that they deserved special attention. When I
                    started, the desk was relatively small. We only had a director, a deputy, and
                    two action officers. It grew in the next years because environmental issues
                    became very big and we had to have an officer solely doing environmental issues.
                    We continued to have someone devoted mostly to economic issues. We also had one
                    doing political/military affairs. Then we had a deputy. But a lot of other
                    issues came into play in the mid-'70s. Boundary issues became a big deal.
                    Fishery issues became very big with the Canadians. So, there were a lot of
                    issues which 99.44% of Americans would never know about and never care about.
                    But only about one percent of Canadians didn't know about them fully and were
                    prepared to fight to the last Canadian to get an advantage if they could. But
                    that comes from the nature of the Alliance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned boundaries. I thought we had pretty well
                        settlthe boundaries.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: You're right. We have pretty well settled them, but every boundary issue
                    with the Canadians, whether there are any anomalies or anything that comes up,
                    particularly when it involved fishing rights, are just as tough as dealing with
                    the Russians. They fight tooth and nail, partly because they don't want to
                    appear to be soft on their great friends, the Americans. In Canadian politics,
                    the worst thing that can happen to you is to be considered a toady of the United
                    States. On the other hand, if you're too tough and get in trouble, that also is
                    dangerous for your political health. I think Diefenbaker maybe was an example of
                    being a little too strong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Prime Minister at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Trudeau. He was a special force also. He was looking forward to detente
                    with the Russians. You do have to realize that the other close neighbor to
                    Canada is Russia, mostly over the pole. But still, in a Cold War situation, the
                    Canadians always thought that if missiles would be flying from the Soviets to
                    us, they'd go over Canada. They also just never were quite as hard line. I
                    shouldn't say “never,” but certainly under Trudeau, they were not as hard line
                    anti-communist. They thought the Americans had kind of gone too far. So, it was
                    an interesting time. There would be from time to time some Trudeau ideas which
                    we thought were not helpful. I wish I could think of an example right now, but
                    he was looking often to find ways of dialoguing with the Russians, sometimes on
                    his own, which made us a little nervous. We thought maybe that he wasn't paying
                    enough attention to this NATO solidarity idea, although we have to remember
                    that, even to this day, Canadian forces are still based in Europe to be a part
                    of NATO.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What areas were you in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I was mostly political/military because of my NATO background. When I
                    became the deputy director, I had to be involved in the other issues. But here
                    again, these are pretty routine issues for the U.S. In the great scope of
                    American foreign policy interests, some of these issues with Canada just don't
                    grab people's attention.</p>
                <p>Q: What we're doing here is, we're trying to look in more detail. Obviously,
                    Canadian-American relations in all its glory and difficulties go on no matter
                    where the public attention is paid. So, we'll look at this. When you got onto
                    the Canadian Desk, what would you say was the accepted psychological profile of
                    Pierre Trudeau at that time? What was motivating him? What was his relationship
                    to the United States?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It's a shame that my memory is failing me, but he had a slogan which
                    implied that Canada was independent of the United States. It was meant to prove
                    to the rest of the world that... He was pushing Europeanization of Canadian
                    foreign relations. There were a lot of things that he pushed. But all of it was
                    against this almost immovable and unchangeable fact that it was living cheek by
                    jowl with the United States and that Canadian business and Canadian prosperity
                    really depended on a good relationship with the United States. If you have a big
                    multinational corporation based in the United States that has factories in
                    Canada, if you're one of the American executive officers of one of these
                    companies, and you dare think of closing a factory in Canada, you're going to
                    have people in Canada screaming, “Why are you picking on us? What is this
                    business? We thought we were all in this together.” When the headquarters of
                    companies were in the United States or were clearly American, Canadians always
                    get a little nervous that somehow they're going to get the short end of the
                    stick. The same way with culture. “Time Magazine” sells very widely in Canada.
                    It's not a Canadian magazine. American television is widely seen all over
                    Canada. Canadians have the desire to live close to the American border for
                    practical reasons. It's a little warmer. So they all live about 70 miles from
                    the border and all of these great American cultural scene pours over. There are
                    periodic attempts to stop it, somehow make sure there is Canadian content. Even
                    football teams, the Canadian Football League had to have a certain percentage of
                    Canadians higher than the Americans. You just aren't aware unless you put
                    yourself in Canadian shoes the force of this great American society and how it
                    affects Canadian life in every way.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's talk about the military first. Were there any problems with the Canadian
                    military during this '73 to '76 time? Nuclear issues, deployment, radar, or
                    anything?</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>KRUSE: There were always ongoing questions. We had military bases still up in
                    Canada—mostly for communications, early warning, things tied into our joint
                    NORAD Command in Colorado Springs. Canadians were fully allied with us on this,
                    but were not as zealous about a lot of it, let's put it that way. They clearly
                    didn't have the resources. When World War II finished, Canada had the fourth
                    largest air force in the world. By the time of the '70s, it was very small. It
                    had some well-trained squadrons, but it was not big. That was, of course, the
                    case in Canada in every phase of military. We're talking about a force that
                    eventually got down to 70,000 personnel. It's a very small military. For a
                    serious military man who wants to do the right thing for the security of his
                    country of 25 million people it's constantly frustrating to find that there
                    wasn't much public support for spending a lot of money. So, they had those
                    problems within their own country. Then with us, of course, we tended to be
                    always pushing, encouraging them to do more. The nuclear issues were always the
                    most sensitive. The question of the use of nuclear weapons, that is, the basing
                    of nuclear weapons, even planes on nuclear alert flying over Canada, these
                    things always made the Canadians very nervous and sensitive. They did not want
                    to appear to be a part of any U.S. nuclear initiatives which would embarrass
                    them. Trudeau wanted the least possible reliance on nuclear weapons. Nuclear
                    weapons were a particular problem for him and for a lot of Canadians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the feeling that Trudeau for both political
                        anpersonal reasons rather enjoyed tweaking the nose of the Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes. It always does a Canadian politician a little good in the country to
                    appear to be able to do that. If you can do it with a little good humor and not
                    appear too uptight about it... There is a certain amount that the U.S. knows it
                    has to live with. Trudeau sometimes would do that quite well, but always within
                    limits. He was certainly a strong figure on the Canadian political scene for a
                    long time. So, his appeal was pretty strong in Canada for other reasons, such as
                    keeping Canada together. Here I will express a very strong opinion. I think it
                    would not be to our good to have a divided Canada. So, we were always glad when
                    we had a Prime Minister who appeared to both the French and the English. Trudeau
                    in many ways bent over backwards because he was a French Canadian who appeared
                    to be putting the Anglos in a tight spot. But that's, of course, a constant
                    concern of the Canadians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At this time ('73 to '76), what was the feeling on the
                        CanadiaDesk about whither the future of Canada? I'm speaking of the
                        partition.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>KRUSE: It was just beginning to be a big issue. I remember writing a paper on
                    Quebec separatism. It got to the Secretary and he actually wrote something on it
                    with his initials. The EUR Assistant Secretary Art Hartman sent it back to me.
                    So, I know that the paper was read by him. So, there was that kind of level of
                    interest in Quebec. It was beginning to show this possibility of breaking away.
                    But it was new. At that time, the question was whether separatism would grow or
                    was it going to wither away? I am not sure I ever made a prediction, but I have
                    been surprised that, in fact, it not only seems to have grown, but it came close
                    to actually happening.</p>
                <p>Q: I'm not an authority, but in 1997 after the last plebiscite, my feeling is, I
                    think it's inevitable that Quebec will split off, but maybe I'm wrong.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, I'll put myself on record as saying that I still resist the idea
                    that it is inevitable. I continue to hope that it doesn't happen. I think it
                    would not be in our interest nor really in the interest of Canada and not even
                    Quebec.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about fishing rights? Did you get involved in
                        varioufishing matters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: On the desk, we had to keep tabs on it. In fact, we had Roz Ridgway doing
                    all of the fishery negotiations in those days. So, we were not the prime office
                    for that. That was another interesting thing about the Canadian Desk. Most of
                    the big economic issues with Canada were still being carried by EB. Jules Katz
                    particularly was the man who kind of knew all the economic issues. Any day,
                    something could come up somewhere in Canada which would be totally off our
                    screen. We would know nothing about it. It would happen often between private
                    entities on both sides. Then the governments would have to get involved. Often,
                    the desk was the last to know what was happening. So, there was this kind of
                    history of many of the substantive issues with Canada like economics, the
                    environment, and fisheries. It was somewhat esoteric for the average generalist
                    Foreign Service person. It was being handled by the more functional bureaus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a period of time, if I recall, when icebreakers
                        in thNorthwest Passage were a big issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>KRUSE: The bigger issue was our submarines and their playing around up north. The
                    Canadians didn't like the fact that the submarines would somehow and sometimes
                    come up in what they saw as Canadian waters. It was a problem. We did our best
                    to kind of walk the narrow line between freedom of the seas and Canadian
                    sensitivities. Except for the odd blow-up and incident now and then, we got away
                    with it. There are a lot of little footnote stories, anecdotal stories regarding
                    this relationship. Once, a Canadian ship was doing target practice out in the
                    Puget Sound area, the Juan de Fuca Straits really. One of the shells went awry
                    and actually hit an American ship. Nobody was hurt, fortunately, but you can
                    imagine the jokes that this was a Freudian slip and that this was the Canadians'
                    aggression coming to the forefront. Given the fact that we were one of the
                    world's super powers and the Canadians just wanted us not to throw that around
                    too much with them, I believe we managed the relationship pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about on the cultural side, cultural domination, too
                        mucAmerican advertising and magazines and broadcasts, what have you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Even to this day, there is always the threat of legislation in Canada to
                    cut back on the American content, somehow keep American T.V. down. I have to say
                    that I have a sympathy for the Canadians. I think Canadian society is a very
                    admirable society. There are many features of it that, I think, are superior to
                    ours, particularly gun control and even their feelings of need to have more of a
                    commonality about health care and other social issues. I think, in fact, the
                    whole idea of community is still stronger in Canada than it is here in the
                    United States, where individualism is so important to us. Individualism is
                    honored and respected and practiced in Canada, but there is also the other side,
                    the idea that we are a community. Maybe that comes because they've always had to
                    make a statement to be seen as different from us. So, they're not as assured of
                    themselves maybe as we seem to be. We had an earlier assignment in Toronto. I
                    remember it fondly. I think there is a great deal for Canada to commend itself
                    on. May they live forever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '76, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: This was a great change. I was GLOP'ed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You might explain what “GLOP'ed” means.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I'm told it all came about when Secretary Kissinger was down in Mexico and
                    asked one of the staffers down there what was happening in some other part of
                    the world, and he knew nothing. Kissinger didn't like that too much. GLOP was
                    the idea that you would be available for global service rather than being
                    completely specialized in some area. So, here I had spent my entire career
                    pretty much involved in European and NATO matters. I had been in almost 20
                    years. So, I saw the handwriting on the wall and bid on jobs outside the
                    European area. The job as the deputy principal officer in Jerusalem was up. I
                    looked at that. It seemed a rather fascinating possibility. I had no idea what
                    was going on in the Arab-Israeli conflict. That had never been my issue. So, it
                    was partly because of the name Jerusalem, partly because I knew it was going to
                    be interesting politically, and partly because I knew the consul general, Mike
                    Newlin. It seemed to me that we should try for it. Lo and behold, we were
                    assigned. It was certainly, as Monty Python would say, something completely
                    different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '76 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: To 1980, which were the years of the Carter presidency, just by
                    coincidence, as you know. We had arrived in Jerusalem in September 1976 with the
                    Brookings report just being completed, which talked about the need for a
                    comprehensive solution to the Arab-Israeli conflict, that is, that all Arab
                    countries would somehow make peace with Israel. That Brookings report had great
                    influence on Carter's thinking and on his administration's actions. We started
                    with some of our own efforts to get this going. Then Anwar Sadat decided to, in
                    fact, follow his own inclinations. As you know, after he talked about his
                    willingness to go to Jerusalem, Prime Minister Begin invited him. And so there
                    in November of 1977, he arrives at Tel Aviv Airport, the first Arab leader not
                    only to recognize Israel, but to actually come and step on the soil of the
                    state. So, that happened just a year after I got there. It was from there on in
                    a roller coaster. We were busy.</p>
                <p>Q: Let's take it when you arrived. You got to Jerusalem. The consul general was
                    Mike Newlin. What was the role of the consulate general in Jerusalem at that
                    time?</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>KRUSE: The district for the Jerusalem consulate general was all of the city of
                    Jerusalem and all of the West Bank. It did not include Gaza. So, aside from
                    handling the typical visas and passport needs and all that kind of business, we
                    were charged with making contact with the Palestinian leadership on the West
                    Bank and in essentially East Jerusalem. We also were dealing with the Jewish
                    mayor of Jerusalem, Teddy Kolleck at that time. We were jokingly called “the
                    outlaw consulate” because we did not recognize Israel's claims to territory in
                    Jerusalem nor, obviously, in the West Bank. Therefore, we did not have
                    exequaturs with the Israeli government. We were not recognized officially as our
                    mission being responsible for dealing with the Israelis. All of that was done by
                    our embassy which was in Tel Aviv. So, it was a kind of an anomalous situation,
                    but it had existed since 1967 when the city was no longer divided. Although the
                    Israelis, of course, wanted us to accept, their claims to all of Jerusalem,
                    etc., we were not about to do that. So, we operated under Israeli benevolence,
                    if you will. They allowed us to do our thing. But essentially, our thing was to
                    deal with the Palestinian leaders on the West Bank in East Jerusalem. At that
                    time, the political leadership consisted mostly of elected mayors. The Israelis
                    had allowed municipal elections in '76, which had PLO supporters, but not
                    identifiable PLO figures becoming mayors in all the cities of the West Bank.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, contact between the United States and the
                        PLO waforbidden by Congress.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Not really Congress at that time, the prohibition stemmed from Kissinger's
                    promise to the Israelis at the time of the '73 agreements not to deal with the
                    PLO until it essentially accepted the fact of the state of Israeli and stopped
                    the terrorism. So, it was first Henry who got this started. The Congress later
                    on codified it. In 1976 there was absolutely no possibility of dealing with the
                    PLO. As you may remember, Andrew Young dealt just quietly with a PLO
                    representative in New York and that got him fired. Some other ambassadors got in
                    a little trouble if they seemed to be talking to or were involved with the PLO.
                    We would say in the consulate that, “If any of these mayors that we're dealing
                    with are PLO, then it's the Israelis fault that they're still there. We're not
                    in the business of deciding whether somebody is PLO or not. That's Israel's
                    concern.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about the relationship between the
                        consulatgeneral and the embassy in Tel Aviv during this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>KRUSE: As you can see, there would be certain different emphases in both places.
                    We were emphasizing the desire to have the Palestinians become involved,
                    particularly after the Sadat visit and the Camp David process, when finally the
                    Palestinians were indeed given a part of the Camp David agreement. That is, we
                    were to get the local Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza to become a
                    Palestinian negotiating partner for future dealings with Israel. This was the
                    first time that we had really given- We said as we tried to sell this, “You're
                    now given a ticket to get into the conference room.” It's the first time
                    Palestinians in any way had gotten such an invitation to join in the discussion
                    of their future. So, that was our prime interest at the Consulate General.</p>
                <p>The embassy's interest, of course, as a typical embassy, is to continue a good
                    relationship between the host country and the United States, to, in effect, help
                    accomplish our goals with Israel, which always is to make it secure and
                    prosperous and all that. So, we dealt with different people, different
                    constituencies. Although we both were reading from the same policy script, we
                    emphasized different things. We were trying to tell the Palestinians that this
                    was a great opportunity for them. I don't know that the Israelis were that
                    concerned that Palestinians joined in the negotiations. There was this built-in
                    difference of emphasis. I think you could say that, personally, some of the
                    officers at the embassy and officers at the consulate had different views. The
                    officers at the embassy would tend to feel that the Palestinians would always
                    resent the existence of the state of Israel and that it's almost impossible to
                    see a peaceful resolution of the conflict. I think those of us at the consulate
                    who had known the Palestinians better felt that there was a possibility. Of
                    course, you can say that in retrospect 20 years later, we were maybe more right
                    than they. But the game is not over yet. We still have to see. There are many
                    Israelis who would certainly agree that it isn't possible to have peace with the
                    Palestinians.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>I'll give you an incident which occurred when we had a Congressional delegation
                    out in which the members typically, if they were a serious delegation, wanted to
                    hear both sides. They wanted the consulate to brief them and they wanted the
                    embassy to brief them. We would usually emphasize the Israeli settlement
                    building activity that was going on indicating that this was something that
                    doesn't help the peace process. The embassy would agree with that because our
                    policy was opposed to settlements. But I think the embassy would be able to put
                    this in a context of why the Israelis were doing it because these were the
                    ancient Biblical lands that were near and dear like Hebron, Jerusalem, Bethel,
                    and other places would be where, naturally, Jews would want to live. So,
                    sometimes CODELs would detect almost a policy difference. You can imagine that
                    they would be more inclined to be favorable to the Israelis and would raise some
                    questions back in Washington as to “Are these two posts really in line out
                    there? It seems like we hear a little different thing from both sides.” Of
                    course, the Department would say, “They've all got the same policy, no change.”
                    There were times when there were complaints about the consulate being not
                    pro-Israeli enough. I don't think anybody ever complained that the embassy was
                    not pro-Palestinian enough. So, we had to live with that. I think you can easily
                    draw the reasons why we were different and often times, depending on the zeal of
                    people at the consulate or people at the embassy, you could have some pretty
                    lively discussions.</p>
                <p>Q: I would have imagined this was the time when, even before the Carter
                    administration came in, Congress had mandated human rights reports shortly
                    before. Then you had the advent of Pat Derian and the increased power of the
                    Bureau of Human Rights. I would have thought this would have been both an
                    opportunity for you and a track for the consulate general. The Israelis are not
                    a benevolent occupying force. They have a difficult job to do, but they also are
                    as rough-handed as probably any occupying power can be.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: They seemed to have learned their lessons well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, how did this play out for what you were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>KRUSE: The human rights thing was a very big part of our reporting. Reporting on
                    settlement activity and reporting on human rights, as well as representation for
                    the Palestinians were the three major political issues that we dealt with. Human
                    rights, we tried to report as objectively as we could, mostly based on hearing
                    stories from Palestinians who had been affected by Israel's occupation policies.
                    We had opportunities often when we interviewed Palestinians wanting to get visas
                    to hear why they have a police record. Usually, it was because it was some
                    political accusations by Israeli authorities. In the course of the interview,
                    often, the visa officer had occasion to ask, “What was the charge? Why were you
                    convicted? Why did you admit your guilt?” In many, many cases, if any infraction
                    at all, it was some nationalist manifestation of some kind, but hardly a bloody,
                    terrorist effort. You got the convictions either because the client had no way
                    of understanding what was going on because the whole thing was conducted in
                    Hebrew or our recognizing that he'd get a little better treatment if he just
                    admitted to something. So, you had that kind of perversion of justice. It was
                    such a consistent pattern. You heard it time and time again. You heard about how
                    they were initially questioned and they were kept incommunicado and had hoods
                    over their faces and made to stand for long periods of time, sometimes doused
                    with water and put out in the cold. I guess you could say that not much of this
                    was really life threatening, but some of it was pretty painful or uncomfortable.
                    So, we would report these things. Then, Washington, of course, wanted to be sure
                    that all of this could be proven. In some cases, it wouldn't have been easy to
                    prove it. Every human rights report was a negotiating process. Of course, it was
                    always the consulate that came in with these reports. Although the embassy was
                    responsible in Gaza, they didn't get the same level of stories that we did. So,
                    it was really the consulate that always was reporting the Israeli bad
                    things.</p>
                <p>Q: I would think that you would have, I won't say a problem, but you're up
                    against really not a policy power with which, close on, a young Foreign Service
                    officer would not be comfortable with. This type of activity and all. It would
                    naturally stir up the underdog juices of a reporting officer and yet you kind of
                    know that the reporting can be accurate as all hell, but it would immediately
                    get leaked to the Congress, which would immediately leak it to the Israelis.
                    It's not completely the Jewish lobby, but it's damn close. I mean, there are
                    other allied groups to it, but essentially, the most politically powerful lobby
                    in the United States during this whole time. Yet you've got these young officer
                    whom it would be very difficult to control. They've got a story and they want to
                    get it out.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, it's clear to them as the truth and they feel it shoulbe reported. In
                    many cases, that's what we tried to do.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>I was going to say that I had been in the Service 20 years in the late '70s and I
                    never had expected that what we reported from Jerusalem was so liable to become
                    public so quickly. Maybe it was the issues I had dealt with before weren't as
                    volatile or the subject was not of as much deep interest as reporting on Israeli
                    violations of human rights and Israeli settlement activities. The one great
                    criticism in retrospect that, I think, one can levy at American policy was its
                    refusal to talk to the Palestinian Liberation Organization. We inhibited
                    ourselves from going down the road to a solution with the Israelis and the
                    Palestinians because we basically said, “We don't believe that the PLO is a
                    legitimate party.” Our reporting from the Consulate General made it clear that
                    Palestinians on the West Bank would never substitute themselves for the PLO. Our
                    contacts always said, “You must talk to the PLO-only it can represent us.” So,
                    we delayed almost 20 years before we began a dialogue with the PLO. I have to
                    think that, if this was a policy that could somehow have been set free from
                    domestic pressures and Congressional pressures, we would not have waited so
                    long. We would not have had the painful burdens of so many people lost on both
                    sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have to work to, one, to a certain amount,
                        restrain youyoung reporting officers and, two, to protect them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We were aware of the need to make sure that individual officers didn't get
                    singled out. Of course, when we sent in the human rights reports, it was the
                    post leadership that took the responsibility. There was an occasion of one of
                    the junior officers named Alexander Johnson, who prepared reports on her
                    interviews with Palestinian visa applicants, which showed the pattern of human
                    rights violations. We allowed those reports to go forward with a covering
                    memorandum that this represented the effort of one officer and that we accepted
                    this as a valid effort on her part. That report apparently became public. We had
                    to go through a season of phone and other inquiries from press people about,
                    “What's this Alexander Johnson doing?” To make it clear, unfortunately,
                    Alexander had a lot of problems personally and in her work otherwise and we felt
                    was not really the best candidate for advancement in the Service. Eventually, in
                    fact, she did not get her tenure. I believe that she quit the Service a few
                    years later went public completely with her book called “Jerusalem 1500,” as I
                    remember because that was the number of the airgram that we had sent in with her
                    reporting. That got a little publicity. It was the same time that “The Sunday
                    Times” in London had done a very thorough report of Israeli practices with
                    prisoners in the West Bank. So, a lot of this stuff was hitting the West Bank at
                    the same time and the Israelis were getting very sensitive to all this. Getting
                    back to the point of what we did with the officers who felt they had to report
                    this, we tried to do it as matter of factly as possible and tried to protect the
                    names of individual officers. I think, to a great extent, we were successful,
                    not that it changed Israeli practices, unfortunately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you concerned about the Israeli secret service
                        doindisinformation on your officers to discredit them and all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, it was an issue. It is true that, from time to time, Israeli
                    officials (high ranking) would say something to the ambassador in Tel Aviv.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Sam Lewis, as you know, a career officer. He was there a long time,
                    although at a certain point, he did resign as a career officer and then was
                    reappointed as a political appointee. There would be times that Israeli—I heard
                    once or twice about Israeli officials complaining to the Embassy about Consulate
                    officers being anti-Israeli. I think the embassy had quickly rebuffed those
                    kinds of accusations. But I will say that I never felt in any way that the
                    Israelis would do anything to us in any physical way because that wouldn't be in
                    their interest to go that far. But they did think of the whole consulate as
                    being anti-Israeli, I'm afraid. Many Israeli politicians would say that.</p>
                <p>Q: What about your contacts with Teddy Kolleck, who was the mayor for many, many
                    years in Jerusalem, who seemed to try to bridge the gap between the Arabs and
                    the Jews?</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>KRUSE: We tried to have a correct relationship. He was the Israeli mayor of
                    Jerusalem. However, we get immediately to this question of where Israeli
                    authority should go, where the Israelis thought it went. They had annexed all of
                    Jerusalem, including the part they took in '67. Without going through all the
                    details, suffice to say that we never accepted that nor did any government in
                    the world. Certainly, the people who lived in Arab East Jerusalem, never thought
                    of him as their mayor. But Teddy Kolleck tried to present himself as the mayor
                    of all Jerusalem. He was a humane person in terms of not wanting to
                    unnecessarily offend Arabs. His vision was to have Arabs in Jerusalem living
                    happily under a Jewish mayor who would be willing to dialogue with them and
                    attempt to treat them, if not equally, because there has never been an attempt
                    by Israel to treat its Arabs equally, at least as humanely as possible. This was
                    a very difficult and, I would say, impossible job that Teddy may have thought he
                    should try. We had some difficulties with him from time to time. We had two
                    separate receptions on July 4th, one for the east side (the Arab side) and
                    invited only the Arabs, and one on the west side for the Israelis and
                    essentially only invited them. This was a great offense to Teddy, who thought
                    that we were attempting to continue the division of Jerusalem. We said that, in
                    fact, we're just trying to fulfill what our policy is. So, we did not ever, in
                    my time, combine the receptions. But this made him very unhappy. To finish off
                    on Teddy, he would constantly tell the United States Consulate General and the
                    other five or six consulates that existed in Jerusalem with our same non-status
                    (the Brits, French, Italians etc), “You consulate people don't get the picture
                    at all. You are helping contribute to the division of this city into Arab and
                    Jew. What we're trying to do is make us all live together.” The implication was
                    that if only we would get on board the program of a single Jewish
                    administration, the Arabs would eventually be happy, would accept it, would be
                    quiet, and that would be the end of it. At the time I was there (I left in
                    1980), the Arabs had still not risen up in the way that we thought, eventually,
                    they would. But with the Intifada, which started in '87, it was clear to me that
                    Teddy has his answer, that he was the one who was wrong and we were the ones who
                    were right, that there were two cultures in Jerusalem, and that they weren't
                    going to mix unless there was a basis of equality.</p>
                <p>Q: What about reporting on the settlements during this time? As we talk today, a
                    settlement is causing civil disturbance and deaths in Jerusalem. The Israelis
                    are putting one up in Arab Jerusalem. It's on the front pages. During this '76
                    to '80 period, what was going on in the Jewish settlements on the West Bank in
                    Jerusalem?</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, a lot was going on, but I think the most important thing was going
                    on here in Washington, where we had a President who effectively said that
                    settlements are illegal. It was very clear cut and very simple. They were not
                    obstacles to peace only, but they were absolutely illegal. Now, that did disturb
                    the Israelis. When the new administration came in in '80 under Reagan, they
                    changed that formula to just being obstacles to peace, not illegal. So during my
                    time in Jerusalem we had a lot of backing here in Washington for reporting fully
                    on the settlements. We did that. We interviewed settlers. We talked to those who
                    were organizing the settlements. This was one issue where we actually talked to
                    some Israeli officials—if not talking to them, we were quoting them because the
                    settlement issue was, of course, a West Bank and Gaza issue, but mostly the West
                    Bank and Jerusalem. Washington welcomed this. It was a big effort going on in
                    the intelligence community to keep completely up to date on this. I suspect and
                    hope that it is continuing. It looks like it is because I see maps from time to
                    time that show the growth of these settlements. It goes back to what Hodding
                    Carter said in these days. When we objected to the Israeli settlements, Hodding
                    Carter said, “It's like two men negotiating over a glass of water and one picks
                    it up and starts drinking from it. This is what Israel is doing with its
                    settlements. It's simply trying to prejudge the outcome.” That's true to this
                    very day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting a fix on who was going into these
                        settlements?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, we would interview settlers. In fact, at one point, one of our
                    officers actually got stopped inside one of the settlements and was challenged
                    as to how he got in. He said, “I just drove in.” But he was detained briefly and
                    questioned because he had been asking questions of the people that were there.
                    This was, of course, before the big settlement push in the early 1980s when
                    Shamir simply advertised cheap living on the West Bank. These were mostly
                    zealots, pioneers, putting up settlements, in some cases wildcat settlements
                    with no authorization and defying the Israeli authorities to get them out. On
                    the other hand, there were some completely approved settlements by Israel that
                    were going ahead. They had a master plan. You knew what they were hoping to
                    accomplish—implant as many Israeli settlers as possible. Particularly around
                    Jerusalem, they had pretty well accomplished that. They have encircled Arab East
                    Jerusalem with these high rise settlements, basically suburban high rises, that
                    now have about the same number of Jews living there as Arabs living in the core
                    of East Jerusalem. When I was there, this was just a gleam in their eye. But
                    they've accomplished it.</p>
                <p>Q: I would have thought you would have had problems because you're the American
                    consulate general. When you talk about zealots, from what I assume, a
                    disproportionate number of zealots are actually American Jews who come to Israel
                    are reinforcing their faith and, like a convert to Catholicism, are more
                    Catholic than the Pope - that they would come, get involved, and then if things
                    got bad, scream and yell for American help.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>KRUSE: You're right. Of course, many of them continue to carry their American
                    passport and therefore had a parachute if they wished to get out. They were
                    usually unhappy with the American consulate and particularly when we expressed
                    our policy. But, in retrospect, they probably thought that it didn't matter what
                    we said or did, they were just going to go ahead and build settlements.
                    Sometimes they did defy their own government. But eventually, most of those
                    wildcat settlements were authorized. It's called “creating facts on the ground.”
                    It's like so many of the Israeli soldiers or settlers who have shot
                    Palestinians. We go through the whole business of the Israelis bringing them to
                    justice and meting out some kind of punishment. Unfortunately, usually, that is
                    followed in a few years by a pardon granted to those offenders by the President
                    of Israel. So, it's very clear that Arabs are treated much differently from the
                    Jewish population. House demolition is standard treatment for a Palestinian
                    charged with a security offense— no Jewish Israeli has ever had this treatment,
                    not even the assassin of Prime Minister Rabin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impact of Sadat's visit to Tel Aviv and the
                        CamDavid process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: When the Camp David Accords came out with the idea of autonomy for the
                    West Bank and Gaza, we finally had a program to present to the Palestinians as
                    something that they should look at and hopefully find it greatly more attractive
                    than their current situation under occupation. We essentially tried to sell it
                    as being the end of Israeli occupation. The question of what it would lead to
                    was open. We never could promise them a state, but we did say that, “You can
                    participate in your own future.” So, our sale was, “This is better than you've
                    ever been offered. It's better than you have now. Join in.” We had a very active
                    program. Washington expected us to sell this to the mayors of Nablus, Bethlehem
                    and Hebron etc. We tried that. But the essential answer, which, I have to say,
                    is very understandable, was that, “You've come to the wrong party. We are not
                    representing the Palestinian people. The PLO represents that Palestinian people.
                    We are like prisoners in a cage. We can't talk for the rest of the Palestinians
                    and we don't have any strength. So, we choose not to be involved.” I think there
                    were some Palestinian leaders who would have joined in if we had made more
                    clearly what the end result would be. They just said, “We're not going to take a
                    leap off into the dark. We don't know where you're going to lead us. The idea of
                    a ticket to the conference table is not enough for us. We want to know what the
                    end is going to be.” You see, we were not prepared to tell them what we wanted
                    the end to be. Frankly, to this very day, we're not prepared to tell the
                    Palestinians what we think they should have at the end. This continues to be one
                    of the great failings of our policy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you looked at this policy, did you see any
                        solution?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Frankly, I didn't. Back then, I had the fear that the Palestinians would
                    just be ground into the dirt, unless we changed our policy toward dealing with
                    the PLO. So, I'm half way encouraged that it does seem that whatever happens now
                    in the future, the Palestinian cause is not a completely lost cause. There were
                    many who thought that it would become a lost cause. How the Palestinian cause
                    can be fulfilled properly and happily is still not sketched out by our policy. I
                    could say that the outcome is uncertain. When Golda Meir was around, she said,
                    “Who are the Palestinians? Where are they? What are they?” Nobody says that now.
                    The whole world now knows who they are. Whether they're treated justly or not
                    depends largely on Israel and the United States.</p>
                <p>Q: You had not grown up in this particular atmosphere. Coming into it,
                    reflections from your memory of how we treated the blacks in the South?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think there was very much that feeling although I thought more of the
                    South African experience, where there was a very definite racial difference that
                    was policy. In Israel, that's a little more nuanced than outright apartheid. I
                    remember from my time in the South before the civil rights movement got moving
                    that... The thing that strikes you is that a lot of people, even when the blacks
                    were treated so poorly in the South, there were a lot of people who thought this
                    was wrong. It was just a question of how you're going to change (inaudible). In
                    the case of Israel and its treatment of the Arabs, what I can never answer a
                    Palestinian is why we give Israel four or five billion dollars a year. It's one
                    thing to let human rights abuses go and not blow a whistle or stop it somehow,
                    but it's another thing to wound the party who is doing all these unjust things
                    continual unquestioned support no matter what it does.</p>
                <p>Q: As a Foreign Service officer, to see the power of domestic politics on
                    something that may not, in your opinion, be in American world interest, not only
                    you, but the young officers, was this something you sort of had to work on to
                    keep people from getting too discouraged and too cynical?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It is a problem. I guess all of the young officers had come to realize
                    that, in many ways, our relationship with Israel is not a foreign policy issue;
                    it's a domestic issue. Certainly, our French and British and other colleagues in
                    Jerusalem would say, “We just can't understand why you do these things. What is
                    the reason for your support of Israel, your vetoing resolutions, etc.” Then in
                    the second breath, they'd say, “But then we know about your lobby.” It is
                    unique. There is no other country that finds itself so under the control of such
                    a powerful lobby. Recently, there has been reporting about the President's
                    reaction to Netanyahu, which is generally a mild one, even though clearly there
                    is disagreement with him. The newspapers are quoting unnamed administration
                    officials, suggesting that how else is the Democratic party going to pay off its
                    debt? But this whole issue of Jewish and Israeli supporters and their
                    contribution to the campaign seems to stay outside the whole ongoing debate on
                    campaign funding. In my view, Israel's influence on our political process and
                    our foreign policy is the most egregious and dangerous example of the influence
                    of a foreign country on our government.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1980, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I went to the Sinai Desert for a year. I was the deputy director of the
                    Sinai Field Mission. That was kind of a follow-on to my years in Jerusalem. The
                    Sinai Agreement came and the reason they had this American team out there, the
                    Sinai Field Mission, was because of the peace agreement that Henry Kissinger
                    brokered in '73 and '74 between Egypt and Israel, which called for the U.S. to
                    monitor the forces in the Sinai. So, we were out there monitoring, we with our
                    helicopters and Cheny Blazers out among the Bedouins and the camels. So, we were
                    right in the middle of the Sinai Desert.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the status during '80 to '81 during this period
                        you werin the Sinai?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It was half way into the terms of the peace agreement between Israel and
                    Egypt; their peace treaty in '78, which called for a complete withdrawal of all
                    Israeli forces from the Sinai within a certain period of time. The period of
                    time was, I think, eventually to end in '82. So, while I was there, we were
                    still half way there. We still had some Israeli forces in part of the Sinai. It
                    was a confidence-building measure for the Egyptians and the Israelis to have us
                    there, particularly for the Israelis. They insisted on us. They wouldn't take
                    the UN. So, we paid the price to do that. It was a fascinating experience. It
                    was unusual because it was the only time in my career when my family could not
                    be with me. In that sense, I would wake up in the morning and look at myself in
                    the mirror and say, “What in the world are you doing out here?”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell about how it progressed while you were there
                        first.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: This was the first time I had dealt directly with the Israelis in an
                    official sense, and Egyptians; dealing with each of them. When you would go into
                    Cairo, you'd have an agenda for the meeting. You had a lot of tschai (tea),
                    coffee, soft drinks, lots of jokes, lots of laughs, get through the agenda, come
                    back in a month or two and not a thing had been done. But we had had no
                    arguments. When we would go in with the Israelis, there were a certain amount of
                    refreshments and that type of thing, but every item on the agenda, every jot and
                    tittle, would be argued over. You would set deadlines for this or that. You'd
                    have courses of action for every one of the items. When you came back in a
                    couple of months, it was all done. Everybody had done their work. So, it was a
                    difference between the way the Israelis acted and the way the Arabs, in this
                    case, the Egyptians, acted. The Israelis were such sticklers for every phrase of
                    that agreement they signed with Egypt. That's why I was so appalled when it
                    comes to the agreement that Israel signed with the Palestinians, they don't care
                    at all about keeping any parts of it, no deadlines, no nothing. No apologies.
                    Just forget it. If we had tried that with the Egyptians, we would have been
                    frayed by the Israelis.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean the Israelis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, if we had let the Egyptians get away with violations. If the
                    Egyptians hadn't met a deadline, boy, we would have never heard the end of it.
                    So, it all depends on who's is a superior position.</p>
                <p>Q: I've talked to some other people who have been involved in this and they say
                    that, as you said, things were a little bit haphazard and sloppy and all. But
                    the Israelis were always testing. They would try to get things they weren't
                    supposed to have—overflights or get arms in or something. It was almost a game
                    of doing this. People I've talked to say it was basic, almost hostility there.
                    Did you feel that or not? Was that unfair?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think what you've got is this dual strain in the Israeli psyche or
                    makeup. You've got the one that identifies with the Labor party, where indeed,
                    they strive and believe that a Jew can make it in the world on his own, that he
                    doesn't need to worry that everybody is after him. The Likud is the mentality
                    that it doesn't matter what the Jews ever do, they would never accept them as
                    normal people. Therefore, according to Likud, if Israel wants something, it's
                    going to have to fight for it and don't worry if the world objects. I think that
                    kind of paranoia is, to a certain extent, in every Israeli. Given the history of
                    the Jewish people, it is understandable. Of course, the history of the Middle
                    East has not been one where their arrival and setting up their state has been
                    wildly welcomed. So, I understand that they may not feel that they are
                    completely a normal state in the region. But I think the Labor people felt that
                    normalcy was a possibility. I'm afraid Likud doesn't think it ever is going to
                    be a possibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any incidents or any particular problems that
                        yomight want to recount?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, just the fact that we almost had the helicopter crash one time with
                    our director and a whole gaggle of Egyptian officers. I wasn't on it. It had
                    taken off with a full load of fuel. They had forgotten that they were at an
                    altitude of about 4,000 feet. It was somewhere near Mt. Sinai. That makes a
                    little difference in your lift. So, the thing got up and bounced a whole lot,
                    turned over, but did not catch fire. It was a scary thing. If a tragedy had
                    happened, I must say, it would have marked the Sinai Field Mission in people's
                    minds forever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I thought we might stop at this point. We're in '81 after
                        yoleft Sinai. Where did you go after that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I came back to Washington to attend the National War College.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>You had asked earlier about the differences between the consulate and the
                    embassy. I think that there were times when the embassy went very much along the
                    lines of protecting Israel, even when it might not really have been in our
                    interest to so protect them. As an example, the formula that we used for
                    settlement activities in the Carter days was that they were illegal. This was
                    something that the Israelis found very difficult to swallow. Complications to
                    peace and all that, that's all right, but illegal? I know that Jeane Kirkpatrick
                    when she came into the Reagan administration very much was of a mind that we had
                    to change this formulation. The President got it in his mind to say that he
                    didn't think they were illegal. I'm not sure that was a very informed opinion,
                    but it was spoken publicly. As soon as it was said, pro-Israeli types among whom
                    I suspect was Ambassador Sam Lewis, picked it up because it certainly made their
                    business in dealings with the Israelis on this issue so much simpler when you
                    don't have to accuse them of illegalities. I think that was unhelpful because I
                    think settlements are totally illegal. Everybody else in the world thinks
                    they're illegal and I think it's wrong for us again to be out of line and
                    protect Israel when it is doing things opposed to international law. So the
                    Embassy in Tel Aviv was delighted with this new formulation while the Consulate
                    was discouraged..</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll pick it up the next time in 1981 going to the
                        National WaCollege.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is June 13, 1997. You went to the War College. You
                        werthere from '81 to '82. Which War College was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: National War College here in Washington.</p>
                <p>Q: What were your experiences there, particularly dealing with the military,
                    having been in the State Department so long? How were you used and what did you
                    get out of this?</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>KRUSE: A lot of my assignments were political/military, so I had dealt with the
                    military a lot. When this opportunity came, I was rather glad to have a year
                    off. It was a rather pleasant year, coming out of the Sinai. It's a nice change
                    and a nice way to readapt to the Washington culture in a more relaxed manner. I
                    enjoyed being brought up to date on where the military were at the start of the
                    Reagan administration. It was clear that the military felt they were coming back
                    into their own after the Vietnam problems. They were very happy to see the money
                    coming into the budget, which they felt they hadn't been getting. This was a
                    good time for the military, feeling that they were again being appreciated. I
                    think that began to play out in a new sense of the American military's role,
                    even though this was still, of course, the Cold War. You might even say this was
                    the heart of the Cold War still because there was Soviet adventurism in
                    Afghanistan still. In the first Reagan term, he made a point of, in effect,
                    trying to talk the Soviets down in other parts of the world like Angola. There
                    was, I think, a wrong perception that the Soviets were taking advantage in the
                    Middle East militarily. To be honest with you, there were some things going on
                    in the Reagan administration that I did very much disagree with, this whole idea
                    that particularly Secretary Haig in his short tenure as Secretary of State, was
                    pushing the idea of strategic consensus in the Middle East, that you could
                    somehow get the moderate Arabs and Israel to be clearly anti-Soviet, kind of
                    disregarding what is the fundamental problem in the Middle East, which had
                    nothing to do with the Cold War, but had everything to do with the question of
                    Israel and the Palestinians. But, to sum up, I enjoyed my year very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there during the Israeli invasion of
                        Lebanon?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Actually, that was just after I had left the War College.</p>
                <p>Q: And then you left. What was your impression of the various services? Did you
                    come away with some way you could characterize the Army, the Navy, the Air
                    Force?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: In a gross sense, yes. I think the Army has always been more associated
                    with the people on the ground. The Army is a land force. Great numbers of
                    American Army officers had spent time in Germany or Japan in the post-war era
                    actually living in the countries they were assigned. The Army gets closer to the
                    foreign environment. It was different from the Navy, which by and large was
                    always at sea. The Air Force also thought of themselves as not too closely
                    related to the foreign environment. It's not easy to make those distinctions
                    either. The draft was over, so all of them were volunteers at that time. It's
                    very true also that the Navy officers who came to the National War College felt
                    that they hadn't quite gotten the best senior training because this was, after
                    all, not just with the Navy. This was with everybody else. The Navy really did
                    think that Newport, where their war college is, is a lot more career-enhancing
                    than the National War College. That may be changing as a result of legislation
                    such as the Goldwater-Nichols Act.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Q: How did the State Department people fit in? Were you used as a resource for
                    helping these people on their way up to senior ranks understand about the
                    world?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think it's true that you're presenting the way the world looks in the
                    eyes of a Frenchman and the way it looks in the eyes of an Israeli or an Arab.
                    Those kind of background skills that we pick up along the way clearly are not as
                    easy for a military officer to ever pick up, even when he or she may be assigned
                    overseas. I think the State Department is well served by sending people over to
                    the War College, not only in terms of what that individual gets himself or
                    herself, but what it presents to the whole War College environment. It's good
                    for us. We need to think about the importance of the military to our overall
                    foreign policy. It's good for them also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for how the military looked at the
                        SovieUnion at that particular point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I did indeed. There is no doubt that the doctrine or the fear of the
                    Soviet military threat was still very high. We saw the Soviets as our equal in
                    intercontinental ballistic missile capabilities. These were the most horrific
                    weapons in the history of the human race. We saw the adventuristic nature of
                    their foreign policy in Afghanistan and other places. There was this concern
                    that maybe the Soviets were delaying a peaceful settlement of the Middle East
                    problem by encouraging the Arabs to be anti-Israel and to think they had a
                    military option. So, I'm afraid that there was a lot of overestimation of what
                    the Soviet threat really represented. I confess to be guilty somewhat in that
                    regard. I accepted the general evaluation of the Soviet threat. Now, in
                    retrospect, I think we do have to recognize that we overestimated the over-all
                    strength of the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Q: I think all of us did. Also, it's one of these things that, in a case like
                    this, it's probably a lot better to overestimate than underestimate. You're not
                    going to be caught by surprise.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I'd rather be safe than sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. In '82, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I stayed in the States for one two-year assignment and that was in
                    Personnel, which was something completely different for me. I was the chief of
                    the Political Officers Division of Personnel. I had two officers working with me
                    doing all of the political officers at the less than senior level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing this from '82 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>KRUSE: For two years, until '84. This was an interesting time, you might even
                    say, a rather dramatic time, for some of the officers, particularly the
                    political officers at the new 01 level, which was the old 03 level. The new
                    Foreign Service Act had created the Senior Foreign Service, and the 01 was then
                    the top of the non-Senior Foreign Service. There was this new idea of the senior
                    threshold, that you had six years to open your window and get across that
                    threshold from the new 01 level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Foreign Service Act of '80 and then '81,
                        wasn't it?It took two turns to get it right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It just turned out that when I got into the job in '82 and then in '83 and
                    '84, these were years when those who had opened their window at the very first
                    crack (that is, to start their competition immediately) were half way through
                    that competition and were beginning to recognize that their chances of getting
                    that promotion into the Senior Service were diminishing every year. The number
                    that were getting promoted was getting less every year. To a certain extent, the
                    Service did not properly prepare a lot of 01s in 1980 whenever the Act came into
                    effect, to recognize that a six year crack might not just be enough,
                    particularly when (and this maybe wasn't even known by the Service at the time)
                    that there were going to be diminishing promotion numbers. We got down to one
                    year where only 15 political officers at the 01 level got promoted into the
                    Senior Foreign Service out of a class of like 400. The effect on morale became
                    very serious because people saw that they would be going off the gang plank in a
                    few more years and thus have a much shorter career than they had thought.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you in Personnel looking at what effect this might have not just on the
                    career of an individual, but let's say, Korean-speaking officers or
                    Arabic-speaking? I mean, we have resources within the Department. We promote by
                    the individual, but at the same time, we have to make sure that there are solid
                    career tracks in geographic or functional specialties, consular officers,
                    economic officers, what have you. But particularly in the political field, where
                    you have such a multiplicity of specialties (political/military, geographic,
                    international organizations). Could you talk about that?</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Of course, the criteria for promotion into the Senior Foreign Service, as
                    you know, downplayed those great Foreign Service unique skills of language and
                    area capabilities and very much put the emphasis on management skills, on
                    executive capabilities, even on running a budget and a program, all the kind of
                    things that you might get best at a DCM level. What it meant was that everybody
                    was running after a DCM job no matter where it was. They recognized that you
                    could be the chief of the Political Section in Paris and it wouldn't mean as
                    much to you in promotion opportunity as if you were a DCM in N'djamena. So, that
                    skewed people's bidding and it made them feel very insecure because to get a DCM
                    job isn't just a matter of the system assigning you, you've got to get the
                    ambassador's approval. So, this was not an easy time. I have to say, during
                    those years, more and more of the O1 political officers who were coming to me
                    and saying, “I think I'm facing the end of a career and I'm not even 50. What
                    can I do?” The best I could tell them was, “Do your best to get an
                    interfunctional job, a job that shows your executive and managerial
                    talents.”</p>
                <p>Those that did have these skills and had the opportunity to show them were by and
                    large able to escape extinction, but there were not that many of them. There
                    just weren't that many jobs that could get you across the threshold. What
                    happened is that in succeeding years, those who came into the 01 level realized
                    that they must think hard about when they started the competition, opened their
                    window for competition. In many cases, they would wait, which again goes against
                    the whole earlier Foreign Service concept that you're going to compete
                    immediately, that you have great confidence in your abilities, and you kind of
                    charge in and, as soon as you are eligible for promotion, you start competing,
                    rather than waiting for several years, in effect, to line up your six year
                    window with your 22 year TIC (time in class) window. It's affected the Service.
                    Frankly, as I talk 15 years later with the officers at the 01 level, there is
                    still some of that residual problem. That is, your geographic and language
                    specialties are still not enough to get you into the Senior Service if you don't
                    show some of these broader abilities.</p>
                <p>Q: What about other concerns which have become almost predominant today after the
                    last few years, women moving in the senior ranks, and minorities?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: That became and I know it is an issue that is thought by many officers,
                    particularly the traditional male white officer, that he has been disadvantage
                    by these either affirmative action programs or efforts on the part of the women
                    and their class action suit to be placed into these promotable jobs like the DCM
                    jobs. I suppose there are legitimate horror stories of people being adversely
                    affected, but the Service is supposed to reflect what the society wishes, the
                    general desire to provide more opportunities for women and minorities. There is
                    a certain sense of what you could say is making equal some of the earlier
                    injustices. It's a problem that society wrestles with throughout.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you have the feeling when you were there that there was pressure on you to
                    try to make sure that women were given a more than equal crack at the jobs that
                    were promotable?</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I think it was too early for that. When I took over the job of 01
                    political officers, which would mean officers in their '40s for the most part,
                    the Service profile for those officers still did not show a high number of women
                    officers. I think I probably had less than 10% women in that class at that time.
                    Of course, that's changed now drastically. It didn't represent a big problem
                    because we didn't have many women at the 01 level to place.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find the system at that time was, if an assignment came along which
                    was less than desirable, people protesting? Was it difficult to fill spots?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Not really. You really can't grieve an assignment. You cagrieve a lot of
                    other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The term “to grieve” means to make an official
                        grievanccomplaint which goes before a board and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I suspect that the process is still the same way. It is still a rather
                    civil process. That is, if you know that someone is simply not going to take an
                    assignment and you can't change that by saying, “Well, it's going to be good for
                    your career” or “You're doing something that the Service will repay you for.” I
                    can't think of many forced assignments that we did in those days. I think in the
                    later years, there has been more and more of an effort to assign people into
                    hardship posts, less desirable posts, early in the assignment cycle so that you
                    aren't left at the end with the fair haired types having gotten their
                    assignments and gone and you have left over the less easily assignable people as
                    your only pool to handle these hardship jobs. I'm quite certain that that's the
                    way it now works, that hardship jobs are assigned early in the cycle to prevent
                    this problem of having people continue to avoid hardship. I suppose you think of
                    the hardship jobs... I often thought it was not hard to get an 02 or an 03
                    officer to bid on a hard to fill 01 job, but the problem was that there were
                    always a lot of 01s sitting around unassigned and the system said, “We have got
                    to get somebody at grade for this job. Go get these people and talk them into
                    it.” There were times when simply those 01s would not bite, would not take it. I
                    think that's probably still the case, although maybe more forced assignments are
                    occurring.</p>
                <p>Q: Would you give a reader of this in some decades ahead or even more, for a
                    senior officer... We're talking about an 01 in those days was the equivalent to
                    a colonel in the Army. What would be a less desirable job, some of the more
                    difficult jobs you had to fill during this '82 to '84 period?</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>KRUSE: There were a lot of deputy director jobs in those days, some bureaus had
                    more than others. EUR, for example, took pride in having an office director and
                    deputy, both of which were senior officers. The deputy would often be an OC job.
                    It was hardly ever filled by an OC, but by a stretch assignment for an 01. Those
                    were considered very desirable and, I think, probably were. But a regular desk
                    officer job, even if it were at the 01 level, became hard to get people to take
                    because they thought they were taking less than they should take. There were
                    other overseas jobs. It seems like Lagos political counselor, even if it were an
                    OC job was very hard to fill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: OC being like brigadier general.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: The first rank in the Senior Service.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you see any geographic bias? Was it harder to fill Africa than Europe?
                    Latin America, ARA, were they people who had always served in ARA? Could you
                    talk about the geographic flow from your perspective?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: In the case of NEA, Near East Affairs, and EAP, Asian Affairs, you do have
                    a lot of language officers. In most cases, you're either dealing with Arabic or
                    you're dealing with Chinese and Japanese. There were some complaints. I
                    remember, the Japanese language officers were always complaining that they would
                    fill all of the grunt jobs in the embassy and posts in Japan. That's certainly
                    also true for a Chinese language officer. You can use a Chinese language officer
                    in many other places besides Mainland China. They would complain that they would
                    have to fill those jobs. Then when it came to senior jobs like a DCM in Tokyo,
                    often times it would go to a generalist who may or may not have had experience
                    in Japan. As far as the attitude toward bureaus in general, I suppose, if I were
                    completely frank, I would say that ARA and AF were considered places that were
                    just less strategically interesting to the United States, even though in the
                    Reagan years, ARA became, in the eyes of the Reagan administration, a
                    battlefield of the Cold War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Certainly, particularly Nicaragua and El Salvador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. So, there were officers whose career was enhanced because they got
                    visibility as a result of the White House interest in Central America. EUR was
                    popular because it had still the most number of posts and European living was
                    considered by most people pleasant. The one kind of down the road disadvantage
                    to EUR is that it's not that often that EUR officers get embassies in EUR. The
                    political appointees like to take them. Everybody thought of AF as the chance
                    where maybe they could get an embassy, even if they hadn't served much in AF.
                    Those kind of caricatures, I suppose, exist even still today.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about the Director General and up the
                        line ithis early Reagan administration were looking at the personnel
                        system?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I guess the most egregious thing was the fact that every bureau had to
                    take a political appointee Deputy Assistant Secretary. It may not have been
                    written anywhere, but we all knew it. That person, even if he or she might turn
                    out to be fairly competent was considered the White House spy. So, you always
                    thought a little bit about what you said around that person, particularly if it
                    came to domestic politics. I think the Reagan people came into town thinking
                    that most of the establishment in Washington were traditionally Democratic or at
                    least sympathetic to continuing things as they were. Many of these Reaganites
                    had come in with the idea that they were going to really capture the town and
                    turn the bureaucracy around, if not reduce it greatly. There is no doubt that
                    there was a feeling that the White House people didn't like much the Foreign
                    Service. I think that was reflected also in the kinds of people who got assigned
                    to NSC jobs. We didn't get the same number of jobs in the NSC staff that we had
                    under previous administrations. They were looking more at CIA types and military
                    types. Of course, I think the NSC suffered greatly for it. You had some very
                    strange selections for the NSC, including people like Poindexter and the
                    ex-Marine, Bud McFarlane. These were people that should not have been named.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Then down below, you had Oliver North. It
                        practicallcollapsed the Reagan administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think it's a mistake to have an active duty uniformed military officer
                    running the NSC because it skews judgements and it puts pressure on the
                    individual to still be an active duty military and yet, presumably, acting in
                    the whole national interest. Zealots like Colonel North never have a place in
                    policy-making jobs</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, they're trained to be short-term result oriented.
                        It'just a matter of...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Unfortunately, that's a White House syndrome in any case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know, but it just plays to it. You left Personnel in
                        '84.Whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Off to Naples to be the political advisor to the Commander iChief of
                    Allied Forces South.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>Q: You were in Naples from '84 to '88. I left Naples in '81 as consulate general
                    there, so I'm familiar with some of the things. Could you talk about, first, the
                    job? Then we'll get into some of the details.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: As you may recall, I had had a lot of NATO experience in my earlier career
                    in Brussels, as well as many of the other Pol/Mil jobs I had. So, I felt very
                    comfortable seeking a NATO assignment. I knew about this southern region command
                    because I had worked in the NATO structure both military and political. There
                    was no doubt that things were heating up in the Mediterranean even though they
                    were not specifically the concern of NATO. As you know, NATO and its members
                    tended to want to stay out of what was termed “out of area” issues. That is,
                    geographic areas that were not in Continental Europe—what was considered the
                    original NATO area. What we had in Naples was a four star American admiral
                    running NATO's southern region for NATO. But in his other hat, he was running
                    all U.S. naval forces in and around Europe, including the Sixth Fleet in the
                    Mediterranean. So, you had day to day operational responsibilities on the
                    U.S.-only side and the NATO planning functions. By and large, all that NATO
                    forces in the south were doing was planning and exercising. Until much later
                    when they got into Bosnia issues, NATO never fired a shot in anger in all the
                    years of the Cold War. This four-star admiral actually had two POLADs, one of
                    whom resided in Naples at his NATO headquarters, where he also lived, and one
                    was up in London, where his headquarters for the U.S.-only side, U.S. Navy
                    Forces Europe. So, I really was not officially an advisor to the admiral on
                    U.S.-only things—i.e., when we decided to launch an attack on Libya, that was
                    done by Sixth Fleet forces solely as an American operation. That was not my
                    business to be involved in, although proximity to the boss always gives you an
                    opportunity to put in your comments.</p>
                <p>Q: I was going to say, after all, somebody up in London talking about what to do
                    about Libya when you're sitting down in Naples. This seems to be one of the
                    problems of the chain of command anyway. The military is continually faulted for
                    this.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: In actual practice it wasn't all that often that the Sixth Fleet or U.S.
                    forces were conducting operations in anger. Whenever that happened, the admiral
                    would simply go up to London and be at the headquarters to be seen and to be
                    directing things in person. I suppose electronically, he could have done all
                    this from Naples. He didn't really need to be on the spot. But the kind of
                    communications equipment that was modern and state of the art was not in Naples,
                    it was in London. That's where the U.S. had put it. Just optically, I think,
                    Washington wanted the CINC up at his U.S. headquarters when American forces were
                    involved in action.</p>
                <p>Q: I'd like to do sort of a geographic tour before we get to events. Let's stop
                    and talk about Spain and Portugal first. During this '84 to '88 period, what
                    were the prime concerns and developments from your perspective? In the first
                    place, who was your admiral or admirals?</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I had quite a number in those four years because we started with Admiral
                    Bill Small. He left within a year and he was replaced by Admiral Lee Boggett.
                    Admiral Moreau replaced Boggett who went on to become SACLANT. The illness and
                    death of Moreau changed everything. It's kind of a sick joke, but the Navy
                    doesn't plan for one of its four stars to die. They don't have contingency plans
                    for replacements. It had to kind of yank people out of their career path. We
                    then had Admiral Busey. Then, finally, Admiral Howe replaced him after a couple
                    of years. So, I had four admirals in the course of... What you had in Naples,
                    and it is worthwhile to emphasize the NATO side because that really was my job
                    (It was not the American side.), we had a command structure in Naples that had
                    other nationality officers. The chief of staff at the command was an American
                    Army three star, but his deputy was an Italian two star. We had, throughout the
                    staff of that headquarters, officers from Greece, Turkey and Italy as well as
                    U.S. and UK officers. France was still not a part of the integrated structure.
                    It had a liaison mission which was very active and very helpful to us. One of
                    the little secrets of the southern region of NATO is that France was the second
                    largest contributor of naval forces to all of our exercises, all without making
                    any great public show of this. So, you had a very integrated and international
                    command. The problem was that the Greeks and Turks barely spoke to each other
                    because of their national concerns about territory and borders and areas of
                    operation.</p>
                <p>You've asked me about Spain and Portugal. They are considered part of the
                    southern region. Spain was just getting into the military side of NATO at that
                    point. It had joined the Alliance politically as the last and 16th member after
                    we had only 15 members for all those earlier years. Spain has come along with an
                    interest in participating militarily, but I think the interest is described less
                    in a Cold War sense, even now that it's over and there isn't any Cold War. In
                    those days, the Spanish saw it as needing to keep an eye on what is going on in
                    the Mediterranean. They felt that the North African situation was very volatile,
                    could turn out bad for them, particularly if something went wrong in Morocco.
                    They were more concerned with the Western Mediterranean than anything out toward
                    the east in the region of Greece and Turkey. Portugal, although part of the
                    Southern Region, is so Atlantic that its participation in alliance military
                    stuff was really more with SACLANT than Atlantic. So, we didn't really have a
                    whole lot to do with both of those countries. Portugal did have a liaison office
                    at our headquarters. Spain was just developing one when I left. I think we come
                    to France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, let's talk about France.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>KRUSE: France was key because the French are a Mediterranean power as well as an
                    Atlantic power and a world power. I love the French and I even love their
                    “orgeil” because from the French you get a genuine “what you see is what you
                    get.” They'll give you an answer. If they have reasons they don't want to do it,
                    you may not understand them, but you know they're going to hold on. Their
                    interest in this command has been reflected these recent events in the last
                    couple of years where they have wanted to have the four star admiral in Naples
                    to be a French admiral. Of course, we're saying, “Over our dead bodies. We don't
                    do that.” Eventually, Chirac has kind of dropped off that demand. But it does
                    demonstrate the feeling that the French see the Mediterranean as vital to their
                    interests. This is not only because of oil, but because of Algeria and because
                    of the Maghreb countries and the concerns for immigration, concerns for upheaval
                    in their own country, and just generally, concerns for trying to get some kind
                    of peaceful resolution of problems in the Arab world and the Muslim world.
                    France feels that it has a role from its long history of dealing with North
                    Africa and Lebanon and it should be recognized. So, politically, they're
                    interested. Militarily, they have been very cooperative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about this cooperation? What does this
                        mean?We're talking about the time you were here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We would have an annual schedule of NATO exercises involving naval forces.
                    For example, there would always be an amphibious landing somewhere in Sicily or
                    in Southern Italy, where we would practice what we might have to do in Turkey or
                    Greece if there had been a Russian or Soviet attack. For those exercises, we got
                    a lot of activity from American naval forces and Italian forces. The Brits would
                    play sometimes, although less and less. They had few ships available. The
                    Germans were beginning to send forces down to participate for military training
                    purposes. The Greeks and the Turks would send over some forces. But more and
                    more, and as I said earlier, it came during my time, the French participated
                    even with an aircraft carrier and were second only to the U.S. It made them
                    completely familiar with the way NATO does things so that, if we ever did have a
                    real life situation that France would agree to participate in, they would know
                    how to do it.</p>
                <p>Q: What about communications and all this? For the military, communications are
                    key. If you have somebody who is out of NATO, how did that work?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: They completely accepted our way of doing things. They learned NATO
                    communications. There was no hangup for them to do things NATO's way, although
                    I'm sure Paris and the political side of France would not advertise this. But
                    they were complete team players.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Mitterrand still the President?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>KRUSE: This was Mitterrand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was a socialist regime which had for years sort of
                        bamouthed NATO and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Possibly, although they always accepted NATO and its political
                    configuration to an extent. What they objected to was any automatic French
                    military response—they didn't want any American general or the NATO Council to
                    tell them when they were going to go to war. That was a Gaullist principle which
                    all succeeding French leaders have accepted, that France will decide when it
                    goes to war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Italian role in NATO?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: The Italians were the ones that wanted to have peace. They hated to see
                    the Greeks and the Turks squabbling. They were always ready to be mediators.
                    They were providing more and more military forces. They were modernizing their
                    navy and their air force and their army. They were good team players because
                    they wanted to be a good, strong, solid member of NATO, even if sometimes the
                    appearance went beyond the actual capabilities. This is not to downplay their
                    good military capabilities. These have been superlative in recent peace-keeping
                    operations. Italians were excellent hosts to our NATO headquarters. Naples was a
                    beautiful location for NATO to have this headquarters, even though Naples was
                    chaotic.</p>
                <p>Q: Looking at Greece and Turkey, I remember, when I was in Naples, asking Admiral
                    Crowe, who was at that point the NATO commander there, about the role of the
                    Greeks and the Turks. I had served for four years in Athens at one point. He
                    just sort of shrugged his shoulders and said, “They're always at each other.”
                    What was the feeling there?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: There was great annoyance and sometimes great anger at the way
                    particularly the Greeks would try to use NATO to advance their position
                    vis-a-vis Turkey. They were very sensitive to any possible perceived slight. If
                    the Turks overflew a Greek island that happened to be three miles off the
                    Turkish mainland, this would be a virtual causi belli. They simply didn't let
                    anything go that appeared to give Turkey some advantage. It's a rather
                    vulnerable position that the Greeks had because here were these Greek islands
                    that were far closer to Turkey, sometimes within eyesight. I remember, when I
                    visited Ephesus that I could look across the harbor and see a Greek island. Of
                    course, Cyprus had been a live example of what the Greeks considered an invasion
                    by Turkish forces. That was way back in '74.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: July '74. I know it well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: You were in Athens?</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>Q: I had just left Athens. I think it was the fourteenth of July. What was your
                    impression of the caliber of the Greek officer assigned to NATO that you
                    observed and the Turkish officer?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think we have to go back just a little bit to talk about the political
                    situation. We had Papandreou. Throughout the whole time I was there, he was the
                    Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>Q: This was Andreas Papandreou.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Andreas Papandreou. He and his Pasok Party, the socialist party in Greece,
                    was having great fun with the U.S. I say “fun” because, to a certain extent, I
                    really thought the Greek position was rhetorical in trying to pretend that the
                    Cold War was a thing of the past and that we should learn to deal with the
                    Soviets in a more natural manner. He would make overtures toward the Soviets and
                    also toward the Bulgarians and other Balkan countries, in effect, pretending, as
                    I say, that the Cold War was over and we were now back to a situation which we
                    kind of have now in 1997. But we didn't have it back in 1984. He insisted on
                    Greek terms for everything, Greek terms for the Common Market, Greek terms for
                    its participation in NATO. I'm not going to get into details of the essential
                    squabble with NATO, except to say it was a question of the areas that would be
                    under the control of the NATO officer involved in the defense of Greece. The
                    Greeks because they were unhappy with the NATO proposed solutions to these
                    problems basically stayed out of NATO exercises. It made it very difficult for
                    my admiral to go over and have a decent, normal conversation with Greeks. There
                    were some things you could talk about, but the question of reestablishing a NATO
                    command, a subordinate command in Greece and in the Aegean, was not solvable in
                    our time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you, in effect, during this '84 to '88 period,
                        almoswriting Greece off?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: We didn't want to write them off. We didn't have them with us to
                    participate in the exercises. We did our best to convince them that they should.
                    To some extent, we could get them to do some things. They were very hospitable
                    when the admiral came. He would be taken and shown Greek military potential. He
                    would go up to the north in the Macedonia area of Greece and see how the forces
                    were set up to counter any possible attacks. They tried to be pro-forma
                    cooperative and hospitable. But there were these underlying issues, all of which
                    stemmed from their concern that Turkey was going to get some advantage over
                    them. That issue was clearly more important to them than cooperation with
                    NATO.</p>
                <p>Q: But I would have thought that in this thing, in a way, we could play the
                    Turkish card in NATO, say, “All right, fine. If you don't want to join our
                    exercises, that's your prerogative. Of course, we'll just have to pay a little
                    more attention to Turkey.”</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>KRUSE: We didn't want to do that. That's not the NATO way. It doesn't like to
                    play one ally off against the other. We all hoped for the better day. The
                    situation that holds today, I would presume, is somewhat different because of
                    the end of the Cold War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the perceived Soviet threat to this
                        southerflank at this '84 to '88 period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's a good question. It was, I think, a misconception. Often, I would
                    talk to the admiral about it. Washington would continue to talk about the
                    presence of the Soviet fleet in the Mediterranean. The issues involving the
                    Soviet presence were how many ships were there, and the U.S. Navy, as you know
                    probably, spent inordinate sums of money to track every Soviet ship everywhere
                    in the world. I have no idea of the cost of that operation, but I know that
                    every four star officer in the U.S., every day, is capable of learning where
                    every Soviet ship was—its long range ballistic missile submarines, and every
                    other kind of warship. We worried about the facilities that the Soviets were
                    able to use, such as from time to time, they would go into Libya. There was a
                    “Soviet base area” in Syria. To my mind, the Soviet naval presence in the Med
                    was almost inconsequential in terms of a military threat. I think any honest
                    U.S. naval officer would have to admit that if hostilities had started, before
                    the end of the day, every Soviet ship in the Mediterranean would have been wiped
                    out. Of course, the Syrians wanted to play up their close relationship with the
                    Soviets so that this would make Israel think twice before it tried to do
                    anything. You asked me about the Soviet threat. I never took the peacetime
                    Soviet naval presence in the Mediterranean as a great threat. The long-range
                    ballistic missile submarines, presumably were as capable as ours, and could have
                    threatened us. The whole idea of the Russians trying for the first time to
                    develop a worldwide fleet the same way we did worried us a lot. But when you
                    look back, you wonder how they even developed what they did, given the economic
                    condition of the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Q: Also, I would have assumed that, when you're talking about the Mediterranean,
                    I think you're talking about the Straits of Gibralter and the Bosporus. I can't
                    think of two more horrendous problems for a Soviet naval threat to the
                    Mediterranean. They have to practically pay a toll to go through, in order to
                    fight their war. They're both controlled by our NATO countries.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Particularly the Bosporus, where the Soviets, to get any ship through, had
                    to get Turkish permission because of the Montreaux Convention. That was another
                    issue as to how the Soviets appeared often to be putting pressure on the Turks.
                    When the Soviets finished the aircraft carrier that they were building, there
                    was a question of whether the Montreaux Convention would allow them to take this
                    ship through because of its size. We were always checking with the Turks to say,
                    “What do you think you're going to do?” Fortunately, the Cold War ended before
                    the ship was finished.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think they finally went through, but more or less to be
                        junkeup in Murmansk or something like that to kill off in Kiev.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Well, there was a Kiev class and then they named one afteBrezhnev. I
                    wonder where it is today?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about, as you were sitting in NATO headquarters, the
                        lanthreat into the southern flank?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: There was always the concern about Yugoslavia, whether, in fact, the
                    Soviets would get upset enough with Yugoslavia that it might do something, or
                    use Yugoslavia as a pathway to get into northern Italy. So, the Italians were
                    always keeping a close eye on what was happening in Yugoslavia. The land threat
                    was really not considered great. The Turks, of course, were concerned about
                    their situation. They from time to time would call attention to the threat they
                    thought they had from Syria, although, I think, most of it related to the Kurds.
                    At this time, the Turks were not even admitting that they had a Kurdish
                    problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Mountain Turks,” I think they were called.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right. The land threat was not considered great. We did not expect
                    that the Soviets would be coming. It was a Central Europe scenario that NATO was
                    most concerned about.</p>
                <p>Q: You mentioned Israel several times. Although this would not be under the NATO
                    hat, Israel had been touted and continues to be touted in the United States as
                    being our firm ally in the Middle East. From the vantage point of NATO South,
                    how did you look upon this?</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I think the one issue that came up regularly, in the NATO context, was
                    whether we could have some of our ships visit Israel when they were under NATO
                    command. We had an on-call force in the Mediterranean, which would bring
                    together allied ships just for a period of time every year as an exercise.
                    Whether they could call at one of the littoral ports in the southern
                    Mediterranean... No one in NATO suggested Israel as a place for such a call, but
                    we were thinking about going to Alexandria or to Tunis. So, to that extent,
                    there was a recognition that it would be good to be familiarized with the
                    southern Mediterranean and the eastern Mediterranean. Because NATO itself in
                    Brussels, at headquarters, had no dealings directly with Israel, the only thing
                    that I did get involved in, even if it wasn't really my duties, was the
                    U.S.-Israeli cooperation that the admiral was engaged in under his U.S. hat. He
                    went to Israel one time for a visit. This was a time when we were trying to find
                    ways that our forces could do more collaboration with Israel militarily. It was
                    during this period of the Reagan years when they signed the Memorandum of
                    Understanding with Israel about military cooperation. Also a standing body on
                    the political side which P/M (Bureau of Political/Military Affairs) staffs met
                    regularly with the Israelis. I'll toss in my reaction. Israel was the most
                    powerful, even though it's a small country, military force in the southern and
                    eastern Mediterranean. From a U.S.-only standpoint, because of our political
                    concerns about Israel, we were seeking ways to collaborate, cooperate with them
                    more militarily. I think, depending on who was in charge at the time and
                    depending on how much pressure came from the White House, you'd find different
                    admirals giving you different answers as to whether Israel was a strategic
                    asset, or whether it was basically something that would give us problems down
                    the road. My own view is that unless and until, Israel comes to terms with the
                    Palestinians and Syrians we should be very cautious in our military cooperation
                    with Israel.</p>
                <p>Q: In your dealings with this command, obviously, there was always the Soviet
                    threat, but no matter how you sliced it, you were sitting in the Mediterranean.
                    Essentially, I look at Algeria, I don't know what the situation was there, but
                    then you move to Libya. Then you have Syria, Israel, and Egypt, who are sort of
                    joined at the hip and don't like each other.</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>KRUSE: It really goes back to what does NATO think its role is in those out of
                    area situations. There is nothing in NATO's history or the wording of the treaty
                    that implies we should have anything to do with these areas outside the basic
                    Cold War area. To be honest with you, I don't know what in the post Cold War
                    era, in which we now find ourselves, what NATO has done in terms of its doctrine
                    regarding “out-of-area” issues. Generally, our European partners recognize that
                    instability down there in North Africa or in the Middle East is going to have an
                    impact on not only their oil, but on their citizens who happen to be in those
                    countries and just generally for regional stability. The individual members of
                    NATO are concerned, but I still think NATO is only very reluctantly going to
                    take on any duties in defending countries in the south of Europe against attacks
                    that come from outside the area. The Bosnia example, which has shown NATO to be
                    involved now, indicates that there is change. Back in my day, if there had been
                    unrest in Yugoslavia, NATO would have been very slow, if at all, to do anything
                    about it. But now, NATO, because there really isn't any Soviet bar to what we
                    are doing, has been invited to become involved in Bosnia. So, I think this is
                    all going to be new history to be written.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There were several events. There was an attack on Libya.
                        Dithat happen during your tour?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes indeed, 1986.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk a bit about the background of this and
                        youperspective on that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I may be wrong on what incident set it off, but think it wathe bombing of
                    the disco in Berlin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where some American troops were killed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right, there were Americans killed. There was evidence that perhaps
                    Libyans were behind that. I confess that I wouldn't swear to that being what
                    raised our level of anger against Libya. They also kept threatening to extend
                    their “zone of death,” as they called it, into the Mediterranean.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Gulf of Sudra and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. So, we had some aerial conflict where their planes had come out and
                    challenged ours in an area that we considered to be international waters. We
                    shot a couple down. I remember, that happened while I was in the War College.
                    So, that happened earlier in the '80s. I think it was the disco thing that led
                    us to decide to attack Libya. Frankly, I was not privy to the kind of attack
                    planning, that was done in Washington and at U.S. Navy Headquarters in London.
                    You remember, they brought the Air Force into this as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the United Kingdom.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. But most of the attack was carried by carrier planes from U.S.
                    Sixth Fleet aircraft operating in the Mediterranean. From the military
                    standpoint, we lost a U.S. Air Force plane. I forget the circumstances. But the
                    Navy attack went off with no casualties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think one American was killed and one captured or
                        somethinlike that. I may be wrong.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think that was Lebanon. I don't think the Libyans ever got one of our
                    people. But the attack then took place. I guess it really was after Qadhafi
                    himself. From what I read in the papers, they attacked where he often spends
                    time. Personally, if I had been asked about that, I would certainly have thought
                    that would not be a wise thing to do. You'd make a martyr out of him. You'd
                    inflame people who otherwise didn't like him. I'm sure the Egyptians would have
                    had to be unhappy. You have to be careful when you're throwing bombs around at
                    people. I suppose you could say, “So, what's the harm? The Libyans aren't going
                    to hurt us. They're not going to shoot our planes down. The Arabs are not going
                    to turn against us on behalf of Qadhafi, whom they consider to be crazy.” So, he
                    was a fairly easy target. One could argue that the attack has deterred the
                    Libyans from doing it again. I hope maybe it did, but I still question the
                    wisdom of going after another country's leader.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your headquarters involved in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: No, Naples headquarters was not involved at all. It was all out of London.
                    The CINC went back to London to be there during the attack.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The timing I'm not sure about, but was the Achillea
                        Laurhijacking during your time there, or was that later?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Yes, it was during my time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That at least impinged on Sicily and Sigonella and all
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering if you were involved on that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Again, because it wasn't a NATO operation, I was not directly a
                    participant in anything there. That was a tough issue because it was an
                    outrageous hijacking of a ship and then the killing of the American,
                    Klinghoffer. There was no doubt who did it. They were seen and heard. The
                    Egyptians attempted to end the affair. You might remember that the ship came
                    into Egyptian waters, I think, in Alexandria, and was still under the control of
                    the hijackers at that time. The Egyptians felt that what you should do at this
                    point was get the hijackers off the ship so there would be no more blood and
                    then deal with them later on. We took a harder line. We wanted those hijackers
                    so that when the Egyptians got the hijackers off the ship, ended the hijacking
                    event, then they were going to attempt to fly the hijackers out of Egypt. I
                    forget where they wanted to actually take them, but in effect, get them out of
                    the area. We forced the plane down that was carrying the hijackers, forced it to
                    land in Sicily. We had this very unhappy thing where the Italian air controllers
                    at that airport in Sicily were refusing to allow our forces to go into the plane
                    and get the hijackers. Eventually, it led to the hijackers being taken by
                    Italians to Rome and, soon thereafter, being allowed to go. We were very unhappy
                    with the Italian response on this. We wanted these hijackers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did that do in your perspective in NATO headquarters
                        durinthis period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: People have personal opinions. I would say that there were some military
                    who said, “These guys are bastards and so anything bad that happens to them is
                    good.” There were others who maybe were a little more sympathetic and would say,
                    “Let's just end the thing as soon as we can. These are Palestinian terrorists.
                    They have their reasons for conducting terrorist activities. Just end it.” The
                    more interesting place would have been up in Brussels out in the NATO Council.
                    Frankly, I never heard that the issue was raised by anyone in the Alliance. We
                    would probably have said, “This has nothing to do with NATO. This is a U.S.
                    action.” We had other things. There were some terrorists off Lebanon who somehow
                    were taken out on a boat and wound up, all of a sudden, with the U.S. capturing
                    them and actually flying them all the way back to the United States and the
                    terrorist actually being tried here. So, that was all Sixth Fleet activity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, the line between the Sixth Fleet and NATO was fairly
                        firm.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>Q: And necessarily so. In a way, we had the NATO side, but then we had our own
                    independent arm, which could get pretty nasty to people at times.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: You have to understand that in NATO terms, U.S. forces anywhere, be they
                    in Germany or the Sixth Fleet, are under U.S. command always until they are, as
                    the military would say, chopped to NATO for either exercise purposes or for real
                    time purposes. So, most of the time, the Sixth Fleet lived out there in a
                    U.S.-only posture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were we going through the insertion of Pershing and cruise
                        missiles into Italy during the time you were there? This would have been
                        NATO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: That indeed was, yes.</p>
                <p>Q: I wonder if you could talk a bit about the background, why we were doing that
                    and some of the politics about this and NATO and what you saw at the time.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: The whole thing came about because of the Soviets in the late '70s-early
                    '80s, developed and deployed intermediate range ballistic missiles whose range
                    would cover all of Western Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think these were the SS20s.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. As a result, in the United States, I think it really became a very
                    hot issue with the Reagan administration. I remember talking to EUR people in
                    those early 1980s, which essentially said, “Look, this is what we're all doing.
                    What we're trying to do is get the Alliance and its member countries in Europe
                    exercised about this threat and counter it by means of the emplacement of
                    equivalent missiles from our side on their territory.” So, it became an issue
                    from the top down. From the President on down, this was the EUR issue for that
                    period. It was to get agreement for INF deployment of American missiles to be
                    accepted by European allies. We got the Germans in early on. We got the Belgians
                    to accept aircraft. I don't think that they accepted any of the actual ground
                    missiles. We really put a lot of pressure on the Italians. It wasn't easy. The
                    Italians have a neuralgia about nuclear weapons, but eventually, the Italians
                    agreed to it. The base at Comiso in Sicily became one of Italy's great marks of
                    fidelity to NATO and being a good ally of the United States. I went down and
                    visited it once with the admiral before the missiles actually arrived. They put
                    the whole structure of the base in there. It was like an American town. The Air
                    Force had built everything. I don't think I saw the golf course, but I was told
                    that would be coming. We had the community center, the chapel, the housing. Here
                    it was out in the middle of nowhere in eastern Sicily, Comiso. Where did we in
                    the Southern Command fit into it? Not very much. Control of all of these
                    missiles and aircraft was out of SACEUR, the senior NATO military man back in
                    Belgium.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume the politics were carried on by the
                        ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, this was a political thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Completely. It turned out because, by the time we got them in, we were in
                    the process then of negotiating an end to INF missiles. In effect, we did away
                    with this whole class of missiles. So, eventually, we never kept the base. It
                    would be interesting for you and I to go to Comiso and see what's there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd love to! Can you talk a bit about relations where you
                        werin Naples, living, problems as you saw them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Living in Naples is an adventure—”inconvenience rightly considered.”
                    Lovely physical location. We had a very charming villa that was up on the
                    Posillipo, which looked out of our window directly at the rising sun every
                    morning over Vesuvius. So, it couldn't have been more Lord Byronesque. But
                    living in Naples had its problems. The corruption and crime and mob and traffic
                    and lack of municipal services were all pretty evident. They tell the joke about
                    two German officers, who had never been to Naples, coming down to visit our
                    command for some reason and sitting at a seafront restaurant having their
                    dinner. They were overheard to be commenting on the chaos. They were saying,
                    “How could you possibly live in a place like this?” The other one said, “But
                    what's even worse, they're so happy!” It was the favorite assignment of my wife
                    partly because the kids were grown up and gone so she could have fun. My wife,
                    it's her favorite assignment, partly because the kids were grown up and gone so
                    she could have fun. But she did a lot of things with the allied officers' wives.
                    For example, they were giving assistance to Mother Theresa's people. Because she
                    learned her Italian pretty well, she had a ball. She'd go back to Naples in a
                    flash. We made a lot of Neapolitan friends. But I have to tell you that, if I
                    were in the government in Rome and responsible for economic and other activities
                    in Naples, I'd tear my hair out. When you go south of Rome, the northerners of
                    Italy are exactly right saying, “You're entering the Middle East. It's a
                    different world.”</p>
                <p>Q: I was told when I was in Naples (This was '79 to '81-ish.) that there is not a
                    single registered glove factory in the Neopolitan area and Naples is the prime
                    producer of gloves in the world.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right.</p>
                <p>Q: Italian politics and the continual obsession of our embassy and all with the
                    infinitesimal number of gains or losses of the Communist Party, which runs
                    around 30% and goes up or down maybe one or two points and has been doing this
                    since 1948, was this going to lead to disaster or not, did that impinge on you
                    at all?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: Fortunately not. The great game of Italy, no, it did not. I should mention
                    though that you might have noticed a change in the job or at least the amount of
                    time that your successors have to spend involved in U.S. military interests. One
                    reason is that the U.S. Navy decided to change the whole configuration of its
                    presence in Naples. In addition to the NATO headquarters, we had all these
                    Americans assigned to the NATO staff, as well as U.S.-only staff because the
                    Sixth Fleet was up in Gaeta. The U.S. Navy has modernized a great deal of its
                    infrastructure in and around Naples—this has required careful dealings with
                    local Italian authorities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were also a very large Sixth Fleet responsible area
                        just outside of (Inaudible).</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>KRUSE: These were all U.S.-only. The American Navy community in Naples that was
                    devoted to U.S.-only activities was in the thousands. So, they were beginning to
                    try to rationalize this because of all the crime and the problems that people
                    were having. They first put people out in a place called Pintatamare, where a
                    lot of them were living. But the real dream, which I understand is now being
                    fulfilled, is to have a U.S. housing area sufficiently out of town that, when
                    you go home, you're not going to be bothered by the problems of Naples. They
                    changed a lot of the hospital and school, even the PX facilities, which, as you
                    know, were somehow located either within a volcanic crater or on the rim.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's all in a crater, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: It was going to be moved out to the airport area and they were going to
                    enlarge it. That involved a lot of dealings with Italians. Of course, the
                    Consulate General was deputized by the embassy to follow that issue. Then the
                    big thing was this space down in the south that NATO was going to put in when we
                    had to move our aircraft out of Spain, a place called Crotone, which involved
                    lots of dealings with Italians and local authorities. It really came into full
                    fruition in Erickson's time after Lou Galtz. He was spending an awful lot of
                    time on political/military issues. Those are chapters that, I think, are
                    closing, except for the Naples presence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '88, whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I told the admiral that I would have to leave Naples after my four years
                    came up. My counterpart up in London, Art Woodruff, was leaving the job there as
                    the political advisor to my same admiral. Frankly, that looked to be the best
                    and most attainable assignment for me. I was working with Personnel trying to
                    get something better, but nothing was working out. So, I told the admiral, if he
                    wanted me in London he would have to ask State. It was certainly not against my
                    interests to go and spend a year in London. So, with his request in the
                    Department, they agreed to have me move over to this U.S.-only job and go to
                    London in the fall of 1988.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from '88 to '89?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Right. It was at the end of that year that I retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>KRUSE: I became the political advisor to the admiral, in his hat as
                    USCINCUSNAVEUR and to the U.S.-only staff in London on U.S.-only stuff, which
                    essentially would be what the Sixth Fleet was up to on any given day.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you find that it was handy coming from where you were because you had been
                    looking at the Mediterranean to get up into the London atmosphere, where I'm
                    sure that there was a difference in attitude. They were looking at the Fulda Gap
                    and everything else like that.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: That's right, although it's true that U.S. NAVEUR, the headquarters in
                    London, recognized that Washington was most concerned about what the Sixth Fleet
                    was doing in the Mediterranean. During that year, we had more problems in
                    Lebanon. The hostage taking was in full bloom. So, we had naval forces around
                    and about. We're talking about '89 at this point. It was still hostage time, so
                    we had forces poised to support any kind of a rescue operation if we were to do
                    it. As it turned out, we didn't do that. But the focus was clearly... The Sixth
                    Fleet was concerned primarily about safety and protection of Americans in the
                    region and also any security threats that might come from either the Arab world
                    or any other part. Q: At this point, was the Iraq-Iran War still being
                    waged?</p>
                <p>KRUSE: It had ended, as I remember, in about '88. We then had about a year before
                    Saddam took his interest in Kuwait. But it was soon after the end of the
                    Iran-Iraq War that we got into this other problem of preparing for our Gulf War.
                    That really didn't begin to heat up until after I left in '89. As a
                    chronological point of reference, the Intifada had just begun in '87.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Palestinian uprising in the occupied part of
                        thEast Bank.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: Which led to many changes. It led the King of Jordan to cease to claim his
                    rights in the West Bank. It led to, I think, a whole relooking at the question
                    of Palestinian nationalism and what was going to be the final outcome of this
                    struggle between Palestinians and Israelis when you had such a clear spontaneous
                    rebellion against the occupiers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wearing the Sixth Fleet hat up in London, was this
                        youconcentration basically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I think every paper I wrote was about this concern, how the Eastern
                    Mediterranean was going to be affected by the Arab-Israeli struggle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to tap into American Middle Eastern experts
                        wheyou were doing this or were you sort of drawing on the cables and
                        all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>KRUSE: Whatever came along. I did not attempt to bring people over to the
                    headquarters who were experts. It was mostly just conversations with the
                    Admiral. This was mostly Admiral Busey, although Admiral Howe came later.
                    Admiral Howe came from the NSC, so he was totally wired into what the U.S. was
                    really going to do whether it made sense or not. He was going to do it because
                    he had to. There were slow changes in our policies. We did recognize the PLO
                    very briefly, finally, in 1988. It was the last year of George Shultz's tenure.
                    So, that gave me an entree to begin to speak about dealing more naturally and
                    normally with Palestinians rather than, “We can't even talk about it because we
                    can't deal with the PLO.” But when the CINC in London running the Sixth Fleet
                    gets the order for the use of military force from Washington, he isn't going to
                    say, “Now, wait a minute. I really think long term this is going to give us
                    trouble.” That's not what a four star is going to say at that time. He's going
                    to figure out how he can do what he's ordered to do.</p>
                <p>Q: Right. Going up to London in this '88 to '89 period feel within the
                    headquarters up there, although you were Sixth Fleet looking at the Middle East,
                    which was hot and got hotter, did you feel a feeling of sort of almost a let
                    down or a relaxation or something about what was going on? We had Gorbachev and
                    Reagan and then Bush were practically in bed with each other during that year or
                    so. The Soviet threat was obviously dwindling away.</p>
                <p>KRUSE: I remember writing a paper a year after Gorbachev came in in which I said,
                    “Let us really look at what he is doing.” He was still being dismissed in some
                    quarters as “the drugstore cowboy.” You remember that famous comment of Marlin
                    Fitzwater, Bush's press secretary. I wrote something like, “If this continues,
                    if the Perestroika and other policies continue (We already were beginning to see
                    the start of the pullout from Afghanistan.), this could be a fundamental change
                    in the Soviet Union.” What did we feel up in London? There is just no doubt that
                    operational interests were all in the Eastern Mediterranean. But there was also
                    the recognition that, if indeed our Cold War opponent was going to disappear or
                    change, then this is going to change everything down the road.</p>
                <p>I might just say (I haven't mentioned this.) that there has been a big question
                    over the years as to why U.S. Naval Forces Europe is still headquartered in
                    London when, in fact, all of its forces by and large are in the Mediterranean.
                    When the Commander in Chief NATO Forces South, became also double-hatted to be
                    Commander in Chief of U.S. Naval Forces Europe, something which occurred just
                    before I arrived in 1989, then people began to say, “Look, why do we have two
                    separate headquarters? Why are we still up in London when that's far away from
                    where we're going to go? Maybe we should bring those guys from London down?” I'm
                    told this was John Lehman's idea when he was Secretary of the Navy, to actually
                    bring the headquarters out of London. That sent waves of fear into the heart of
                    most naval officers—that they would have to leave London. So, it didn't happen,
                    although a lot of people would say that there is really no great overriding
                    reason that it continues to be in London in terms of what the U.S. Navy is doing
                    with the British anymore. But I wouldn't bet on that headquarters ever leaving
                    London.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you retired in '89.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I retired in '89.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just briefly, then what did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KRUSE: I came back to the U.S. and settled in Washington. My wife accuses me of
                    being addicted to Washington. I guess, at the moment, I don't see any other
                    place. I have been working a day or two a week as a WAE (When Actually
                    Employed). Most of my time in that capacity has been spent in the review of
                    classified documents. In my personal time, which I like to think is over half of
                    my time, I very much continue to be interested in the Middle East and, in
                    particularly, American attitudes toward the Israel-Palestinian problem and
                    American attitudes toward the Arab world in general and the Moslem world also.
                    This is something I do more in private efforts having to do with church
                    activities. But I think it's vital for our national interests, let alone for the
                    cause of justice and peace, that Americans do a better job of getting informed
                    of what our policy, as well as just the facts of the Middle East. I think our
                    press and media do a horrible job of attempting to inform Americans of what the
                    real facts are. I don't know how we can change that. No other Western country
                    sees the Middle East the way we do. I have been leading pilgrimage groups to
                    Jerusalem each year, in which I try to have American church people recognize a
                    more factual understanding of what is happening, particularly in and around
                    Jerusalem. I believe I owe that to my faith and my conscience on behalf of
                    justice. In our Foreign Service careers, we base much of our actions on what is
                    perceived as the national interest. I am persuaded however, that, at their
                    roots, all of mankind's problems are spiritual. That is part of a much larger
                    game which we ignore at our peril.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
