<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001168">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Howell S. Teeple </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>HOWELL S. TEEPLE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Earl W. Sherman</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: January 27, 1999</p>
                <p>Copyright 2000 ADST</p>
                <p>Q: My name is Earl W. Sherman, and I am the interviewer for our subject of
                    interest this morning for the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training
                    and the Foreign Affairs Oral History Project. The date is the 27th of January,
                    1999, and I have the pleasure of working with Mr. Howell S. Teeple, whose age is
                    77, retired from the United States Department of State and the Foreign Service.
                    Howell was born in Dallas, Texas. Good morning to you, Howell.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Good Morning.</p>
                <p>Q: And we're certainly pleased that you can join us for this interview for the
                    Oral History Project. In discussing our objectives here today, certainly one of
                    the points of interest is to identify you by the usual statistics, that you are
                    age 77, and that leads me to ask the question when did you retire from the U.S.
                    Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I retired in 1980 after 35 and a half years of service. That included my
                    military service, of course. I had two and a quarter years in the U.S. Army
                    during World War II.</p>
                <p>Q: That is a rather unusually length of time for service. I certainly feel that I
                    should join others to commend you for that length of time in the Service. And
                    where did you start?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I started in Korea. That was my first overseas assignment. I worked there
                    in the Information and Cultural Program of the Department of Defense. It was
                    [during] the military occupation of Korea. We were actually Department of Army
                    civilians, and we went to Korea with the idea of opening an embassy in a year or
                    two. We took over the information and educational programs from the military
                    when the embassy opened.</p>
                <p>Q: Certainly that's a vital part of our interest in your history program about
                    what you've accomplished in the service, but prior to that it might be pertinent
                    to get some of the early history of your life. You were born in Dallas, Texas, I
                    understand, and were you a member of a large family, small family?</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was born in Dallas, yes, and had a brother and two sisters. My father
                    died when I was only eight years old, unfortunately, and my mother only lived to
                    be only 56. She died of breast cancer when I was 25. We grew up in a very nice
                    area of Dallas called Highland Park and went to a wonderful high school there
                    that was rated one of the 10 best high schools in the United States at that time
                    by Life magazine. You had to take Latin or Greek, and you had to take three
                    years of math - I took four - and you had to take four years of English, as well
                    as a foreign language also. So it was a very good preparation for a
                    university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What language did you specialize in in high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I took Latin, like everyone else in my school. I took threyears of Latin
                    and that was it. After Cicero, I left Latin.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find later on that Latin had been helpful to
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, it was very helpful, especially in English composition, and then in
                    studying French, which I studied in college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a point of interest, did they have any type of cadet or
                        ROTC [Reserve Officer Training Corps] training in your school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: They did have ROTC at Highland Park High School. I wasn't a member of it,
                    though. I never did join the ROTC in high school but I had to be in the ROTC for
                    two years at my university.</p>
                <p>Q: Following that very interesting program that you had in what appears to have
                    been an outstanding type of high school training, did you move directly into
                    academia and go to the university?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I went to a university after graduating from high school. I was very
                    interested in studying journalism, and I went to Louisiana State University
                    [LSU] in Baton Rouge starting in the fall of '39, and graduated in January of
                    '43. I had to take a three-and-a-half-year abbreviated college career because
                    the draft board was breathing down my neck. I went to summer school at LSU in
                    1942 to make up enough credits to graduate in January. It was the first midterm
                    graduation that the university ever had. Then I went into the Army in March of
                    1943.</p>
                <p>Q: Were you able to follow through with your special interest in journalism? Did
                    you have an opportunity to work with the paper there in the university?</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: I did work on the college paper, of course. They had a paper called The
                    Daily Reveille, and it was good training. And then we had to work at the local
                    downtown paper. I worked on The Baton Rouge State Times during my junior year,
                    and then during your senior year you were sent out for a period of a month to
                    work in a local paper, usually in the rural area of Louisiana. I went down to a
                    place called Plaquemine, Louisiana, and worked on the local paper there for a
                    month, to get on-hand experience in a working newspaper. LSU had a very good
                    journalism school, and while all my family had gone to the University of Texas,
                    it didn't have a journalism school when I was entering college. They had a
                    journalism department, I believe, but I wanted to go to a full-fledged
                    university journalism school, and that's why I selected LSU.</p>
                <p>Q: When you had completed your work at the university, did you take up graduate
                    work, or was that not possible because of conditions at the time and the war in
                    the way?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I got out of the Army in December of 1945, just before Christmas. I had a
                    lot of points from my overseas Army combat service. They gave points for the
                    number of active combat days you had in the Army, and I had 85 points, which
                    enabled me to be discharged early, although the war in Europe, for all intents
                    and purposes, was over in April of '45. I went home after discharge at Fort Sam
                    Houston in San Antonio, Texas, and went to Dallas. I remember going home on the
                    Greyhound bus and getting home very early in the morning and just going into the
                    house. At that time nobody locked their doors in Dallas, and I just walked in at
                    about five o'clock in the morning and surprised my mother and sister that I was
                    out of the Army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any special recollections about your
                        experience therin service, having been apparently in combat units?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was in the Army field artillery battalion. When I got out of basic
                    training, I was assigned to a field artillery battalion. They were known as
                    school troops at Fort Sill, Oklahoma, training the OCS [Officer Candidate
                    School] students on artillery warfare. It had been the old National Guard unit
                    from th28th Division in Pennsylvania, but it was redesignated as the 193rd Field
                    Artillery Battalion. It was sort of a bastard outfit, as they called it, since
                    it got cut out of the 28th Division when they triangularized the divisions from
                    four battalions to three. But it was a crack outfit and mostly National Guard
                    people with a lot of experience, and that's why they were made school troops at
                    Fort Sill.</p>
                <p>Q: Howell, I'm wondering if you recall from your experience there in service
                    during the war and all of the chaos that you had seen there in Europe as a
                    result of action in the war - did that have any special effects on you, or was
                    it of some value? Did it give you a more mature viewpoint, do you think? Did it
                    relate in some fashion to the profession you had selected, journalism, for
                    insistence?</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Not directly at first, but of course, it did give me wonderful
                    perspective, as we were sent to England. I was always interested in traveling,
                    and this was my first time overseas. We trained there for several months with a
                    British group and then just an American group. Then we went over into France
                    some time after D-Day [the allied invasion of Europe on June 6, 1945].
                    Fortunately, we didn't go in on D-Day. We joined the 1st Infantry Division,
                    known as the Big Red One. In the Army, I wanted to work on The Stars and
                    Stripes, and I tried to get out of the artillery to pursue my journalistic
                    pursuits, but I was unable to do that. I stayed with the artillery battalion my
                    whole career in the Army, and I certainly got a great insight into Europe at
                    war. Conditions in England were very bad at that time, with rationing and the
                    bombing of cities by the Germans, and it wasn't the best time to be traveling
                    abroad, but at least I got to see the people and many places in England. Then we
                    went through France, and were the first American troops into Belgium and the
                    first America troops into Germany. That was at Aachen, Germany. Our artillery
                    battalion was [in] back of the 1st Infantry Division, thank goodness. We were
                    behind them all the way through France and Belgium and into Germany as artillery
                    support.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, do you recall seeing one of the publications that was such a favorite -
                    that's from my own experience, I recall - Yank Magazine and Bill Mauldin's
                    cartoons?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Oh, yes, I was well acquainted with Yank Magazine. That was published, I
                    believe, in the States, however, but The Stars and Stripes was published in
                    several places in Europe, and was a daily newspaper that was delivered to the
                    troops. And a lot of well- known journalists worked for it. But I was unable to
                    get with it. That would have been my ideal, to work for The Stars and
                    Stripes.</p>
                <p>Q: I refer to a question of a moment ago about how your experience in the Army
                    might have led you to select journalism even more intensely, being more
                    interested in it as a result of your experiences in Europe, and if that interest
                    continued to grow as you finished your Army service. Did you go to school
                    again?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: No, after I got out of the Army, I was intent on going to work as soon as
                    possible, and I got a very good job with a radio station in Dallas, KRLD. It was
                    a 50,000-watt CBS [Columbia Broadcasting System] affiliate. I got a job as a
                    continuity writer there, and was very pleased to work in radio, although the pay
                    was quite low. It started out at $30 a week in 1946. This was in January of '46.
                    I got out of the Army in December of '45 and went to work immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the station again, KRL-</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: KRLD. It's still going strong in Dallas, a very big station. You can hear
                    it all over Texas and up into the Midwest. Now it's an all-news station. When I
                    was there, it was before television, of course, but I wanted to work in radio or
                    newspaper.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, this certainly would be an interesting formative period of your early
                    life for the work that ultimately you did for the U.S. Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was always interested in the news and world events, whicI followed
                    rather closely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And for what length of time were you associated with the
                        station?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I worked there for about a year and a half, and then I got an opportunity
                    to go to New York City to work on that quiz program - we sort of laugh at it now
                    - called The Quiz of Two Cities. And it was a summer replacement program on CBS,
                    and another fellow and I wrote the program. We had done the program in Dallas,
                    and at that time it was just between Dallas and Fort Worth, The Quiz of Two
                    Cities. It was a program of questions and answers. I went up in June of '47 and
                    it was on several cities all over the country then, select cities like
                    Chicago-Milwaukee, Oakland and San Francisco, New York and Boston, and
                    Washington and Baltimore - sort of [paired] cities. We got people from each city
                    to vie against each other answering questions. There were prizes, of course, and
                    great competition between the cities. That was a wonderful experience for
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I would think so, and excellent preparation for the
                        worthat you did later, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Well, somewhat, although I must say, the questions we wrotand asked
                    weren't all that substantive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not too profound at that time-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: No.</p>
                <p>Q: -but nevertheless a contact with the public and the interviewing process and
                    the search for information and getting people interested in what your projects
                    were.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes. We had questions on many subjects, of course, history, literature,
                    etc. We used to go to The World Almanac quite often to get questions and
                    answers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was living in New York City at that time still the great
                        thrilthat so many found it to be?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was very interesting. I was very young then. I was only 25 years old.
                    And it was a rather exciting experience for me. I was in the big city, and at
                    that time New York was safe; there was no problem of any violence. I used to go
                    to the Broadway shows, musicals and plays, and saw a lot of theater and enjoyed
                    that part of New York.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That seemed to be such a vibrant time in the history of
                        New YorCity.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, it was right after the war, and we had a 13-week contract, as I
                    recall, and they said if the radio program was a success, they would possibly
                    continue it through the regular season for 26 weeks, from September through May.
                    But unfortunately, the program didn't continue. It was just a summer
                    replacement, and so I was out of a job in New York after that period, in August
                    of '47.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you continued then to live in New York City?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I continued, and I was doing a little freelance work in radio, writing
                    some continuity for musical programs, but then I was looking for a job and I
                    heard about the overseas positions in the Information and Cultural Program of
                    the government. I went down and applied for one. As I recall, the application
                    office was in Rockefeller Center, at the Department of Army. I was interviewed
                    and took a written test and an oral test, too. Two weeks later, I got a telegram
                    under my door, “You have been selected to go to Seoul, Korea, as a radio officer
                    with the Army Information Service.” I was to be an advisor to the Korean
                    Broadcasting System.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an interesting title.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: So in September of '47, I went to Seoul, Korea, which was under U.S.
                    occupation at that time. General Hodges was the commanding general, but the
                    military occupation was being turned over to Korean civilian control. The
                    Department of State was to open an embassy in Seoul and take over from the
                    military. I remember taking the train from New York City to San Francisco on my
                    way to Seoul, Korea, in September, '47. Then I flew in Army aircraft - this was
                    before the separation into the Army and the Air Force - to Hawaii. I stayed
                    there for a while waiting for the next plane to go to Japan. We flew to several
                    small islands - Johnston Island, Kwajalein Island, and Guam - to get to Japan.
                    So that was an extensive flying experience, flying in a DC-6, four-motored
                    transport planes. We finally got to Japan and stayed awhile observing General
                    MacArthur's military occupation. Eventually, I flew to Korea to take up my
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any indications at the time you were there of
                        thstruggle that was to come in '51?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Actually 1950, the war broke out, in June, June 25th, 1950. The Japanese
                    had occupied Korea since the early 1900s and they only left at the end of World
                    War II. Korea was a poor country, and it was divided at the 38th parallel. We
                    were very conscious of this because the north part of Korea at that time
                    generated all the electricity for the whole country and quite often the North
                    Koreans would turn off the electricity in Seoul and other South Korean places,
                    just to let us know they were in charge up there. If some ripple happened to
                    their dislike, they would turn off the electricity for three or four hours, and
                    we were in a fix. We were very conscious of the Russians, who were occupying
                    North Korea, while the Americans were occupying South Korea. I never got to
                    North Korea, but we did have a United Nations [UN] mission in Seoul, whose
                    members went up to Pyongyang periodically. I knew those UN people and got to
                    talk to them and heard about the northern part of the country.</p>
                <p>Q: In your work, was the language problem severe? Did you have interpreters
                    there?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We had interpreters, and I had a Korean language tutor. I had to learn
                    Korean on the job. Every morning, from 7:30 to 9:00, I studied Korean with my
                    tutor and I got somewhat conversant in it, although never learned to read or
                    write the language. I was working right at the Korean Broadcasting System
                    advising them on how to operate a radio station, because they had little
                    experience. The Japanese had run all radio up until World War II ended. I had
                    four or five other Americans working for me at that young age, so it was an
                    enviable position. We set up a program schedule, and, of course, we had certain
                    propaganda programs that were beamed to North Korea, special commentaries every
                    night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. This would resemble in some aspect a Voice of
                        Americ[VOA] approach?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: No, it wasn't like the Voice of America at all. The Voice of America was
                    broadcasting from New York to Korea at that time, and the signal wasn't good.
                    VOA had a completely separate operation, which was under the State Department.
                    Then on January 1, 1948, we opened the American embassy in Seoul, Korea, and I
                    was asked to join the embassy group there, along with three other information
                    and cultural types in our previously Army office. The PAO [public affairs
                    officer] was a wonderful man, Jim Stewart. He was my mentor and taught me so
                    much. He'd been a Time correspondent in China. He was born in Japan of
                    missionary parents, both he and his wife. The first ambassador was John Muccio,
                    an outstanding Foreign Service officer. The DCM [deputy chief of mission] was
                    Everett Drumright. One of the distinctions of the embassy at that time - it was
                    mostly all male, except for some secretaries, and mostly all bachelors. The
                    ambassador was a bachelor; the DCM was a bachelor; Jim Stewart, while he was
                    married, his wife wasn't there - she was in California; and I was a bachelor.
                    But after the McCarthy hearings of that period, when the Senator was commenting
                    on homosexuals in the State Department, suddenly all of us got married. I
                    actually got married some years later, but I remember the ambassador married a
                    year or two after I left the post in 1950, and so did Drumright, the DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's interesting you mentioned Mr. Drumright because he
                        has been a member in the past of the retired Foreign Service group that we
                        know here in San Diego.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, until he passed away a couple of years ago. I used to see him at our
                    Foreign Service luncheons in San Diego, and I met his wife there. I had never
                    met his wife previously.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and when was it that you completed your work there in
                        Seoul?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was scheduled for transfer in January of 1950 but was first sent down
                    to the Philippines, to Manila. Being a bachelor, they sent me there to fill in
                    for some chap in the information program who was on leave.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was to Manila?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, this was in Manila, and then I went over in a similar position to
                    Hong Kong, where we opened the first American Library in Hong Kong in 1950, in
                    an old movie building there on Nathan Road. Then I went on home leave. I was
                    then assigned to the Voice of America in New York, which pleased me very much. I
                    joined VOA in April, 1950 in New York, where they were broadcasting on 57th
                    Street and Broadway in three different buildings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And for what length of time did you stay there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: I stayed at the Voice of America quite a while, because this was my
                    field, interest and my liking. I stayed in New York from 1950 to 1954. The Voice
                    was transferred to Washington in 1954. I was the executive producer for the Far
                    East Division. At first, we only had only Chinese and Korean language broadcasts
                    when I joined, and then we added Southeast Asian languages. We added Vietnamese,
                    Malay, Indonesian, and Thai and I was the chief of production for all VOA
                    programs in those languages.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, it would seem to me that the wonderful experience that you had in Korea,
                    having gone from New York City earlier, across the country, and then flying
                    through the islands over to Seoul and then having that wonderful experience of
                    working there with the South Koreans and setting up in broadcasting, must have
                    been invaluable when working for VOA.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was. And I was one of the few people at the Voice who had had any
                    Foreign Service experience. They were mostly local people in New York who were
                    experienced in radio. Of course, all the broadcasters, the people on the air,
                    were native-language employees. We didn't have any Americans broadcasting in Far
                    East languages, but Americans were in charge in the production and the writing
                    of programs.</p>
                <p>Q: I see. In your work, and in setting up all of this variety of programs and in
                    the variety of Asian languages, was it difficult to obtain people? How did they
                    screen them, for instance?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: When they enlarged the Far East Division to include Southeast Asian
                    languages, they sent a recruitment team to Vietnam, Thailand, Malaysia, and
                    Indonesia, with an FBI [Federal Bureau of Investigation] agent. They went to the
                    local radio stations in the countries and hired on contract employees from the
                    local radio stations to come work at the Voice of America on two- or four-year
                    contracts. The FBI man cleared them on the spot. That was the way VOA hired
                    Asian broadcasters. Later on, some people living in the U.S. would apply -
                    Chinese and Koreans and South Vietnamese - to work at VOA, but they had to have
                    broadcast or journalistic experience, usually, to qualify. All had to go through
                    the usual security clearance. This was right after and during the McCarthy
                    hearings, and the State Department was extra sensitive about security
                    clearances.</p>
                <p>Q: Did you feel that, from your experience in Asia and in South Korea where you
                    were in daily contact with the language, that once you were in New York and in
                    Washington working in the VOA programs, that you had some control of Asian
                    languages that gave you some rapport with the people that you worked with
                    directly?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I had a limited speaking ability in Korean, but there were Americans on
                    every language desk who were fluent in the language. They had to check the
                    translation of all scripts and check the broadcasts as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were working probably more directly with
                        programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was working in the studios putting on the broadcasts, yes. We had to
                    get the news together. Every broadcast started with the news. We tried to be
                    objective with the news. Then we would usually have a commentary and then
                    features. And this was in the days before tape, so we recorded everything on
                    disks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that interesting. That's a rather rudimentary
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We even put on dramas and had to record them on disk. You didn't have the
                    beauty of being able to edit very often, or not at all, so you had to rehearse
                    extensively.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were live, and that was it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: The news was always live, but features and commentaries werusually
                    recorded before broadcasts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Later on we did get tape at VOA. First it was wire, and then the regular
                    tape we are still using. Productions became very adaptable with tape, after when
                    we moved to Washington, after 1954.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, from those very early times, working with VOA, it must be interesting to
                    look back and see what magnitude of increase in the VOA's range and magnitude of
                    its influence worldwide.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: VOA has always been popular in Asia, I'm glad to say. We had good signals
                    into China, especially, and into Korea. We had many listeners there - we know
                    because we got a lot of mail. Even during the communist period in China, we got
                    mail, and also from North Korea as well. VOA had a large listening audience,
                    especially in Korea and China.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, as a part of that, it seems to me when I had heard VOA from overseas in
                    posts that I enjoyed, VOA would have listener letters. Was there any recognition
                    of people sending in, by person, that is, recognizing the person's name and
                    saying, “We have a letter from...”?</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, there were programs like that. They had programs where they
                    acknowledged a listener's letter and encouraged people to write in. And
                    sometimes VOA had contests where they would give away radios or calendars. We
                    got a lot of mail, and there was a section that dealt with the mail, did
                    research on mail and tried to analyze the mail.</p>
                <p>Q: From that time you spent in Washington and with VOA, you were working with
                    programming. Can you remember any particularly incidents related to that
                    critical time and the war in Asia?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, one of the most critical times was shortly after I joined VOA in New
                    York at the outbreak of the Korean War. That happened June 25, 1950. It was a
                    Sunday morning, I remember, when I heard the news on the radio. I rushed to the
                    studios immediately from the Brooklyn Heights place where I was living, and
                    arranged immediately to go on the air with a Korean language special program,
                    mostly news, of course. That was a critical time. There were others, too,
                    similar, during the '50s. The outbreak of the Korean War was the one crisis time
                    I remember so distinctly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any TDY? For instance, did they send you back
                        tAsia for any particular special-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I didn't go, but we did send people from the Far East Division out to
                    Korea as correspondents. A chap who worked with me, Bob Lasher, I remember,
                    volunteered immediately to go to Korea as a correspondent for VOA during the war
                    period. He had never been overseas before, but did well as a foreign
                    correspondent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had been in VOA in Washington, I believe, for as I
                        recall...What length of time were you there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I stayed in Washington from '54 to '59. USIA [United States Information
                    Agency] Personnel was continually asking me to go overseas during this period.
                    We transferred from State to USIA when they established a separate agency in
                    '53. At one time they had me going to Teheran as information officer, but it
                    didn't work out. In 1959, I was selected to go to India as information officer
                    for USIS [United States Information Service]/New Delhi, and had the designation
                    also as press attach�.I was married then. I met my wife, Jane, in Washington in
                    January 1957. We got married on June 1st, 1957 and had a nine-month-old baby,
                    James Leland Teeple, when we went to New Delhi in April of 1959.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this opens up a whole new chapter in your career, does
                        it not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Exactly. It was the first post I'd been to overseas married, with a
                    family, and yes, it was quite a different situation for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the name of the ambassador then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: At the time we arrived in '59, the ambassador was Ellsworth Bunker, a
                    well-known ambassador, and an outstanding man. It was such a pleasure to be
                    there and to work under Ambassador Bunker. We had three really outstanding
                    ambassadors in India during my period there, from '59 to '63. We had John
                    Kenneth Galbraith following Ambassador Bunker, and then we had Chester Bowles
                    after Galbraith left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, those were certainly three well-known and
                        illustrioufigures in American history.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Indeed. I had quite a bit of contact with the ambassadors,being in the
                    press and press attach�.</p>
                <p>Q: Of those three, Howell - we're talking about Ellsworth Bunker and Chester
                    Bowles and John Kenneth Galbraith - of those three, working with them, probably
                    more intimately than some of the others, which one of those three impressed you
                    the most?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Ambassador Galbraith was very impressive, of course, and he was
                    interested in the press. He liked to have press conferences, and he was such a
                    figure in his own right and had an outstanding reputation as a scholar and
                    economist. He also was well connected with the White House at that time, the
                    Kennedy administration. Chester Bowles was most impressive also. I only had
                    about six or seven months with Ambassador Bowles. We left India in 1963, about
                    six, seven months after he had arrived. Ambassador Bunker was the great diplomat
                    of the three. They were all quite different in their approach, completely
                    different, in fact. Ambassador Bunker was a very smooth, suave diplomat and got
                    great respect from the Indians. It was exciting times in India then because
                    Nehru was alive, and his daughter Indira was his hostess, more or less, because
                    he was a widower. We had a large USIS establishment in India. Ken Bunce was the
                    first PAO, with John Lund as the deputy when I arrived. Then Bill Weathersby
                    came in, and later went on to be ambassador to Sudan and then went back to India
                    as DCM. That is unusual in the Foreign Service - to become an ambassador and
                    then go back as a DCM. Barry Zorthian was our deputy PAO under Bill Weathersby.
                    We had outstanding people with the embassy and with USIS in India during my
                    tenure - 1959-1963.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, among those leaders who were not from the United
                        States,Admiral Mountbatten was there at that time, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Admiral Mountbatten was in India at the time of partition. He did come
                    out to India, again while we were there, and we met him. Lady Mountbatten used
                    to come out quite often, and she used the same dentist we used, so we would get
                    all the news about Lady Mountbatten from our dentist.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, there was some very interesting linkage, was there
                        not,between Lady Mountbatten and Nehru?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: There was. She was a good friend of Nehru's, and he had her out every
                    year as his guest. They were very friendly and there were many rumors linking
                    them romantically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Those were exciting times in India, and also while we were there,
                    President Eisenhower visited India. He was the first U.S. president to visit
                    India. Unfortunately, just as he was coming, I came down with hepatitis. We had
                    been over to the Maharaja's palace in Jaipur visiting and I apparently got
                    hepatitis there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So India and the fact that President Eisenhower had come,
                        as wcontinue:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, and unfortunately I came down with hepatitis during that time and
                    was unable to work. It was one of the biggest news events of my career, and I
                    missed it, the President of the United States coming to India. As I said, we'd
                    been over to the Maharaja of Jaipur's palace, which he'd turned into a luxury
                    hotel. It wasn't opened to the general public, but they would take people in who
                    were “invited,” so to speak. People from embassies could go stay there, and it
                    was a lovely place. They assured us that the water was boiled, but it wasn't,
                    apparently, because I got hepatitis exactly three weeks after coming back from
                    Jaipur and was laid low for the Eisenhower visit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I ask the question, wasn't it common practice at that time
                        tkeep people confined to bed in order to handle hepatitis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Oh, yes. I was in bed for six weeks, and the doctor said, “Don't get up
                    except to go to the bathroom.” I said, “What about shaving?” He said, “Let your
                    wife shave you.” I said, “Oh, no.” So I grew a beard. When I went back to the
                    office after six weeks, no one recognized me with my full beard.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Q: Well, isn't that something of real importance for those outgoing officers from
                    the State Department representing the U.S. overseas, that health hazards enter
                    into the lives of virtually every single Foreign Service person in one fashion
                    or another-TEEPLE: Indeed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: -because of the very limited health facilities people have
                        ithose overseas countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We did have an American doctor at the embassy and an American nurse, but
                    the doctor was assigned as the regional medical officer. He traveled throughout
                    the area covering other posts, and we used a list of qualified Indian doctors.
                    There were some good doctors in India, American-trained. My doctor - I remember
                    his name - was Dr. Mehra, who had been American-trained, and he's the one that
                    put me to bed for six weeks when he said, “You've got jaundice.” Health hazards
                    were a major problem. Our young son got very sick in India at one time, and it
                    was critical, but he survived. India was a difficult post for maintaining one's
                    good health because of the enormous population and different hygienic
                    practices.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Amoebic dysentery seems to have been something that was so
                        commoin so many of these locations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We used to call it “Delhi belly.” Oh, yes, that was common
                    occurrence.</p>
                <p>Q: On reflection, fortunately there seems to have been, since that time that you
                    and I were overseas, many new medications now available to deal very quickly
                    with common maladies.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, fortunately all the antibiotic drugs had come to the fore and many
                    other types of medicines which have been a great help to people living in Third
                    World countries.</p>
                <p>Q: When you were the IO [information officer] and the press attach� there in New
                    Delhi, did you have a staff of some size? I would expect-TEEPLE: I had a staff
                    of one American, an assistant information officer, and quite a large national
                    staff. There were two press attach�s in New Delhi. There was the press attach�
                    at the embassy, who worked directly with the ambassador, and I was at USIS and
                    handled the local press, the vernacular press, the Hindi papers and Urdu papers
                    and English papers. India had a very active press. It was interesting to work
                    with those chaps. Many were well-educated. They'd been to Cambridge or Oxford,
                    mostly British-trained, and worked on the English newspapers. And then there was
                    a large vernacular press. I dealt with the local press and got to travel around
                    all over the country, visiting newspaper editors to get them to use our
                    materials. I must say, the personal approach to Indian editors paid off and I
                    was able to place a great many USIS press articles and features in newspapers
                    and magazines.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that the rail system in India was one of
                        reallexceptional size and-</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was excellent at that time. The British had put in the infrastructure
                    during their 400 years of occupation, so to speak, and India had a fine rail
                    system. I understand it's changed since then. We did travel by train quite
                    often, but we flew most places because India's a large country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What part of India did you find to be of really superior
                        interesor of intense interest? You were posted to New Delhi most of the
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I was in New Delhi, and it was a very interesting post. As I said, Nehru
                    was alive. There was a very active press there. We had many foreign
                    correspondents from England, the United States, Germany, France, and Japan, so
                    it was a busy press operation. I think at that time USIS India was one of the
                    largest Information and Cultural Programs in the world. It had a large American
                    library and a big exchange program, the Fulbright Program. We had a lot of
                    visitors come through the post for lectures and exhibits. It was a very active
                    post. We participated in the World Agricultural Fair, which was held in New
                    Delhi in 1960. We had an American pavilion there which we publicized and
                    promoted. India was an exciting place with so many different cultural
                    activities. We enjoyed India very much. Of course, I was in India during the
                    height of the Cold War and we were very competitive with the Soviet Union in our
                    information and cultural programs. The Russians had a large press and
                    information operation in New Delhi, quite of bit of it covertly done, which made
                    the competition complex and involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have much contact with your counterparts from
                        othegovernments that were represented there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, especially with the British. We had good contacts with the British
                    Information Service. They had an active information program also. They also had
                    the British Council, which dealt with cultural and exchange programs as well as
                    library operations. We had limited contact with the Soviet embassy press people
                    and on the surface were friendly with them. Some of the Russian correspondents
                    were KGB [Soviet security service] operatives, working under a Russian news
                    agency, Novosti, and while we were cordial with them, we remained wary of
                    them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you had English teaching programs such as our
                        owbinational center programs.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: We didn't have a big English teaching program in India because English
                    was the lingua franca of all the educated people at that time. They kept saying,
                    in 10 or 15 or 20 years, English would not be the dominant language, but it has
                    remained so, I believe, because of the diverse sections of the country all
                    speaking different dialects and languages. For instance, down in south India,
                    the Telugu and Tamil languages are completely alien to Hindi and Bengali in
                    north India, as well as different from Urdu and Gujarati. English has been the
                    glue that's held the country together, so to speak, language-wise. Therefore,
                    the English-language press and English education has been maintained. I don't
                    think English is as strong as when we were there, however.</p>
                <p>Q: Considering the great size, the magnitude of the U.S. representation in India,
                    what impression did you have of the people that you were working with that came
                    from the U.S. at the time that you were there? Was it a fledgling group? Was it
                    because of the expansion of the U.S. representation there?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: No, we had outstanding people in the embassy and in USIS, as I mentioned,
                    by the ambassadors who were there, Bunker, Galbraith, and Chester Bowles. The
                    same way, down the line, the career people were very good, some really
                    outstanding people. India was an important post. It was one of the largest
                    American embassies. And in USIS we had equally high-level people. So from that
                    standpoint it was a vital post and very competitive for the American officers
                    assigned to New Delhi.</p>
                <p>Q: Considering the experience you had before you went to India and the variety of
                    things in information services that you enjoyed prior to going to New Delhi, did
                    you find those who were sent out by the Department to work with you directly had
                    ample training and that they were able to fit in quickly with your programs?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Generally, yes. We didn't have too many Hindi speakers. Incidentally, I
                    had to go to Hindi language training at FSI prior to my assignment to India. I
                    spent a year at FSI studying Hindi, and I must say, it was pure torture. I did
                    manage to pass the vocabulary and the conversation tests. I never got literate
                    in the language, of course, but then on arriving in India, I found I didn't use
                    Hindi that much, because the people we were contacting were educated people and
                    all spoke very good English.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, in your Hindi training at the Department for that year, how much area
                    study did they throw in with the actual language?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: There was no area studies. I took a separate course in area studies for
                    two weeks, I believe, but the Hindi language was strictly language, and it was
                    intense. It was six hours a day.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's heavy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was four hours with a lecturer, and there were just one or two others
                    in the class with me; four hours of tutoring, and then two hours on the tapes
                    every day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's intense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Intense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that there was some success in that degree of
                        timinvolved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Well, I learned to speak Hindi on a limited basis. I wasn'fluent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the Indians respond to this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Very much. Yes, they loved if you spoke their language, ocourse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were patient?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: That was a benefit. We did have some excellent Hindi speakers in the
                    embassy and in USIS. We had Tom Pinch, who was very fluent in Hindi, and we had
                    people in the embassy who were very fluent, but they took the two or three-year
                    course.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, one of the aspects of representing the U.S. overseas that I found in my
                    own experience, if I may take just a moment for that, was that anyone who came
                    armed with, for instance, a talent in music, automatically had a ticket into
                    most homes or most target audiences that he might wish to contact. I always
                    regretted that in my own experience, that I had not learned the guitar or
                    learned the piano or something involving music. I don't know if you share that
                    at all.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, it certainly gave you an entr�e into a lot of places if you had
                    musical ability. I remember a chap we had in Korea who was a really outstanding
                    musician. He was asked to be the conductor of the Korean Symphony Orchestra. He
                    was an accomplished musician, Rolf Jacoby.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, from that time that you were in India, for what
                        length otime was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: We were there for a four year assignment. We had twtwo-year tours with
                    home leave in between.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see, you went to India in '59.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We left in '63.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1963. You went where in '63?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We went to Turkey. I had asked for a branch post. I wanted to be a branch
                    PAO. I found out a branch post was just as busy or busier than an embassy press
                    job. Originally, I was selected to got to a branch post in Iran, Isfahan. But
                    suddenly I was reassigned to Adana, Turkey, because the BPAO [branch public
                    affairs officer] that had just arrived there, Jim Brophy, died tragically in a
                    drowning accident. I was very upset about the assignment at first, because I'd
                    never heard of Adana, and I was interested in going to Iran. But I went to
                    Adana. It was a consular post, and we had a very large U.S. air base adjoining
                    Adana, Incirlik Air Force Base, which is still going strong. Much of my duties
                    was handling community affairs between the airmen and the Turkish populace in
                    Adana. Adana was a town with almost a million population. It was in southeastern
                    Turkey. We could drive in six hours to Beirut from there. It was a wonderful
                    post from that point of view, and we went to Beirut several times. Or you could
                    drive up to Ankara, which was also a six-hour drive, and onto Istanbul. We used
                    to say we were in the armpit of the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can't picture easily how driving from Turkey down to
                        Beirut.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: You had to go through Syria and then into Lebanon and intBeirut. The
                    roads were quite good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see, my, you were around the Mediterranean.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: At first I was disappointed in the assignment, but then I got to like
                    Turkey quite a bit. I got to like the Turkish people very much. And again,
                    immediately, I had to try to learn the language, and the consul and I had a
                    tutor every morning from eight o'clock to 9:30, a Turkish lady teaching us
                    Turkish, and we became somewhat conversant in the language.</p>
                <p>Q: I have a hard question for you to answer. In all of that spectrum of travels
                    and the wide variety of people and ethnicities that you've contacted, from Asia
                    clear over to Europe and all of that distance, is it reasonable to generalize
                    that practically every place you go you can adjust to people, that people are
                    somewhat the same, even though the languages and the cultures are so different,
                    that they respond to you?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: They do respond to you if you have the right approach. And that was, of
                    course, our job in USIS - public diplomacy. We were contacting people directly,
                    much more than officers in the embassy. With the libraries, the cultural and
                    exchange programs, the information programs, exhibits, and the lecturers we
                    brought in, we had intimate daily contact with the local people to schedule and
                    promote these operations as well as the audiences the programs were directed to
                    - this was public diplomacy.</p>
                <p>Q: Perhaps my question wanted to elicit, among all of these ethnics, all these
                    different countries, was there one country where people seemed to be warmer,
                    more forthcoming than some of the others?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: They're all a little different, I must say, but the Indians were very
                    affable and very easy to get to know. They liked Americans at that time, pretty
                    much. They tried to emulate us. The Turkish people at the beginning of my tour
                    were more standoffish, and were harder to get to know. I remember it was some
                    time before we were invited into a Turkish home after arriving at the post, but
                    once we got to know the people and associated with them, we found them very
                    warm. We had some good close Turkish friends and enjoyed them very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the language, or rather several different
                        languages iTurkey, involved - Kurds, for instance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: There is a Kurdish language, but Kurds there all spoke Turkish. There was
                    a large Kurdish population in southwest Turkey where we were and we had Kurdish
                    people working in our house. But they knew Turkish. Turkish was the lingua
                    franca language. Not as many Turks spoke English as in India, and that was
                    another reason to try to learn the language. They spoke actually quite a bit of
                    French. Southeast Turkey was in the French Levant area after World War I.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you develop any skill with Turkish, or was it really
                        todifficult or you were too busy to work with the new language?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I had a limited knowledge of Turkish, yes. I wasn't fluent at all. The
                    Turks appreciated Americans trying to speak with them, and we had this tutor
                    every morning, Tom Davis, the consul and myself, and we picked up the
                    conversation somewhat. But, we relied a lot on interpreters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find for the family all of the necessities, for
                        instance,education for the children, schools there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: There was a school at the air base in Turkey. Our oldest boy was in
                    kindergarten there. We had one son, born in India, and when we got to Turkey he
                    was only nine months old. So he wasn't of school age, but our oldest son did go
                    to the Air Force school at Incirlik Air Base, and that was fortunate. He was in
                    kindergarten, first, and second grade there.</p>
                <p>We were three years in Turkey, and again we had outstanding ambassadors. We were
                    in a consular post about 300 miles from the embassy in Ankara. We first had
                    Ambassador Raymond Hare, who was known all over the Department as an outstanding
                    Middle East expert. Then we got Parker Hart as ambassador, and he and his wife
                    would come to Adana quite often and visit with us. Also, we would go up to
                    Ankara for meetings, so I had good exposure to the ambassadors and I found them
                    outstanding people to work with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of housing would you be able to find, for
                        instance, iyour location?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We had a wonderful house in Adana. It was a French provincial large
                    house, two-story, with a full basement. There were some modern large apartment
                    buildings in Adana where a lot of the consulate staff lived. The consul and his
                    family lived in an apartment building there. The housing was quite good in
                    Adana. We lived on the local economy pretty much. We did have access to the Air
                    Force commissary, of course. We could use that and other Air Force facilities,
                    so that helped out. We found the Turkish fruits and vegetables excellent, and
                    the lamb, of course, was first class.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes, in those earlier times, smoking, I suppose, by Americans in these foreign
                    areas was totally accepted and just the pattern of living? I suppose Turkish
                    tobacco had its place there in the local economy and was an export item to he
                    United States?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was. We weren't in a tobacco growing area in Adana. We were in what
                    they called the Cuborova area of Turkey, where they grew wonderful fruits and
                    vegetables. All the Turks smoked, pretty much, the men especially.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>They had one interesting custom, the Turks, as we learned. The eldest son usually
                    went into the army. The army was all-important in Turkey. The second son usually
                    - those from affluent families - would go into the government or politics. And
                    the third son would go into business. They didn't put that much emphasis on
                    business in those days. Now I think that's changed. And another nice custom was
                    this: when a son was born in Turkey, the father would buy a piece of land, one
                    hectare of land, and plant it full of trees. When the son became 20 years old,
                    they would harvest the trees, sell the lumber, and that would be the son's
                    inheritance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: His legacy, his inheritance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes. I thought that was a wonderful custom. We were in Turkey at some
                    exciting times, too. It was a time of tension between Turkey and Greece, and
                    especially on Cyprus. We heard the Turkish airplanes from Incirlik Air Base fly
                    right over our house one Sunday on their way to bomb Cyprus. Again, it seems
                    like every crisis happens on a Sunday. The Incirlik Air Force Base was a Turkish
                    base with an American presence. There was a Turkish commanding officer and an
                    American colonel, but it was a Turkish base. The Turkish flag and the American
                    flag flew over the base.</p>
                <p>But that Cyprus crisis happened during my tour in Turkey. That Sunday afternoon,
                    when the Turks first bombed Cyprus, the consul and I went immediately to the
                    base to see what was happening. We found the Turkish pilots with big smiles on
                    their faces when they returned from their bombing run. It was the first time
                    they'd been in combat, I think. But it was a problem for us, because we
                    controlled all the petrol for the aircraft, and we threatened to cut off their
                    petrol if they bombed Cyprus again, which didn't make the Turks happy at
                    all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, the Cyprus... can we call it a “conflict,” I expect,
                        or wait termed a war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It turned out to be a conflict.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is between Greeks and Cypriots.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: As I remember it, Cyprus was two-thirds Greek and one-third Turkish, but
                    the Turks felt discriminated against in getting government jobs and being
                    represented in the government. So the Turks attacked to try to get their full
                    recognition. At first they attacked with the aircraft, and then later with land
                    forces and occupied the northern part of Cyprus, which they still do.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's interesting to speculate that there hasn't been a
                        recurrencof this, that somehow they've been able to resolve the issue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I believe there's a United Nations group there observing the line between
                    the Turkish Cypriots and the Greek Cypriots. There have been some skirmishes now
                    and then but no major conflicts that I recall. But it's still unresolved, and I
                    don't see how it's reconcilable, frankly.</p>
                <p>Q: Yes. You had distinguished visitors come into Adana, I would expect, from time
                    to time, even though it was distant from the main post.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We got some visitors there, yes, through the cultural programs. We had
                    the Robert Shaw Chorale come to Adana, and we had some celebrities come through
                    to lecture. We had the distinguished actor Frederic March and his wife, Florence
                    Eldridge. We had a well-known pianist and others, but not as many as the embassy
                    in Ankara got, or even Istanbul. We did get a number of speakers and lecturers.
                    Incidentally, Incirlik Air Base was the place where the late Francis Gary Powers
                    took off on his ill-fated flight over the Soviet Union. He was based at Incirlik
                    Air Base.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The famous U-2.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, that famous U-2 flew over Turkey to Pakistan to refuel, and then
                    flew over Russia and was shot down. This became a problem for us, one of the
                    biggest public relations problems in my whole career. President Eisenhower went
                    on the air and denied that we had any spy plane over Russia, but then a couple
                    of days later he had to admit it when Gary Powers was actually captured. And
                    while we in USIS had put out the President's denial, then we were faced with the
                    embarrassing and somewhat humiliating admission later. Turkish press people, I
                    remember, came running up and saying, “Oh, you said this wasn't true and it was
                    true. How do you answer to that?” It was embarrassing, very embarrassing. The
                    embassy, the consulate, and USIS were only as good as the White House, so to
                    speak.</p>
                <p>Q: What did you look forward to after you had completed your tour there as your
                    next post?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: After Turkey, I got an assignment to Vietnam, which I really wasn't
                    looking forward to. But while I on home leave, I had to maintain contact with
                    Personnel in Washington, and I called, and they said, “Well, we've got good news
                    and bad news. The good news is you're not going to Vietnam. The bad news is
                    you're going to North Africa.” I said, “Well, that's not too bad.” Then they
                    said, “Well, you're going to Tripoli, Libya.” And I didn't know anything about
                    Tripoli, Libya. It was an Arab country, but I was to go there as the information
                    officer. After home leave, we went to Tripoli, Libya.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was 1965?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: 1966 to 1969. We spent three years in Libya. It was before Qadhafi, I'm
                    glad to say. They had a king on the throne, King Idriss. The British always put
                    a king in charge after they leave a country. It turned out to be an interesting
                    post. We had a lovely bungalow, as they called them, right on the Mediterranean
                    Sea. It was nice living. Here again there was a large Air Force base outside of
                    Tripoli, Wheelus Air Base, which at that time, I think, was the largest overseas
                    American Air Force base in the world. There were 15,000 U.S. Air Force personnel
                    at Wheelus and we had a large oil company community there. They discovered oil
                    in Libya in the early '60s - I think it was ESSO, or Exxon, as it's now called -
                    and the American oil companies came into Libya in droves. We had a community of
                    18,000 American oil company families in Libya. Almost every major American oil
                    company was represented there drilling oil or doing some kind of oil business.
                    Again we had an outstanding American ambassador. I really got some of the best.
                    We had David Newsom my whole tour, David Dunlap Newsom, from 1966 to '69. He
                    went on to be ambassador to Indonesia and to the Philippines and then to the
                    University of Virginia as a diplomat in residence after retirement. Our DCM was
                    Jim Blake, who later became ambassador to Iceland. The first PAO was Bill
                    Hutchinson, an outstanding USIA officer who later went to the highest heights of
                    the agency as area director for Africa. John Hogan came next as PAO, a humorous
                    man with a lot of charm.</p>
                <p>This very large American community was in a large country, geographically, with a
                    small population. There were less than two million Libyans in the country at the
                    time. I worked with Wheelus Air Base closely. In fact, I had a desk at the base
                    Public Information Office to work on community relations. Our big crisis in
                    Libya was during the Six Day War when the Egyptians marched into the Sinai and
                    then supposedly into Israel, according to their own propaganda. There was a
                    community of Sephardic Jews living in Tripoli, as they did all over North
                    Africa, running most of the commerce. The Libyans, listening to Nasser's
                    emotional propaganda on the radio, which came into Libya like a ton of bricks,
                    took to the streets demonstrating and tearing into the Jewish shops and
                    businesses. Also, it was a problem for us in the USIS library building and at
                    the embassy. We closed up the USIS library and the USIS offices and put the
                    metal shutters down, and went over to the embassy, where they had the Marines,
                    of course. Then the American women and children were ordered out to Wheelus Air
                    Base to be evacuated, because there was a breakdown of law and order. My wife
                    and children were at the base overnight and were evacuated, as were most of the
                    embassy dependents. I stayed with a core of other officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it that precipitated that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: This was the Six Day War, which broke out between the Arabs and the
                    Israelis in June 1967. All embassy officers, staff, and dependents did move out
                    to Wheelus Air Base for security measures. As events settled down after a couple
                    of days, I went back to our house. We had a wonderful houseboy there, Omar. I
                    remember he put a sign on our house saying “No Americans here” in Arabic, and he
                    fed our dog. I went back and stayed in the house, and the women and children, my
                    wife and two children, were sent to Rome. I got up there once for a visit with
                    them, and then we decided to move my wife and children to Malta, which had good
                    English schools. So they went to Malta and rented an apartment, and we were
                    ready to send the boys to Malta schools (which were based on English public
                    schools), but things calmed down in Tripoli and my wife and children were the
                    first to come back to Libya. They got on the first plane that was available when
                    women and children were allowed to return. Several dependents stayed on in Rome,
                    and some even went to the States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The children got back into school there at Wheelus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you moved from Tripoli then to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Being 10 years continuously overseas, I was transferred to Washington in
                    1969. I had a wonderful job as the North Africa Desk officer for USIA, covering
                    Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia, Libya, and Sudan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was called the North African Desk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, I was the North African Desk officer for USIA, working in the
                    African Area. Later in 1971, we were put in with the Near East and South Asia
                    Area office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was 1970?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: This was 1969 when I was transferred to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '69 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was in September, 1969, to '72, and I worked as desk officer, traveled
                    to all the posts every year. It was a very interesting job and I enjoyed it very
                    much. In '72, I was ready to go overseas again, and I was sent to Monrovia,
                    Liberia, as the public affairs officer for the embassy and director of
                    USIS/Liberia.Liberia had this unique American connection, so to speak. We'd sent
                    back the first American slaves to Liberia during President Monroe's time, and
                    Monrovia is named after him. The U.S. had an intimate connection with Liberia up
                    until the recent difficulties, which I missed, thank goodness. I was in Liberia
                    from 1972 to '76 as the public affairs officer. Again, we had a very large
                    American presence there because of Liberia's unique position with our country.
                    It was a regional embassy post. We had the regional doctor there. We had a big
                    AID [Agency for International Development] mission. We had a large Voice of
                    America transmitter site there. VOA had built 12 100,0000 watt transmitters
                    outside of Monrovia. There was a staff of engineers and technicians with
                    families living in their compound.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What has happened to those now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: They've all been destroyed, I understand, during thterrible conflict
                    there.</p>
                <p>Also, we had a big communications installation in Monrovia that electronically
                    connected with posts around the world. It was run by another agency. So we had a
                    large American community in Monrovia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you estimate by size?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Oh, by size... There was a good-sized American business community there,
                    too, working in banks, insurance companies, etc. Many major American companies
                    had branches in Liberia, including Citibank and Chase Bank. There was also a
                    Firestone rubber plantation 30 miles outside of Monrovia, which was the largest
                    rubber plantation in the world - a huge place - I think half the size of the
                    State of Rhode Island. Firestone had its own American community running the
                    plantation.</p>
                <p>Q: By numbers?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: By numbers, I think there were estimated to be 5,000 or 6,000 Americans
                    in the country. We had many American missionaries there also. There was a large
                    American missionary broadcasting facility called ELWA there. And then Liberia
                    had a lot of iron ore, which was being mined by American, Swedish, and British
                    companies. One large American-Swedish company called LAMCO was way up-country.
                    It wasn't near Monrovia, but they had quite a few Americans there. In my last
                    two posts, Libya and Liberia, we had too many Americans for the size of the
                    local population. I was fortunate to leave Libya before Qadhafi, and I left
                    Liberia before the terrible civil war broke out in 1980.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>But I enjoyed Liberia. It was there I had the highest ranking I achieved in the
                    Foreign Service. I was counselor of embassy and had a three-American-man USIS
                    post, with about 35 national employees. I got to know West Africa and traveled
                    to the neighboring posts, Nigeria, Ghana, Ivory Coast, Sierra Leone, and went on
                    leave to South Africa and to Tanzania and Kenya.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>Q: We're going to be here this morning for a second interview regarding the Oral
                    History Program. The date is Monday, the 5th of April, 1999. You'll recall that
                    we had completed the first set of the tape conversations beginning in January on
                    the 29th, and we completed two hours, approximately, and we're now beginning the
                    second set of tapes. And to recall, you had completed your description of your
                    work in Monrovia, Liberia, and at that point, I believe, you were ready for
                    transfer to the United States, and perhaps you would like to pick it up at that
                    point, where you have returned to Washington.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, we stayed in Liberia from 1972 to '76. I'd finished my tour there of
                    four years, and I went to Washington on home leave without orders to another
                    post. Things were tight in the agency then on assignments. A lot of people had
                    come back from Vietnam awaiting assignment, and I came back to Washington on
                    home leave and wanted another overseas assignment. I didn't want an assignment
                    in Washington. We stayed around Washington during the summer of '76. I had to
                    enroll my young son in junior high school there as we awaited an assignment.
                    Finally, they offered me the position of a branch public affairs officer in
                    Cebu, the Philippines. Wanting to go overseas again, I took it. It was a less
                    important post than I had just previously served, but I went to Cebu as branch
                    PAO and stayed three years. We flew out to Manila and I had orientation in the
                    embassy for about a week. Bill Sullivan was the ambassador at the time, another
                    outstanding ambassador who is well known for his Iran ambassadorship. We flew
                    down to Cebu in October 1976 to take up the post. Cebu was a two man consular
                    post. John Ellson was the first consul. He was followed by Terry Tull, a Foreign
                    Service female officer, who later went on to be ambassador to a couple of
                    countries. I had the best national staff in Cebu of all my posts. They were very
                    competent people, well versed in English, and hard-working. Our PAO in Manila
                    the first year or two was Maury Lee. He was followed by Horace Greeley Dawson. I
                    served under them. After Bill Sullivan left, he was replaced by David Newsom,
                    whom we'd served with in Libya, so he was an old friend and very welcomed
                    ambassador for us. After David Newsom left, he was replaced by Richard Murphy,
                    who had been mostly in the Middle East and was an Arab expert.</p>
                <p>Q: At that point I believe I had wanted to ask you about the political situation
                    in the Philippines and how it might have affected your work there in the
                    consulate and as branch PAO. The president of the Philippines at that time
                    was-</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: -was Marcos, yes. Marcos was the president the entire period we were in
                    the Philippines. When we arrived in October 1976, there was martial law and
                    there was a curfew of midnight. That didn't last too long, less than a year.
                    Then things were relatively calm. There was some insurrection up in the northern
                    part of the country, up in northern Luzon, and there was insurrection down in
                    the south in Mindanao, especially in the city of Zamboanga, but it didn't affect
                    us very much. We had the usual USIS operations of an American library - very
                    good American library, well attended - and we had exhibits, of course, that
                    would come in. We had a regular motion picture schedule of classic American
                    films once a month. We had a press operation, because there were four or five
                    English daily newspapers in Cebu, and we supplied them with wireless file
                    material and other items. We had a speakers' program. We had speakers come in
                    quite often. They were programmed out of Tokyo - American speakers. And we had
                    some performing artists. We had concert pianists. We had a chorale group. It was
                    an all-around operation with just one American in USIS, myself, and a staff of
                    about 15 national employees, who, I have said, were most competent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I wanted to ask you, Howell, about the size of a city like
                        yowere working in there. What was the population of that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Cebu was a relatively large city. It was close to a million people, and
                    it became over a million by the time we left, in the three and a half years we
                    were there. It was the second largest city in the Philippines, after Manila,
                    situated about 300 miles south of Manila. It was on the island of Cebu and was
                    called Cebu City. You could only get there by flying or by ship. Cebu had a
                    port. They had an active port. We had visits of U.S. Navy ships every year.</p>
                <p>Q: In recounting other posts where you had served before, and as your interview
                    indicates, you had in your background five or six different places where you had
                    lived, served in PAO activity, and by comparison was Cebu one of your favorite
                    places?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I didn't have the responsibilities I'd had in Monrovia, where I was the
                    country PAO and had a larger staff. Cebu was a branch public affairs post.
                    Because I had such a good Philippine staff, it made my life relatively easy
                    there, frankly. So it was a lesser post, so to speak, less responsibilities
                    there, but still an important one. The Philippines had been our only colonial
                    experience. When we arrived in '76, we found the Filipinos quite pro-American.
                    It has changed since then, but we enjoyed it there and got to travel through the
                    Far East, including a trip to China with a group of Filipinos. We went to China
                    in 1979, on our own, as tourists, but we might not have been able to have gone
                    to China if we hadn't been stationed there. And then we visited Hong Kong and
                    Taiwan and all the ASEAN [Association of South East Asian Nations] countries out
                    of Cebu when we got leave. We went to Thailand and Malaysia, Singapore,
                    Indonesia, and back, taking advantage of a special airline fare where you could
                    visit all ASEAN countries that I just mentioned for a reasonable cost. We took
                    advantage of that when we got leave, got to see quite a bit of East Asia.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you complete your work there at Cebu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I finished the tour in the summer of 1979, and I had an onward assignment
                    to Washington, DC. I had put in for this job and fortunately got it. It was
                    director of USIA National Employees. I was the personnel director for all of our
                    national employees worldwide, and that was a job I had sought out because I had
                    often thought our national employees did not get all the credit and recognition
                    that they deserved. I was going to try to improve that situation and help them.
                    I worked closely with the State Department national employee personnel officer.
                    I took that job in 1979, and at the time all national employees were all being
                    reclassified under the Civil Service. As you know, they're under Civil Service
                    regulations, and all jobs worldwide were being reclassified. This was a real
                    upheaval. I made several trips to posts with classifiers that were reviewing
                    these jobs. We would interview every national employee and decide what Civil
                    Service grade he or she should be in due to their responsibilities. It was the
                    first time we had a worldwide standard system of personnel classification for
                    national employees. While many national employees got demoted because they were
                    way overgraded, others got promoted. The worldwide standard of personnel
                    classification for national employees is still in existence till this day, I
                    believe.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, that certainly is an interesting fact, so you must have felt a great
                    sense of accomplishment and achievement with obviously some great loyalties that
                    you developed with Foreign Service national in your posts, and recalling your
                    very warm experience with the Philippine foreign nationals who were so competent
                    with your staff, and returning to Washington and getting into the details on a
                    worldwide basis must have been a fascinating challenge for you.</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was, and I had a relatively big staff in Washington. I had six
                    American officers working with me in the national personnel office, and we would
                    travel to posts with State Department people and professional personnel
                    classification specialists. I went on several trips. I went to Venezuela and
                    Peru. Then I went out to Thailand, Burma, and India. India had the largest
                    national employee staff in the world. I also traveled to New Zealand and
                    Australia in this job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the total population of that local Indian
                        ForeigService national program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: It was about three hundred. We had posts in Bombay, Delhi, Calcutta,
                    Madras, and branch posts in Bangalore, Hyderabad, and Lucknow. It was a big
                    operation.</p>
                <p>Q: Was this work that you were doing in Washington in the revision of the Foreign
                    Service National Civil Service review program - was that the final contact you
                    had with the agency? Did you retire shortly after that?</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes. That was my last job. I worked there in '79 and '80, and with my
                    military service, I had 35 years' service, so when the agency offered an
                    incentive to retire - I think it was a 13 percent bonus - I couldn't resist
                    that. My wife wasn't too happy when I retired, because I was only 58, and she
                    didn't want to be known as a wife of a retiree. It worked out because soon after
                    I retired I went to work at the State Department on the Freedom of Information
                    Program. We were clearing documents under the Freedom of Information Act [FOIA],
                    and I enjoyed that work very much. While it wasn't full-time, it was two or
                    three times a week. There was a formula on how much you could make - I can't
                    remember what it was - in salary. They paid us at a GS-15 level, and we worked
                    in the areas where we had served overseas, clearing documents under the Freedom
                    of Information Act. I did that from 1980 to 1989, so had almost a second career.
                    Also, I was called upon on several occasions to escort international visitors
                    around the country. I took more than 30 trips with international visitors
                    brought here under the Fulbright Program and other programs. I got to see a lot
                    of the United States from these trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the official date of your retirement? Do you
                        recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: My official date of retirement was August 31st, 1980. But I stayed on as
                    director of Foreign National Personnel under a reserve officer appointment until
                    the end of the year at the request of the USIA Personnel director, Angie
                    Garcia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you living in Arlington, Virginia, at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: We were living in Falls Church.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Falls Church.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Falls Church, yes. In the Lake Barcroft area.</p>
                <p>Q: And following [the retirement] date in August 31, 1980, you continued in your
                    work as you described, and then in 1981 you began your escort service work?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: Yes, in 1981 I began the work in the Freedom of Information Office at the
                    State Department. There was a big staff, several former ambassadors, working
                    there, and it was a fun job really because of the camaraderie with the other
                    officers. In '81, I did the first escort work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm curious about your escort work. Would this involve
                        thvisits of foreign nationals?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: No, it wasn't foreign nationals at all. These were foreign visitors
                    selected by embassies and USIS posts around the world to participate in the
                    International Visitor Program. I took the minister of the interior from Jordan
                    around the country. I took the minister of Education from India. I took another
                    minister of education from Egypt and the deputy foreign minister of Pakistan. We
                    had quite a few VIP types, and then there were groups. When we were having
                    elections in the United States, journalists would come over to observe American
                    elections, and that would be a group of anywhere from five to 15 people.
                    Sometimes there would be two escorts on those trips. But this wasn't part of my
                    official career; this was after I had retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, this certainly must have been one of the most
                        entertaininparts of your experience in working in foreign affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I enjoyed it very much. The Freedom of Information work, declassifying
                    documents, and also the escort work, and I got to see my own country quite a
                    bit. I went to places I probably never would have gone to otherwise, including a
                    wheat farm in North Dakota, an Indian reservation in Arizona, and other
                    places.</p>
                <p>Q: It was so impressive for me to hear you say that you had completed 35 years of
                    service work for your government, for our country. That has great meaning to me
                    personally, and I'm sure it wold for most Americans, to all who have some
                    appreciation of what our country tries to do overseas. And this prompts a
                    question that may be difficult for you to answer, but in reflecting on those
                    great numbers of experiences and these great varieties of countries and also for
                    the purposes of the Oral History Program, others who will be listening to what
                    you have to say, can you think of some valuable or some lessons that young
                    people coming into service might consider, that will be helpful to them from
                    your experience?</p>
                <p>TEEPLE: I think the best advice is to get a well-rounded education in liberal
                    arts, especially if you want to go into information and cultural work. And of
                    course now with all employees taking the Foreign Service Exam, it's almost
                    mandatory. American studies programs are very useful for an information/cultural
                    officer also.</p>
                <p>Of course, the Service has changed considerably since we left in '80. And it's
                    gotten more difficult, with terrorist activities all over. It's completely
                    different now, so I hesitate to make recommendations because I'm not that
                    familiar today with what's happening now in the Foreign Service. Being in
                    California, we're somewhat distant from it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, understood.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>TEEPLE: But I certainly enjoyed my career very much and would repeat it again,
                    maybe with a few different post assignments. I had wonderful experiences, and I
                    believe it was a real asset for our children, our two boys, growing up abroad
                    and getting appreciation of world affairs and other people and cultures.</p>
                <p>Q: We've been talking with Mr. Howell Teeple about his experiences in his 35 y
                    ears of service in foreign affairs, and from his descriptions of the various
                    places where he has served, anyone can appreciate the vast amount of work that
                    he's enjoyed in foreign service, and we trust that this will be useful for all
                    who follow on who are able to enjoy the Oral History Program. This terminates,
                    then, our second interview with Mr. Howell Teeple, concluding information about
                    his 35 years of service. My name is Earl Sherman, San Diego, California,
                    terminating this interview on Monday, April the 5th, 1999.</p>
                <p>End of Interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
