<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000427">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="interview">Interview with Barbara J. Good </title>
<title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
<name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and scholarship.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or greater.</p>
</editorialDecl>


</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
<body>
<div>
<p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History Project</p>
<p>BARBARA J. GOOD</p>
<p>Interviewed by:  Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
<p>Initial interview date:  May 25, 1993</p>
<p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I wonder if you could give me a bit about where you grew up, when, your education, before we move into the foreign affairs field?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  I grew up in Oakland, California, and graduated from the University of California in Berkeley in 1950.  My ultimate goal was to be a painter and professor of Art History.  Unfortunately, I had no funds to continue my studies in Europe and particularly in Rome.  However, when Foreign Service recruiters arrived in San Francisco in 1951 seeking college graduates to become cryptographers, I thought this would be a solution, especially since I was assigned to Rome.  Little did I realize, however, that my work hours would change every two weeks, thus preventing me from attending an evening college or studying Italian except with a private tutor on my own.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: As a cryptographer, did you feel you were off to one side?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Not really, we encrypted all the classified documents and sent them back to the State Department.  The most extensive work was usually from 8 PM to midnight.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: That's always, of course, the end of the work day.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: The nicest thing about it was that there were so many wonderful young college graduates and we had a very good time working together in the fantastic capital - Rome.  After my first assignment in Rome I was assigned to Bolivia as a Foreign Service secretary and then transferred to Buenos Aires, Kobe-Osaka, and Paris.  I was then sent back to Washington as a Foreign Service Recruiter in the State Department's Personnel Branch for five years.  I then spent nine years as Program Officer in the State Department's Secretariat for the US National Commission for UNESCO.  Then two years as Director of International Women's Program and Alternate Delegate to the UN Commission on the Status of Women.  My last two assignments abroad were on detail with USIA as Cultural Affairs Officer in Calcutta and Amman and in between I served in the State Department as NGO Liaison Officer in the Bureau of Public Affairs.</p>
<pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Bolivia?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: I was a secretary in the Economic Section, but secretaries were not even allowed to have a car.  And at 12,500 feet, the only place I could find to live was a fifth-floor walk-up apartment.All the officers could live at 10,000 feet because they were allowed to have cars.  AID clerks could also have cars because the Bolivian Government believed only AID gave them funds, not the State Department.  So it was not ideal physically, especially because I had hepatitis and several operations in Rome, one of which soon led to severe complications.  However, I was dating a wonderful man, Director of the United Nations Development Program (UNDP), and it was very exciting to have many UN friends.  That's when I realized that I wanted to be involved in multilateral work.  Unfortunately, after I was sent to the military hospital in Panama and it was discovered that I had 80 gallstones my gall bladder was removed.  When I returned to La Paz I remained in such pain that I insisted upon a transfer, saying I would otherwise have to resign.  Fortunately, within 24 hours I was transferred to Buenos Aires.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in Buenos Aires?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Again I was secretary in the Economic section but for only 10 months because the State Department wanted to reassign me to Buenos Aires.  Since I couldn't have a car there either, I decided it was time to move to another part of the world so that I could learn more about global history and another foreign language.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reason behind that — was it cost?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: No, they said that only diplomats were allowed such privileges as a reciprocal rule.  I liked Argentina because it was very Italian, but it was time to move on.  Fortunately, I was assigned to the American Consulate in Kobe/Osaka.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How long were you in Kobe/Osaka and what were you doing there?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: For two years I was the secretary for the Consul General.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did Japan strike you?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
<p>GOOD:  I adored it because I had studied Japanese painting in college.  Also, at night I taught English for the USIS American Center and met many journalists who became dear friends for decades.  A number of colleagues and I rented a little house on an island just off from Kobe where we spent the weekends.  Also, I liked learning Japanese, especially because I was the only person in the Consulate who wanted to be taught Japanese every morning at 7 AM.  Unlike FSOs, I had not been given the opportunity to learn Japanese before my assignment and in order to strengthen this language I had my Japanese maid speak only Japanese to me.  I learned so much about Japanese culture and the arts and studied Ikebana with Japanese artists.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression — what was the Consul General doing there at the time?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  He was carrying out commercial and consular functions that covered a large area.  Consular officers were also heavily involved with the Nisei citizen questions.  Because Post Management had not found a real role for the Consulate General in the transitional period, it was not a particularly effective office.  The early days of occupation were just giving way.  We had no idea that this period would turn out to be the take-off of Japanese economic power.Then in 1960 I was assigned to Paris for two years and worked as a secretary in the US Political Section in NATO.  I worked for a very prolific woman officer whose output required a great deal of attention and effort from me as her secretary.  Because the excessive assignments given her were unappreciated, she was under great strain; working for her was difficult.  When I was allowed to have another two year assignment in Paris (from 1962 - 1964), I requested a position in the Embassy. I was then very fortunate to be assigned to a very dynamic Commercial Counselor who was on detail from the Commerce Department.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was he interested in doing?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: He thought the Embassy should be doing more to help the US Government and private sector to increase commercial sales abroad just as other foreign diplomats do. The Commercial Bureau had approximately 12,000 visitors each year.  My boss recognized my commitment and gave me far more than just clerical work.  Therefore, I received a meritorious honor award for a very rewarding assignment.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the de Gaulle era there?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
<p>GOOD: Before the de Gaulle era there was a popular hostility toward the US as a result of the US action taken during the Suez crisis. The de Gaulle era was marked by a comprehensive policy at all levels of the French government to interfere with what de Gaulle called the American hegemony.  Despite wide anti-American attitudes pleasant and strong relations were formed between US and French individuals. Nevertheless, it was very difficult to be personally close to the average French person in Paris because the political situation was always the topic of discussion and the factions (right or left wing) responded violently to any views that supported the US.  But I liked my French friends and their culture and I learned their language and could converse with them, unlike most of the clerical staff who didn't make the effort to associate with French citizens on their terms because there was a safety problem due to the widespread civil unrest.  The French right wing was setting off bombs and the left wing organized enormous demonstrations that ended in riots.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, it was during the Algerian War that the French colonials were having their fight against de Gaulle and the government and the Embassy were having bombs going off.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Bombs, yes.  The famous French left-wing intellectual Jean Paul Sartre's apartment was bombed and I lived very close by.  At the time we were outside the cafe Flore next door to Les Deux Magots, which I lived above.  Even when you walked on the streets and saw a little package you didn't know if it was going to explode.  After the last two years my personnel officer thought I would be just the right person to recruit clerical staff for the Foreign Service.  This was a marvelous assignment for me because I was able to spend the next five years traveling and recruiting all over the United States.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I came into the Foreign Service in '55, and at one point — up until really about the '70s or so — we were getting absolutely top-caliber Foreign Service secretaries.  We were getting basically over-qualified people.</hi>
</p>
<p>What was your impression of the people you were seeing in different parts of the country?  Was there pretty much the same type of person interested in the Foreign Service down in, say Louisiana, Georgia, as there were in the North?</p>
<p>GOOD:  It depends on the individual.  I couldn't believe the South.  I was always walking too fast for all the people on the street. I couldn't believe it was America.  Although it was fascinating to see the South, I felt out of place because I considered the situation far less liberal than my world in California.  It was also difficult because I was a feminist even in those days.  During my college years, I had been thrown out of several summer jobs because I would always stand up and insist that part time workers be treated equally.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you find your best recruits?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Actually, California.  Because so many people would come from all over the United States to California, they were ready to take the further step of going overseas.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  More venturous...</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Also, some women had bad marriages and wanted to find a lucrative way out.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So this — I'm not using the term a pejorative way — but this was an escape, a way to change one's life.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Yes, it was, but I realized that what I was doing was not just recruiting, I was helping everyone to do what they should do.  Many of the persons that came to see me did not like their current careers and just wanted to find a way out and I encouraged them to join the Foreign Service because it was so enriching.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a problem with doing this, with your experiences of recruiting people with college degrees, because we're really talking about women.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: I recruited men, too.  Most of them weren't secretaries, but they were all doing the same kind of cryptography work.  Actually, at one point the State Department decided they only wanted to hire retired military men and not college graduates because they discovered how cryptographic work bored us.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I know.  I was involved in the military in monitoring Soviet broadcasts, and God this was dull!  The women who came to you: did you have a problem because you would see a bright woman coming and you knew the Foreign Service was not going to use them very well?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
<p>GOOD: Well in those days most women college graduates found it difficult to find the right career, but every time I returned to the US on home leave, suburban married women convinced me I didn't want their boring life.  This convinced me it was not that bad to be a Foreign Service clerical employee.  Many married men who served abroad were not accompanied by their wives so we always had interesting men to date and since we couldn't marry without losing our career perhaps this was a good solution.  But a lot of my homosexual colleagues and friends always treated me as an equal partner.  In 1953, when homosexuals were thrown out of the Foreign Service I was terribly annoyed to lose so many witty colleagues.  Then I realized that the government didn't even recognize lesbian women in the Foreign Service, because women's role was never considered sufficiently important.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what happened in '53?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Republicans decided they didn't want any homosexuals in the Foreign Service because they considered them liable to blackmail, but married men who had affairs with foreign women in Eastern Europe could also pose the same danger.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, this was McCarthy times...</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: And frankly it was so much fun to be with homosexual men who didn't see you as a sex object. When I studied art history in college, I had a number of homosexual friends because so many preferred the worlds of art and writing. In fact, one of my dearest friends who was a brilliant writer and poet came to visit me in Paris when I was assigned there and also when I served in Rome.  FSO's wives didn't think it was appropriate for him to stay at my residence, but I didn't want to let them know he was a homosexual.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I don't want to get off on a sociological thing, but it was just my impression that there was a kind of concentration of homosexual men in cryptography at one time.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
<p>GOOD: Yes, but there were also heterosexual men.  I just think a lot of them wanted to leave the US because their parents didn't want them around at home.  And that is why we met so many who were not only in the Foreign Service, but sent to Paris and Rome by their families.  I liked them because they also found me witty and clever.  They never put me down like certain heterosexual males who just wanted to control me or use my body.  However, in Rome, I had many wonderful Italian boyfriends because I was fascinated with foreigners.  But a lot of my Foreign Service colleagues only wanted to see Americans.  I thought they should get out of the Foreign Service if they didn't want to meet foreigners.  I could never accept American isolationism.  It's a global community today and I always thought it was then, too.  I was always so fascinated with different people and their unique cultures.  The only reason I didn't want to marry a foreign man in Europe or Latin America was because in those cultures, it was so acceptable for men to have mistresses.  And I couldn't possibly accept such a situation.  Besides, if I gave up my career, I would have been very insecure.  When I grew up during the Depression I started working at 13, doing anything to help my family, so the last thing I wanted to do was to lose my career and marry the wrong man.  Frankly, As I now look back, I realize that everything happened the best way for me.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: I graduated from college in 1950 also, and I think because of the Depression — a career was something you hung on to, you didn't mess around with it.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: You are absolutely right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You did this recruiting — how competitive was the State Department at that time with comparable careers for women?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  Well, we never had the money the CIA did.  CIA recruited on campus, and we could not afford to compete with them.  And then, CIA clerical personnel were promoted far more often than State Department personnel. A career in the Foreign Service was a perfect way to see the world, even for a few years.  In those days, most Americans, especially women, couldn't afford to travel abroad extensively.  Also, it was very difficult to find a decent career.  But the Foreign Service was perfect for me because I just wanted to be global.  One of my colleagues once said: “You won't get rich in the Foreign Service, but you will get rich in experience.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like when you were in Recruitment?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
<p>GOOD: In addition to recruiting, I was also asked to write articles for newspapers about the role of Foreign Service staff officers and draft brochures.  I interviewed many bright young women and men across the country and was also interviewed on television.  So I learned to be a good speaker.  I didn't realize I was learning the right skills needed for an officer position.  Then I just happened to meet a friend who was assigned to the Secretariat for the US National Commission for UNESCO.  She found another position and suggested that I volunteer for her position.  Twelve people sought the job, and the Secretariat wanted someone with my writing and public speaking skills as well as my overseas background.  Therefore, I could easily promote the Foreign Service.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you were in the Bureau of Cultural Affairs in the State Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  That's right, and then the Commission moved over to the Bureau of International Organization Affairs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You were dealing mainly with UNESCO?  This was when?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: I was assigned as Program Officer in the Secretariat of the US National Commission for UNESCO from 1970 to 1979.  They wanted me to write and edit the newsletter, but I was more interested in issues and ideas and that is when I became involved with human rights, women's rights, and cultural issues.  I really got excited about UNESCO because I kept meeting so many brilliant persons.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: It was first in Cultural Affairs and then IO.  In those nine years, how did you see the American relationship to UNESCO?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  I was trying to help on the cultural side, because I believed America should be doing far more to support the arts. The US has always believed in leaving the arts to the private sector.  At one point I was advised that I could be reassigned overseas, but the President of the US National Commission for UNESCO said that I was needed in the US far more than abroad, because we had to wake up America to the importance of the United Nations and the necessity of our doing so much more.  Therefore I became a Program Officer focusing on human rights, women rights and cultural affairs.  At that time the US government was not focusing appropriately on women's rights.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When you say 'womens' rights' and we're talking about the 1970s — these things change definitions from decade to decade — what were you thinking about?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
<p>GOOD: The tragedy of millions of poor illiterate Third World women, who were forced to bear many children.  Literate mothers generally tend to resist childbearing pressures and to promote the education of their children so they at least can break out of the vicious circle of poverty and ignorance — girls as well as boys.  Having served in Bolivia, I'd seen this — and I learned much more about the problem from a brilliant Palestinian friend in UNESCO, Yasmine Zahran, with whom I worked to put together a number of education programs for women — with the help of many good NGOs.  The US never sufficiently understood the importance of education for Third World Women.  This was one of the reasons the government thought we didn't need UNESCO.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At that time, did you see UNESCO being something of no relevance to the US?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Oh, no.  The US definitely needed UNESCO, if only to learn how important culture is in international relations.  The US also failed to see that running a worldwide intergovernmental organization as much more difficult than running a bilateral organization or one in which the countries involved have a great deal in common, like the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: We're talking about this 1970 - 1979 period.  Was there a problem at that time with UNESCO in the State Department?  Later on there came this feeling that UNESCO was playing around with the media, going for censorship.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  Well, yes that was a problem, for all the Western countries from the mid-70s to the mid-80s.  It was by and large resolved when UNESCO shifted its emphasis to helping Third World countries in building the infrastructure for their own national news coverage.  But we have to realize that Western media are far from perfect. They still do not cover women's issues adequately, among other things, which is why I am now active with the Institute for Freedom of the Press.  Our press consistently neglects social issues — except if it can find bad or sensational news in those areas.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you working in Washington? At the State Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: At the Secretariat for the US National Commission for UNESCO which was in the State Department's Bureau of International Organization Affairs, but previously the Secretariat was in the Bureau of Cultural Affairs.  The membership was a hundred members, sixty of which were NGOs so I worked very closely with a lot of persons outside of government.  They were actually very effective in helping some of the political officers who covered the political side of UNESCO.  I liked working with the political officers, but their responsibilities were not creative enough for me.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the international UN management of UNESCO at the time you were dealing with it?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  Well, frankly, I was not very happy with the way women were treated, either.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: At this point, did you see it as a bureaucracy?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  Yes, an international bureaucracy, but in 1989 I was amazed when I found out how UNESCO has been working against female sexual slavery and female genital mutilation.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: When you were in IO, who were some of the people running things?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Sam Lewis was Assistant Secretary for the IO Bureau and did an excellent job.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How was his interest in women's concerns?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: I don't remember him being very strong on women's issues, but I got along with him very well.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you have a problem with an American organization dealing with international organizations?  People in the foreign affairs field aren't supposed to be lobbying in the United States.  They're supposed to be working externally, internally.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD:  I was working with NGOs who were far more internationally-oriented than the Foreign Service on women's issues because they had worked on these problems for decades.  That is the good side of UNESCO, but few Americans realize that NGOs with consultative status with UNESCO do so much to change the situation regardless of the US government's absence from UNESCO.  It is just so tragic that we did not provide a leadership role during the past 12 years of the Reagan/Bush Administration.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved with any women's organization with the State Department during this period?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
<p>GOOD: In 1970 I was the only woman on the American Foreign Service Association (AFSA) Board because the men wanted to make the organization more democratic and bring on a representative for clerical members.  They treated me like an equal partner and supported me in changing rules which improved the status of the clerical staff.Because women's issues were being ignored by the 13 task forces convened by the State Department and AFSA to reevaluate its management and personnel policies, Jean Joyce, a journalist in the Bureau of Cultural Affairs, approached the AFSA President stating that not one of the 13 task forces had even looked at how Foreign Service regulations negatively affected women.  She was told to contact me and we then brought together a group of nine women from State, AID and USIA and in July 1970 we formed the “Ad Hoc Committee to Improve the Status of Women in Foreign Affairs Agencies” in order to do battle against the Department's long-standing discrimination against women and to demand equitable treatment.  In 1969, women FSOs constituted only 4.8% of the Foreign Service.  In November 1970, the Ad Hoc Committee formally became the Women's Action Organization (WAO), a voluntary nonprofit association with branches in State, AID, and USIA.  Toward that end, WAO monitors the status of career women, provides programs in career development and other employee issues, and maintains a dialogue with senior management on these issues.  We worked with Deputy Under Secretary for Management William B. Macomber, who sympathized with our proposals for policy changes, to overturn in 1971 the Department's regulation banning married women from having a Foreign Service career, and to provide for reappointment of those women who had previously resigned.  By working directly with management, WAO helped to bring about other significant reforms such as: increased recruitment of women into the career service; increased representation of women on promotion boards; revision of regulations adversely affecting single officers (chiefly women) at overseas posts; elimination of references to sex or marital status in performance evaluations; and provisions for appointing tandem couples to the same post.  In 1972, we received a Presidential Management Improvement Award for our initiatives and our first President, Mary Olmsted, received the Christian Herter Award for “intellectual courage.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Effect change — what were you working on?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Well, for example, for 20 years I couldn't get married in the Foreign Service.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Well the rule was that anyone married to a foreigner would have to resign, but if a woman did, the resignation was accepted.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Even if you married an FSO, you had to resign.  Well, the good side is that a number of women FSOs who had married and had children came back and now have moved to the top level. This was one of the most wonderful initiatives I could ever have been involved with - at the right time and the right place.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q: In working on the Women's Action Organization, you were at the time when the real revolution happened.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Yes, because that was the resurgence of the women's movement, and the fact that a lot of feminists were pressing the government for change it was the right moment to effect change.  Then when I was appointed Director of International Women's Programs and Alternate Delegate to the UN Commission on the Status of Women, (1979 - 1980) I was also nominated President of the Women's Action Organization.  It was a wonderful time, both career-wise and coordinating with USIA and AID to strengthen ties for improving the status of women in the foreign affairs agencies.  In that position I was able to organize a group and draft a World-wide Policy on Status and Rights of Women because I was able to bring the right men and women to collaborate with me.  Also Secretary Vance was very supportive as well as Warren Christopher.  That's why I want to bring this Policy back again because for the last twelve years it was dismissed by the Reagan/Bush Administration.  Now, I want to reintroduce it and add the elimination of sexual exploitation of women to the policy and send it abroad to embassies and consulates around the world.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Before we go back to the Reagan-Bush thing, you worked in Calcutta, didn't you, for a couple of years, what were you doing?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
<p>GOOD: I was then very fortunate to be accepted on detail to USIA in Calcutta as Cultural Affairs Officer for 2 l/2 years from 1981 to 1984.  The education and cultural program is one of the most effective ways of putting a human face on America and Americans in foreign lands and is a central and indispensable vehicle for promoting our international objectives in the political, social, commercial, economic and trade arenas.My previous multilateral experience contributed significantly to my role as CAO with responsibilities as Director at the American University Center (AUC) and the libraries in both the AUC and the American Center (AC).  Serving in a highly intellectual city was unique; one of the most rewarding experiences of my 37 years in the Foreign Service.  Perhaps the most impressive element was related to collaboration with high-level Foreign Service Nationals (FSN) who worked in USIS American Centers.  Calcutta Bengali FSNs are among the most intelligent, creative and work-oriented employees of any USIS operation in the world.  As a result we were able to  accomplish outstanding programs and relations with leaders throughout our Consular district.At the AUC, in addition to presenting dissemination of key US foreign and economic concepts (in order to challenge Marxist world views as subscribed to by important elite groups in Calcutta), I was required to strengthen and increase both educational and cultural programs and projects in the arts.  I had to achieve this goal by expanding programs which stressed their inter-relationship, and carried out US policy on advancing human rights for all minority groups with particular emphasis on rights of women by developing contacts with experts in this field in Eastern India.  After 4 months in office my boss described my accomplishments as a remarkable job in both adapting to and being productive in a totally new job and cultural environment; an environment demanding enough to test the capabilities of even experienced officers.  USIS Calcutta was much larger than many single-country posts in the Near East/South Asia, and a review of my work requirements indicated both the deep substance and considerable variety of work as Program Officer, that I charted for myself at the beginning of my assignment.During USIA's planned Reduction in Force (RIF) I was able to play a special role.  This was an extremely difficult period for FSNs and members of my staff at the AUC who felt particularly vulnerable inasmuch as one of the options was to close the Center.  Allaying their fears and apprehensions in a city with practically no employment opportunities presented a challenge in winning their confidence and trust in helping to cushion the blow of the RIF.  With a reduction in the Indian personnel force the work situation became even more demanding of my patience and perseverence, especially since we lost such outstanding FSNs who were artists and cultural affairs experts.My concern for human rights and women's rights in particular, resulted in my calling for an extension of post audiences to include Indian women prominent in business, social, political and educational fields.  As a result of my contact with such people, and the women and men of Calcutta's media world, I was invited to discuss human rights issues with them in media sessions.In addition to facing the frustrations arising from the continued deterioration of basic facilities of communications and transport in Calcutta, the AC and the AUC were subject to an unprecedented number of anti-American demonstrations, sometimes numbering one a day.  Often students who participated in these demonstrations would tell me that they would join us in our international visitor dialogue programs right after their demonstrations ended.  As an example of Indian resentment of US foreign policy, AC's Library was attacked and ransacked on June 23, 1982 by 300 students protesting against an American who was alleged to have tried to destroy a mosque in Israel.  But many Indian AC participants supported us and denounced the students' action.  One Indian participant in an AUC program denounced our role in promoting foreign policy with press releases because he said they had enough toilet paper in their bathroom and didn't need our press releases for that purpose!  Also, for nearly eight months during this period the post was without a Branch PAO, obliging me to often assume important management responsibilities (including the Acting Branch PAO).  On human rights and social processes I helped to lay the groundwork for a linkage with Jadavpur University's Department of International Relations and an American University and was able to convince USIA to send an international legal expert and activist Professor Richard Lillich.  His visit marked the high point of the post's activities in the field of human rights since the 1981 Human Rights Day seminar resulted in a publication of the seminar papers on human rights implementation.  His lecture at Calcutta University was tied in with that institutions's 125th anniversary.  Audiences were challenged to take a more active role locally in the enforcement of human rights.  One of the AC's supporters -international lawyer Subrata Roy Chowdhury, who also served as legal adviser to Prime Minister Indira Gandhi, took off two weeks from his job to work with our task force and help to put this program together effectively.  While it took two years to strengthen contacts and initiate long range programs in the field of human rights, I believe we finally developed a strong group of academics, social workers and legal experts working together to increase the enforcement of human rights.  As a result of one of our programs there was interest in procedural aspects in utilizing international law in India with the ultimate goal of establishing a human rights law institute in Calcutta.I was invited to address the Women's Christian College in Madras on the inauguration of their course in women's studies, having been instrumental in advising them on how to set up the women's studies course.  This was related to my former position when I was assigned to the Secretariat for the US National Commission for UNESCO and worked to convince UNESCO to broaden internationally women's studies.In previous seminars I presented papers on women's rights and social justice in the US.  I played a leadership role in organizing and participating in Hyderabad American Studies Research Center's Seminar on “Indian Perspectives of the Women's Movement in the US” I was then instrumental in organizing a follow-up seminar in Calcutta on “Women, Family and Social Change.” I invited some of the leading Indian women experts whom I had met at the UN when I was Alternate Delegate to the UN Commission on the Status of Women and other leaders of successful organizations throughout India to participate in the seminar in order to provide a more positive view in Calcutta of efforts underway to improve the status of women.  Given group rivalries, this took considerable time and patience in gaining the confidence of the leaders of these organizations and convincing them to work together.  As a result of this seminar I worked with FSNs and US Consul General George Sherman and his wife Nancy to establish a Women's Resource Center.  This coalition of women's nongovernmental organizations comprised both traditional entities along with the more newly established radical feminist groups.  This was obvious proof of what American CAOs can provide in “institution building” and with highly talented FSNs you can achieve far more.Through a series of programs with this network of NGOs and social workers we sought to improve the status of women and minimize misperceptions of the women's movement in the US by providing a forum for similar organizations to exchange ideas and resolve mutual problems.Working with Indian colleagues at the AUC we were successful in carrying out an “alternative programming” concept to counter the influence of predominantly doctrinaire Soviet Marxist ideology in academic circles in Calcutta.  The Center provided a forum for such ideologues, primarily academics, to interact with proponents of alternatives to Marxism.  Since many Bengalis thoroughly support American jazz, the American University Center developed a Jazz Club in Calcutta.  When I was Director I was able to increase the knowledge and support of American jazz because this is a field I have focused on for decades, especially since this is one of the most unique contributions the US has made to the world — jazz, a truly classical style of music.  It was my pleasure to introduce visiting American jazz musicians and describe the history and background at our jazz festivals where thousands of jazz lovers joined us.  When I lectured in South Asia last January the members of the Jazz Club held a special party for me and we played many jazz tapes with primary focus on my brother Jerry Good, a jazz musician who formed a group titled the San Francisco Jazz Express.  When I was assigned in Calcutta the Jazz Club requested his group visit them, but USIA couldn't afford to fund him.  Unfortunately, Jerry died in 1990 at 55.  In reflection of my fascinating assignment in Calcutta it was particularly gratifying to have been invited to deliver lectures in Calcutta as well as outside our Consular District and to moderate seminars at Calcutta University or participate in poetry reading programs for the public and media organized by local groups.  In sum, I felt totally at home in public diplomacy and when I return to Calcutta these days it is like going home to family.Now that I am working against female sexual slavery with the Coalition Against Trafficking Women and the International Abolitionist Federation, I am still in contact with women leaders and NGOs in India such as the All Bengal Women's Union which has spent decades rescuing women who are forced into prostitution, educating them and finding them careers and husbands.</p>
<pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Your next post was Jordan, wasn't it?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Well, then I was assigned back to the State Department Bureau of Public Affairs as NGO Liaison Officer because I had previously been assigned to the US National Commission for UNESCO Secretariat.  I was also able to lecture on special issues.  But at that time the Reagan political appointees were not pleased that I had worked with UNESCO especially IO Bureau Assistant Secretary Gregory Newell who was opposed to UNESCO. When he saw a UNESCO portrait of women leaders on the wall in my office, he did not want me to be assigned to the US Committee the Administration was planning for US participation in the UN Decade for Women's Final conference in Nairobi, Kenya in 1985.  A number of FSO career women serving on the Secretariat Committee read documents I had drafted for the 1980 UN Women's Mid-Decade Conference in Copenhagen and other meetings worldwide. They suggested I be assigned to their staff to facilitate relations with women's nongovernmental organizations in addition to the official Administration political appointee delegates.  I was also very impressed with these women FSOs such as Ellen Bonaparte, a Political Officer, and previous professor who had organized international women's conferences and programs in Greece and other countries during her decades as a university scholar prior to joining the Foreign Service.  Another FSO Ann Stanford, an African-American academic woman Ph.D., served in the American Embassy in Nairobi previously as Administrative Officer and was then assigned to the Bureau of International Organization Affairs in my previous position as Director of International Women's Programs and Alternate Delegate to the UN Commission on the Status of Women to support.  Maureen Reagan was then assigned as US Delegate to the UN Commission on the Status of Women.  We tried to convince her of the unique role that State Department career officers could play in helping political appointees organize international conferences and link foreign policy objectives with the private sector. Unfortunately, she refused to accept the role of career experts in this field and therefore we were not allowed to serve on the US Delegation to the Nairobi Conference.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Maureen Reagan was the President's daughter and was considered very conservative, wasn't she?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Yes, she was at least more supportive of women's rights.  I was trying to help her by strengthening contacts with all the women's nongovernmental organizations, but she didn't understand my role and told my boss that I was being too politically active.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: What was her definition of being too politically active?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
<p>GOOD: Well, because I was coordinating with NGOs she must have considered this political.  But that was my responsibility, therefore, I told my boss that if she wanted me to be less politically active, I'd be very happy to be sent ten thousand miles away.  I was then fortunate to be assigned on detail to USIA again as Cultural Affairs Officer in Amman, Jordan from 1985 - 1987.  I worked with excellent foreign service nationals, and it was an enlightening two years in the Arab world.  When I first arrived in Amman, a party was held at my residence to bring together approximately 100 Jordanian scholars who had served as Fulbright scholars in the US.  I was immensely impressed with the links we had established as a result of encouraging academics and students to learn more about American history and society.While my regular duties included carrying out an extensive educational exchange program, there were many other aspects of my position which required managerial skills and organization.  A great deal of my time was spent dealing with our American Fulbright students and professors.  With the celebration of the 40th anniversary of the Fulbright program from 1947 - 1987, I helped organize and participate in events such as an interview on Radio Jordan to explain the history and status and unique role that Senator Fulbright played in organizing an important international, intellectual dialogue to strengthen ties worldwide.I also worked with various organizations such as the Eisenhower Exchange Fellowship Program, the Hubert Humphrey Program and we brought American academic specialists to Jordan for two weeks to promote excellence in American academia and to help Jordanian universities plan or design curricula.My staff and I also worked very closely with the American Center for Oriental Research (ACOR), which receives USIA grants and was established in 1968 as a non-profit institute for research and education in the fields of archeology, anthropology, political science, history, pre-history, languages, Islamic Studies, Biblical Studies and other related disciplines.  ACOR serves in its primary capacity as a local agent for seasonal American archeological projects in Jordan.  It was founded to facilitate fruitful interaction between American scholars and students and their counterparts in Jordan, Syria, Iraq and Saudi Arabia.  ACOR continues to represent a vigorous American academic and cultural presence in this part of the Middle East.  ACOR offers lecture series and courses, resident fellowships, and engages in Cultural Resource Management.In addition, we collaborated fruitfully with Amideast, established in Amman in 1963 as a nonprofit organization that offers free educational guidance for students seeking study in the US.  Its leaders are representatives of the majority of Educational Testing Services (ETS) in Jordan.  Amideast also administers the Fulbright Foreign Student Program, the Royal Diwan scholarships, West Bank and Yemeni scholarships.  Amideast receives USAID grants to support legal and democratization projects, and is currently working on a needs assessment for the Jordanian Parliament.I also collaborated with Mrs. Inam Mufti, President of Queen Noor's Noor Al Hussein Foundation in bringing experts to Jordan to work with a number of their 25 programs, and maintained close ties with the societies for the handicapped by offering them sports specialists in the field of athletics for the handicapped.One of my duties was to chair the International Visitors' Committee and ensure that appropriate offices in the Embassy and USAID participate in this program.  I coordinated closely with USAID regarding programs they could finance such as a group of directors from the Ministry of Education, a summer research fellowship for Arwa Amiri, Professor of Psychology at the University of Jordan, who was perceived by Jordanians as a woman leader who could best help Jordanian women achieve higher education and greater roles in Jordanian government and the private sector.  Again, my previous contacts in this field were very useful in arranging for her to study at the University of Minnesota about women's rights with one of the most outstanding experts in this field, Director Arvonne Frazer, who had previously been appointed during the Carter Administration as Director of Women in Development (WID) for AID, a result of Senator Charles Percy's Amendment to give more financial support from AID to third world women.One of my most rewarding experiences came about during the first month of my assignment to Jordan.  USIA had organized a worldwide program to bring painters together worldwide to share ideas on their various artistic styles in different cultures worldwide.  Since I had not yet met any artists in Amman, I went to the museum to determine who was the most gifted and talented Arab artist in Jordan.  After looking at the paintings of many different Arab painters, I came to the conclusion that Ali Jabri was without doubt the best painter in Jordan.  He was very pleased with the opportunity to meet with painters of different countries and visit many museums throughout the US.  I was pleased to learn that not only did I consider Ali Jabri a very gifted artist, but King Hussein also recognized his impeccable skills; paintings still appear in the King's Royal Palaces.  Ali Jabri has always been concerned and also involved in museums and conservation work for the preservation of traditional rural environments and vernacular architecture in which Jordan is so rich.</p>
<pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Then you retired when?</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: From Jordan in 1987.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: One can look back on one's career with great satisfaction.</hi>
</p>
<p>GOOD: Can't you though!  And every time you read the newspaper it is like returning to your assignment. After serving in Argentina I was so disappointed to read that some of poor Argentina mothers' children were put in jail and killed because they wanted to change the military government.  I was so fortunate not to be able to marry in this country.Serving abroad with the US Information Agency was such a fascinating life and supporting your society and representing it abroad is truly a privilege and great fun besides.  Now that I volunteer and serve on the board of five organizations: National Woman's Party, National Council of Women, United Nations' Association/National Capital Area, Coalition Against Trafficking in Women and International Abolitionist Federation; it is still a rewarding life because I was at the right place at the right time and I did what I really believed in and still do.</p>
<p>End of interview</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>