<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001112">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Marguerite Hovey (Margo) Squire </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>MARGUERITE 'MARGO' HOVEY SQUIRE</p>
                <p>Interviewed By: Kristie Miller</p>
                <p>Initial Interview Date: January 22, 1993</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Kristie Miller and I am interviewing Margo and
                        Grady (infant son) at Margo Squire's home on January 22, 1993, in Bethesda,
                        Maryland ... Margo, you are the third generation in the Foreign Service,
                        that's got to be fairly unique. I gather your grandfather was in the Foreign
                        Service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, he worked for Commerce and also Agriculture. While he was at the
                    University of Chicago he put himself through working summers at stockyards so
                    when he graduated he worked for Commerce until they were opening up in London
                    and they opened up an Agricultural office there. They asked him to work for
                    Agriculture there, so he went back and forth between Commerce and Agriculture
                    for awhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And he went in before 1921, right after World War I?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I'm not sure exactly when he went in, but yes, that's my
                    understanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then I gather that your grandmother, who was a widow,
                        helped your mother with some of her Foreign Service connections, and was
                        something of a role model.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: My grandfather was stationed in Poland at the time that World War II was
                    breaking out, as Poland was taken over by the Germans. He was actually
                    reassigned and on his way back to Washington when he died and so they were in
                    transit. Everything, all their money was tied up because of the war, and so my
                    grandmother, who was originally British - they'd met in London - suddenly had no
                    money and had one child in university, although my dad went to the war, and
                    another daughter who was in boarding school and then university, to support. So
                    she took a secretarial course and became an executive secretary. The people that
                    hired her were the Australians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Australian Embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: The Embassy, because the Ambassador she had known from living years and
                    years and years as a dependent in Sydney, because my grandfather was the Trade
                    Commissioner there. She actually organized all the social events and the parties
                    and receptions for the Ambassador, and so met lots and lots of people and knew a
                    lot of people. So through that as well as earlier career in the Foreign Service,
                    and particularly in Australia, when my father was assigned to Australia, was
                    able to help my father and my mother a lot. Q: Did you know her?</p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. Well, I knew her vaguely. Most of the time she lived in Australia.
                    Obviously it's so far away we didn't really see much of her. She would come
                    through, Australians always tend to make the great jaunt around. She had
                    remarried an Australian. Meanwhile, my father's only sister, only sibling,
                    settled in Australia and married an Australian and lives there too. So my
                    grandmother was pretty settled there, but she would come through and visit us in
                    Moscow, or wherever we were. Occasionally.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you decide early on that you wanted to be in the
                        Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I did. I think when I really decided that I was interested was in the
                    '70s. I wanted to find something that was overseas. My interests were history
                    and geography and cultural relations. In 1976 I saw a brochure put out by the
                    Carter administration on the U.S. Information Service. This was when USIA was
                    renamed and reorganized into International Communications Agency, USICA. I
                    remember thinking, “This is what I'm interested in.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How old were you then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was a freshman in college. My interest in things American, because of
                    growing up overseas. I had a real thirst for finding out what the United States
                    was and what it meant to be an American, as well as history. The whole range of
                    social studies all seemed to come together in what was then USICA. I actually
                    got an internship when I was graduated from college at ICA. That was in '79, but
                    it wasn't until '84 that I actually joined USIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do in the meantime?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right out of college I took the Civil Service exam. Believe it or not, I
                    got a job with the Justice Department as a paralegal, because I thought, “Maybe
                    I'll go into law.” I had a romantic interest in someone who was interested in
                    law and clearly wasn't going to be traveling anywhere. My interest in law soon
                    petered out working at the Justice Department. It was the Reagan years and
                    constitutional law was really being pulled out. I was working in Civil Rights
                    and that really was being pulled back more and more and more. It was a really
                    tough time and I decided, “No, I really want to get back into international
                    relations.”</p>
                <p>I ended up going to graduate school. My father, in the meantime, had been
                    transferred from Australia to Leningrad so I took some time off, went to
                    Leningrad. I ended up quitting my job, deferring graduate school for another
                    year, and working in Moscow and Leningrad for a year. Taking advantage of him
                    being there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Actually, in Moscow I got a job in the Cultural Section so I was working
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, great!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I worked there for a while until... It was a really bad time in our
                    relations and our cultural relations were cut back after Afghanistan in the
                    Carter years. One of the things that we did was cut back not only the Olympics
                    in 1980 - this was 1981 - but also our cultural exchanges were cut. Things were
                    really slow and I decided that there was a good job in Leningrad. They had a
                    contract position for an economic political junior officer, which after I left
                    became a Foreign Service position and they expanded the Consulate. For me it was
                    just wonderful. I could wander around and go to all the markets and report on
                    what was being sold, and how much things were, and what was in the stores.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you were a local hire at that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was a local hire. Absolutely. Then I came back and did two years of
                    graduate school. In my second year of graduate school I got married to a Foreign
                    Service officer that I met in Moscow. I also joined the Foreign Service,
                    USIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you study in graduate school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was at SAIS, which forces you to have two areas of concentration. One
                    of them was international economics and the other was mostly Soviet, Eastern
                    European. I was trying to branch out to do more Western European and Asian
                    things too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's your husband's area of specialty, if he has
                        one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Eastern Europe, former Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then your first post overseas was back to Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, my first post overseas was in Munich. I was a junior officer trainee.
                    At the same time my husband was sent to Prague. It was good because we could
                    drive back and forth on the weekends. USIA refused to send a junior officer
                    trainee to Prague. That was in 1984, '85. Things were not opening up. Eastern
                    Europe was pretty dead and Czechoslovakia in particular. Ironically, two classes
                    after mine, we did assign a junior officer trainee to Czechoslovakia, and, try
                    as we could, we couldn't get my assignment changed around. Anyway, so I ended up
                    doing a year in Munich and a year in Moscow apart from my husband. He joined me
                    there after I was there a year. He joined me and we were there for three more
                    years together. So I was there for four years from '86 to '90.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And by then you were a full-fledged officer. You were no
                        longer a trainee. And what was your responsibility in Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: To the Press Section. I was Assistant Information Officer, AIO. There
                    were two of us under the Press Spokesman and I was mostly responsible for
                    television, film, radio - electronic media. And the other Assistant Press
                    Officer was on the written press, but we backed each other, and long periods of
                    time I was the press spokesman because you draw in the course of four years a
                    lot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because the head guy would be gone?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: He'd be gone. In fact, three came and left in the time that I was there,
                    so I was sort of training people right and left. That was sort of fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is sort of fun.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: The first time that I was Acting there came very soon after I'd arrived
                    in '86 when we arrested in New York - and I don't know if you remember the whole
                    Daniloff affair - but we arrested a Soviet UN employee who was non-diplomatic in
                    New York. Caught him flagrantly trying to buy atomic secrets. His name was
                    Dmitri Zakharov. And in exchange the Soviets snatched somebody in Moscow who
                    didn't have diplomatic status and this was the American journalist Nicholas
                    Daniloff, the U.S. News and World Report correspondent.</p>
                <p>And so instantly this was a big story because this was a particularly bad point
                    in U.S.-Soviet relations. We had put a ceiling on the Soviet employees at the
                    UN. Completely unrelated, but it all tied together and we'd given them a
                    deadline of October first that they were to draw down the number of people that
                    they had or we were going to start making cuts. And in fact we started doing
                    that and expelled a number of people from the UN. Well, they turned around and
                    then started expelling people from our Embassy in Moscow. And then...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever think you might be expelled? Was that a
                        worry?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Not really because I had just arrived and they were basically pinpointing
                    people. It was a little bit of a concern because it was a tit for tat so that as
                    we would expel a certain rank officer, they would expel the same rank. I
                    remember going through this with my father back in the '60s when we caught two
                    diplomats in Washington, two Soviets spying, and they turned around and one was
                    a... I think my dad was a first secretary and it was a first secretary in the
                    Soviet Embassy. And there were only three first secretaries in the Soviet
                    Embassy in Moscow. One of them was my father. And so we went through about a
                    five-day period when we didn't know - we had just arrived - whether we were
                    going to be leaving. And in fact they kicked out two other people who have never
                    been able to go back since.</p>
                <p>In this latest round, we kicked out a group of five and they kicked out a group
                    of five. Then they kicked out another group of five in retaliation, and they
                    kicked out another group of five. And it got down to the third group when they
                    raised the ante by saying, “And not only that, but we're going to take away all
                    the Soviet employees of Embassy.” Well there were a number, a couple of hundred,
                    maybe three hundred, working... Most of them were drivers and mechanics and
                    things like that. But there were also people like press assistants. Most of them
                    were substantive jobs. They were mostly chars and drivers, I guess. Translators,
                    things like that.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>We found out about this on the 9 o'clock evening news. They announced, “And we're
                    going to blah, blah, blah.” Well, of course we turned around and kicked out all
                    the Americans working for the Soviets. Well there were six editors working for
                    Soviet Life Magazine because the Soviets around the world bring their full
                    staffs with them. They bring their chauffeurs, they bring everything, basically
                    to avert any sort of counter-intelligence threat. Of course we have a poorer
                    society to begin with. So what's a driver going to find out, and we're being
                    bugged anyway, so who cares? We'd rather not have to spend the money to bring
                    drivers and all those people over there, because Americans are expensive as you
                    can imagine.</p>
                <p>So literally the next morning we went in and there was no one there. And so the
                    second day they had to come up with a system to keep us afloat and so came up
                    with two different rosters. One was for laborers and one was for char corps. And
                    the laborers were mostly able-bodied, mostly men and the char corps were mostly
                    women, mostly men with bad backs or anyone else who had a bad back who couldn't
                    lift and haul things. And everyone from below the DCM, so counselors on
                    down.</p>
                <p>So the first day it was pretty amazing. There were two counselors. My counselor,
                    for Press and Culture, Ray Benson, who was certainly an older gentleman, an
                    scholarly type, who had never been anything under a Public Affairs Officer, and
                    he came in at that rank and he had been to several posts and retired from
                    Moscow. And then the Administrative Counselor also, David Beal. So unfazed,
                    everyone set to work and they came back at the end of the day calling themselves
                    the “Killer Bees.” (laughter)</p>
                <p>We had a sort of semi-staff meeting in fact, and Ray Benson came in. Of course
                    all of us were a little bit intimidated by Ray Benson to begin with who worked
                    for Press and Culture. And he was kind of concerned about how he was going to
                    take having to be out there. He'd been assigned to washing cars in the Motor
                    Fleet. And so he came in in the middle of the meeting and just burst in and
                    started explaining how he had discovered this new way to use the sprinkler so
                    that you could wipe everything off, and he was in full force explaining this
                    whole thing, and we were just amazed. He was clearly into the spirit of
                    things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that's what it was like. Morale was very high.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: In it was probably higher because we were all working together. You knew
                    that many more people in the Embassy because you were working with them. (Child
                    break)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The APWhat does that mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I don't remember what that stood for. I can't remember. That's what was
                    called the rosters and the work.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh. The sort of work assignments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, and every other week you were on duty which meant that you had to
                    scrub the floors and wash the toilets or stock the shelves in the Commissary or
                    drive delivering. There was a lot of delivering of invitations to receptions and
                    things like that because of course there were no messengers and no drivers. One
                    thing that kept us going was the comradeship because it was a very large Embassy
                    at that point in Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I've heard the number 350, but I don't know if that's exactly right.
                    There were lots of employees. In fact it was a real problem because another
                    thing that the Soviets did at the same time that they pulled our local hires,
                    they also set a ceiling. And of course we then matched that with the ceiling in
                    Washington. But it was very hard because nobody knew exactly how many people
                    there were because there were so many coming through doing construction in the
                    new Embassy. At any given time, we didn't know how many visas were out.</p>
                <p>And that's what the Soviets were counting. How many visas. And how many
                    diplomatic spots there were versus how many people were actually there. How many
                    people would you want to hire. And then when they started replacing Soviet
                    drivers with Americans - you know, college graduates and contract employees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started bringing people in for that kind of work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: We started bringing people in. Basically we had to go from October until
                    April just keeping the place afloat, and them from April on the first few people
                    started coming in that were hired to work under contract at the Embassy doing
                    manual labor and things like that. And we didn't know how many slots we had or
                    how many people we could actually hire for a while. Constantly you were
                    submitting lists to the DCM or the Admin Counselor to discover how many people
                    there were at any given time. But it was very funny how it kept fluctuating.</p>
                <p>But one thing that kept us going also was the thought that if the Soviets in
                    Washington had had all their drivers pulled, we couldn't imagine a Soviet
                    Colonel driving himself or having to scrub toilets and things like that. But
                    good old Yankee ingenuity would see us through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh I love the idea of your boss out there, the “Killer
                        Bee.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Out there. Yes, it was wonderful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It didn't wear thin as the months dragged on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well it did in the sense that of course you were supposedly excused from
                    your work, but you never really could be, and so you were constantly going to do
                    your job at lunch breaks or whatever and then after hours. But I think the
                    morale was never as high in the Embassy as it was in that period. It was also a
                    great period of very anti-Soviet and anti-American sentiment in the two
                    countries, so it was a tough time to be there, even without the lack of local
                    hire and that whole sort of unpleasantness. Our contacts were limited, and there
                    was a very hunker-down mentality to begin with. So that it was actually a very
                    good time to get to know your other fellow Americans there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was at the beginning of your four years
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: This was the beginning of my four years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were also separated from your husband?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you didn't even have the luxury of seeing him on the
                        weekends the way you had when he was in Prague.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, it was pretty good. We saw each other every four to six weeks,
                    something like that. And a lot of my salary went to flying back and forth.
                    Between Prague and Moscow there are two airlines - the Czech and Aeroflot, the
                    Soviet Russian airline, and they're both monopolies so they basically charged
                    you what they wanted to charge you. Discount rates? (laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even that did not dampen your spirits, being separated or
                        having that as a hardship?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, but another thing that was hard... Ironically, because of our
                    relationship and also the security threat, we were constantly getting lectures
                    and being warned about counter-intelligence threats and things like that, so we
                    always had to go everywhere in pairs. If you went out to a Soviet apartment or
                    anything, you had to be with another American, and obviously as a married couple
                    it's very easy because it's very logical that you do something with your spouse.
                    Singles, it was also pretty logical. Maybe you'd bring along a friend. But I was
                    in this weird position where my husband wasn't there, so I was constantly having
                    to ask people in the Embassy to come with me which is a little bit awkward.</p>
                <p>And in fact, the way the whole situation was, I was under greater fear from our
                    own security than from Soviet security. I knew I could handle myself, but I was
                    constantly afraid that if I went out and did something on my own which people
                    did - I mean there are times when you have to - someone was going to find out
                    and somehow it was going to hurt my job or whatever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd get a security violation.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: So I was more afraid of our staff. (laughter) And there was a real
                    mentality where Security was... This was just after the Lonetree affair where
                    the security of the Embassy had theoretically been breached. A Marine had let
                    Soviets into the Embassy, which it turns out he probably hadn't, although he had
                    given out plans and things like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With his girlfriend, right? A Soviet girlfriend?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right. It was in fact a former employee of the Embassy on the char force.
                    So that Security basically had its heyday. It was taking its stand and they were
                    not going to be caught sleeping like the previous Security Force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Under whose watch the Lonetree incident had happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they were really vigilant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: And so that was a...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Pain in the neck.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Pain in the neck, yes, it really was. And on top of that, then you had
                    the Soviet KGB who were also doing very nasty things. Whenever the Jewish
                    Anti-Defamation League in New York would knock some windows out or do something
                    to the Russians there, they would turn around and break our windows and things
                    like that. And so there was a whole spate of windows being broken. In the first
                    six months I was there, I had this little Toyota Starlet which they don't sell
                    in this country. It was one of the earlier Honda Civics. A very, very small
                    little car that I'd bought in Germany which was perfect for me while I was alone
                    there. The muffler went and I thought this was very strange.</p>
                <p>Well, it just so happened that they opened up a Toyota shop. The Japanese in
                    conjunction with a Finnish company. So they had Finnish employees coming through
                    occasionally, but mostly it was run by Russians. They had just opened it up. I
                    took it out and the first thing that they say as they hoisted up the car and
                    they were looking at the car was, “Do you have an enemy?” Because it turned out
                    that it had been cleanly shaved through.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the Japanese body shop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right. Oh actually they were Finnish workers who were there. So early on
                    I had my taste of it with my muffler and I think looking back at the time I had
                    a feeling that it was because they were basically trying to warn me. To keep me
                    away from...</p>
                <p>At that point our major contacts were with unofficial artists and cultural types
                    who were on the verge of dissidence, and Jewish Refuseniks who were trying to
                    leave because the average Russian was just petrified of having an association
                    with an American. Most of my life when I've been going back and forth to the
                    Soviet Union, our relations have just been terrible. There with my father it was
                    the post-Khrushchev thaw, pre-Detente. 1966 to '70 was a terrible time in
                    U.S.-Soviet relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how old were you at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was nine to twelve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so you were old enough to feel that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me a little bit more about that. That would be an
                        interesting comparison.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: The beauty I think of growing up in the Foreign Service is the different
                    cultures that you're exposed to and the different nationalities. Everything that
                    goes with it. The festivities, the awareness, flexibility, hopefully, that it
                    gives you, and better understanding of your own self and your own culture. In
                    Moscow, you could get a veneer of the Russian culture, but you couldn't get to
                    know Russians. Chance encounters, yes. Most of my friends were then Americans or
                    actually other nationalities. Japanese, Finns, Latin Americans, Pakistanis,
                    Indians. Mostly English-speaking, but a lot of time Russian was the lingua
                    franca because we were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you learned Russian then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. Enough street Russian and getting around. The society was such, it
                    was basically a martial state. It was a very safe place for young children to
                    wander around and basically we could go anywhere. It's a city larger than New
                    York City, something like 6 million people at that point. I can remember being
                    ten and twelve years old and just going everywhere on the subway and buses alone
                    or with one or two friends. So I was exposed to the various cultures, but it
                    wasn't Russian so much as it was the various people that I went to school with
                    at the Anglo-American School which were mostly Commonwealth nations. A lot of
                    Africans and Asians. Some Europeans. Not as many Brits because they go to
                    boarding school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your parents deal with the bunker mentality there
                        and did that affect you? How was morale during that tough period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well again, at any hardship post, you tend to make very good, close
                    friendships with a few people. In our apartment building, there were Americans,
                    Canadians. Along this one. It was a big square with a huge courtyard in the
                    middle. And on one side it was mostly the NATO countries, and so you got to be
                    very close with them. My father's job as Science Attach� brought him actually in
                    contact with probably as many Russians as anyone in the Embassy. That was the
                    time when we were having a lot of scientific exchanges and a lot of fishery
                    groups, a lot of space exchanges and things like that. So he did a lot of
                    that.</p>
                <p>It was also the heyday of Soviet science. There was a big effort to start a whole
                    new scientific utopia out in Siberia. So my father was going out there to
                    Akademgorodok just outside of Novosibirsk quite often and he got to know a lot
                    of people.</p>
                <p>And we ended up staying there four years and he became the Economic Counselor.
                    And with that job, he lost basically the contacts he had before. It was a whole
                    new group of people. There was a little bit of overlap, but basically he was
                    told that was it. I don't know - my mother probably has in her transcript this
                    story of how people that they had seen for three years and all the time and
                    gotten very close with, because there was that official veneer, were suddenly
                    gone.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>One night they were at the ballet and ran into someone at the intermission or
                    somebody came up to them in the dark. I can't remember exactly how it was. They
                    said basically, “I can never see you again, but it was wonderful. I just wanted
                    to say good-bye and I'm sorry that we can't meet each other.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was so nice to let them know.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: But you got chance encounters like that. There was one time we spent a
                    vacation in Greece and came back in through the Black Sea on a Soviet cruise
                    ship and until it got actually to Istanbul, it was very Greek. Once it turned
                    into the Black Sea, it suddenly became Soviet. The dining room was cut back in
                    half. Most of the tourists got off in Turkey. They went along the Greek coast
                    and then got off. But because we were a week or something like that with the
                    same group of people, my mother got very close with...</p>
                <p>My father had actually had to fly back so it was my mother and my two brothers
                    and I on the boat. So she got very close to this one gentleman who was there
                    with his young daughter. And he would have dinner with us every night and he
                    played chess with my brothers. And so we got back to Moscow and we had all these
                    plans to get back together. And so we did invite them once and he came and he
                    was clearly so nervous about the whole thing and having to run the gauntlet of
                    coming by the Soviet guard in the front and the whole thing, he said, “I can't
                    ever come again.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your house was probably bugged.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that affect you, either as a child or when you
                        were back there as an adult in your own post?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: You knew it so you worked around it. And I basically took the mentality
                    that... Basically you were always warned not to talk about sensitive things. Not
                    to talk about personal things because the majority of people who have been
                    blackmailed have been blackmailed for personal problems. They've needed money or
                    whatever. So we were told to never argue with your spouse, never to talk about
                    things. Well, that's unreal. That's ridiculous. And I basically took the
                    attitude that anything that they could learn from the walls about me they
                    probably already knew. It wasn't worth knowing. The whole idea was that you were
                    going to go into the Embassy to a special place and argue these things out and
                    have your fights or whatever, but that's unreal. And people fight and people
                    live and you have problems. It doesn't mean you're vulnerable to the KGB.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your husband adopted your attitude when he came to
                        Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, and I think also by the time... In earlier times when we were there
                    in the '70s, when I was visiting my father, or 1980, that was also a very hard
                    time in U.S.-Soviet relations and I remember my father and my mother would go
                    for long walks in the park in Leningrad when they had things that they had to
                    talk about. I guess in retrospect that's also dumb because any strong
                    intelligence service can pick up conversations like that in parks and in the
                    middle of cities. But it was probably pretty good for them to get outside
                    anyway. They used to walk their dog. They had an Irish setter, and they would
                    walk the dog. I don't know whether that's also in my mother's story. I was back
                    here when they were leaving Leningrad and they were packing up and they were
                    going to stop somewhere en route. So they sent the dog out early. I was in New
                    Hampshire so I went down to Boston to pick up the dog and the dog didn't arrive.
                    And they had carefully arranged a way that the dog could go through in one day -
                    I don't know whether it was Finnair - and then it passed through Frankfurt and
                    on. And they handed the dog over to the Finnair representative in Leningrad who
                    they knew and so the dog didn't arrive. So we traced her back, and she was in
                    Frankfurt overnight and hadn't made the flight or something. There was this
                    whole sort of strange thing.</p>
                <p>So I went down the next day and picked her up and she was fine. My parents came
                    two days later at which point she started having problems swallowing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The dog.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: The dog. And she got this big tumor in her throat. We took her to the vet
                    and he said, “Basically this will either get healed by antibiotics or, sorry.”
                    And it turned out that something irritated her throat and the doctor, sort of
                    thinking this whole thing out, said that it's very possible that in the loose
                    folds of skin there had been some sort of listening device implanted that was
                    removed when she left. There was a yard man who used to walk the dog a lot who
                    would take her to the Soviet vet occasionally when she needed check-ups. The
                    Soviets are very stringent about these yearly things. And so it's totally
                    possible because they knew that my family would go out and walk the dog to talk
                    that it was a very logical place to put something. Whether that's being paranoid
                    or just chance that that happened to happen at the same time. But she was lost
                    for those 24 hours or 12 hours or whatever, and...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the thought is that they were de-bugging her.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: And I'm sure that that's not beyond the realm of possibility, particular
                    since my father was the Consul General and so would have a lot of things
                    concerning him and other things. But I can't imagine that they would ever go out
                    and talk about things anyway. My father was a very closed person to begin with.
                    But anyway, that was sort of interesting, and in that period I remember being a
                    lot more careful and worried about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the 1980 period when your parents were there and
                        you were just there visiting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, but when I was there on my own, I can occasionally remember writing
                    things down on a piece of paper, particularly in the beginning because...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To show to somebody so they wouldn't hear it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Exactly. Particularly because that was only the very beginning of
                    Glasnost and Gorbachev and Sakharov was still in Gorky. There was still a strong
                    crackdown on dissidents. And the contacts that we had in the Embassy were
                    essentially out of that group. It was either a totally official Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs type relationship, or it was these people who had nothing to
                    lose. In fact they had something to gain from being associated with you. And I
                    think that's one of the reasons that - back to my muffler being cut - they were
                    trying to warn me to stay away from some of these people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, of course not. And particularly when I knew that there was a Toyota
                    repair shop! But another thing that happened was we went away for Christmas
                    after Ross had joined me. And the day that we came back, it was freezing cold,
                    and we couldn't figure out why it was so cold. And we noticed that our plants
                    were moved from the windows. And we asked the people downstairs who were
                    watering our plants and kept an eye on our apartment. And they said, yes, they
                    walked in that morning. Clearly they had one of these, “Uh-oh, they're coming
                    home today, we'd better quickly water the plants.” And the windows were wide
                    open.</p>
                <p>And this was a trick that the Soviets did a lot, particularly when there was an
                    empty apartment. They would open windows so that the pipes would burst. First of
                    all it would be a real mess. They would do that or they would unplug a freezer.
                    Of course you had all your meat for six months or something like that and you'd
                    come back and there was a horrendous smell and everything was gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was not really the kind of security problem where
                        you were in danger, but you were being harassed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: It was harassment. That's exactly what it was. It was trying to break
                    down your will. But they had very carefully moved the plants away from the
                    windows. It was all done so that... And also they knew that we were getting back
                    that day, so I think it was more again just so that we would arrive back and
                    have a freezing apartment as a reminder that we were back there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Cold War literally!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: So that was '87 Christmas. But '88 June, it was a lovefest. We had the
                    1988 Summit between Reagan and Gorbachev and everybody was embracing and kissing
                    babies. Americans were the greatest thing ever. Soviet people from when I
                    arrived - I can still remember - people asked me, “Why does Reagan want war? Why
                    is Reagan so against peace?” To, “Oh we think Reagan is wonderful. We just love
                    your country.”</p>
                <p>And the doors were open. Sakharov was brought back from Gorky. Intellectuals were
                    suddenly being used instead of being suppressed by Gorbachev and the whole
                    Communist apparatus to stir up discussion and to sort of get people moving and
                    move toward economic liberalization and make the changes that they were really
                    going to have to make with the country. And so suddenly we went from small
                    receptions and trying to drag people into our Embassy to having to be more
                    exclusive because the place was just teeming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that change the atmosphere in the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well it changed the atmosphere definitely for the better for officers who
                    had contact, who had Russian, who had a working knowledge...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had Russian, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. And also my job was reaching out to the press. When I first arrived,
                    95 percent of our work was with the American journalist community. Nick
                    Daniloff, when he wrote his book about his experiences in Russia and about the
                    time that he was captured by the Soviets in exchange for Dmitri Zakharov in New
                    York talked about researching his Decembrist grandparents' roots. Having time to
                    go to the Lenin Library and setting up an exhibit at thLenin Moscow State
                    University. And he had that time. His replacement was still getting letters from
                    Nick Daniloff asking him, “Could you please look up such and such in the
                    library?” and he was saying, “Get real! Life is too exciting.”</p>
                <p>And partly the journalists turned to us because they had no access except to very
                    staunch, officially approved people, the Soviets. So they were looking to us for
                    information and we were looking to them for information and helping them. Our
                    job was mostly trying to help them and setting up briefings in the Embassy with
                    the Ambassador and various people. By the time I left, it had completely
                    flipflopped and our work was all with the Soviet press and we were setting up
                    briefings with the Ambassador with the Soviet press. Either open or on
                    background. Which is pretty amazing, that there was enough trust that the
                    Ambassador would meet with a group of twenty or twenty-five Soviets and just
                    talk openly knowing that the background rules would follow and they wouldn't
                    identify him as the American Ambassador saying blah-blah-blah.</p>
                <p>I was working very closely with Soviet television placing things on television
                    and working with Soviet journals and things. And people were calling. In the
                    beginning, we'd get calls from wrong numbers from people who would find out they
                    had reached the American Embassy and go, “Aaaagh!” to the end when we were
                    swamped with calls from people who wanted an American film or some closed city
                    was dying for magazines. Could I come out and talk to them about...</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>It was just a wonderful period where you could travel around the country. All
                    these places that had been closed which meant that we couldn't travel to, let
                    alone the average Soviet citizens couldn't travel to, were being opened up and
                    we could go out to these places. My husband did a wonderful trip along the Volga
                    through all these different areas including Mordovia, the only American who had
                    been there since... I think there were a couple who were sent there - it's a big
                    prison camp area - because they were caught trying to smuggle drugs through the
                    country. It was just amazing. It was like opening up a country because there
                    were these places that had never been touched by Westerners let alone an
                    American. There was this sense that they'd come up and want to touch you.</p>
                <p>I was very involved with our Ambassador at the time, Jack Matlock, who had very
                    good Russian and was eager and anxious to be interviewed and get as much
                    exposure as possible. And we'd travel around the country and people would say,
                    “Oh, we know your Ambassador! Oh he's wonderful! He speaks” Ukrainian or
                    Georgian or whatever because he had this knack of - if he was being interviewed
                    by a certain nationality - of at least learning a few words in their language.
                    He's a great linguist.</p>
                <p>At that point USIA had these large traveling exhibits that were traveling around
                    the country. They had been stopped again through the Carter years and had
                    started up again during this period while I was there. And he would go down to
                    open it up and he would start out in whatever the native language was. So
                    whether it was Latvian or Georgian or Ukrainian, and so everyone just assumed
                    that he spoke the language. So I remember being in Kiev and people said, “Oh he
                    speaks Ukrainian! Oh isn't this wonderful!” And everybody knew him across the
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wow. Does your husband also work for USIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, he works for the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is that good or bad? How does that partnership work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well it's good and bad. It's good in the sense that it's two different
                    organizations when we're applying for jobs overseas, we're not both trying to
                    draw out of the same, say USIA, pool of two officers or three officers or one
                    officer in many posts. So to that extent it's good that he's State and I'm USIA.
                    But in general it's a lot harder to get tours together because our assignment
                    cycles are different, our personnel officers are different. USIA, because it's
                    so much smaller, assigns a year ahead of the State Department so that you really
                    have to start working early to try to get an assignment or to try to keep enough
                    jobs available so that when finally Ross, my husband's list of available jobs
                    comes up, we can find out.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>When we were coming from Moscow, we both put our lists side by side to find out
                    where there were jobs together and they were mostly places like Lesotho. You
                    know, countries that we hadn't heard of in East Asia. So we sort of gulped and
                    we found about a handful including Tel Aviv. At that point we didn't want to
                    come to Brussels, we didn't want to come to Washington right away. Well, we
                    ended up coming back to Washington. There are always lots of jobs back here. In
                    general, they say that tandem couples end up spending a lot more time in
                    Washington because of the job situation. It's that much tougher to find a job
                    plus it's also that much easier to get a job when you're in Washington. You can
                    really work on it and talk to people and find out what's available, what may be
                    coming up and things like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you think it might be easier now going out from
                        Washington to find an assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well, that's always been the idea! (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've been here for two years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: We've been here for two. This is the third year and actually I'm on a
                    leave of absence right now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you feel about that, being on a leave of
                        absence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I like working so it's hard, but I also really like my children. I think
                    growing up in the Foreign Service I appreciated having my mother there and she
                    had to work doubly hard to create a life for us and make the transitions easy
                    for us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I remember your saying something about her providing
                        canned milk or something like that. You now are in a position as a mother
                        yourself to really appreciate what she had done.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh absolutely. One of the things that she did as they were going to
                    Czechoslovakia in 1951, and I guess even more when they went to Hungary just
                    after the Revolution. Both of those countries were still feeling the devastation
                    of World War II, but mostly the Soviet takeover. Shelves were stripped bare and
                    there just wasn't food. Health was a real concern. They knew that they couldn't
                    eat the dairy products or drink the milk, that they were going to have to live
                    on condensed milk. And in order to get my brothers used to the idea of having
                    condensed milk, for about six months before they went overseas, every Sunday as
                    a special treat she would give them half a cup of this condensed milk. And of
                    course they thought it was just wonderful! What a wonderful thing! And so when
                    they got there, the idea that they could have it every day! That was just the
                    greatest thing for them.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>And some other stories that she has. For example, just little things like knowing
                    your children well enough and knowing how they take to traveling. There were
                    four of us and three of us she thought could basically travel out of one
                    suitcase. All we needed were the clothes we had on and maybe a toy. Whereas my
                    second oldest brother - he's just older than I am - had to have everything. He
                    had to have a suitcase all of his own. Mostly all his stuffed animals, and he
                    knew exactly how many he had even before he could count. His special toys, his
                    special clothes and things like that. So that when they would get to a hotel,
                    she would throw those all out on the bed and he would feel at home. It's things
                    like that that you have to know about what is important to your children.</p>
                <p>And I can remember never feeling that any one particular bed or any one
                    particular room was... [End of Tape I, Side A; Beginning Tape I, Side B]</p>
                <p>SQUIRE: ...that we didn't get attached to any one particular place. And so
                    periodically we would either change rooms or switch around. If there were two
                    beds in one of my brother's rooms, well maybe one night I'd sleep in there with
                    him. This was encouraged. And I can remember even into my teens, for some reason
                    we were all awake late at night and we'd suddenly decide, “I'm going to go and
                    sleep in so and so's room and so and so will sleep in my room,” and we would
                    just switch around in the middle of the night. And it was kind of fun instead of
                    feeling, “Oh this is my room and I have to be in this room.” I think that also
                    helped with the moves. It was always really exciting to move, to stay in a hotel
                    and go somewhere else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you really had two role models: your father as the
                        officer and the mother as how to be the mother of a movable family.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I think that's really true. And my father was a strong role model as a
                    Foreign Service officer and had the traditional Foreign Service sense of service
                    and...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is all what you've gotten from him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, it has very definitely come across.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That you feel that you have an obligation to serve, that
                        kind of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Absolutely. And it's sort of corny, but a love of one's country and a
                    need to really represent the country. And I can remember feeling as a small
                    child that I had to act a certain way or I would bring dishonor to my country.
                    And to the extent when my father was in Vietnam for two years and we were back
                    in my mother's home town in Massachusetts, I can remember in junior high they
                    had the little softbound yearbook and people got different awards. And I had the
                    best mannered, which again I think comes out of this whole thing because you
                    learned when you were overseas, you curtsied, you shook hands, you did all these
                    things that goodwill diplomats did, and you certainly never did anything
                    wrong.</p>
                <p>And I can remember even when I was back on a study tour in Leningrad in 1977 on
                    my own, still being concerned that I had to be careful in what I did. I had to
                    be careful and not be entrapped in any way because my father was a diplomat and
                    no matter where he was at that point - I think he was in Australia or just going
                    to Australia - I didn't want to bring dishonor to him or to my country.</p>
                <p>And coming back fro- I think everyone feels this way when they've been overseas
                    for a long time. Coming back this last time from Moscow after being there for
                    four years, my husband and I were up in Maine on a little vacation before our
                    son was born. And there were some Brits or some Germans or... Anyway, we heard
                    these other people. And all of the sudden I remember thinking, “I can relax. I'm
                    an American. This is my country. I don't have to worry that someone's going to
                    look at me askance and say, 'Oh those Americans! Those loud Americans,'” or
                    whatever people's stereotypes of Americans tend to be. And it's sort of a
                    liberating feeling in its way. (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Terrifically. (pause)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: ... in Mozambique, so all the more so. These were the Americans that they
                    knew, so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's right. How old were you when your parents were in
                        Hungary? Do you remember that at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was born while they were there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you don't remember that really.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No. I remember vague things about it, but not really.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Nothing substantive.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like when your father was in Vietnam for those
                        years, having no father for two years practically?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: That was really hard. That was the hardest adjustment. If you ask any
                    Foreign Service dependent what the hardest adjustment is, it's coming back in
                    pre-teen or teen years or even university years when you've been overseas for a
                    long time. And that was hard. I was coming from Moscow and of course that was
                    sort of exotic, and we went to this little town in Massachusetts. The furtherest
                    anyone had been was Boston, maybe Maine. One girl had been to California. But I
                    was coming from the moon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That made you really different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh my gosh. And another thing, when you're that age, you don't want to be
                    different. That's really at the point where you just want to meld in with
                    everyone else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were about thirteen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Thirteen. And so to be hauled up in front of assemblies and in classes
                    and, “Talk about the Soviet Union!” Well Russia. “Tell us about Russia!” And of
                    course the thing that was really eye-opening to me that I'm sure other
                    dependents also feel was that when we were in Moscow, we were constantly
                    bombarded by anti-American propaganda and propaganda. There were posters
                    everywhere comparing the Americans to Nazis, and there was a lot of anti-Vietnam
                    sentiment, obviously. You'd see American soldiers bayoneting Vietnamese and
                    things. There were some really sort of nasty things. So there was all this
                    anti-American propaganda and propaganda in general about what life was like in
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>I remember thinking, “Oh it's going to be such a relief to go home because it's
                    home and you don't have that.” And so coming back and in a way to meet sort of
                    the same anti-Russian propaganda was very interesting to me. They had the sense
                    that Russia was a big concentration camp which, yes, there were and there
                    probably still are concentration camps in some areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had a sense of divided loyalties a little
                        bit.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well no, it was just a shock to me to find out that, no, the United
                    States wasn't totally open and totally objective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That they could do the same kinds of things the Russians
                        were doing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: That there was stereotyping. And this idea that I had come from... And
                    the question I kept getting was, “How did I escape?” Because there was this idea
                    that somehow it was twisted in people's minds with, again, Nazi Germany, and
                    this idea of this huge barbed wire fence that I had somehow climbed over or
                    through or something. So that was a shock to me. And all Russians are bad and
                    the Soviet Union is an evil place. And obviously it wasn't. You had enough
                    examples and you knew enough people there to know that people are people. But
                    that again was the hardest return because, here it was my country, and why did I
                    feel so uncomfortable coming back?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the anti-war movement disturbing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, because again I think when you're overseas, you have to support your
                    government and our government was in the war. My father went to Vietnam very
                    unhappily. He did not support what we were doing there. But he had one boy in
                    college, another one just about to go. It was the one time when he really did
                    look for another job and decided that he basically...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mean outside of State?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Outside of the Foreign Service. On his way back, he went to Brussels and
                    talked to different banks and organizations. He had a few leads, but I think he
                    was nervous enough about supporting a family. But he went and he did his job,
                    not very happily. Although it turned out, probably, to be one of the most
                    interesting tours he ever had because he was out there. Not in Saigon, in the
                    Central Highlands. He got very close to a lot of people.</p>
                <p>I can remember two times in my life seeing my father cry. One was after our dog
                    was poisoned in Brussels and they did an autopsy in the bathtub and left it just
                    all there and he had to clean that all up. And the other time was when Vietnam
                    fell and everyone that he knew and that he had been close to was going to be
                    wiped out because they were the Montaignard hill people who had never really
                    been assimilated by the South Vietnamese and then clearly were never going to be
                    accepted by the Communists. And he knew they were just going to be slaughtered.
                    And that was awful.</p>
                <p>But anyway, that was really hard.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And all of you were going through something bad at that
                        time, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well my brother was in college and going on peace marches and my other
                    brother was a senior in high school and starting with these marches. My one
                    brother in college was coming down to Washington and marching. So he was very
                    definitely against the war and ready, if he got drafted, to sign up as a CO
                    [conscientious objector]. My other brother couldn't see himself doing that and
                    so if he had been drafted, he probably would have gone. That was the point where
                    they pulled the student deferments back and it was toward the very end of the
                    Vietnam War. And plus my Dad was there and would come back with this incredibly
                    shaved military hair cut.</p>
                <p>But for the longest period of time we weren't getting any news from him because
                    they had given us the wrong address when he first went out there, and for six
                    months, our letters were being returned. Well he stopped writing because he
                    didn't know why we weren't writing, and there was this total disconnect until
                    finally Goldwater's phone link - I don't know if you know anything about this.
                    But Goldwater set up through Arizona a whole link for...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like ham operators?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. And so about every few months we would get a phone call, and it came
                    via, you know... And it was just wonderful because you could hear his voice and
                    talk to him. And he actually came home one Christmas and then - I think he came
                    back twice in the period that he was there. But that was a very hard time. It
                    was particularly hard for my mother, you know raising these teenaged kids in a
                    very conservative small town in Massachusetts after she had been living overseas
                    and realized that she no longer... I mean, yes, this was her town and she had
                    lots of relatives and friends, but they were living one life and she had lived
                    another and didn't quite fit in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel very close to your mother because of that?
                        Did you two have a bunker mentality there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh absolutely. My mother and my younger sister very definitely. And my
                    brother who was a senior. The decision was made to keep him in boarding school,
                    keep him at the school that he was going to so he could graduate that year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He had been in boarding school while you were in
                        Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. For three of the four years. And my other brother had been the whole
                    time and then been in college. So that they were basically gone and we would see
                    them at breaks. But the three of us who were left were absolutely very, very
                    close.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And were you able to stand back to back and support each
                        other through all these difficulties?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: To a large extent, but on the other hand I was only thirteen and my
                    sister was only seven and so that was hard. I think it was definitely the
                    hardest on my mother. A very, very hard time for her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I'm sure. Because the two of you must have adapted to
                        a certain degree.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. And you do I think with the Foreign Service. And that's another
                    thing. It makes people that much stronger. My mother is such a strong person
                    because of all the adversity and the changes and things. I mean starting out
                    with going to Hungary, as you asked, and en route to Hungary when they were in
                    Vienna ready to go to Hungary when the Revolution hit. So they were out for
                    basically six months before they got in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, she has quite a story about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. That's tough, but it prepares you for being separated. And when my
                    father died, I think she was that much more prepared because of all the moves
                    and all the adjustments that we were forced to make.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I didn't even know she was a widow. She has such elan. She
                        doesn't seem like a person who is bereaved.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: That's the way she is. She's probably the first to admit that a lot of it
                    is the Foreign Service because of the adjustments and the moves that you're
                    forced to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's right. Do you have any trepidation about
                        bringing up your sons in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. First of all, safety is always a concern. When we were growing up,
                    there wasn't as great a fear of terrorism as there is today. Although when my
                    parents went to Czechoslovakia in 1951, that was the worst place in the world,
                    the worst part of the world that you could go to at that time. I don't know
                    whether my mother talked about it, but the Diplomatic List was five people long
                    and my father was number six. And so they didn't know, if the Soviets were going
                    to sweep through, whether they would be carted off because they didn't have
                    official diplomatic immunity. So what it meant was that they lived with packed
                    suitcase with vitamins and medicines and things in case they were whisked off.
                    And they literally did that for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I don't think she mentioned that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: And today, you think, “Czechoslovakia!” For most of this whole period of
                    the Cold War, it was probably one of the safest places again for the same reason
                    that the Soviet Union was, because it was such a strong police state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fascinating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: So we didn't have the concerns that people had, say in Africa, where you
                    had to worry about health and illnesses. I think of the people I know who have
                    died from virulent malaria and things like that. But Czechoslovakia even when
                    Ross was there, they had a part-time nurse, but basically they had to be
                    medevaced to Germany which was three hours away, and every once in a while a
                    regional medical person would come through, and he compared them to Ghana. And
                    they were shocked to think that they were being compared in terms of evacuation
                    to an African country where you think of having to fly hours to get anywhere.
                    And that's a concern, particularly with little ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a very big concern. (break) We were talking about
                        the problems of medical facilities in some of these posts, and getting
                        evacuated and all that kind of thing, how hair-raising it is, and you said
                        you had some problems in Moscow.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh this last time, yes. Well, again, the Soviet facilities are in general
                    probably about the equivalent of Third World, except for really specialized
                    things. I can remember when we were in Leningrad, for example, when my father
                    was there, the Security Officer fell down the stairs - it was a really freak
                    accident - and hit his head hard. They were really concerned about his brain.
                    Well, the best neurosurgery facility in the country - or a major one - was right
                    around the corner from the Consulate, and he was taken there and it saved his
                    life. They're wonderful. I can really see brain surgery, anything like that. Or
                    laser surgery.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>At the same time, there was a woman who had been involved with Joseph Kennedy,
                    Jr.'s accident. I don't know if you remember that. He had a car accident at one
                    point. I think one woman was killed and another woman was paralyzed. Well she
                    was in a town outside of Leningrad at a special facility where they were really
                    on the forefront of surgery. They had her walking around. She had come in a
                    wheelchair and they had her off a wheelchair, so there were great strides and
                    things that weren't done in our country. But in terms of day-to-day medicine....
                    (phone rings)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were saying the day-to-day medicine you wouldn't
                        want for your dog?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. Obviously there are times when there are medical emergencies and
                    people have to go into the hospital. There was a woman who was there when my
                    husband was originally assigned to Moscow in 1980-82 when we met there who was
                    back again in the Embassy when we were there again later. People tend to sort of
                    rotate through. When she was there the first time, her appendix ruptured and
                    burst and she had to be taken to Botkin Hospital which is the hospital for
                    foreigners generally. One of the things when she came out, she had these strange
                    round welts on her back. And it turns out there's this technique that they still
                    use called “cupping” where they create a vacuum.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh you're kidding!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: You take a glass jar and you put a candle under it to get the air out and
                    you put it on someone's back or wherever you have an illness or a wound or
                    something and it's supposed to draw the... Originally when it was done in this
                    country at the turn of the century, it was used to draw the evil humors out. But
                    then it's supposed to bring the blood close to the surface and maybe that will
                    heal, if it's an obstruction or something. So anyway, they did that to her.</p>
                <p>And you'd see people in the markets with these welts and things as they were
                    healing. So that was always sort of alarming. And another they did was give a
                    lot of shots. They gave a lot more shots than we would. People would go off and
                    they would have their arm bandaged and come back with shots. Nobody really knew
                    why, but they had shots.</p>
                <p>I was medevaced with a miscarriage only I wasn't medevaced in time. It happened
                    in the course of a Friday, or sort of leading up to a Friday. And there was one
                    Finnair flight out because our medevac point was really Frankfurt, but a lot of
                    people chose to go to Helsinki because it's that much closer and Finnair was
                    always flying back and forth. And I didn't make the flight so I ended up having
                    the miscarriage in the nurse's apartment and then getting on the next
                    flight.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it advanced or was it early in the pregnancy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: It was right at the thirteen-week point, so it was right there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The sort of normal time to do ... ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, exactly, exactly. But one of the nice things was that the doctor
                    that handled us, and also Leningrad, now St. Petersburg, was a woman, and she
                    had had three or four children of her own. That was very nice. She had
                    originally hoped to specialize in obstetrics, but she was a general internist
                    and she was very nice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were lucky then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. But again, there was no thought of putting me into a Soviet
                    hospital. It was more-or-less get out of the country as soon as possible.
                    Attempts were made and then it just didn't work. There was a lot of that,
                    arranging to get people out very quickly. As Duty Officer, when the rotation
                    would come up on the weekends, you were often involved with some sort of a
                    medevac or other. There were a lot of things. Also, I think the mentality was to
                    get someone out rather than worry about the complications if you didn't, so
                    people were medevaced for slight provocation rather than...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In case it should develop into something. You wanted to
                        avoid that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right. But back to worrying about children growing up in the Foreign
                    Service. I think that in general children can be pretty impervious. There are a
                    lot of things that parents have to do. There are ways that you can cushion the
                    moves and the changes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As your mother did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. And I think it's very important to do that and to make sure that
                    they come back to this country so that they are Americans and that you take
                    vacations here. One of the nice things about being overseas, obviously, is being
                    able to travel if you're in Europe or in East Asia, to travel. You know, go to
                    Bali and those wonderful exotic places. It's also very important to come back
                    and spend the time in this country developing roots.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With the children. When you have the children.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: With the children. I mean developing the children's roots because the
                    children that I've seen that have had the most problems are people who went from
                    one Latin American country to another and they grew up in the local schools,
                    bilingual, but never really belonging to any country. And to expect them to be
                    able to come back and adjust when they're in high school or college is just
                    impossible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So for you, that was never a problem because your father
                        almost always lived in the Eastern bloc and there was no way that you were
                        going to assimilate there!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Right. In fact, when we first got to Moscow, my parents tried to get us
                    into the Russian schools and I actually could have gone, but my two older
                    brothers were too old. The Soviets refused to even take them. So the one went to
                    the Anglo-American School for the eighth grade and then had to go to boarding
                    school. The school didn't go any further. And the other one had to go to
                    boarding school because he was already too old.</p>
                <p>My younger sister, however, went to the Russian kindergarten, the “detskysad”
                    which is literally “children's garden”. She still has these wonderful stories,
                    remembers vividly the learning style that they had. Everybody would take a nap
                    at the same way and they'd face the same way, put their heads down and face the
                    same way, and they'd be yelled at if they tried to move. When they were playing
                    outside, they were told how to play and what to do. When you're in the sandbox,
                    this is what you will build. It's sort of like the Montessori extreme.
                    (laughter)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was only there a few years? Enough to imprint on
                        her?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: She was only there for about a year and a half. Basically my parents took
                    her out after Lenin's birthday when they had these pageants and little songs and
                    things. And she announced - she was probably about four at the time, maybe four
                    and a half. She announced to my parents that Lenin was like Jesus. And she had
                    just realized. We'd been home the summer before and she'd been to Vacation Bible
                    School and had gotten a little pin with Jesus on it and they'd sung little songs
                    and Jesus loves little children. And Lenin. They had little pins with Lenin on
                    it and they had little songs and games to sing to Lenin, and Lenin had loved
                    little children. And at that point, my parents decided that she needed a little
                    more acclimatizing to American life and it was time to move her out of the
                    Russian school. (laughter) So she went to the kindergarten.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh dear, that's great! What are you doing about deciding
                        where you're going to go next, or is it time to do that yet?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well for me very definitely it's time. For Ross...</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long have you been on leave?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Six months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you'll be going back to work in six months?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well I should be going back to work in six months, yes. I'm still
                    debating trying to extend it and really work for a job two years from now when
                    we'll be going overseas. It's tough because both of us... Ross was promoted a
                    year ago and I, ironically enough, was just promoted while I was on leave. You
                    know, I laugh that if I stay out long enough, I can become an ambassador!
                    (laughs) I just won't get paid!</p>
                <p>But it's tough because now we're both FSO-ones which means that there's a limited
                    job pool that we can bid on. And in fact I was sort of hoping not... I mean I
                    wasn't expecting to be promoted and I wasn't thinking I would be, and there are
                    certainly a lot of jobs that I could apply for. I can still apply for [FSO
                    level] two jobs, but it gets tougher clearly as you go up, and Ross is now
                    debating whether to try for the Senior Foreign Service which will make it even
                    that much harder trying to get jobs together. So we're sort of at a turning
                    point really. Does my career take precedence? Does his career?</p>
                <p>Most tandems who have successfully found jobs together have found they have to
                    alternate. Like we went to Moscow because of my job there. We came back here.
                    This is just sort of the way it worked. Ross ideally would not have gone back to
                    Moscow so soon and from Prague. It certainly didn't hurt him and it was a
                    wonderful time to be there. I'm glad it didn't hurt him. We came back here now
                    very definitely because of a job that he got here. That's fine. This is a good
                    time. We'd been out for five years. It's sooner than we wanted to, but fine.</p>
                <p>But now it's really a question, and he's wondering, “Should I take the lead and
                    then try to get the job?” And I'm not sure I want that. Again, as a woman I have
                    concerns about family. Again, how driven am I? How driven do I want to be? Yes,
                    I really enjoy the Foreign Service life and it's very hard for me to imagine not
                    working overseas. And as you know, the jobs are very limited if you're not a
                    Foreign Service officer.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>Many people think that it's an ideal situation to be a tandem. But I think you
                    really have to want to be a Foreign Service officer to do a good job. I really
                    don't recommend that people take the Foreign Service exam unless they're
                    interested in doing it because there are a lot of things. You're not a free
                    agent, you have to support your government no matter what, you have to do
                    certain things. Fifty percent or ninety percent of what you do is junked or it
                    never goes anywhere and you have to live with that. You have to live with all
                    the dignitaries who come through, the senators and their wives and everything
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course you have to do that if you're anybody's wife,
                        even if you're not an officer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: But not necessarily anymore.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know not necessarily, but if you're the senior wife it's
                        awfully hard?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh it's very hard, and of course everyone always wonders, “What's wrong
                    with her?” if she's not involved. So that, for example, people who were teachers
                    or had a profession that could travel, I envy to some extent because they were
                    in some ways I think much more flexible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really! (laughs)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: If they enjoyed it. Again, I think there are a lot of people who go into
                    teaching English as a second language because they think, “Oh I can do it.” But
                    they don't like teaching. And I think that's again like being a Foreign Service
                    officer when you don't want to be a Foreign Service officer, but you think, “Oh
                    well, it's a career and I can follow my husband.” It's a bad reason to do
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think that's very good advice. I love teaching and I was
                        a teacher before we went into the Foreign Service, but ironically I always
                        wanted to be in USIA. I did some contract jobs for USIA both in the States
                        and overseas. I always thought, at least if I worked for USIA, I'd always
                        have a job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes. Well...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you see, when I was interested in it was the early
                        '70s and it really hadn't started hardly at that point and so we didn't
                        realize what happens down the pike is that, in fact, you both have job
                        problems at that point instead of just one of you having problems.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>SQUIRE: It is true, right. And you can imagine, it's that much harder trying to
                    place two, plus family and schools and all the other concerns that you have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Medical.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh, absolutely. And then in the back of your mind you still have the
                    aging parents and all the things that are happening back home that are tugging
                    you, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes. Some of the transcripts are heart-breaking. About
                        being in this sandwich situation with kids in boarding school and parents
                        are ailing and you're in China.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh it's terrible. Exactly. I was very lucky. When my father had a brain
                    tumor and was dying, I was able to get on a plane instantly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Moscow then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I was in Moscow. But I was lucky. I just went to the airport and I got a
                    ticket and I came which I didn't think I could do, but I could do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But it wasn't something you could count on, you're
                        saying.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, but again I wasn't in Mozambique, for example. I didn't have to worry
                    about this connection and that connection and whatever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had to come that fast?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Yes, because I thought I could. He still died while I was en route, but
                    at least I was there a few hours later and my family was there and we could all
                    be together. But it's terrible. And people ask, “What do you think about being a
                    tandem and joining the Foreign Service?” And I always tell them, “Think before
                    you do it. The Foreign Service can be tough for everyone. For a single officer,
                    it's tough. It can be very lonely. For an officer with a family. I can remember.
                    My mother was basically a career woman who had to give up her career and all my
                    life I heard, “You have to be your own person, you have to have your own
                    career.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, there was a part of her that regretted
                        that and that didn't want you to have that problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh absolutely. No question. Q: Interesting. That doesn't come on in
                    hers.</p>
                <p>SQUIRE: She's not going to like this, but when my husband and I were engaged, we
                    were visiting his family in Minnesota and decided, yes, we were going to get
                    married. I called up my parents and I said, “We're going to get married.” This
                    was while I was still in graduate school in Washington and I hadn't gotten an
                    offer from USIA yet. And my mother's reaction was not “Congratulations,”
                    although they loved Ross, but “Are you sure you want to do that when you're not
                    in the Foreign Service yet?”</p>
                <p>And my father got on and said, “Listen to your mother.” (laughs) Because
                    obviously he had had to listen to her all his career and he knew. And here I
                    was, educated, college and master's and everything and the idea, I guess as they
                    saw it, of following Ross around the world. And again in the old Foreign
                    Service, the wife was an appendage and not... In some ways... My mother would
                    argue that now it's even worse because then at least to some extent you were
                    credited. She, unlike, most women, liked the old system with the evaluation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think people her age do. All the ones I've met did like
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I would just hate that. I would really resent that. And I can see that
                    the idea of Ross being rated by whether I entertain or how well is just crazy.
                    But for my mother, that was very important because that's what she could do. And
                    she still can do it so much better than I ever will be able to. But to some
                    extent it's not expected of me the way it was. And it really isn't of the
                    spouses who aren't Foreign Service officers nowadays.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather even the Foreign Service officers don't do as
                        much entertaining as they used to.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, they don't. Absolutely not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The whole modus operandi has changed. It's very
                        interesting. They're going to have to give some kind of recognition to the
                        dependent spouses and I don't think they've figured out how yet. It's such
                        an uncomfortable position. I'm very interested that your mother felt that
                        way about you, about how you should have your own career.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh, absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was she relieved then when you were panelled?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh very definitely, very definitely. (laughs) No question. And I think my
                    father was delighted that I went with USIA, because at two different points in
                    his career he had covered USIA. In Hungary, when they cut back the staff, he was
                    the PAO as well as other things and had loved it, had really gotten into the
                    whole jazz world and was very interested in it. That was one of the real areas
                    that you could branch out there. And then he worked for VOA two different times
                    in his career. He was very interested... I think that had a lot of influence on
                    me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well that's great ... I was interested in USIA too. I
                        think it's a fun branch of the service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I think it is also. You don't have to take yourself as seriously.
                    (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You often meet more interesting people, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Oh, much mor(overlapping voices). And also in this day when traditional
                    diplomacy is being taken over more and more by Washington and shuttle diplomacy
                    and the individual diplomat isn't sent off for years and years and years as I
                    think of the last century when people would be sent off. Oh, like ... have you
                    read Mrs. Little's transcript? That's the only one that I've really listened
                    to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Of going off to China and just six ... Every year they'd have to send in
                    this document of what her husband had accomplished. And that was it. No one had
                    ever read it and no one would ever read it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No weekly telegrams.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No. Or passing dignitaries, or anything. Nowadays, so much is done by
                    these Secretaries of State flurrying through - certainly in Moscow, and other
                    places - that I think USIA has that much more of a role. Reaching out to the
                    people who are in the cultural elite, the journalists and people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I think it's really fun. I love those people anyway.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you miss it, being on leave now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: It's hard, but it's also a hard life, because when you are overseas
                    you're working all the time. And particularly with USIA, I think, even more than
                    State Department, your job is outside of the office and so you're doing that
                    much more entertaining and receptions and traveling around to all the various
                    centers, and you're involved with the academics and the cultural types who are
                    leading the after-hours lives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's harder to do once you have children.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: It's much harder. It's much harder. Ross and I really worry about what
                    will happen if we go back to Moscow, which we've thought about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That would be your most logical next choice?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No. Actually, I think neither of us really wants to go back right now. We
                    want to branch out and do something else. But, our lifestyle was... We were
                    working all the time, and it was nice because the two of us could do it
                    together. But with kids you don't want to do that. You can't do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. But, on the other hand, it's very hard to get the job
                        done. When you're overseas it's very hard to do part time work. There is no
                        such thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Absolutely. No. Ironically, I remember it during the time I was there,
                    because our contacts were so few with officialdom, official Soviets, it meant
                    that a lot of people in the Embassy had sort of regular hours because you did
                    your job, you met with officials, even people in USIA. My counterpart the first
                    year basically went home every night and spent time with his family. Because
                    Ross wasn't there - even more because he wasn't there - I didn't want to go home
                    alone, so I'd go out and do things. I met with a whole lot of people and got to
                    know a lot of the unofficial community and a lot of the other people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To shift the perspective though, when you were growing up,
                        did you feel in Moscow - or was it the same for your father when you were in
                        Moscow - that he was home in the evenings? Did they do a lot of
                        entertaining?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: They did a lot of entertaining.</p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It doesn't seem to have bothered you any.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, they did a lot of entertaining. He was very busy. Again, as the
                    Science Officer, he was one of the few people who really had a lot of contacts
                    in the Embassy. The Cultural Affairs Officer and my father had probably the most
                    contacts, except for the Ambassador and DCM, because of their rank. So we were
                    always having a lot of people over, or my parents were always going out.</p>
                <p>They also did a lot with Third World or third country diplomats that we just
                    didn't have time to when I was there this last time. But when Ross was in
                    Prague, because the situation was so similar, a very closed society, there were
                    always these very formal dinners. (overlapping voices)They would drive me crazy,
                    I hate that, in a way I'm glad I wasn't there. He was always going to these
                    black-tie dinners at the Swedish diplomat's, or the Swiss diplomat's, or vice
                    versa. He was having them.</p>
                <p>And everybody had a lot of help, so they all entertained each other. In Moscow,
                    because he was the Economic Officer and did Soviet internal economics, he had to
                    meet all these people. There were like two different groups — the NATO group,
                    small, seven, I believe, of which perhaps five would get together for lunch on a
                    regular basis, say, once a month. Then a larger expanded OECD group that would
                    convene maybe every other month. And amongst themselves they were always having
                    little parties. We just dropped out of that, it was just too much. It was just
                    crazy to spend time with the same people when you could reach out and see
                    Soviets and Russians and travel, and do things.</p>
                <p>Growing up, I know that my parents did so much more entertaining than I did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you mind that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well, I minded it when I didn't see them, and there were long periods of
                    such time. The worst period was when they were in Canberra. I took time off and
                    was there with them. I was a junior in college. My father, the DCM, would have
                    three receptions a night, he was very busy. I remember his saying one night, “I
                    don't have to go out tonight!” And that was so rare, because they were always
                    busy. And doubly so because our Ambassador was a political appointee who didn't
                    like any of that. He'd arrived around the Fourth of July, thought the Embassy
                    party was a terrible thing, didn't like it, so he said “We're not going to do
                    it.”</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>Well, the Australians couldn't have cared less but it was all the other embassies
                    calling up — little embassies who would say, “Did we not get our
                    invitation?”(laughter) “Are we not in favor this year?” And we would have to
                    explain, “Well, you know ... “So my father was having to do a lot of
                    representation that traditionally an Ambassador would do while ours was
                    jet-setting round the country doing what he wanted to do.</p>
                <p>My father also had a lot of friends because he'd spent 11 years growing up in
                    Australia with his father. A lot of those people were now in Canberra or Sydney,
                    plus his sister and family were in Sydney. It was wonderful but it kept him that
                    much busier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were thinking, “Why am I dropping out for a year
                        when I never see my parents?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: I know! I can definitely remember growing up without a father around a
                    lot, because he was working so hard. That's one of the tough things about the
                    Foreign Service. I look at Ross now, here, and one of the really nice things
                    about USIA when you return to Washington, by five p.m., most people are out, you
                    leave the office. And I did — and I was working for the director, so probably I
                    should have stayed longer, but I didn't. And that was fine, as long as I worked
                    hard during the day.</p>
                <p>At the State Department, forget it, they keep these incredible hours. Ross was
                    working for the Counselor, Bob Zoellick. Almost two-thirds of the first year it
                    was all right, there were three of them. Then one left, his job was never filled
                    so that left two, and they were working later and later at night. At least now,
                    as Deputy Executive Secretary, he's on duty every other night, so every other
                    night I know he's not going to be home until late. It can be really late, then
                    sometimes it's as early as nine or nine-thirty, other nights it's 11 or
                    11:30.</p>
                <p>On the alternate night, though, he's home for dinner so he sees our sons whereas
                    before, he didn't at all. It got so that during the week he would only see the
                    nineteen-month-old Blake in the morning, but if Blake slept late that morning he
                    didn't see him. Or if the sleeping schedule changed and we didn't want to wake
                    him up at seven, we were out the door.</p>
                <p>At least I had time in the afternoon. I would get home, we'd play, have dinner,
                    et cetera, but Ross never did. And that's one of the reasons I wanted to take
                    time off now, too. That's another thing that really worries me about life
                    overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's very hard to put that on hold. And it's hard for you
                        to absent yourself from a lot of those things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Absolutely. And the children are only little, as you know, for such a
                    short period of time.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, actually I found it was easier when they were
                        little, because they went to bed at 7:30.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: And then you had some time together?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well no, because Mozambique was like Prague for you: we
                        went out all the time. There would be a “window” when we would come home —
                        well, I was working part-time so I would be home a lot. But we would put the
                        children to bed early, so that when we went out for dinner they were always
                        asleep.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: That's good, because they didn't always see you leaving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: True, but the bad part was that since they went to bed
                        early, they also got up early. I'd come home at midnight from a party, and
                        at six a.m. I'd have a child coming in wanting breakfast. I was determined
                        not to have them brought up by nannies, so I just basically didn't. It seems
                        to me it might be even harder when they're of a certain school age, because
                        they then stay up until eight-thirty or nine, want help with their lessons
                        and so oWhen you were that age, living in Moscow, did it bother you that
                        your folks went out a lot? It doesn't sound as if it did.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Well, another thing about getting up in the morning: We always had
                    breakfast together, that was very important, we'd always have one meal a day
                    together. Many people don't do that, even back here. Even if we ate separately
                    in the evening, at least we'd had that one time to be together as a family for
                    breakfast in the morning. We're all relatively “morning people,” probably
                    because of that or despite it. And then my mother was home, she wasn't working.
                    So while I was in school I knew she was there at home.</p>
                <p>We did have a nanny for three of the four years, mostly for my little sister. It
                    was sort of a chance thing. A friend of ours living in Germany had a wonderful
                    friend whose daughter was coming over. Her job had fallen through and she wanted
                    to come. Did we know someone who needed a nanny? So my parents said, “We'll take
                    her.” She came, and she was so wonderful that they decided to try again, and we
                    went through two others during a year but it didn't work out and we didn't have
                    another.</p>
                <p>But that was nice because my parents didn't have to worry about a babysitter in
                    the evening, when I was younger until I could be it. Sometimes being on your own
                    would be scarier at night - the electricity would go out, things like that, but
                    in general, no. And it was just bad, because my father wasn't around a whole
                    lot. I think of that - during my childhood growing up without a father to a
                    large extent because he wasn't there, he was working on weekends and ...</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you had a big chunk when you were in middle
                        school of him ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: That was really hard, too. But I think most Foreign Service families
                    become closer then because you are the unit, you are the support as you travel
                    around the world. So we were always very close. I mean — yes, I grew up without
                    my father in the sense that he wasn't there but I knew he loved me and we were
                    very close. So I didn't have the estrangement that people go through as they
                    grow up, and I never felt that sort of rebellion against my family. It was
                    precious, it was my solidity, my strength I guess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. You didn't have to do muc(laughing) to get away.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: No, true. And also, the fact that my mother was there made a big
                    difference. I think some of the most successful families I know also, if they
                    had a nanny, had a good one. I can think of a couple of tandems and they've kept
                    the same person all the way...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it's like an aunt...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Exactly, or like an older sister that travels around the world with the
                    family. That's been wonderful, I know people who've had that. And then there are
                    always heartbreaking stories of people who've returned from lower Africa and
                    their nanny leaves them in the lurch when they're back in the States. I know
                    people to whom that has happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They've gotten the Green Card...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>SQUIRE: Exactly. Or even without the Green Card, they've disappeared. I know of
                    one case: after three weeks. That's hard, for two working people having suddenly
                    to come up with someone, and the poor child having gone through the wrenching
                    experience of ... [end of tape]</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA</p>
                <p>Spouse: Ross Wilson</p>
                <p>Spouse's Position: Econ Officer; Deputy Executive Secretary, Department of
                    State</p>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service:1979Left Service: N/AYou Entered Service:1984Left Service:
                    N/A</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>Status: Tandem Couple</p>
                <p>Posts: Marguerite Squire as child: 1957Budapest, Hungary 1959-62Brussels, Belgium
                    1966-70Moscow, USSR 1978Canberra, Australia 1981Leningrad, USSR</p>
                <p>Marguerite Squire as officer: 1985-86Munich, FRG 1986-90Moscow, USSR (now Russia)
                    1990-presWashington, DC</p>
                <p>Ross Wilson: 1977-80Washington, DC 1980-82Moscow, USSR 1982-85Washington, DC
                    1985-87Prague, Czechoslovakia 1987-90Moscow, USSR 1990-presWashington, DC</p>
                <p>Place/Date of birth: Frankfurt, FRG; October 21, 1957</p>
                <p>Maiden Name: Marguerite Hovey Squire</p>
                <p>Parents (Name, Profession):</p>
                <p>Christopher A. Squire, FSO (Deceased)</p>
                <p>Patricia Cody Squire</p>
                <p>Schools (Prep, University): Holton Arms School, Bethesda, Md.; Dartmouth College,
                    BA;Johns Hopkins SAIS, MA</p>
                <p>Profession: Foreign Service Officer, USIA</p>
                <p>Date/Place of Marriage: Washington, DC; March 1984</p>
                <p>Children:</p>
                <p>Blake Wilson, 2 years</p>
                <p>Grady Wilson, 4 mos.</p>
                <p>Honors (Scholastic, FS ): Phi Beta Kappa, Dartmouth; USIA Meritorious Honor Award
                    and Superior Honor Award for service in Moscow</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
