<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001315">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with G. Michael Bache</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs History
                    Project</p>
                <p>GERALD MICHAEL BACHE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Theresa Tull</p>
                <p>Initial Interview date: October 22, 2004</p>
                <p>Copyright 2004 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the first tape of an interview with retired
                        Foreign Service Officer G. Michael Bache, October 22, 2004. So, Michael,
                        let's start with a look at your early life. Where were you born? Tell us a
                        little something about your family life.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I was born on September 20, 1927, in a hospital in Bronxville, New York,
                    which is in Westchester County, just north of New York City. My family lived in
                    Scarsdale, New York, which is also in Westchester County, and I lived in the
                    same house in Scarsdale, from birth until after I graduated from the public high
                    school there.</p>
                <p>My father, Frank Semon Bache, was a building contractor in White Plains, which is
                    the county seat of Westchester County and is just north of Scarsdale. He led
                    family conversations, at the dinner table and on other occasions, which centered
                    heavily on international affairs, including much discussion of world events
                    leading up to and including World War II.</p>
                <p>Although my father had his own construction business, the major business interest
                    of the extended Bache family was investment brokerage, which was active in many
                    foreign countries. My grandfather, Leopold Bache, and his older brother, Jules
                    Bache, founded the investment brokerage firm of J.S. Bache &amp; Co. in 1892
                    and, when Jules died in 1944, my uncle, Harold Bache, took over as senior
                    partner. He had contacts all around the world and he often gave me postage
                    stamps of countries where he did business. My postage stamp collection
                    stimulated my interest in languages, history and international relations from my
                    earliest days.</p>
                <p>Through his contacts in the construction business, my father found work for me,
                    during a couple of summers of my high school years, as a rodman with a survey
                    party, preparing for various construction projects, including Stewart Field,
                    which was the wartime airport for West Point. Before and during those war years,
                    my father was also an avid gardener and I helped him in the vegetable garden
                    behind our house and in mowing our extensive lawns (we had an acre of ground).
                    He also took me to football games of Cornell (his alma mater) and to other
                    athletic events.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>My father was also an avid sailor. Because of the Depression, we were forced to
                    sell our 35-foot ketch in the fall of 1934. But, just before we did so, I spent
                    the summer of that year (when I was six) aboard that boat, hardly stepping
                    ashore from the Fourth of July until Labor Day. Later (but still during the
                    1930s), we belonged to a yacht club, where I learned to race 17-foot sloops.</p>
                <p>My mother, Helen Elizabeth Rosenbaum Bache, was a stay-at-home mother, who had a
                    strong interest in European languages. Before the First World War, she had
                    traveled extensively in Europe with her parents and had learned to read and
                    speak French, German and Italian quite fluently. My mother was also a singer and
                    sang in those languages. My bedroom was directly above the living room, where we
                    had a grand piano. My earliest memories are of going to sleep at night,
                    listening to my mother singing directly below me, while she accompanied herself
                    on the piano.</p>
                <p>I had an older brother, Kenneth, and an older sister, Elizabeth. My sister would
                    have been class of 1940 at Scarsdale High School, but she went away to school
                    for her last two years to the Westtown School, which is a Quaker school outside
                    Philadelphia. My brother would have been class of 1941, but he also went away
                    for his last three years to Westtown.</p>
                <p>I graduated from Scarsdale High School in June, 1944, third in a class of 250. At
                    the recommendation of the high school principal, I applied to and was accepted
                    at Yale University. I started right in at Yale in July 1944, because during the
                    war, they had accelerated semesters, three semesters a year, rather than the
                    traditional two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Michael, were your parents and grandparents both born in
                        the United States? What was their ethnic background?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, both of my parents were born in the United States; in fact, both were
                    born in New York City. Three of my four grandparents also were born in the
                    United States, but my mother's father was born in Germany in 1856. Our second
                    Foreign Service post, Munich, was near his birthplace and we went to see it when
                    I was stationed there. Seven-eighths of my family background was German-Jewish
                    and one-eighth was Dutch, from the Netherlands. So that is the ethnic background
                    of my family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that your sister and brother had gone to a
                        Quaker school for a couple of years. Does that suggest there was a Quaker
                        leaning in your family, or were your parents just looking for the best
                        education? Or, were you raised a practicing Jew?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BACHE: I was not raised a practicing Jew; in fact, I went to a Presbyterian
                    Sunday School. My parents did not practice the Jewish religion, either. Their
                    parents, my grandparents, were probably brought up as Jews, but when I knew
                    them, Judaism played no significant role in their lives.</p>
                <p>I believe that my parents chose Westtown for my brother and sister, simply
                    because it offered a good education. My parents felt that my sister and brother
                    were not doing as well as they could in high school and might benefit from a
                    private boarding school like that. After Kenneth went to Westtown, however, he
                    became interested in the Quaker religion and its pacifism; in fact, he went on
                    from Westtown to Haverford College, which is also a Quaker institution.</p>
                <p>My father had served in the U.S. Army in the First World War; during the Second
                    World War, my father and my brother had serious arguments about pacifism and the
                    rightness or wrongness of military service. My brother became a conscientious
                    objector and went to a Civilian Public Service camp during the Second World War,
                    rather than going into the army. My sister, meanwhile, volunteered for service
                    in the U.S. Navy and became an Aviation Machinist Mate in the WAVES.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your brother's conscientious objector decision have a
                        negative impact on his relationship with your father and mother, or was this
                        just an intellectual decision they accepted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: For a couple of years, there was strong controversy among them, but, in
                    spite of the arguments, they always remained close. My brother, my father and I
                    all wrote long, argumentative letters to one another on this subject, but I
                    don't think there was ever any real animosity. There was certainly never any
                    interruption of communications.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, with regards to the political implications of the
                        Second World War, would you say that your family, your parents at least,
                        were supporters of the war, of U.S. involvement in the war? Would you say
                        that they were liberal, conservative or middle of the road?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: My mother and father were both very supportive of U.S. intervention in
                    World War II and, in fact, urged intervention even before Pearl Harbor. My
                    father and uncle, Harold Bache, had both been U.S. Army officers in the First
                    World War and my uncle had served in France. After the First World War, my uncle
                    was an officer in the New York State Guard and remained so right through the
                    Second World War. My father, my sister and my uncle were all enthusiastic
                    supporters of U.S. participation in the Second World War. It was only my brother
                    who had the objections. My sister argued on the side of my father against my
                    brother.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within your own home, how were religious values instilled?
                        Were you left on your own? Were you encouraged to read, or was it just a
                        question of following as good an example as you could?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: My mother primarily was the one who was interested in this, and she did
                    not want us to carry forward any Jewish traditions. She sent me to the Sunday
                    school at the local Presbyterian Church and I went for several years, where I
                    was confirmed and earned a Bible, which I still have. I was, and still am, a
                    believer in the Protestant approach to Christianity.</p>
                <p>Later in life, when we were in Munich, we attended the Army Chapel and the
                    Chaplain happened to be a Methodist. We admired his sermons and I sang in his
                    choir. We liked him as a person and kept in touch with him until his death, more
                    than twenty years later. Probably as a result of this experience, we later
                    joined Methodist churches in Maryland and New Jersey and sent our children to
                    Methodist pre-schools and Sunday schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you. You started to tell about your education. You
                        went to Yale.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Since I did well in math and science in high school, my father recommended
                    that I pursue pre-engineering studies at Yale, so I took calculus and chemistry
                    in my freshman year. But, at the end of that first year (this was still during
                    the Second World War), I felt very strongly that, even if engineers could move
                    mountains and control nature, their work was destroyed in wars, so it was more
                    important to prevent wars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So then you switched to an international relations
                        focus?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Almost. At the end of my freshman year, I decided not to go into
                    engineering and I selected an interdepartmental major in philosophy and
                    government. I took courses in that direction during my sophomore year.</p>
                <p>In September 1945, I turned 18, the war was over, but there was still the draft.
                    I found out I could enlist in the army for 18 months and be sure of getting out
                    after 18 months, so that is what I did. I was in the Army from January of 1946
                    until July of 1947. In September 1947, I returned to Yale and that is when I
                    switched again to the international relations major, which is what I followed
                    for those last two years and was my degree major.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do in the army?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>BACHE: In the army, after completing basic training at Fort Belvoir, Virginia, I
                    was selected for Officer Candidate School, but that would have meant extending
                    my enlistment for a longer period of time. Since I did not want to extend my
                    enlistment, I chose not to go to Officer Candidate School (OCS).</p>
                <p>In the meantime, however, all those who were candidates for OCS were put into the
                    cadre, training recruits in basic training. As a result, I went through basic
                    training eight times, the last seven times as a trainer. In the training
                    company, I was the squad corporal and my immediate supervisor was the platoon
                    sergeant.</p>
                <p>In such activities as teaching the recruits to march, the platoon sergeant would
                    often yell, scream and swear at the recruits when he was unhappy with their
                    performance. I usually found that quiet, patient explanation - sometimes
                    supplemented by further drill in the evening - was more effective in getting
                    results. I received commendations for things like teaching knot tying and map
                    reading. I did not enjoy my army experience at the time, but afterwards I was
                    very glad that I had had that experience.</p>
                <p>Q: After you got your degree from Yale in international relations in 1949, did
                    you then immediately go to Harvard?</p>
                <p>BACHE: Immediately after graduation in June 1949, I went to Europe on a concert
                    tour with the Yale Glee Club. We sang in England, France, Holland, Denmark,
                    Sweden, Norway, Finland and Germany. Needless to say, it was a thrilling
                    experience. After reading so much about the historical places in Europe, it was
                    really exciting to see them at first hand.</p>
                <p>After the concert tour in June and July, I spent much of August on a bicycle tour
                    of France with the man who had been my roommate during junior and senior years
                    at Yale.Also, later in life, at college reunions, I found that more of the
                    people who really mattered to me were fellow Glee Club members, rather than
                    academic classmates.</p>
                <p>In September of 1949, I entered Harvard Law School, where I learned to read all
                    over again. At Yale, I had learned to skim through voluminous texts and get the
                    gist of the contents. At law school, I found out, in the first few days, that,
                    even though I thought I had read the assignment, I had no idea what the
                    professor and the class were talking about, because they were analyzing
                    sentences, word by word and phrase by phrase. So that experience taught me how
                    to read carefully and to deal with new problems, no matter what the subject
                    matter.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>In my second year at Harvard Law School, I took the Foreign Service examination,
                    because at that time the State Department told us that you often had to wait a
                    year or two or three after taking the exam before getting into the Service. But
                    after I took the written exam in the fall of 1950, I was given the oral exam in
                    the spring of my second year at law school. I was told then by the State
                    Department that I had to come right away or not at all. So, at the end of my
                    second year of law school, I did go and went right to the Foreign Service
                    Institute in the summer of 1951.</p>
                <p>Q: Well, before we move on to your Foreign Service career, let's see if there are
                    any other details of your early life you might want to cover. For example,
                    growing up, what were your hobbies, or sports activities? Did you do any
                    writing? Were there any particular teachers who were influential in steering you
                    in a particular direction?</p>
                <p>BACHE: Well, taking the last question first, I was fortunate at Scarsdale High
                    School to have an excellent public school education. One of the outstanding
                    teachers, whom I had for American History in both 7th and 8th gradewas William
                    Steele; he gave us the facts of American history in a way that stayed with me
                    for the rest of my life. Also in junior high school, I had an outstanding
                    English teacher, Oliver Melchior, who later became principal of the high school.
                    I also had an extraordinarily talented math teacher, Carroll Ross.</p>
                <p>In 11th grade, I was inspired by a European history course with Dorothy Connors
                    and she also taught an advanced section of American history in 12th grade. In
                    the latter class, because we already had command of the basic facts (from Mr.
                    Steele's course), we could analyze trends and issues in a meaningful way.</p>
                <p>At Yale, in the international relations major, I took American Diplomatic History
                    with Samuel Bemis, who wrote our textbook, and European Diplomatic History with
                    Harry Rudin, both of whom were memorable. In Comparative Government, we had
                    Cecil Driver, an Englishman who had run for a seat in Parliament himself; when
                    he described the British institutions, he made us feel as if we were sitting
                    right there, watching the parliament in session (which I later did during a
                    visit to London).</p>
                <p>For the History of Philosophy, I had Professor Robert Calhoun, whose precision in
                    the language of his lectures was absolutely brilliant. In a course on French
                    Critics, Historians and Political Thinkers, I had Professor Henri Peyre, who had
                    an encyclopedic knowledge of French literature, history, philosophy and science.
                    Every one of his lectures (all in French) was eloquent.</p>
                <p>At Harvard Law, I had Austin Scott on trusts and Warren Seavey on torts, both of
                    whom were the top experts in their fields at the time. In my last year at law
                    school, I had a seminar on the Legal Aspects of U.S. Foreign Economic Policy,
                    taught by Kingman Brewster, who later became president of Yale University.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>And there were many others at Yale and at Harvard Law. I was very fortunate to
                    have the best education the United States had to offer at the time. All of these
                    high school teachers and college and law school professors inspired me to try to
                    leave the world in a better condition than I had found it.</p>
                <p>My main hobby all through school and college was music. I mentioned that my
                    mother was a singer. At age six, I started with piano lessons; at age ten, I
                    started on the cello. I soon found I couldn't keep up with both, so I dropped
                    piano, but continued with the cello and it has brought me great joy throughout
                    my life. Music has played a big role in my Foreign Service life, as well as in
                    retirement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you specifically play any sports during this
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: In our neighborhood, I used to play in a pickup softball game or touch
                    football on weekday afternoons. At school, I took the required physical
                    education courses and played some intramural games, but I was never an
                    athlete.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In addition, you went to Yale, which certainly is a fine
                        college. Was this a family decision that your parents encouraged you to
                        make? Did you have a scholarship? Did you have to work to get yourself
                        through Yale? Was it something your family helped you with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: My father and uncle were both alumni of Cornell University. I expected to
                    apply to Cornell, knowing very little about other colleges. But the principal of
                    my high school, Lester Nelson, who was an inspiration to many of us, told me
                    that I ought to apply to a school like Yale. I never dreamed that I would get
                    into a place like that. He wrote a glowing letter of recommendation.</p>
                <p>I was accepted and I also won a scholarship, which was not based on financial
                    need, but on merit. This scholarship did help me in my first two years at Yale.
                    I also worked sixteen hours a week at the University Library to earn my
                    board.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Michael, how did you first become interested in foreign
                        affairs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: As I said earlier, my stamp collection and family conversations got me
                    interested in current events and world history. I enjoyed reading up about the
                    history and events that were portrayed by the stamps. I entered junior high
                    school in September, 1939, which was just the time of the beginning of the
                    Second World War, and a lot of the daily news was about things overseas. We
                    often discussed these events at home with the family.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Also, I did enjoy studying foreign languages, which I first encountered in trying
                    to decipher what was written on the postage stamps. I started with French in 7th
                    grade and Latin in 10th. There was a four-year sequence of Latin courses at our
                    high school, but after 10th grade, I had only two years left in high school.
                    Therefore, I arranged to take second-year Latin (Caesar) in summer school
                    (between 10th and 11th grade), so that I could get into Cicero in 11th grade and
                    Virgil in 12th. I always found Latin very helpful in understanding the structure
                    and learning about the grammar of English and other languages.</p>
                <p>When I got to Yale, I took elementary German. It was an intensive spoken German
                    course (ten hours a week). After freshman year in that elementary German course,
                    I went into a 4th-year German class at Yale, where they were reading Lessing,
                    Goethe and Schiller. I was not only able to keep up, but the intensive spoken
                    German course had made me very comfortable with the classical literary elements
                    of the spoken language.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, my high school course in European history had reinforced my interest
                    in foreign affairs and my decision at the end of freshman year at college to
                    jump from engineering to social science was certainly a significant turning
                    point in directing me toward international relations. Such Yale courses as
                    comparative government and diplomatic history, mentioned above, as well as the
                    Yale Glee Club concert tour in Europe, reinforced this interest even
                    further.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that certainly would have given you a leg up in
                        joining the Foreign Service. When did you decide that joining the Foreign
                        Service was of interest to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I think it was some time in college, after I had decided on a major in
                    international relations. I had always thought that the Foreign Service was a
                    possibility, but I frankly doubted very much that I would ever get into the
                    Service, so I didn't take it too seriously.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, I have often thought that the reason I passed the written
                    exam was because I didn't expect to pass it. I just took the exam like a puzzle,
                    for the fun of it, like a game. I was relaxed, because I didn't seriously think
                    that I had a chance. I knew that I was interested in international affairs, but
                    I did not seriously think I could get into the Foreign Service until I found out
                    that I had passed the written exam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the first time you took the test?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said earlier that you then actually joined the Foreign
                        Service then, in about 1951.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, the oral exam was, I think, in March of 1951 and then very shortly
                    after that, I was invited and so I did join. The introductory class, A-100, was
                    from June to August of 1951.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you think of that course, the A-100 course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I enjoyed it. I enjoyed getting to know the other members of the class.
                    Mr. Thomasson was the director and Mr. Ralph Miller was his deputy. Mr. Miller
                    and his wife taught us things about protocol, how to conduct ourselves, calling
                    cards, invitations and social functions. Mr. Thomasson supervised the rest of
                    the training, which was given mostly by other individuals, who taught us the
                    basics about consular work, as well as economic, political and administrative
                    activities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In retrospect, did you find it useful as an introduction
                        to the Foreign Service? Was it boring, or interesting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: It was not boring. It was definitely very useful. As you will see, my
                    second tour of duty was in consular affairs, although most of my career was in
                    economic affairs. Yes, it was a very good introduction.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many other people do you recall, roughly, were in this
                        A-100 class with you, and what was your general impression of them? What
                        were they like, a mixture, men, women, ethnic diversity?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I think there were about 25 of us, mostly men. Several of them were
                    veterans from the war, who were older than the rest of us, but the others were
                    close to my age. I believe there was only one African-American in the whole
                    class. The group kept in touch and we had several reunions, one of them at my
                    house in Washington, in the early 1980s. Several members were very friendly and
                    supportive over the years, but all of my best friends from the class are now
                    dead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that most of your career you were an
                        economic officer. What prompted you to choose that particular path?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I mentioned that my major at Yale was international relations, but I did
                    take courses at Yale in elementary economics and international trade. At law
                    school, after completing the basic elementary courses that were required, I took
                    courses in subjects related to economics as much as I could. I took courses in
                    corporation law, accounting and statistics, all of which I felt were useful
                    background for economics. I also took two years of international law.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>During my studies of comparative government at Yale, I got the impression that
                    most of the issues that were discussed by the legislative bodies of the world
                    were economic issues. This impression did not change after I entered the Foreign
                    Service. Also, I guess my interest, because of my family's position in the stock
                    brokerage business, has always been in the economic side of world affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever work with your family enterprise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. One of the summers when I was at law school, I worked at Bache &amp;
                    Company in Wall Street. I had the basic training course, which meant a week as a
                    messenger, a couple of weeks in the Margin Department and a couple of weeks in
                    the Research Department, being introduced to the different elements of a stock
                    brokerage business. My uncle encouraged me to come to work for the firm, but I
                    wasn't ready to do so at that time.</p>
                <p>Q: Looking at your career pattern, I notice there is a break of a few years. We
                    will get into the details of your Foreign Service postings, but I notice there
                    seems to be a three-year period, '58 to '61, when you did work for Bache &amp;
                    Co. Had you left the Foreign Service?</p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, after my second overseas post in the Foreign Service, which was
                    Munich, Germany, I did resign from the Foreign Service and I did go to work for
                    Bache &amp; Co., first in their Legal Department and then in their Foreign
                    Department. I enjoyed those jobs, but I felt, at the end of those three years,
                    that what we were doing to help rich people get richer was less important than
                    what I had been doing in the Foreign Service, serving my country and being
                    present when history was being made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were you able to return to the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: At that time, there was a provision of law for reappointment of former
                    Foreign Service Officers. I don't know whether it still exists, but, at that
                    time, it was a specific statutory arrangement, so I was able to get back in
                    quite easily.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, let's take a more detailed look at the Foreign
                        Service Career itself. Your first posting, 1951 to '53, was as a junior
                        officer in Pusan, Korea. That must have been an interesting time to be
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. As you know, that was during the Korean war and the embassy had been
                    forced to retreat from Seoul to Pusan, because of the military operations. I
                    served under Ambassadors Muccio and Briggs. The Deputy Chiefs of Mission (DCMs)
                    were Alan Lightner and Niles Bond.</p>
                <p>As a junior economic officer, I was doing reports on subjects like the Korean
                    government's budget, under the supervision of our financial attache. I also
                    handled east-west trade matters, which included investigations of suspected
                    violations of U.S. export control regulations.</p>
                <p>In addition, I helped our agricultural attache do a couple of rice crop surveys;
                    the latter assignment offered an opportunity to travel throughout the country. I
                    remember that, along with the rice crop survey, we would do a livestock census.
                    The Korean government offered us the services of a mid-level official of the
                    Agriculture Ministry as an interpreter; I knew enough of the Korean language at
                    that time to recognize that, for example, every time the village chief would say
                    they had ten goats, this official would say eight goats. I reported these
                    discrepancies to the agricultural attache, who would make appropriate
                    corrections in his numbers. More than a year later, after I got to know this
                    mid-level Korean official quite well, I asked him why he did that and he said,
                    rather apologetically, that he was following orders of the Minister of
                    Agriculture, who wanted to give the Americans the impression that conditions
                    were bad, so we would increase the amount of U.S. economic aid to Korea.</p>
                <p>During this first experience for me in East Asia, I quickly learned that Koreans
                    considered it impolite to say “No” in answer to a question, so I learned not to
                    ask a question, which required a “yes or no” answer. Along these same lines, I
                    believe that many current misunderstandings between the U.S. and China, for
                    example, have been caused by this cultural difference. One case in point is the
                    fact that China, in joining the World Trade Organization, has signed many
                    complex agreements, promising many things in areas like intellectual property
                    law, without intending the kind of serious commitment that Americans would
                    consider implicit in the signing of such agreements.</p>
                <p>For the first year and a half of that two-year tour of duty in Korea, I got to
                    know the people who worked with the Finance Minister. Then the Finance Minister
                    became the Prime Minister, so, for the last six months of my tour, I was moved
                    over from the Economic Section to the Political Section of the Embassy, because
                    I knew the Prime Minister's entourage and was able to help with that kind of
                    reporting. That experience gave me a brief introduction to the work of an
                    Embassy political section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the war encroach on the mission there physically? Was
                        Pusan, while you were there, a scene of military action?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>BACHE: No. The Second Logistical Command of the U.S. Army was at the port of
                    Pusan, where a lot of military freight came in and out of the port, but
                    otherwise, we didn't see much of the military. The primary military activity was
                    up in the north, near the demarcation line between North and South Korea. The
                    really active part of the war was pretty well over before I got there in
                    September 1951. I did take field trips and I would see abandoned American tanks
                    in the middle of rice paddies. I would see what was left over from the war, but
                    the war itself did not interfere much with what we were doing.</p>
                <p>Before the Korean War, Pusan had been a city of 300,000 inhabitants. During the
                    war, 900,000 refugees arrived, swelling the population to 1,200,000. The result
                    was conditions of the most abject poverty, with refugees living in the depth of
                    winter in corrugated cardboard boxes. There were open sewers surrounding our
                    house and a smell that was ubiquitous.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular highlight of your Pusan experience that you
                        would like to mention?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, there were several things. There was a group of junior officials in
                    the Korean Foreign Ministry, who asked me to teach them some English, at an
                    advanced level. I used some material from my Yale courses in American and
                    European diplomatic history, in order to give them some of the vocabulary they
                    needed. When I was getting ready to leave Korea, they wanted to give me a very
                    generous gift, which, under State Department regulations, I had to refuse. It
                    was a difficult thing to deal with, because I didn't want to hurt their
                    feelings, but eventually we found a token gift that I could accept.</p>
                <p>I mentioned that I had always been interested in music, so I took my cello with
                    me when I went to Korea. Many members of the Seoul Symphony Orchestra had joined
                    the Korean Navy and there was a Korean Navy Symphony Orchestra, in which I was
                    invited to play. An example of the war conditions was the fact that, in the cold
                    winter weather, there was often no heat, so we would play with our overcoats on,
                    even in concerts. There was often no electricity, so we used candles, and there
                    were other problems from war conditions, but we persevered with our music.</p>
                <p>Later on, during my tour of duty in Korea, there were many Korean music students
                    who came to me, trying to get to the U.S. to study. So I wrote to a professor I
                    knew at the Yale Music School, and asked if he could offer a music scholarship
                    for a Korean student and he said yes. In order to be fair about offering the
                    scholarship, the American cultural attache and I, together with the conductor of
                    the Korean Navy Symphony Orchestra, decided to have a competition for the
                    scholarship and to be the judges of the competition. One contestant, named
                    Nak-ho Paik, whom we had never seen before, was head and shoulders above the
                    rest, so we awarded the scholarship to him. He went to Yale Music School, and
                    then on to Juilliard, and later became a professor of music at Seoul National
                    University.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Nak-ho has kept in touch with me and, over the years, he has given concerts
                    around the world, some of which I have attended. In fact, I played in an
                    informal concert with him in New Jersey just a couple of years ago. So that was
                    a memorable experience with music in Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were relations within the embassy? Did all the
                        sections get along well? Were the Ambassador and the DCM well regarded?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, I would say it was a very close-knit group. You remember, this was
                    during the war and living conditions were harsh. Married officers were not
                    allowed to bring their families. We were mostly bachelors and single women,
                    until - shortly before I left - Ambassador Briggs was allowed to bring his wife,
                    but none of the other members of the Embassy staff had their families with
                    them.</p>
                <p>There were very warm feelings among all of us and we had quite a few social
                    activities together. I shared a house with two bachelors, who worked in the
                    political section; one was a Chinese language officer and the other was a
                    Japanese language officer. The Chinese language officer was Philip Manhard, who
                    later on was captured in Vietnam and spent many years as a prisoner of war.</p>
                <p>One other social and recreational comment: I mentioned earlier that I had learned
                    to sail various sizes of boats under various conditions. Vincent Brandt, another
                    embassy officer in Korea, and I jointly purchased a sailboat and sailed it along
                    the Korean coast. Frankly, we enjoyed being out on the water, having some fresh
                    air and getting away from the smells of Pusan for a brief period. We had to
                    navigate difficult current conditions at the mouth of the Nakdong River, but we
                    succeeded in sailing as far as the island of Koje-do, which some people will
                    remember was the site of the main camp for Chinese prisoners-of-war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It sounds like it was a good experience, despite the
                        hardships that the embassy experienced for a long while. You were all
                        working for a good effort, a good cause. After that, what was your next
                        post?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: After I left Pusan in September 1953, I had to take nine months' leave
                    without pay, in order to go back and finish my third and final year at Harvard
                    Law School.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>My next Foreign Service post, beginning in the summer of 1954, was Munich,
                    Germany, where I was a visa officer. As you may recall, after the Second World
                    War, there were many refugees in West Germany from Eastern Europe, living either
                    in refugee camps or on their own. During my first two years in Munich, my job
                    was to examine applicants for immigrant visas to the United States and decide
                    whether or not to issue visas to them. Many of the applicants were refugees, who
                    were helped by voluntary agencies, which I will mention in a few minutes.
                    Virtually all of the interviews were conducted in German.</p>
                <p>By the way, the Consul General, when we arrived in Munich, was Alan Lightner, who
                    you remember had been DCM in Pusan; his successor as Consul General was Edward
                    Page. The deputy principal officer throughout my four years in Munich was
                    Raymond Ylitalo.</p>
                <p>After those first two years, I was promoted to chief of the visa section in
                    Munich, which was one of the largest U.S. visa operations in the world. It meant
                    that I had ten Americans and 27 Germans working under me. At the time, I was an
                    FSO-6 and the job was supposed to be filled by an FSO-4. I had to deal with all
                    the refusals and other difficult cases. I decided to have a panel of three visa
                    officers review those cases before we made a decision. When I was reviewing
                    those difficult visa cases, I often had to read the court records in German of
                    criminal cases, where the applicant had been convicted. We had to decide whether
                    or not this was a “crime involving moral turpitude,” as defined in U.S.
                    immigration law. Obviously, my experience in law school was very useful for that
                    purpose and was probably one of the reasons I was promoted to chief of section.
                    Another advantage was my fluency in the German language.</p>
                <p>When I had to inform an applicant that he had been refused a visa, I prided
                    myself on handling the discussion in a patient way that usually ended with the
                    applicant thanking me for my careful consideration of his case, rather than
                    going away angry. These were some of the same tactics I had used in the
                    Army.</p>
                <p>I also spent a lot of time on Congressional correspondence; I remember I once
                    calculated that we wrote an average of 30 letters a month - more than one per
                    working day - responding to Congressional inquiries about visa cases. We also
                    had occasional Congressional visits; one memorable occasion was when
                    Representative Emmanuel Celler, then Chairman of the House Judiciary Committee,
                    came to visit. My wife and I went to the opera with the Cellers - at his expense
                    - and then he came to our house and accompanied me on the piano as I sang and
                    played the cello.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>As chief of the visa section, I had to deal with the representatives of a large
                    number of voluntary agencies, such as Catholic Relief Services, Church World
                    Services, the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society, and other religious organizations,
                    as well as ethnic organizations, such as the American Fund for Czechoslovak
                    Refugees and the Tolstoy Foundation, which represented Russian refugees. I found
                    it was a nuisance for me to have to keep repeating myself in talking to each of
                    these representatives separately, so I started bringing in all of them once a
                    month. I would report to them on the news from Washington, the new directives
                    and instructions about procedures for visas and the like. They would bring up
                    their problems and questions and complaints. It was a help to me to do it all at
                    once, instead of separately with each of them. But they said they were very
                    grateful and kept thanking me for initiating the practice of the monthly
                    meetings. I believe that practice, which I started, continued after I left the
                    post.</p>
                <p>When I became chief of section, I was also aware that the local employees, over
                    the years, had developed a great number of form letters in German that they
                    would send to applicants to inform them of the status of their cases. I thought
                    it was inefficient to have so many different form letters (there were more than
                    100 of them) and I felt that there should be an official record in English of
                    all communications with applicants. I also found, sometimes, that applicants who
                    knew English, but not German, would receive these form letters in German from a
                    U.S. government office.</p>
                <p>Therefore, I reviewed all of these form letters, removed duplications, simplified
                    the language and reduced the number of different forms to about twenty. I also
                    translated all the texts into English and had the English text printed on the
                    back of the German letter. This was an example of the kind of streamlining that
                    I introduced to the visa operation. Another was rearranging the location of some
                    offices, so that both applicants and paperwork flowed through the office like a
                    production line.</p>
                <p>I mentioned earlier that I did music. In Munich, there was an amateur orchestra
                    that had been going for almost a hundred years before I arrived. I was invited
                    to join that orchestra, whose members were German doctors, businessmen, travel
                    agents, retired postmen and all kinds of people who enjoyed music. Again, it was
                    a chance to meet people and to get a better understanding of the culture and
                    society in which we were living.</p>
                <p>I also mentioned that I was interested in improving my knowledge of the German
                    language. Munich University was quite near the Consulate General, so I started
                    attending lectures on international law, being given in German, to get used to
                    the terminology. Then the professor invited me to participate in his seminar,
                    which I did, and had another academic year with a small group of students
                    studying law at Munich University.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is while you were still fully employed heading the
                        visa section?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BACHE: That is correct, but I was able to do this in the evening or in off hours,
                    one way or another, that didn't interfere with my work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe you mentioned earlier in our interview that,
                        when you were in Munich, you looked up family places?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, I mentioned that three of my four grandparents were born in the
                    United States, but my mother's father was born in a little village called
                    Unsleben. The family joke was that it really must have been 'Hundsleben,' which
                    means 'a dog's life.' Until my grandfather was six years old, he lived in
                    Unsleben, which is a village in Oberfranken (Upper Franconia) that is now part
                    of Bavaria in Germany. While I was stationed in Munich, we visited there and it
                    probably looked about the same as it had one hundred years earlier, with ducks
                    waddling in mud puddles in the middle of the main street of the village. On the
                    advice of the Gemeindeschreiber (village clerk) of Unsleben, we visited the
                    Catholic Church in a nearby village, which had the records of all the births and
                    deaths before the unification of Germany in 1870. There I found out more about
                    my mother's family and ancestors than she had ever known, by getting birth
                    certificates and other documents from that church office in Upper Franconia.</p>
                <p>When my grandfather was six, his family moved to a bigger town nearby, called Bad
                    Neustadt an der Saale, where he went to school. When he was sixteen, he
                    emigrated to the United States, to avoid being drafted into the Prussian army at
                    the time of the Franco-Prussian War. On the same trip that took us to Unsleben,
                    we also visited Bad Neustadt an der Saale, which was a typical German small city
                    or large town, where much of the architecture dated from the 18th and 19th
                    centuries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are there any other particular incidents that stand out
                        with regard to your service in Munich?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, shortly after my arrival in Munich, I noted the effect of the German
                    tradition of the Beamte, or government official, from the Nazi time and before
                    then. The Beamter would order people around and tell them what to do in a
                    peremptory manner. I felt strongly that U.S. government officials are public
                    servants, who are paid to serve the public and be helpful to people, not to bark
                    orders at them. Therefore, when I became chief of the visa section, I tried to
                    instill this attitude into our German employees in the Consulate General and I
                    saw a noticeable improvement in their behavior as a result.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The way that they would treat the public, the visa
                        applicants?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, and there were hundreds of them coming through the visa section every
                    day.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>Speaking of incidents in Munich that stand out and recalling my sailing
                    experience, I also wanted to mention that we had purchased a little sailboat on
                    the Starnberger See, which is a small lake not too far from Munich. On at least
                    one - maybe two - summer weekends while I was chief of section, we invited the
                    whole visa section to a picnic on the Starnberger See; I took several of them on
                    short sailing trips on the lake. This is one example of the way we helped morale
                    and got people to work together.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is the second tape of the interview with Michael
                        Bache on October 22, 2004, conducted by Theresa Tull. Michael, after Munich,
                        that is when you went back and tried the family business for a few years. We
                        have covered that. After that, you returned to the Foreign Service, the next
                        posting was Africa. That is a change!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, I went to Abidjan, Ivory Coast, West Africa, in the summer of 1961. I
                    remember, when I got the assignment, I had never heard of Abidjan and I thought
                    they had made a mistake and were talking about Abadan in Saudi Arabia. But, in
                    fact, they meant Abidjan, Ivory Coast. I served under Ambassadors Borden Reams
                    and James Wine.</p>
                <p>My job there was as commercial attache, the first American commercial attache
                    after Ivory Coast got its independence from France in 1960. I found that my
                    principal job was to help American businessmen to get around the French
                    stranglehold on trade with their former colony. I was helping American
                    businessmen who either wanted to export to Ivory Coast, or more often, wanted to
                    invest there. I felt it was my job to get to know the right people, so that when
                    an American businessman came to Abidjan, I could introduce him or direct him to
                    someone who could be helpful to him, either in government or in business.</p>
                <p>When I arrived in Abidjan, I had just come back from three years in Wall Street,
                    so the Chamber of Commerce of Ivory Coast invited me to give a few lectures in
                    French on the workings of the U.S. stock exchanges. That was fun to do, but also
                    a way to meet some of these people and get to know them, so I could call on them
                    for help when I needed it in introducing American businessmen to their local
                    counterparts.</p>
                <p>Naturally, it took some time for me to get to know the right people and some of
                    the French businessmen in Abidjan were resentful of my efforts. Thus, after my
                    first 18 months there, I realized that I had only just begun to carry out
                    effectively the duties of an American commercial attache in a former French
                    colony that was newly independent. That is why I volunteered for a second
                    18-month tour of duty in Abidjan, because I really did not feel I was earning my
                    pay until I got to know who was who and what was going on. Also, I really
                    enjoyed the job very much.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>An example of how I got to know who was who and what was going on in the
                    commercial world happened on a pineapple plantation. Pineapples were one of
                    Ivory Coast's major exports. When I met the French manager of the plantation, he
                    was complaining that he wanted to buy an Italian machine for processing
                    pineapples that was better and substantially cheaper than the available French
                    machine. He mentioned that the French machine cost about $150,000 and the
                    Italian about $100,000. When the plantation manager applied for the required
                    import license, however, the Ivoirian official in charge of licenses notified
                    the French manufacturer's association (the 'Patronat'), which, in turn,
                    prevailed upon the French manufacturer to offer the machine at $99,990. The
                    result was that the plantation manager was forced to buy the inferior French
                    machine, although he would have much preferred the Italian one. This episode
                    helped me to understand how the French government maintained its stranglehold on
                    trade with its former colonies and was very useful in later discussions with
                    American businessmen seeking to export to, and invest in, the Ivory Coast. Such
                    insights do not come in the first days of a tour of duty.</p>
                <p>My musical activities continued there. I did not bring my good 19th century
                    European cello, because I was afraid that the tropical heat and humidity would
                    damage it. Instead, I got one of my friends in Germany from the Munich days, who
                    had been president of our orchestra society and was also an importer of cocoa
                    and coffee from Ivory Coast, to buy me a cheap cello in Germany and ship it to
                    Abidjan. The USAID planning officer in Abidjan was a flutist and there was a
                    Frenchman, who worked in the Ivory Coast Ministry of Agriculture, who played the
                    viola. There were others and, in this way, we formed a chamber music group and
                    we performed at the U.S. Cultural Center (USIS) and the French Cultural Center.
                    Once again, I found that music is an international language, which helped me to
                    get to know people other than the government officials, with whom I had to deal
                    officially, and thus get to know the culture of the country where I was
                    stationed.</p>
                <p>In Abidjan, we had three small children at that point, at kindergarten and first
                    grade level. When they arrived, they did not know any French. We enrolled them
                    at a daytime school, run by the Catholic Church, called Externat St. Paul, where
                    the language of instruction was French. Fortunately, one of the priests there
                    was from Canada and spoke both French and English. When our children really
                    needed help, they could go to the Canadian father and make their needs
                    known.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned children and we didn't even mention the fact
                        that you had gotten married. Tell us a little something about your wife and
                        family.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. You will recall that, after returning from Korea and before going to
                    Germany, I took nine months' leave without pay to complete my third academic
                    year at Harvard Law School. There was a long weekend in January between the fall
                    and spring semesters. I was married on January 28, 1954 to Eleanor Krout, who
                    had been a classmate of mine at Scarsdale High School. Eleanor's father was a
                    professor of American history at Columbia University, who later became Dean of
                    the Graduate School, then Provost of the University. Eleanor and I had been
                    friends ever since high school and, during the autumn after I came back from
                    Korea, I persuaded her to marry me.</p>
                <p>Our first child, Marion, was born in a military hospital in Munich, in May of
                    1955. She, unfortunately, is severely mentally retarded and, even now, lives in
                    a group home. After Munich, when I was working in Wall Street and we were living
                    in northern New Jersey, we enrolled her in a special school for the mentally
                    retarded, but when we moved to Abidjan, we had to keep her at home. When we
                    returned to Washington, we again found a special school for her, as we did when
                    we got to Stockholm.</p>
                <p>Our second child, Stephen, was born in September 1957, also in a military
                    hospital in Munich. Our third child, Nicholas, was born in October 1958 in New
                    Jersey. Thus, we had three small children during most of the time - from 1958
                    until 1961 - when we were living in Westfield, New Jersey.</p>
                <p>Later on, when we were living in Abidjan, we decided that we had better sell our
                    house in Westfield. Therefore, while on home leave from Abidjan, we had some
                    work done on the house to get it fixed up and ready to sell. Some of the
                    construction workmen who came to the house were African-American. When the
                    workmen came to the house, the children immediately started speaking French to
                    them. They had seen in Abidjan that, whenever you saw someone who was black, you
                    had to speak French, so they did.</p>
                <p>Our fourth child, Vivian, was born in Washington, DC in April of 1965, after we
                    had returned from Africa. That completed our family of two boys and two
                    girls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did they like the Foreign Service life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I think they enjoyed it; I know they enjoyed it. I always felt that any
                    disruption of their education - from having to move from one place to another
                    and one school to another and one set of friends to another - was more than
                    offset by the experience, the tolerance of other cultures and the breadth of
                    view that comes from that kind of a life. I have felt that way and they have
                    said that they also felt that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have a publication in your hand. I think we ought to
                        hear about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>BACHE: When I left Abidjan, I had a two-year tour of duty in the U.S. Department
                    of Commerce; the first of those two years was spent in the Africa Division of
                    the Bureau of International Commerce. For some years, the Commerce Department
                    had been issuing a series of publications called “..., a Market for U.S.
                    Products.” During my time at Commerce, I wrote an 84-page booklet entitled
                    “Ivory Coast: A Market for U.S. Products.” The material in the booklet was based
                    on my observations during my three years in Ivory Coast, plus my readings in
                    French.</p>
                <p>At that time, there was absolutely nothing on Ivory Coast written in English.
                    This was in the mid-1960s and, as I mentioned above, there were a number of
                    American businessmen interested in investing there, because Ivory Coast was one
                    of the few African countries with a reasonably prosperous economy. Therefore,
                    when my booklet was published, many English-speaking businessmen from around the
                    world went to the U.S. Department of Commerce, wishing to buy copies of the
                    booklet. The Ivory Coast Embassy in Washington also wished to buy hundreds of
                    copies, but the Commerce Department didn't have hundreds of copies, so they did
                    a second printing. As a result, I feel that I earned some money for U.S.
                    taxpayers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Fabulous. What else were you doing? You worked for the
                        Department of Commerce. Is this before commercial officers were separated
                        out from the State Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, as commercial attaches in the field or as individuals on loan to
                    Commerce, we were still State Department employees at that time. The first year
                    of my two-year of duty at Commerce was spent in the Africa Division of
                    Commerce's Bureau of International Commerce, where I worked on the booklet I
                    just described, evaluated the performance of commercial officers stationed at
                    the larger posts in Africa and dealt with various trade problems as they
                    arose.</p>
                <p>My second year at Commerce was spent on the India-Pakistan desk in the Near East
                    South Asia Division of the Bureau of International Commerce. In addition to
                    duties similar to those just described in the Africa Division, I represented the
                    Commerce Department at the weekly interdepartmental meetings, chaired by the
                    Director (Carol Laise or Bruce Laingen) of South Asian Affairs at the State
                    Department. These meetings were instructive in helping me understand the roles
                    of the various U.S. government agencies represented at the meetings, such as
                    Treasury, Agriculture, ExImBank, Central Intelligence Agency, etc.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>For a couple of months at the end of my stint at Commerce, I was loaned to an ad
                    hoc organization, called (rather misleadingly) 'the Balance of Payments
                    Program,' where I reviewed applications by American corporations for direct
                    investments (i.e., American ownership of factories and the like) in developing
                    countries. This was a short-lived program of the Johnson administration,
                    ostensibly to reduce the deficit in our balance of payments. In connection with
                    that program, I worked closely with other government agencies, especially the
                    Treasury Department.</p>
                <p>From January to June 1967, I was sent to a six-month economics course at the
                    Foreign Service Institute, which was supposedly the equivalent of an
                    undergraduate major plus some graduate courses in economics. I doubt if the
                    course accomplished that much, but it did acquaint me with the terminology and
                    some of the methods of reasoning in economics, which were very useful in later
                    jobs that I held.</p>
                <p>From July 1967 until July 1969, I was assigned to the Bureau of European Affairs
                    at the State Department, in what was called EUR/RPE, which stands for 'Europe,
                    regional political/economic.' Under Dean Hinton and Tom Fina, I was dealing with
                    internal developments in the European Community in the late 1960s. At that time,
                    the EC was in its early development stages and it was a very interesting time to
                    observe those developments. For example, the U.S. Securities and Exchange
                    Commission sent some commissioners over to Brussels to discuss securities
                    regulation. As you can imagine, the work involved coordination with many other
                    U.S. government agencies.</p>
                <p>During the period (1965-69) that I was in Washington, both at Commerce and at
                    State, my family and I were able to spend some spring, summer and fall weekends
                    at our place here in New Jersey at the Atlantic Ocean shore. We had a sailboat
                    (an O'Day Daysailer) on Barnegat Bay. In the winter in Washington, I was able to
                    continue my musical activities by playing in an orchestra and a chamber music
                    group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were in the Department, working on these
                        economic issues in European affairs, how did you perceive the relationships
                        between the Department, in formulating policies with regard to Europe, and
                        other government agencies, such as the Commerce or the Treasury Departments?
                        Was there any conflict over things of that nature?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: As I mentioned, I regularly represented the Commerce Department in 1966 at
                    weekly interdepartmental meetings on India and Pakistan. When I was in State's
                    Bureau of European Affairs from 1967 until 1969, we again had frequent
                    interdepartmental meetings.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>But the primary contact with other agencies came when I had to 'clear' numerous
                    outgoing messages with officers representing various other bureaus of the State
                    Department, as well as other agencies of the government; this meant visiting or
                    telephoning individual officers in those organizations and either persuading
                    them to accept our draft message or negotiating with them to reach agreement on
                    some new language that would satisfy their bureaucratic requirements, as well as
                    ours. In general, I would say that most of these negotiations went smoothly,
                    partly because I took the same patient stance that I mentioned above in dealing
                    with army recruits and with visa applicants who had been refused a visa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But, by and large, did you feel there was pretty good
                        coordination among the various departments of government formulating policy?
                        You mentioned Congress, for example. Did you have contacts with Congress in
                        this position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Unlike my experience in Munich, where Congressional correspondence and
                    visits were heavy, I didn't have much personal contact with Congress in EUR/RPE,
                    but my bosses did. As I mentioned above, at the end of 1967, during Lyndon
                    Johnson's term as president, I worked on a special program in direct investment,
                    which involved close coordination with the Treasury Department and some contact
                    with Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You worked there compatibly, no real hassles?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I wasn't aware of any friction; there may have been some I didn't see.
                    But, as I mentioned above in connection with visa refusals and cable clearances,
                    my approach has always been patience and an effort to understand the other
                    side's point of view.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you finished the tour in RPE in '69. What was next on
                        the agenda?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: At this point, I was assigned to Stockholm, Sweden. The whole family
                    moved, but I went ahead in July and the rest of the family came along in August.
                    I remember watching the moon landing when I was alone there in Sweden; then the
                    family came a month later, after I found a house in a Stockholm suburb.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>My job in Stockholm made use of my experience with interdepartmental
                    coordination, especially because Sweden, even though it is a small country, is
                    big in the multilateral area. For example, at that time, Sweden was a member of
                    the Group of Ten in the International Monetary Fund, so I sometimes had to
                    deliver messages to the Governor of the Bank of Sweden on monetary questions.
                    Sweden was also very active in multilateral aid to developing countries and I
                    worked closely with the head of the Swedish International Development Agency
                    (SIDA), on multilateral aid. Also, in civil aviation, there was a Swede who was
                    head of the European Association of Civil Aviation Chiefs, so I often delivered
                    messages to him and from him about civil aviation questions for all of
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the specific position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I was the number two economic officer; there were only three of us. I
                    served there under Ambassador Jerome Holland. As you know, the State Department
                    defines economics really broadly, so I was dealing with trade policy (including
                    export controls), monetary policy, aid to developing countries, aviation policy,
                    intellectual property issues, regional planning and just about any other issue
                    that could conceivably be called 'economics.' My main job was reporting and
                    representation, which, as we all know, means delivering messages to the host
                    country, getting their reaction, reporting their reply; and making
                    recommendations of our own on U.S. policy in the area. It was mostly a matter of
                    coordination; we worked closely with the Swedes, as I say, on a lot of
                    multilateral issues, so it was a busy office.</p>
                <p>Then, in addition to all the rest, I wrote the semi-annual economic trends
                    report, which was published by the U.S. Department of Commerce. It told about
                    opening markets for U.S. products in Sweden. Of course, the work I had done in
                    Ivory Coast and the Commerce Department was a helpful background for that. We
                    had very able local employees, including some who could write first drafts of
                    some of these reports, but I had to review them carefully and put them in final
                    shape. As I say, we did the overview of the whole Swedish economy twice a year,
                    but in between we prepared separate reports on numerous products in more depth.
                    It was a demanding assignment, consisting mostly of economic reporting,
                    representation and market research.</p>
                <p>I was also the Embassy escort officer for several Congressional and other
                    visitors, who were interested in Swedish urban and regional planning and other
                    economic issues mentioned above. Eleanor and I would occasionally give dinner
                    parties for these visitors and the Swedish officials with whom they had met. As
                    you know, the escort officer and dinner routine is something that happened at
                    every post, but we did it in Stockholm (and, later, in Bonn) more than at most
                    other posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, I noticed the years you were there were 1969 to 1973,
                        the peak period of our involvement in Vietnam. My recollection is that
                        Sweden was not exactly supportive of U.S. efforts there. Did that impact on
                        your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: It was very interesting. They made a very strong separation between
                    political and economic issues. They made their statements on Vietnam and other
                    political issues, but they said that shouldn't interfere with our good, close
                    relations on economic issues. Of course, it was in their interest to treat it
                    that way, and they did, and I think pretty successfully. We let them get away
                    with it, I suppose, but that was it. I had close relations with all the
                    ministries and the banks and the Swedes who were involved with these economic
                    issues. I just didn't talk much about the political questions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any anti-Vietnam demonstrations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, there were lots of them. The prime minister, Olaf Palme, was even
                    leading the marchers sometimes. So, yes, there was a very noticeable dichotomy
                    there.</p>
                <p>Q: So, as good diplomats on both sides?</p>
                <p>BACHE: I just pretended that I didn't hear it. I mentioned Jerome Holland; I
                    think he was an ideal non-career diplomat. He trusted his professional staff and
                    consulted us a lot. Every time he was going to give a speech or go before the
                    press, or whatever he was going to do, he would call together the senior
                    officers of the embassy and ask us to give him a dry run on the questions he was
                    going to get and give him recommendations on how to treat those issues. He then
                    followed our advice. That made us feel as though we were wanted and respected.
                    It helped a lot in the morale of the whole Embassy staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your children, who were living with you at the time, were
                        they impacted by the anti-Vietnam sentiment? Did they ever complain to you
                        that they were being taunted about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I don't think so. The three of them (other than the eldest) went to the
                    Anglo-American School in Stockholm, where they had a good educational
                    experience. The lower grades were taught mostly by British teachers, while the
                    junior high school was taught mostly by Americans, so it was a mixture of
                    British and American curriculum. Most of the other students were children from
                    other embassies, children of businessmen from other countries and relatively few
                    Swedish children.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>Unfortunately, the Anglo-American School only went to the ninth grade, so we had
                    to send our older son, Stephen, to boarding school in the United States for his
                    senior high school years, but that actually turned out to be a good experience
                    for him. Our oldest child, Marion, who is mentally retarded, went to a special
                    school in Stockholm for the retarded, where much of the educational program was
                    non-verbal, so that language was not as much of an obstacle as you might expect.
                    She was even sent to a summer camp for the retarded in Norway. Thus, we had a
                    good situation for all of our children when we were in Stockholm.</p>
                <p>Again, I was able to do some water sports. There are 28,000 islands in the
                    Stockholm archipelago. We had a 17-foot sloop and sailed among those islands,
                    part way out into the Baltic Sea. Some of the islands are bird sanctuaries,
                    where you are not allowed to land, but you can get quite close with a sailboat
                    and observe the birds without disturbing them.</p>
                <p>In connection with my interest in languages, I should mention that the winter was
                    severe; after it snowed in November, we usually didn't see the ground again
                    until April. To get away from that winter, we decided to take the two boys to
                    the Canary Islands, which is Spanish territory. I wanted to know what was going
                    on around me, so I went to adult education night school to learn some Spanish.
                    We had a textbook in Swedish and a Swedish-speaking teacher, who was teaching us
                    Spanish in Swedish! So I knew a few words of Spanish before I got to the
                    Canaries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you speak Swedish too before you went to
                        Stockholm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: No, but I obtained a few phonograph records from the Foreign Service
                    Institute before I arrived in Sweden. Upon arrival, however, I found that I had
                    to read the newspapers and economic reports in Swedish right away. I found that
                    all the complex words in Swedish were either like French or German or English.
                    It was only the simple connecting words that were Scandinavian and that you had
                    to learn and understand. So it wasn't really hard to read and understand
                    Swedish. To speak it is a little harder, but I learned to make myself
                    understood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was to New York to the UN
                        Mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Exactly. That was from August 1973 to June 1976, so I was there under
                    Ambassadors Scali, Moynihan and Scranton. I was assigned to the Fifth Committee,
                    which was the committee on administrative and budgetary questions. I worked
                    mostly with the representatives of the finance ministries of the other
                    countries. In many ways, I think that committee is the most interesting place at
                    the UN. Each of the other committees (political, economic, social, etc.) dealt
                    with their own issues, but everything costs money, so when we were reviewing the
                    budget, we were dealing with every issue that came before the United
                    Nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>We lived in Maplewood in northern New Jersey and I commuted into New York. Since
                    I had grown up in the New York area, I could easily find my way around. Those
                    were enjoyable years; I was able to spend weekends at our place at the beach in
                    New Jersey and to play in an orchestra and a chamber music group in the
                    neighborhood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular budget issues that were
                        highlighted during the time you were there? I know that sometimes the
                        argument is made that the U.S. pays too large a percentage of the cost of
                        the UN. Did that come up at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: When I was at USUN - in the mid-'70s - there was a formula, based on gross
                    national product (GNP), which would have required the U.S. to pay more than 25%
                    of the UN budget. But the other UN member states had pretty well accepted by
                    that time the U.S. insistence that we were not going to pay more than 25% of the
                    principal elements of the UN budget. I think that the fight about what was our
                    share was over.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, however, while that fight had been going on, there had been
                    several occasions when the U.S. Congress had insisted on withholding some part
                    of our agreed contribution to the UN budget as the result of various
                    disagreements that had come up between the U.S. and the UN. In other words, the
                    U.S. was in arrears in making its contributions. We were committed to making
                    certain payments and we did not pay them on time. A big part of our job at USUN
                    in the mid-'70s, therefore, was to push Washington to get the money delivered,
                    because the UN was often hamstrung in its operations by the lack of cash that
                    had been promised and committed by the U.S., but not paid.</p>
                <p>In addition to the arrears problem, we were drafting resolutions all the time for
                    the General Assembly on a great variety of issues related to the budget and UN
                    administration. We would negotiate in the following manner: We had a little
                    caucus first among the Europeans, the Canadians, the Australians and the
                    Japanese, i.e., the major contributors.</p>
                <p>I always used to describe this method of negotiation, in Stockholm and again in
                    New York, on these multilateral issues, as concentric circles. You would go
                    first to Japan, Britain, Germany and France, i.e., those who contributed the
                    money and had to be on board if you wanted to get something done. After that,
                    you drew your circle of the more influential and friendly developing countries
                    and then, finally, the total circle of everybody. Just as I had seen this
                    negotiation method in Stockholm, it was the same in New York at the UN, only
                    there were many more such negotiations. We had a group called WEO (Western
                    Europe and Others), who caucused first and figured out what we wanted to
                    accomplish and how we could get agreement on that, and then we went to the
                    smaller circles and the bigger circles.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would you say was the most interesting thing you
                        dealt with at the UN? Do any particular issues stand out, or any particular
                        triumph or disappointment? For the U.S., not just from your personal
                        view.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: At one time, the issues of evaluation, auditing and inspections came up
                    and a sub-committee was formed, of which I was co-chairman; the other
                    co-chairman was a young man named Sethi from India. We worked well together and
                    produced a report, which was published by the UN Secretariat. The subject was
                    not very controversial, but I have a sense that I contributed, in a small way,
                    to the history of the UN and its administrative structure. That is an example of
                    a triumph, if you will.</p>
                <p>The following comment may be very political, but it was a fact. As I said, Pat
                    Moynihan was our ambassador for part of the time I was at USUN. Those of us on
                    the staff had spent months - and sometimes years - trying to develop good
                    relations with other delegations at the UN and then, in one wisecrack or one
                    ten-minute story, Moynihan would insult other delegations and destroy what we
                    had been building up for years. That was frustrating at times. He was, of
                    course, trying to get into a position to get elected as U.S. Senator from New
                    York, which he later did. He felt, just as human beings have since the days of
                    the Greeks and the Romans, that the way to get political support is to bash the
                    foreigners. So he practiced that and it was one of the disappointments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, moving along then, after the UN, where you were for
                        almost four years, you went off to Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, I went to Bonn, Germany in the summer of '76 and stayed until the
                    summer of 1980. For the first few months, I was civil air attache, working with
                    French and British officials on the special air regime governing air travel
                    between Berlin and West Germany. That regime was one of the last remaining
                    vestiges of the old occupation of Germany after World War II, but that
                    assignment was only a temporary one.</p>
                <p>After a couple of months as civil air attache, I became Counselor of Embassy for
                    Economic Affairs in our Embassy in Bonn, which, as you know, is one of our
                    bigger embassies. We have a very large economic section there and I was the
                    number two man in that section, under a Minister for Economic Affairs and under
                    Ambassador Walter Stoessel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know, when you were assigned to Bonn, that you
                        could become the economic counselor, or did this just evolve?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>BACHE: My recollection is that I didn't know and it evolved. I am glad it
                    happened, frankly, because it was a much more responsible position. I mean the
                    civil aviation job was interesting, but it was pretty narrow, whereas the
                    overall economic job I felt was much more important, because there you were
                    dealing with one of the 'big boys' in the world. It was reporting and
                    representation again, but on a more decisive level, because we were talking to a
                    key ally. Our policies on many of the issues were formulated only after we had
                    talked to the Germans, the Brits and the Japanese on these big economic
                    issues.</p>
                <p>As I mentioned before, the State Department defines economics broadly. A lot of
                    my time was spent on multilateral aid, with the German Ministry for Economic
                    Cooperation. At other times, it might be patents and copyrights or anti-trust
                    questions, where again my legal training was useful. It might be obvious
                    economic issues, like trade and energy policies. It was simply all the broad
                    issues with which the U.S. and the major powers in the world have to cope. So I
                    felt very satisfied, from a career point of view, with that job.</p>
                <p>We were located right in the birthplace of the composer Beethoven and I played in
                    a string quartet there; the other three players were German. I could practice my
                    German language and get to know non-official German people. The first violinist
                    was a retired official of the German Economics Ministry, who had been a prisoner
                    of war in Russia after the Second World War; the second violinist was the wife
                    of a professor of Greek at Bonn University; and the violist was an engineer at
                    Siemens. Again, they invited me to play in their orchestra. Thus, in Bonn, I
                    again found a combination of cultural and professional interests; it was one of
                    the most enjoyable posts I had.</p>
                <p>Our daughter Vivian, our youngest child, started in sixth grade at the Bonn
                    American School, which was run by the U.S. military school system. Between sixth
                    and seventh grades, at her choice, we sent her to a summer camp, where she could
                    learn some German. For seventh and eighth grades, she attended the Nicolas
                    Cusanus Gymnasium, which was part of the local German public school system.</p>
                <p>The gymnasium, i.e., secondary school, had a foreigners' division
                    (Auslaenderabteilung), which she attended in the autumn of her first year. There
                    she was given some of the terminology in math and history, so she could
                    understand what was going on. After Christmas vacation, she was in regular
                    classes with the German and other students and had a good experience there of
                    the other cultures. For example, one of her best friends at Nicolas Cusanus was
                    the daughter of a Turkish diplomat assigned to Bonn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that the ambassador at that time was Walter
                        Stoessel.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, Walter Stoessel was a very good leader and a generous man. He, like
                    Holland, did 'dry runs' with the country team before press conferences to help
                    him prepare. We helped him with a lot of his entertaining of officials and
                    visitors. Ambassador Stoessel and his wife were delightful people to work
                    with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As economic counselor, then, you would have been a key
                        element of the ambassador's country team?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Absolutely, although there was also an economic minister. The country team
                    included, of course, the DCM, the CIA station chief, the political counselor,
                    the public affairs counselor, etc. We also had a so-called 'legal attache' who
                    dealt with drug enforcement questions. It was a big embassy, as you would expect
                    in a country like Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the ambassador meet with the country team? Was it
                        a daily thing, a couple of times a week, or once a week?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: It was usually once a week, early in the morning and it took place in a
                    special room that was soundproofed. But, if there was some special occasion, the
                    country team might meet more often. Most of the time, however I think it was
                    once a week.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you felt like your contacts with him were adequate,
                        the ambassador and DCM, that you had all the contact you needed for your
                        work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Oh, yes, good strong support. I also felt that way in Abidjan and
                    Stockholm, but both of those posts were so much smaller, while Bonn was really a
                    big operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, moving on then, your next assignment was in
                        Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. After Bonn, I became the sole economic officer in the Human Rights
                    Bureau. People might wonder, what is an economic officer doing in the Human
                    Rights Bureau? There, I was chairman of the interagency Working Group on Human
                    Rights and Foreign Assistance. This working group evolved from the Christopher
                    Committee, which was established when Warren Christopher was Under Secretary of
                    State; he started this interagency committee and then it was continued at a
                    lower level.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>We had people from Treasury, Agriculture, AID (the Agency for International
                    Development), Commerce, the ExportImportBank, and any other relevant agencies of
                    the government. Every time we had to vote in the World Bank or one of the
                    regional development banks or some other place like that, on a loan to a country
                    with a poor human rights record, we had to decide how the U.S. would vote. We
                    also had to decide on the U.S. government action on a proposed bilateral U.S.
                    loan or grant to such a country.</p>
                <p>We had to do our analysis and make our recommendations, based on a combination of
                    political and economic factors. When we met, I was chairman, so I was able to
                    set the agenda. The members of the Working Group usually took turns drafting the
                    reports. That was also a good interagency experience for me.</p>
                <p>Another activity of the Bureau, in which I participated, was preparation of the
                    annual country reports on human rights practices. Along with others in the
                    Bureau, I reviewed the drafts prepared on each individual country's record for
                    the previous year and made recommendations for revisions. I concentrated, of
                    course, on the descriptions of economic activities of those governments, but I
                    also made other recommendations on other aspects of those governments' policies
                    and activities. My recollection is that my recommendations were always received
                    with good grace and I was aware of no significant friction resulting from those
                    recommendations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: My recollection of that time, when I also worked in the
                        Human Rights Bureau, was that having human rights as an element of foreign
                        policy was not universally a thrilling situation for a lot of our
                        colleagues, not only in State, but in other branches of government. How did
                        you feel about that? Did you feel you had to be in a combative mode, pushing
                        ideas or pushing views?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I guess I came to the Human Rights Bureau with the same prejudices as some
                    others, i.e., that this really is a side issue for foreign policy. In the past,
                    my experience was that the way to be successful in talking about human rights
                    and other domestic issues with other countries was to do it privately and
                    quietly and out of the public eye. Other countries often were willing to listen
                    if we kept it away from the public. I really was in disagreement with the policy
                    at the tail end of the Carter administration, where there was an effort by Pat
                    Derian, who was then head of the Bureau, and other political people to push this
                    as a public policy, to speak loudly about it.</p>
                <p>On the contrary, I have found it always to be more effective to keep it quiet and
                    let other countries' leaders know how we feel about human rights, but not have
                    to argue with us in public. That approach ties in with my attitude, ever since
                    my days in the Army, as described above. Thus, I was uncomfortable with those
                    activities of the Human Rights Bureau and I tried to push them in the direction
                    of keeping our actions quieter and less confrontational, because I thought that
                    would be the more effective way of dealing with these issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started off there for a few months when Pat Derian was
                        still Assistant Secretary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You joined the Bureau, what was it, June of '80?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: I guess it was July 1980. Yes, Pat Derian was there when I first
                    started.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then, when the administration changed, you worked there
                        during that period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. And, frankly, I was quite sympathetic. While I didn't agree with
                    everything Reagan said by any means, on that aspect of the Reagan administration
                    policies, I was more sympathetic to their approach than to the Carter
                    approach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Assistant Secretary who ultimately came in was Elliott
                        Abrams.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: That is right. Before that it was Steve Palmer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Steve was an acting deputy assistant secretary during that
                        period in 1981. What was your opinion of Elliot Abrams and how he conducted
                        the Bureau?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: It must have been a very short period that I was with him, because I
                    retired in February of 1982. I don't have a very strong impression of Elliot
                    Abrams. He seemed to have an axe to grind, too, but I honestly don't remember
                    clearly. I didn't have any problems working with him, but I haven't any clear
                    recollection of how I felt about those issues with him.</p>
                <p>Q: You did mention you preferred the Reagan administration approach, the quieter
                    approach.</p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes, absolutely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Abrams was Assistant Secretary, he pursued the
                        quieter approach.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was an interesting time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>BACHE: It is sort of ironic, because most of my life I have been more sympathetic
                    to Democrats than to Republicans. On the issue of human rights in foreign
                    policy, however, I felt that Carter had it wrong.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Quiet diplomacy rather than public, journalistic
                        diplomacy. You retired then in February of '82?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After what, 30 years in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Yes. Because of that interregnum from '58 to '61, it was not a full 30
                    years, but almost. My first post in Korea was a hardship post. In those days,
                    instead of getting hardship pay, we got credit towards retirement. So I retired
                    as if I had had 30 years, although it was really 29 plus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Michael, would you recommend the Foreign Service as a
                        career to young people coming along, to your grandchildren, perhaps?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BACHE: Very definitely, yes. You always have ups and downs and maybe problems
                    with current foreign policy, but the relationship between the United States and
                    the rest of the world is an exciting area to work in. The opportunities, even
                    for beginners and people quite young and inexperienced, are very worthwhile and,
                    of course, if you do well, you can advance and can influence policy. More
                    important, even at the working level, interacting with representatives of other
                    governments and understanding how the U.S. fits in the world is as exciting a
                    career as I can imagine.</p>
                <p>So, I certainly would recommend the Foreign Service to anyone who is so inclined.
                    Don't think it is just parties and games. There is a lot of hard work; it isn't
                    nine to five. You also have to learn some languages, you have to get some
                    expertise in some areas, but you can have an exciting life in the Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you, Michael.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>EPILOGUE</p>
                <p>[The following is a brief review of the highlights of my life after I retired
                    from the Foreign Service:]</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>From 1982 until 1989, I worked in the Washington, D.C. office of Prudential-Bache
                    Securities, as a registered representative. Many of my clients were State
                    Department employees. Since I had managed my assets when I was overseas, I knew
                    what they needed in managing their assets while they were overseas. During that
                    time, I took a correspondence course and became a Certified Financial
                    Planner.</p>
                <p>Then, in 1989, I left Prudential-Bache, but continued to work at home part-time
                    as a financial planner. In the meantime, my son Stephen had established his own
                    business - first as Yosemite Asset Management, then as Hamilton &amp; Bache and
                    later as Bache Capital Management - and I became a vice president of his
                    company. My business was quite separate from his, but I used the umbrella of his
                    registration with the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) and various state
                    regulators, rather than having to register myself separately.</p>
                <p>While in Washington, I continued to play cello in orchestras and chamber music
                    groups and we spent many weekends at our summer house in Lavallette at the
                    Jersey Shore. In 1991, we winterized the Lavallette house, i.e., we put in
                    insulation and heating. Then in September 1992, after shipping some furniture to
                    our children in South Dakota and California, we simplified our lives by selling
                    the house in Washington, D.C. and moving full-time to Lavallette.</p>
                <p>Since then, we have enjoyed a quieter life here in New Jersey, receiving the
                    visits of children and grandchildren here at the beach, usually in the summer,
                    and visiting them in the winter. We have also participated in a few local civic
                    activities, such as the local Democratic club and the local chapter of the
                    National Association of Retired Federal Employees. I have continued playing
                    cello, first in an orchestra and later in chamber music groups.</p>
                <p>My open heart surgery in 1997 led to an effort on my part to take care of my
                    health by carrying out a daily exercise program at a local gym. The result was a
                    substantial improvement in my health. Then, in May 2004, I was diagnosed with
                    pancreatic cancer. Since then, I have been limited in my activities to seeing
                    doctors, playing the cello in quartets and quintets and editing this
                    autobiographical 'oral history.' By and large, however, I have enjoyed good
                    health for most of my life and had a very satisfying retirement.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
