<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001002">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Frank S. Ruddy </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR FRANK S. RUDDY</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 9, 1991</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today is September 9, 1991 and this is an interview with
                        Ambassador Frank S. Ruddy on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic
                        Studies and I am Charles Stuart Kennedy. Mr. Ambassador I wonder if you
                        would give me a little of your background—where were you born, brought up
                        and your education.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>RUDDY: I was born in New York in 1937 in Jamaica, New York and went to St. Joan
                    of Arc grammar school in Jackson Heights, New York. St Joan's has a number of
                    famous alumni/ae such as John Guare whose play “Six Degrees of Separation” is
                    all the rage on Broadway; Father Tim Healy, the president of Georgetown, and on
                    and on. I went to a Jesuit high school, Xavier, in the city. To New Yorkers “the
                    city” is always Manhattan. I went to college at Holy Cross in Worcester. During
                    that period the Jesuit high schools in the city (there were five of them) would
                    not recommend students or send their transcripts to non-Catholic colleges. (West
                    Point, Annapolis and MIT were exceptions). I completed my military obligation
                    with The Marines (I was discharged with the exalted rank of corporal). After the
                    Marines I got a Master's in English from N.Y.U. and taught English to pay my way
                    through law school. I began teaching in high school and going to law school at
                    night and in the summer and then I got to teach in college. I taught Chaucer,
                    the English Romantics and a survey of American literature at a small liberal
                    arts college outside Chicago, and later I taught World Literature at Dillard
                    University in New Orleans. Dillard is called an “historically black university,”
                    and I taught there in 1964-65, beginning just about the time those three young
                    fellows from Brooklyn were murdered in Mississippi. I suppose I should have been
                    scared of Ku Klux Klan types, me, a northern white teaching at a black
                    university, driving around in a car with New York plates on it, but I was
                    probably too dumb to be scared. The truth is we had no trouble with anyone down
                    south, and we drove into Mississippi many times. Dillard itself was a beautiful
                    sprawling campus, white Georgian buildings, green lawns, probably the prettiest
                    campus in New Orleans. It was also a very sad place, and it depressed me. In the
                    same class I had juniors and seniors, bright enough to get selected for special
                    graduate programs like the Woodrow Wilson scholarships, sitting right next to
                    others who could not read. Those who could not read went back to teach in the
                    black schools in Louisiana! That is a fact. I later taught poetry at Fordham
                    when I was getting an LL.M. at N.Y.U. and I taught international law at
                    Cambridge. After I got my law degree I went on for an LL.M. at N.Y.U. and a
                    Pd.D. in international law at Cambridge (not Harvard, but the university John
                    Harvard went to!).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your Ph.D. in?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>RUDDY: International law. I was a lawyer when I went to Cambridge. At Cambridge
                    (and Oxford) a Ph.D. is purely a research degree. You're supposed to know the
                    basics by the time you get there so there are no obligatory courses. You are
                    truly on your own. You attend the lectures you want to, go to the library as
                    often or as seldom as you want, and generally control your own destiny.
                    Eventually, of course, you have to produce; that means finding something
                    important and original to say about your topic and then defend what you have to
                    say before a panel of very well read and incredulous professors. None of it is
                    easy. After meeting my supervisor for the first time, he said: “All right then,
                    Ruddy, get on with it.” That was it. Like the Nike ad, “Just do it.” The good
                    part was that I had a marvelous year reading all kinds of things trying to come
                    up with an original research project, and eventually I did. Two very well known
                    professors, one a historian, one a lawyer, were trying to get some research done
                    on a fascinating and very important character in the development of what we call
                    international law. His name was Emmerich de Vattel; (He is usually confused with
                    Vatel the chef of Louis XIV who killed himself when the souffle fell or the fish
                    didn't arrive.) My Vattel was Swiss; a dandy; a lady's man; a social butterfly;
                    an undistinguished diplomat without any original ideas. Yet this man produced
                    the most important book on international law (it was a bible to foreign offices)
                    from the middle of the 18th century until World War I. (Read my thesis if you
                    want to know how this all happened.) Very little had been written on Vattel, and
                    he was a research student's dream come true. I had French, so reading Vattel
                    (whose French was quite elegant) was no problem, and Latin as well for getting
                    into some of the thinkers whose ideas Vattel used. It also meant reading most of
                    the prominent French Enlightenment writers since the philosophes dealt with the
                    bases of law (Rousseau was going to write a sequel to his Social Contract
                    explaining the social contract among nations that created the international
                    community, but he never got round to it). Anyway, I finished my work after three
                    years at Cambridge and was lucky enough to get my thesis published a few years
                    later. I even made a few bucks on it. It's still in print, and I still get those
                    little (I emphasize little) royalty checks twice a year.</p>
                <p>Cambridge is more than a place where I went to school. It is part of our family
                    history. Our oldest son, Neil, was born there, and our daughter, Stephanie, is
                    buried there. She was a little over two about the time we were getting ready to
                    return to the States. We had Neil and her inoculated against measles, and, on
                    the last day of the incubation period, she died. About 10 children died of the
                    vaccine in England about that time. The cause of death was encephalitis, a fatal
                    case of measles. The vaccine was too strong.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>For a long time we couldn't think about Cambridge; now we can remember the happy
                    times. Simon Schama, the Harvard historian who wrote the very readable Citizens
                    about the French Revolution, was at Cambridge when I was there, and we even
                    shared a professor when I was bouncing around trying to come up with a research
                    project. He has an article in yesterday's (9.8.91) New York Times Magazine about
                    that wonderfully dotty professor, Walter Ullmann, we shared. I was translating
                    14th century Latin court records for him, and I think Schama was taking
                    tutorials from him. Schama mentions sitting in Ullmann's rooms in Trinity
                    reading his essay on the conversion of Emperor Constantine to Catholicism when
                    there was a loud thunder clap. Ullmann ran to the window. “Do you hear it?” he
                    asked Schama. “Do you know what it was? I hear the death knell of Byzantium.”
                    That was Ullmann. Eccentric, absorbed in the middle ages, a great character,
                    and, as Schama notes, a wonderful teacher who made history come alive. Cambridge
                    had a number of eccentric professors, some giants in their field. I had an
                    appointment one day with Professor MacKinnon of the Divinity School. He was an
                    authority on Kant who, for reasons too boring to go into, was very important to
                    my work. I arrived outside his office on time, but I could hear that he was
                    talking to someone, so I waited, and waited. After an hour, I couldn't wait any
                    more because of another appointment, I stuck my head in to interrupt him and see
                    if I could make another appointment. He was the only one there. For all that
                    time, he was talking to himself. I wound up working with Professor Sir Harry
                    Hinsley and Clive Parry. Both got chairs just after I left, probably as a reward
                    for putting up with me. Hinsley had a ritual. We got to his rooms, right above
                    Denis Brogan's, in a 15th century tower at St. John's, he would look around the
                    room for somewhere to put his overcoat. There never was room because the entire
                    floor, hip high, was covered with books. He would select a low pile, file his
                    coat neatly in quarters, and drop it. Always the same. Then to the fire for
                    sherry and a review of my latest chapter. Hinsley always had nice things to say
                    about my work, even when it was abominable. He was the good cop. Parry not
                    infrequently told me that the same chapter Hinsley had praised was “rubbish.” He
                    was the bad cop. Since I had to show my work to both, I began seeing Parry first
                    so I could go home with the nice words of Hinsley ringing in my ears.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What attracted you to the foreign affairs business of the
                        United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: At Cambridge I was working on public international law, and I wanted to
                    continue in that field. I got a chance to work for USIA as a lawyer, and I liked
                    that. I'd have preferred State, but there was no room at the inn. USIA turned
                    out to be a good choice because I could do a lot more than I could have at
                    State.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>There was also another connection. At Cambridge I volunteered to talk to student
                    groups about the legality of the United States role in Vietnam. (There were 401
                    Americans at Cambridge. 400 marched against the war. I was the one who didn't.)
                    As an international lawyer I was qualified to do that. USIA, or USIS as it is
                    known overseas, sent me all over England to speak to university groups. I was
                    usually booed, shouted down or simply refused the right to speak by the same
                    audience that had invited me. It was a good experience, certainly good
                    preparation for testifying before House committees which frequently employ a
                    version of this tactic. Some people said I was CIA. I wish I had been. I would
                    have been paid. As it was I got train fare. Worst of all, USIS didn't have a
                    clue about what they were doing. The best was a trip they arranged for me to the
                    Socialist Club of Liverpool University. In fact, the invitation was from the
                    Communist and Socialist Club of that university. I arrived in a dark blue suit
                    ready for “meaningful dialogue” with Fabian Socialists. I found instead people
                    in turtlenecks, Lenin caps and work clothes, led by the London editor of Pravda,
                    shouting me down. That was one of the places where I never got to speak. I think
                    maybe another reason I went to USIA was that they owed me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was from 1969-72. What type of work were you
                        doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: A lot of the usual boring stuff like contracts, which older lawyers pass
                    off on the newcomers. I was USIA's lawyer for Africa, and that was my first
                    exposure to Africa. USIA got me an extraordinary trip to Africa. During the
                    Angela Davis trial in California...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you explain what the Angela Davis trial was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: She was the person who was tried as a principal in the murder of a judge
                    in Marin County, California. During the trial of the so-called Soledad brothers,
                    they were called the Soledad brothers because they were in Soledad prison, there
                    was an escape attempt. A judge was killed. Angela Davis was implicated in
                    planning the escape. She made the FBI's “10 Most Wanted List” and was tried as a
                    principal because under California law a person who participates in a crime,
                    either helping people get away or planning a crime, is treated as a principal.
                    Since she was black, the American left saw a great propaganda opportunity and
                    made a big fuss about it, “ U.S. racism, legal lynching, the Scottsboro boys
                    revisited, etc.” The Bloc countries broadcast the same propaganda worldwide,
                    concentrating in Africa. (Angela Davis later ran three times as the Communist
                    Party's candidate for U.S. vice president.)</p>
                <p>To counter Bloc disinformation, USIA sent two lawyers to Africa . I went to
                    Anglophone Africa, probably because of my Cambridge connection, and lectured at
                    universities from Ethiopia to Nigeria down to South Africa, just basically to
                    try to explain the US position on that. They sent another lawyer into
                    Francophone Africa.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>The intensity of propaganda arriving in Africa from Eastern Europe on this case
                    amazed me. When I would get to places like Accra or Lagos, the students all had
                    copies of the book, Soledad Brothers, written by one of the defendants in the
                    Soledad trial, and, of course, presenting himself and his fellow defendants and
                    political prisoners, victims of a racist system, etc. The Bloc had funded the
                    distribution of the book throughout Africa. My job was simply to explain the
                    processes of American justice and hope that the Africans I addressed would see
                    the Davis trial as quite a normal and reasonable procedure to deal with someone
                    implicated in the murder of a judge. In addition, the tour was my first visit to
                    Africa. Have you ever been to Africa?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No I haven't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: It gets in your blood. It is such an exciting place once you have been
                    there. The French call this feeling, the need to get back to Africa, le mal
                    d'Afrique. We were talking to someone the other night asking that if I had a
                    chance to be an ambassador in any place in the world where would I go. I said
                    Africa. It is just the most exciting place that there ever was. At least that's
                    my opinion, and that opinion started from that time, that Angela Davis lecture
                    tour, from just being there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time why did it strike you as being so
                        exciting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: I suppose first, the mystery of it. You know, growing up with the Tarzan
                    movies and all that stuff. To actually be in this exotic place, I suppose that
                    was it. Once you are actually there and try to put things into perspective you
                    can't. It is so big. It just overcomes you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find on landing that you sort of wanted to move in
                        and help things get going?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>RUDDY: No, oh no! I went to Ghana first where I stayed in a hotel in Accra, in a
                    room where the door wouldn't lock. That was a good metaphor for my first visit
                    to Africa. This was a strange place, and I didn't know how Africans viewed white
                    people like me or what they would do (remember: I grew up in New York City). As
                    I traveled around I felt as vulnerable as a person in a hotel room that wouldn't
                    lock. There were also awful diseases. While I was there some American AID worker
                    died of blackwater fever. What was blackwater fever? Would I get it too?
                    Throughout the tour I continued to be wary of everything. I didn't want so much
                    to change Africa, I just wanted to survive it. Ghana, the Gold Coast, turned out
                    to be a good place to start. The markets in Accra brought you the real people of
                    Africa, exotic and wonderful (and some not so wonderful) smells, the crush of
                    Africans buying and selling. The beaches and clear blue water were right out of
                    Conde-Nast's travel magazine. A few hours in the slave museum in Accra teaches
                    you more about slavery than a shelf of books, and it is, or at least was when I
                    was there, politically incorrect. There were some (to me at least) surprising
                    African culprits along with the usual suspects.</p>
                <p>There were some funny things as well. I had just finished a television appearance
                    in Accra a few weeks after a coup d'etat. Some fellow I later learned was the
                    president of the country, General or Colonel Acheampong, went storming through
                    the studio firing TV people right and left (it was government TV). It seems the
                    president, dressed in a British style military uniform, safari jacket, short
                    trousers and high socks, had just made a television address to the country to
                    assure all Ghanaians that he was in charge, all was well, etc. It might have
                    gone well except for the fact that he gave the address sitting behind a desk.
                    Someone forgot to put up a modesty panel, and everyone in Ghana saw his
                    short-panted knees knocking together as he tried to inspire the nation. He was
                    not amused.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>From Ghana I went all the way across the continent to Ethiopia. This was while
                    Haile Selassie was still there. My lecture was to Ethiopian judges and lawyers
                    in a city called Asmara, next to the Red Sea. An Army helicopter was supposed to
                    take me over the Red Sea, but The Eritrean Liberation Army was active in the
                    area and we had to turn back. From Asmara I took a DC 3, called appropriately
                    the “vomit comet” for the way it bounced through the Ethiopian skies. Much of
                    Ethiopia is like our West, with mountains and canyons and very rough terrain.
                    That's why the Ethiopian guerrillas were so successful in attacking, then
                    evading, Mussolini's soldiers a half century ago. The terrain does not make for
                    friendly skies, however, and that's why the DC 3's were a godsend. They can go
                    anywhere. If you look out the window you feel you're on the Giant Teacup ride.
                    If you don't, you see people in various stages of distress and hear the
                    ululations of the women as the plane hits another air pocket. The only ones
                    unaffected were the goats and chickens and other animals which traveled right up
                    there with the passengers. The plane stops at the great old cities of Ethiopia,
                    places like Axum, Gondar, Lalibela. Entry to these once magnificent cities was
                    through airfields that were nothing more than large dusty fields. I thought of
                    the poem by Shelley, Ozymandias, another African “king of kings,” who insolently
                    inscribed his own monument with the words: “Look on my works, ye mighty, and
                    despair!” Shelley described the irony: “Nothing beside remains. Round the decay
                    of that colossal wreck, boundless and bare, the lone and level sands stretch far
                    away.” I spent a day in Lalibela, traveled up a mountain to a Coptic shrine by
                    donkey, visited St Michael's, a giant church built out of a boulder, from the
                    outside in ! I stayed at what passed for a motel, and people knocked at the door
                    during the evening trying to sell me Coptic crosses and other national treasures
                    which were supposed to come from St Michael's. I probably should have turned
                    those folks in to the police, but I couldn't bring myself to do it. The lives of
                    so many people I encountered, living in tukels, round wattle huts resembling
                    miniature Norman towers (the wealthy living in two- story tukels), were going
                    about their daily business as they might have 2,000 years ago, as if there had
                    been no industrial revolution, no communications revolution, no Europe or
                    America. Ethiopia was a time machine, and the dial was set for “way back.”</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>I then went down to South Africa to lecture to law students at Witwatersrand and
                    the University of Pretoria. I had the good fortune to run into a friend of mine
                    from Cambridge, John Dugard, who was, is, a lawyer very active in the civil
                    rights movement in South Africa. He was at this time the lawyer for Desmond
                    Tutu, as I later learned, although I wouldn't have known Desmond Tutu then if I
                    tripped over him. Dugard took me to see the pass courts, an institution which
                    happily no longer exists, and I was one of very few foreigners to see them in
                    operation. In apartheid law and theory, blacks were supposed to live in the
                    black homelands or bantustans. They needed a pass to get into the cities. Those
                    found without passes or with expired passes were hauled into the pass courts,
                    fined and sent back to the homelands. That, as I say, was the theory. The
                    reality was that the cities could not continue to function without black labor
                    from the homelands. The judge passing sentence on blacks for pass violations
                    probably had illegal blacks working in his house. In fact, generations of black
                    South Africans grew up in the cities and as city slickers, they knew no more
                    about farming or grazing, the kinds of things people did on the homelands, than
                    a cabby in New York City. Everyone knew this was the case. The pass courts were
                    just a way for the government to save face while winking at its own apartheid
                    laws. The pass laws and pass courts were new to me, and, in addition to being so
                    stupid, they seemed such a cruel game. The police rounded up a token number of
                    blacks without passes, put them in holding cells, brought them into court
                    (that's where I saw them), weak, shabbily dressed, fined them, sent them back to
                    the homelands, and then they would return from the homelands, and the process
                    would start all over again. It was like the judgment of Christ, the worse thing
                    I ever saw in South Africa. Of course, if they really wanted to eliminate the
                    system, they would have imposed severe punishments on the employers. But that
                    never was the idea.</p>
                <p>What the visitor saw of apartheid was mostly inconvenience. If you want a cab,
                    and you're in a hurry, you couldn't jump in any empty cab (as I attempted to do
                    when late for a reception by the U.S. ambassador). It had to be a racially
                    correct cab. The cab I jumped into couldn't take me because it was a black cab.
                    (The bureaucracy and costs required to keep this system going were immense.)
                    These kinds of things for a foreigner were stupidities, inconveniences, but for
                    the South Africans affected by them, the effects were devastating, families
                    separated, that sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the reaction of the people you were seeing after
                        you explained American justice?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>RUDDY: It was very different from what I had expected. To prepare myself for
                    tough questions, I had done a lot of research at the Library of Congress and
                    read the criminal law of all the countries I was going to visit as well as the
                    criminal law of the Eastern European countries which were making such a stink
                    about the Davis trial. I paid particular attention to the laws involving
                    accessories and the penalty for accessories. Not surprisingly, they were
                    basically identical to our own (California's in the Davis case) with little
                    variations here and there. That research paid off in Ghana, at The University of
                    Legon in Accra, where I was giving a talk to the law students. When I finished
                    talking about the Davis trial, there was a very loud and dramatic objection from
                    a student. He was carrying on about “the organized lynching California was
                    carrying out on Angela Davis...,” etc., and losing control. I suspect the
                    students may have agreed with him, but his out-of-control manner lost him the
                    audience's sympathy. I could sense that and felt I could toy with him a little
                    bit, something I never would have done if the audience were with him. I asked
                    him, relative to his outburst, “Can you really disagree with the reasonableness
                    of a law that says that a person who participates in a crime by “supplying the
                    wherewithal to commit that crime or providing counsel on how to commit the crime
                    “ should be tried as a principal? Is that really such a bad law?” “Yes,” he
                    responded. It is outrageous. It is fascism.” “But what I just recited to you,” I
                    said, “is Ghanaian law.” At that point the chairman of the meeting, the dean of
                    the law school, intervened and told the young man to sit down and keep quiet.
                    You don't get those kinds of “gotchas” often, at least I sure didn't, and the
                    African students I faced all across Africa were pretty cynical.</p>
                <p>There wasn't much of a difference between the student audiences in black Africa
                    and the in South Africa. The students were just critical of the United States.
                    It was more or less dealing with hormones and with kids who were 18; it didn't
                    too much matter where they were. I was from the Establishment and they were
                    against it. Pretty much like colleges in the States. The only place that
                    surprised me was at the University of Pretoria where I felt the students were
                    brain dead. They accepted whatever I said...they really didn't act like
                    university students. But every place else, including the university students in
                    Cape Town and Wits in Johannesburg, the students were critical, cynical and
                    pretty well informed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were Assistant General Counsel, who was the head
                        of USIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Frank Shakespeare.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel...you were a lawyer sort of sitting off
                        on one side...how did you feel about how USIA was run?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>RUDDY: First of all, you have to remember that I was in the trenches. I will give
                    you my view from the trenches since there doesn't seem to be any sand-bagging in
                    this interview. Frank Shakespeare is a good friend. When he was Ambassador in
                    Portugal, before he went to the Vatican, my sons and I went over from Madrid for
                    a couple of days. I thought he was terribly competent. I had to write statements
                    for him dealing for various committees. I would spend a long time learning about
                    satellites, or whatever we were testifying about.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By satellites you are referring to satellites in the sky
                        as opposed to satellites in the Soviet Union.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Oh yes, communication satellites. There was also at that point a big to-do
                    about the international law of satellites and what we could legally do with
                    things called direct broadcast satellites, satellites that could theoretically
                    (I emphasize theoretically) bypass state censors and broadcast directly into
                    people's homes. The Russian solution was simple. They said they would blast any
                    such satellites out of the sky. It was a classic Cold War scenario, and USIA had
                    the point in the debate. Shakespeare was called to testify on the question , and
                    I killed myself preparing his statement. I met him for the first time as I rode
                    up to the Hill with him. I realized in the ride up, he had never read my magnum
                    opus. I thought he was going to get killed. I was wrong. I guess his years at
                    CBS taught him about the technical side of international broadcasting, including
                    satellites, and nobody had to teach him about the Russians. He was a pro.</p>
                <p>When I got back from Africa after the Davis lectures, I told him about Roy
                    Wilkins. I had been with him in Cape Town and heard him lecture. He was watched
                    every where he went and his words were screened by the South African...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wilkins was...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: The head of NAACP at the time. He didn't have anything bad to say about
                    the United States. He said that American blacks at that time had the right to
                    vote, and they were going to use it to make changes. He dwelled on the
                    achievements that American blacks had made and the progress they were going to
                    make. He spoke that way of blacks in the United States as models of what could
                    be achieved in South Africa and about the crossroads that South Africa would
                    have to come to, crossroads between revolution and accommodation. The important
                    thing, I thought, was that here was a fellow who could really have blasted the
                    United States for its treatment of him and his race, but he had too much class
                    to do that. He was too good an American to do that on foreign soil. He dwelled
                    on the good things.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>When I got back and mentioned to Shakespeare how impressed I was by Wilkins,
                    Shakespeare's reaction was typical. Out came the old blue felt pen, and he
                    immediately wrote Wilkins a note saying how pleased he was to hear this report.
                    That is how Shakespeare was. He was decisive. When things were good he would
                    react quickly to them. He was fun to work with.</p>
                <p>There was a post script to the Wilkins story by the way. Congressman Diggs of
                    Michigan who was then a member and possibly chairman of the African Affairs
                    Subcommittee in the House, and several of his cohorts complained bitterly of
                    Wilkins' failure to excoriate the United States treatment of American blacks,
                    called him an Uncle Tom, etc. Diggs was to my mind an airhead, and I think he
                    actually wound up in jail. Diggs charges were pure demagoguery. Despite his
                    bloviating, Diggs had never read, or couldn't remember, the words of Franz
                    Fanon, the Che Guevara of North Africa. Although Fanon proclaimed the need for
                    revolutionary violence almost everywhere, he drew the line in The United States.
                    His words on the situation of blacks in the USA were remarkably similar to
                    Wilkins'. Fanon wrote that American blacks were better off than those in France
                    because in the United States “the Negro battles and is battled. There are laws
                    that, little by little, are invalidated under the Constitution. There are other
                    laws that forbid certain forms of discrimination. And we can be sure nothing is
                    going to be given free.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: USIA in those days was relatively a happy ship wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: From what I could see. Remember, I was just a lawyer and in the civil
                    service, not the Foreign Service. I didn't know much about The Foreign Service
                    or the exams people had to take to get into State, USIA, etc. As a lawyer you do
                    get a look at it all, but I wasn't examining it from a management point of view.
                    It was just a job and these foreign service folks were my colleagues .... One
                    thing I thought very interesting about USIA was that I used to car pool with
                    some people who were, I confess, extremely boring, but when they talked about
                    where they had been, what they had done, foreign characters they met, they
                    became interesting. What they had observed made them interesting and their jobs
                    seem exciting. If the business could turn these folks into great story tellers,
                    I thought there must be something pretty good about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were then moved for a while, in 1972, to dealing with
                        Congressional liaison?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>RUDDY: In 1972 I wanted to work on the Nixon campaign. Frank Shakespeare said
                    that there are only two people you want to work for—John Mitchell or Jim
                    Magruder -otherwise you will end up blowing up balloons. He arranged an
                    interview with Len Garment at the White House. I had written quite a few
                    articles for USIA, and they went all over the world. I can say, and it's so long
                    ago and so minor a distinction that I hope I can say I it without appearing to
                    boast, that I was USIA's hottest writer. I was the only one, and a hated lawyer
                    (is that redundant?) at that, who had pre-clearance from the press and
                    publications people. That meant they had enough faith in my work that I didn't
                    have to check with them before sending something out. You know how USIA does, or
                    at least, did those stories. Someone like me would write a story on some hot
                    American topic, The Pentagon Papers, for example, and USIA would send them to
                    USIS posts overseas (USIA is called USIS overseas; don't ask why.) At post our
                    people would use the material, of course, and adapt it, and frequently give them
                    my article to some influential local journalist and hope he would use it in his
                    column. It was common for foreign journalists to run my article intact, without
                    so much as a comma changed, under their bylines. I had done a great deal of
                    professional writing, good publishable stuff, and my proof was that all these
                    people around the world were publishing my work under their name. I was quite
                    confident when I went to see Len Garment, but I got nowhere. I didn't even get
                    offered a job blowing up balloons. I was really crushed but, of course, it
                    turned out in light of Watergate to have been the best thing that could have
                    happened to me. I should probably have worn it as a badge of honor that I didn't
                    make the cut because they really did hire some Bozo's.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The names you just mentioned, for anyone who might not be
                        familiar with the Watergate scandal during the Nixon Administration during
                        the 1972 campaign, are people who were very prominent in the Watergate
                        blowup.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, indeedy. John Mitchell was the head of the reelection campaign, the
                    Committee to Re-elect the President, which was called CREEP by its enemies. I am
                    not sure what McGruder's exact title was, but he went to jail. John Mitchell was
                    convicted as well and has since died. All of these people became very virtuous
                    when they were convicted with the exception of Mitchell, who was a man about it
                    as was Gordon Liddy. Liddy was a character, but he was the only guy to say, “I
                    knew what I was doing, I committed a crime, I am sorry I got caught, but I am
                    not going to rat on my friends.” He got hit with a very long prison sentence by
                    Judge “Maximum John” Sirica while the rest of them came up whining and got off
                    with much lighter sentences. Anyway, I didn't get the job at the White
                    House.</p>
                <p>Shakespeare asked me if I would like to work in the White House for Clay
                    Whitehead who was the head of the Office of Telecommunication Policy (OTP). I
                    did and was their senior attorney for a while. I was interviewed for the job and
                    hired by Antonin Scalia, who is now on the Supreme Court. He was the OTP General
                    Counsel at the time. He had gone to high school with me, about two years ahead
                    of me. I was at The White House for about a year.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>While at OTP I was called back to USIA sporadically to write a lot of Watergate
                    material because the General Counsel of USIA, Gordon Strachan, had been accused
                    of being the bag man in Watergate. He was obviously not the one to be writing
                    disinterested accounts of the investigation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Bag man is term for carrying money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, that was the term used. He was a very young, very pompous young man.
                    Not a bad fellow. Just overcome by Washington, the power he had and the
                    immaturity to deal with it. He was disbarred, but I think he has been reinstated
                    in Utah. I hope so. As I say he wasn't an evil person, just a young kid over his
                    head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the effect of Watergate on the
                        USIA side of our operations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: I don't think it could have mattered much less to the functioning or
                    morale at USIA. The White House Aparatchiks and individuals like Strachan, who,
                    as I mentioned had the reputation of being very arrogant, virtually ignored
                    USIA. Strachan, twenty something, told Jim Keogh, The Director of USIA, and a
                    respected journalist in his own right, that he (Strachan) would take care of him
                    when he could, but his real concern was with the White House. It was a situation
                    where you almost had an SS officer telling a Wehrmacht officer what to do. Keogh
                    had come down from Time where he was a senior editor. He was a media pro.
                    Strachan was just an ambitious yuppie who wound up getting very badly burned,
                    although I think the experience made him a changed man.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>This kind of ambition isn't a partisan thing. I dealt with some real lulus in the
                    Carter Administration when I was at Exxon, and I saw the same phenomenon among
                    some of the young hotshots in the 80s when President Reagan's Administration
                    began. Young people who think they have been appointed with a mission to change
                    the world tend to become terribly self important. That's Ruddy's law. You can
                    quote me. The worst manifestation of puppy-political-arrogance, to create an
                    Agnewism, I ever saw, however, was in the current (Bush) Administration. Many of
                    these young folks are not only out of touch with the people of the country, but
                    they go out of their way to offend and drive away the Reagan folks who are their
                    natural allies. They will learn. They all do, eventually. I suppose, at Energy,
                    at least (The Department of Energy) where I was working, there was some excuse
                    for the young people's attitude: The example of the incoming (and current)
                    Secretary of Energy, James Watkins. Mr Watkins, or rather Admiral Watkins as he
                    insisted, made it a point to denigrate the Reagan at DOE, and particularly that
                    of his predecessor, John Herrington. John Herrington is a strong man, but he's
                    also a gentleman and would never unnecessarily embarrass a predecessor, or
                    anyone for that matter, Republican or Democrat. Watkins was like a big girl,
                    whining publicly about all the problems he inherited. And he really was a piece
                    of work. I hope there aren't many more in the military like him. He had a staff
                    of thousands, not really thousands, of course, 37 was the number I heard, of
                    young people who treated him like a maharajah and presidential appointees as
                    beggars who should be content whenever they might touch the hem of his garment.
                    His chief of staff, Polly Gault, could have gotten a part in Macbeth. A young
                    Bella Abzug, make-up by Sherwin Williams, a raver and a ranter with a mouth that
                    would make Eddie Murphy blush. Watkins himself was, of course, quite content
                    with this state of affairs. With his 6 feet, 4 inches or so, and his
                    vainglorious ways, he always reminded me of Inspector Clousseau in the body of
                    Charles de Gaulle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am right now transcribing an interview with Ambassador
                        Henry Villard, who is 94, but is talking about how he got dumped on by the
                        young people of the Kennedy Administration. He was too old. The Kennedy
                        Administration thought ambassadors should be in their 40s, if that. Each
                        administration brings their own arrogance with them for a while.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Did you get involved in dealing with Vietnam? What was your impression of the
                    USIA side of Vietnam?</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>RUDDY: No, I didn't get too involved with Vietnam issues. I wrote a book review
                    of Telford Taylor's Nuremberg and Vietnam which compared U.S. actions in Vietnam
                    to the war crimes that led to the trial of high ranking Nazis at Nuremberg....Do
                    you remember that book on Vietnam? I thought it was an absolute fraud and said
                    so in my review. I wrote a review of his book when I was at USIA for the
                    American Bar Association. If I had written a review in praise of Telford
                    Taylor's book, the ABA Journal would have published it just as it was. But since
                    it was critical and suggested that Taylor was sensationalizing his argument to
                    sell the book, as well as engaging in some very sloppy scholarship, they ran a
                    counter review. They couldn't not run my review, but they weakened its effect as
                    much as they could.</p>
                <p>I mentioned earlier that when I was in Cambridge I went around England talking
                    about Vietnam and the legality of the U.S. position. Those were the kind of
                    things I did. It was a great experience. All these years later I often think of
                    that period. I learned a lot from it. I learned a lot about gullibility, dealing
                    with crowds, especially hostile one, all that was helpful (especially in
                    appearances before Congressional committees.) Just kidding !</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left USIA in 1973.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: From 1972-73 I was at the White House and then I came back because USIA
                    had a new General Counsel, Edward Hidalgo. Hidalgo was a Republican then, but
                    changed parties to work for Carter and become Secretary of Navy. He became a
                    Republican again when President Reagan came into office and wanted to be
                    ambassador to Mexico. Of course, they saw through him. But to return to the
                    question, when I knew him he had just become USIA's General Counsel, and I was
                    brought back as the Deputy General Counsel to basically run the office. He was
                    an experienced lawyer, but didn't have a lot experience with USIA or with
                    government in general. So I ran the day-to-day business of the office; I was
                    sort of the chief cook and bottle washer, and he would deal with important
                    political issues. I did that for about a year.</p>
                <p>At that point Exxon called. They were actually calling to talk to my predecessor
                    who had long since gone, and they wound up talking to me. There was an
                    opportunity in Houston and I took it. I had had enough of government for a
                    while.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, you were with Exxon from
                        what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: 1974-81.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of this big multinational
                        organization, how well equipped was it and responsive to a very volatile
                        world? OPEC was reaching its peak in those days and there were a lot of
                        challenges in different countries.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>RUDDY: I liked Exxon very much. It was a good company to work for. One of the
                    disappointments that I had with Exxon was that it wasn't as aggressive as I had
                    hoped it might be. Mobil, for example,...and all the employees at Exxon cheered
                    for Mobil's positions...took quite an aggressive stand on the harshly
                    anti-business bias of the Carter regulations and went to war in the press,
                    attacking the economic absurdities the Carter Administration was imposing. Exxon
                    never got out in front on issues like that. Exxon, through its foundations,
                    funded many of the organizations that were attacking Exxon and businesses
                    everywhere. I never could understand that. Working for Exxon was, in some ways,
                    as routine as working for the government. They hired very good people, almost
                    always over qualified for their positions, and many more than they actually
                    needed. They had very good lawyers, and over 200 of them in Houston alone, many
                    more than they needed. They had many more engineers than they needed. They had
                    many more everything than they needed. Since the employees were generally very
                    good at what they were hired to do, they became bored when there was so little
                    to challenge them. It was in this respect that Exxon resembled government work.
                    Many people who worked for Exxon, people like me and many others, found other
                    things to do (I edited a professional legal journal for The American Bar
                    Association in my free time, and Exxon picked up all costs, going so far as to
                    provide a part-time secretary to handle the considerable correspondence.) Others
                    “retired on the job;” That is, they came to work each day, did mechanical chores
                    and went home. A great waste really. Advancement was very slow because there
                    were so many people just as good as you were, and it wasn't what you would call
                    an exciting a place to work. It was a sound company, however, a decent company
                    that took it's public responsibilities seriously, and treated its employees
                    well. This thing that happened to Exxon in Valdez is just incredible. That's not
                    how Exxon does business. It was a terrible aberration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about an oil spill in Alaska.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: The Valdez was the name of the tanker that went aground in Prince William
                    Sound in Alaska. The captain apparently lost control. I am not sure where the
                    liability was ultimately found to lie. There was a very modest fine on the
                    captain. In any event, that sort of thing, a ship captain with a history of
                    alcoholism, for Exxon was extraordinary. I spent three months with several other
                    senior executives of Exxon just touring the country to visit other companies to
                    review their safety standards, just to keep Exxon up-to-date with the latest
                    safety techniques. That is how they did things. It is a very waspish company,
                    and they don't tolerate vices like drinking on the job, sometimes even off the
                    job. People noticed how executives behaved, how much they drank at Exxon
                    functions, and getting the reputation of a drinker, drug user, philanderer, etc.
                    was a sure way to block advancement. So, it is extraordinary what happened at
                    Valdez.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Exxon is a very decent company which employs, on the whole, nice people; very
                    competent people. If you finally got real responsibility, you could expect to be
                    at the office early, leave late and spend your weekends there. Upper management
                    at Exxon was a seven day a week job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you become involved in the Reagan campaign?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, I was for Reagan in 1976, the year he lost the nomination to Gerald
                    Ford. I remember driving back from Corpus Christi, the night of his famous
                    speech when he was invited up on the stage by Ford. I had been captivated by
                    him. I used to do a lot more speaking when I was in Houston, and I would listen
                    to tapes just to get the rhythm of good speakers. Some of those speeches I
                    listened to were Reagan's, and I thought whoever did his material, was a master.
                    Maybe his speaking style got me interested in his positions. I don't remember. I
                    was also working at that time for a right to life group called Life Advocates in
                    Houston.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right to life in today's jargon means opposed to
                        abortion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes. I used to tell picketers and protesters what their First Amendment
                    rights were, what the police and property owners could legally tell them to do,
                    that sort of thing. I also appeared on television and radio and testified before
                    the Texas legislature. As a matter of fact, the Texas legislature passed a law
                    which I wrote dealing with the rights of survivors of abortion, if you can
                    believe that. There is such a thing, people who are not completely aborted. It
                    is still law in Texas. Reagan was, of course, very strong on right to life, so
                    there was that connection.</p>
                <p>When he was elected I got a chance to come to Washington. I was interviewed for
                    the Legal Adviser position at State. I made the short list, the final 6 or 7,
                    but no cigar. Davis Robinson got the job. What then happened was that there was
                    a problem of Senate confirmation for the head of AID, Peter McPherson, and, I
                    think, for Chester Crocker, as well. I'm not sure whether Crocker was involved.
                    Some senators, Jesse Helms prominent among them, wanted to have a Conservative
                    in AID as a sort of counterbalance if Peter McPherson, who is a Republican but
                    of the Rockefeller-Northeast Establishment variety, were to be confirmed. So I
                    was the token Conservative at USAID. I didn't know quite what I was getting into
                    at the time. It was probably a pretty stupid thing to have done. But I was
                    offered the job to head his Africa Bureau in AID, and as the quid pro quo,
                    McPherson would be confirmed as the Administrator. And that is how I got there.
                    I guess I was chosen for Africa (as opposed to some other area) because I had
                    been there, and although I didn't know much about Africa I probably knew more
                    than the others being considered. I was an Assistant Administrator which is an
                    Assistant Secretary of State level job. The Houston radio station described
                    it...I remember listening to it one morning while I was shaving...as a low level
                    job, and probably in the general scheme of things, given all the jobs in
                    Washington, that probably was accurate. I guess if you have to explain how
                    important your job is, it isn't. So that is how I returned to Washington.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got there, was the thrust of our dealings with
                        Africa different under the Reagan Administration than under the Carter
                        Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Not really. That, I think, was the biggest surprise. I felt that under
                    McPherson there wasn't much leadership at all. I confess to no fondness for the
                    man, his strange dietary habits, (he used to sit during meetings drinking
                    glasses of very hot water), his problems pronouncing foreign names (we sat in
                    anticipation at staff meetings for what had become standard mutilations of
                    friendly nations: Guatemala became something like Gwala-mala, Zimbabwe was
                    Zim-bwab-WEE, with the last “wee” hitting a high note, and on and on. It was
                    like a game, and people could not look at one another when McPherson was
                    speaking for fear of bursting out laughing. You know how being unable to laugh
                    makes it more difficult not to laugh. More importantly, on substantive issues, I
                    lost all confidence in him as a leader and manager. So I am prejudiced. I admit
                    it. I felt he had betrayed the whole Reagan agenda. One of the biggest
                    controversies that we had was over population control in Africa. The law said
                    very clearly that we were not supposed to force population control on African
                    countries but to make assistance available to those countries that wanted it.
                    The population reference bureau, hardly a conservative institution, had done
                    polls during my watch at AID, that showed that of the countries in the
                    Sub-Sahara something in the neighborhood of 7 or 8 wanted population control
                    assistance. The rest were very happy and some wanted more children.</p>
                <p>My point was simply that AID shouldn't be forcing population control programs on
                    Africans. If they want them, the law says we have to make it available, but we
                    should not be coercing them. AID's position was that we were to push this
                    problem. If you can believe it, AID had even conditioned levels of aid to
                    several East African countries on their accepting population control programs.
                    This kind of pressure was not only inhumane, taking advantage of the poverty in
                    these countries, it was clearly and absolutely illegal. I sent out cables
                    countermanding these policies, and since their author is quite ill now, I will
                    leave it at that. In addition, I didn't think it made much sense to treat
                    population as the problem when it was, in all likelihood, the symptom.
                    Historically, most of Africa's population problems are really man made:
                    Variations of Marxist economic systems that can't work, civil wars in places
                    like The Sudan, Ethiopia, Zimbabwe, and, of course, the predictable and
                    avoidable famines in places like The Sahel, caused by blundering and incompetent
                    governments. If you ever want to see demonstrated the truth of one of those
                    three great lies, “I'm from the government, and I'm here to help you,” go to
                    Africa. But you see the emaciated faces of starving people in posters and
                    television, and the natural reaction is to agree, “Yes, there are just too many
                    people to feed over there.” That's what you're supposed to think and why those
                    kinds of campaigns are so successful. Take China, everybody's candidate for a
                    greatly over populated country. Is it ? China that has the same population
                    density as Pennsylvania. Is it really a question of population or is it a
                    question of form of government? You can compare China with Taiwan which has a
                    greater population and say why isn't China doing better.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>I personally thought pushing population programs was a terrible abuse of
                    individual freedoms, and amounted to subsidizing and supporting incompetent and
                    very oppressive governments whose only way of achieving progress was not to
                    increase the economy to meet the needs of the population but to cut down the
                    population to fit a meager economy. But in any event, I thought the President
                    had spoken on that. I thought the position of our Administration was fairly
                    clear but there continued to be a big to-do on that within AID. You must
                    remember that the AID career people were brought up on government-to-government
                    programs. That's all they knew. Many came from The Peace Corps. Hardly any had
                    worked in real jobs, where business made the money that paid the taxes that paid
                    their salaries. Their idea was good (Help poor people), but the only way they
                    knew to achieve that was to have the government do it. When the government said
                    population control was the answer to Third World poverty, and that was AID's
                    answer for years, they bought it, not out of some ideological motive, but
                    because they trusted in the wisdom of government. Remember. You don't have a lot
                    of independent thinkers at AID. So, when someone new, like me, came along and
                    said we have to rethink our population policy, they were not buying. And when
                    the saw The Administrator was taking the old Democratic line on population
                    control, they knew where they came out. McPherson and I went back and forth on
                    this issue, and I felt, and told him to his face, that he had sold out to the
                    Rockefeller population type interests. There was continual tension there, as you
                    can imagine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you give a little feel of the power dynamics at that
                        time within AID? You have an Administrator who you felt was relatively weak.
                        Who would be pushing for this? Was it professionals in AID, people from
                        outside...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: It wasn't that the Administrator had to be weak. He actually had a very
                    strong position, a bully pulpit if he chose to use it. I thought his weakness
                    was that he wasn't upholding the Administration's position, Reagan's position.
                    For example, in Cancun...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cancun was a conference on an island off Mexico concerning
                        economic development around 1981.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Right. The President's message was that you could trust in the good sense
                    of people. The individual is foolish, but the species is wise as Edmund Burke
                    said. There is a lot of wisdom and that when, for example, Africans are having
                    children, those Africans have to live with those decisions, with those children,
                    but the experts that USAID sends over don't. Experts can come in and say you
                    must to this and that and then they go home. In Africa, 80 percent of the farms
                    in Africa are 5 hectares or less. It is a family operation. Infant mortality
                    used to be extremely high. Having a large number of children made good economic
                    sense in most cases. In that context, the Africans probably know what they are
                    doing; they are not just propagating mindlessly, as the population crisis people
                    would have you believe. I thought respecting the good sense of Africans was
                    quite consistent with the Reagan philosophy. I didn't know it at the time, but
                    an economist from Chicago would win a Nobel Prize for demonstrating the good
                    economic sense exercised in daily household decisions. That was my point, but I
                    didn't have any Nobel laureate to quote.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>On the other side, you had the Erhlich (of The Population Bomb) mentality, a type
                    that goes back to The Enlightenment thinkers. These folks have a problem
                    reconciling the rationality of people with their actions and therefore must step
                    in and guide the under developed rationally until they are in a position to act
                    for themselves. “We know what is best for you” is their motto, and they see
                    their role as that of deciding what is best for people everywhere, especially in
                    The Third World. You know their propaganda: “The earth is running out of vital
                    natural resources. Here on life boat or space ship earth (choose your own
                    metaphor) we have to conserve our precious resources because when these are gone
                    there won't be anymore available.” You've heard it a million times. Again, if
                    you read somebody like Julian Simon, you see the nonsense of Erhlich's position.
                    The naivete of the reading public is amazing. Here you have Ehrlich, a
                    lepidopterist, a butterfly specialist, and, all of a sudden he passes himself
                    off as an expert on the environment, economics, sociology, and he gets away with
                    it. Can you imagine a professor of butterflies walking into the dean's office of
                    some university and saying: “This term, instead of butterflies, I want to teach
                    economics, or geology or earth sciences?” He would be laughed out of the office,
                    but the same person can write a book, and magazine editors and talk show hosts
                    who don't know much about science or the scientific method, fall all over
                    themselves getting out the message (If, it is apocalyptic and/or sensational, as
                    it usually is, see, e.g. The Population Bomb.) Dixy Lee Ray, the former AEC
                    Commissioner, Washington University Professor, Assistant Secretary of State, has
                    a book about to come out, or, maybe it's published by now, on the subject of the
                    selling of pseudo science in America. On the other hand, every once in a while
                    there is a piece which deflates the popular pseudo-scientists. I don't know if
                    you saw the article in the New York Times last December describing the bet
                    Julian Simon, the fellow I mentioned earlier, a professor at Maryland, made with
                    Tom Ehrlich 10 years ago on whether the price of the six important metals would
                    go up or down in the next decade. If The Population Bomb thesis was correct, as
                    population increased and exhausted precious metals, the price of those metals
                    would rise as they became scarcer. Conversely, if the prices did not rise, it
                    was a sign that they were not becoming scarcer and the population bomb hysteria
                    was bunk. The New York Times Magazine, in a long article on the bet reported
                    that and Ehrlich lost on every single metal. Yet, reported The Times, even
                    though Simon's stock was rising in the academic community, Ehrlich's doomsday
                    mentality still captivated the general public. I could add that it still
                    captivates the State Department and USAID establishments as well. I thought this
                    kind of pessimism and defeatism was the exact opposite of what President Reagan
                    stood for: people are not the problem; inefficient, oppressive governments are.
                    President Reagan's approach was to empower people, unlike the Carter
                    Administration's Global 2000 Report, which saw people as a problem getting in
                    the way of dirigiste governments. When there got to be too many people, you just
                    had to lop off the excess. Take a look at China's forced abortion programs.
                    Anyway, what concerned me was that McPherson bought the Global 2000 approach
                    completely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the Rockefeller...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, in the same sense that Keynesian economists called Keynesians, you
                    could describe this approach as “Rockefelleran” or whatever the adjective is for
                    Rockefeller. It was certainly an approach to global problems the Rockefellers
                    supported and continue to support. The Global 2000 Report, itself, was something
                    created at the end of the Carter Administration. Essentially, it updated the
                    gloomy and discredited Club of Rome report from the 70s. Even though the Club of
                    Rome analyses and predictions were so egregiously wrong, and proved to be so, in
                    their report on the state of the world, the doomsayers were never in doubt that
                    the sky was indeed falling, resources were running out, population was getting
                    out of control and that only super government, like Superman, could save the
                    day. It's really a very old approach going back at least to The Enlightenment.
                    Faced with the reality that reliance on reason was not the great panacea it was
                    cracked up to be, (some people were not too bright) one school of philosophies
                    realized that what these sheep needed were shepherds to point them in the right
                    direction until they were capable of reasoning for themselves. The philosophies
                    appointed themselves shepherds since the lack lacked the capacity to choose
                    intelligently. You see the same phenomenon in those environmental-population
                    zealots who somehow see themselves chosen to lead humanity out of the
                    wilderness. That's the kind of person who looks to state control as a solution
                    to every problem because he has no confidence in the good sense and judgment of
                    ordinary people (read sheep).</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>The Reagan position, and I think a more sensible position, was human ingenuity
                    will solve most of the world's economic problems if it is has the incentives and
                    is given the freedom to do it. Most of the problems described in the Club of
                    Rome and the Global 2000 Report were the result of human errors, things like
                    oppressive governments and unreal economics, and if the basic problems were
                    dealt with, as opposed to just dealing with the symptoms, real solutions could
                    be found. For example, is population the cause or a symptom of China's economic
                    stagnation? If you say the cause, how do you explain the prosperity of places
                    like Hong Kong and Taiwan where there is the same racial group and a much higher
                    population density? Anyway that was a basic difference that I had with the
                    bureaucrats and power structure at AID. I think I made some progress in getting
                    the senior officials in the Africa Bureau to understand what was meant by a free
                    market economy, even if they didn't buy it. I organized departmental wide
                    seminars, debates would be a better word, on a wide range of issues. I brought
                    in people like Max Singer, Julian Simon, Lord Bauer, Herman Kahn (I don't
                    remember everyone, but that's the kind of guests I had), and they would
                    challenge some AID policy or position on economic grounds. I remember well when
                    I invited Max Singer, a forceful critic of Global 2000, to debate it with the
                    very people from USAID and State who had authored the report. I got three calls,
                    from McPherson's office, from Jay Morris who was McPherson's #2, and from Nyle
                    Brady, the USAID science advisor, asking me to call off the seminar. I said I
                    would if anyone could convince me it was a bad idea to debate the economic sense
                    of a highly flawed document which still influenced USAID policy, or, if any of
                    them, (they were all my superiors) would go on record with a written order
                    directing me to cancel it. Of course, they were all scared to death of going on
                    record to squelch a debate on Global 2000, and the debate went off as planned.
                    Singer annihilated the State/USAID contingent and got people talking about
                    Global 2000 instead of just accepting its findings blindly. I called that
                    progress. In another sense these kinds of victories were few and far between,
                    and I began to think it wouldn't have made any difference if Abby Hoffman or
                    William F. Buckley were running AID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Abby Hoffman being a member of the extreme left and
                        William F. Buckley being on the extreme right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>RUDDY: It wouldn't make any difference if either one were running USAID, or, I
                    should say, if either were titular head of USAID. The bureaucracy runs USAID.
                    Buckley, Hoffman, you name the director, the results would be the same. Some of
                    the USAID bureaucrats might really think they are in favor of private
                    enterprise, but, as somebody said of the conservationists, their heart in the
                    right place but they wouldn't know an entrepreneur if he kicked them in the ass.
                    Most USAID people have had no experience in business, by and large; they never
                    had to create products people would buy or provide services people would pay to
                    use, and, of course, they never had to meet a payroll. A great many USAID have
                    worked for the government all their lives, beginning with the Peace Corps or
                    spending their whole career with AID. Their idea of getting things done was
                    having the government do it. For these people to go out and encourage people to
                    create wealth through private enterprise instead of relying on the government to
                    supply what they needed was not, is not, something these folks are equipped to
                    do. They had never done it themselves. Like Rush Limbaugh talking about the
                    virtues of jogging, it was not part of their world. Aid folks were exactly the
                    wrong people to sell that message. It wasn't that there was any conspiracy or
                    that they were somehow acting behind the scenes to subvert free enterprise
                    initiatives. You can't expect an organization like USAID to promote free
                    enterprise any more than you can expect the Post Office to understand what makes
                    Federal Express or UPS tick.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Going back to the population problem and looking at
                        Washington as a political machine. Here the President had made his
                        announcement, everybody knew where he was coming from. He was not in favor
                        of the United States pushing birth control—certainly coercive birth control
                        methods. Here you had AID not really responding to this and you represented
                        the President's position. Were you able to tap into the White House? Often
                        there is a way of getting things from the Chief of Staff at the White House
                        or some other way to get the government apparatus on the right track.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>RUDDY: No. At least, none I knew of. Remember: I wasn't a movement Conservative.
                    I was a lawyer who happened to be Conservative. I didn't belong to the old boy
                    Conservative network. I had friends in some important positions, and they knew
                    what was going on. There probably was a much more effective way than I used for
                    getting The White House's attention, but I didn't want to be seen as a whiner. I
                    thought of myself as manning an outpost in enemy territory and having to look
                    out for myself. To get back to your question, clearly, the President's position
                    was very clearly against abortion and those kinds of coercive birth control
                    methods. For example, in the 1984 Mexico City conference on population, Senator
                    Buckley headed the U.S. delegation which took, I thought, a very moderate
                    position: that population by itself was not a crucial economic problem for the
                    world. Population could be good for the economy; it could be bad, but it was not
                    the key problem. You would have thought that he was urging some wild new flat
                    earth policy, and, of course, there was a lot of sniping, a lot of leaking meant
                    to embarrass Senator Buckley within the Administration where the population
                    lobby had a strong fifth column. And that's completely understandable. Apart
                    from the ideologues who see themselves appointed to instruct humanity in what's
                    best for it, a great many people are getting a lot of money to carry out
                    population programs. If someone comes along and says: “there is no population
                    crisis,” their golden goose may stop producing. It also goes across party lines.
                    You have the population controllers within the Republican Party—Rockefeller, as
                    I mentioned, is a big supporter of this, as is Senator Simpson of Wyoming,
                    Senator Goldwater, and others.</p>
                <p>So, to get back to your question, no, it isn't just getting to the right person
                    and everything is hunky-dory. It is a continuing controversy now, as much today
                    as it was then. There were people in the White House who knew exactly what the
                    situation in USAID was; that was why I was put there. Eventually, after a lot of
                    in fighting, guerrilla warfare really within USAID, McPherson tried to get me
                    out of there. I saw Senator Helms and ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Senator Helms represents the Republican conservative wing
                        from North Carolina.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: I told Senator Helms it was war over at USAID and asked him, “Can you get
                    me out of here? I am getting killed over there. It is awful to go to work
                    anymore.” He said, “Well, Frank, we know you are doing a great job over there.
                    We would like to keep you there if we can.” So that meant that I had to stay;
                    his answer meant there was really no place to go. If McPherson had his way I
                    would have been on the street. On the day he actually tried to fire me, I was
                    sitting in Jack Kemp's office. “Don't do it,” Jack told McPherson on the phone,
                    and McPherson backed off.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Shortly thereafter (in 1983) I became an Assistant Administrator without
                    portfolio. They couldn't fire me because the White House wouldn't let them, but
                    they could reassign me. For about a year I was watching the cars come in and out
                    of the 23rd street entrance to The State Department. It was a battle I lost, but
                    I didn't give in; I didn't resign. They offered me all kinds of do-nothing jobs,
                    teaching at the War College was their favorite, but I wasn't buying. I said that
                    if I were guilty of doing something wrong they should fire me. As a matter of
                    fact, I said if they could show me I had done something wrong, I would resign.
                    McPherson and company did nothing because they had no case. The White House
                    certainly was aware of what was going on, and their failure to support McPherson
                    meant they didn't believe him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But this was a battle that you were not going to
                        fight?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: It was a battle I was fighting vigorously, but not publicly and not in the
                    newspapers. There was a fellow in the Peace Corps at that time...he was the
                    Deputy Director and he had a lot of problems with Loret Ruppe, the Peace Corps
                    Director, not on the same issues that separated McPherson and me, but on
                    liberal/conservative issues. He went public, told his story in the newspapers,
                    and although he got his story out, he basically got nowhere politically. I
                    didn't go public, but I did make sure the White House knew what was going on.
                    There was a good deal of White House interest in my case, and I had lots of
                    visitors wanting to know what was going on.</p>
                <p>After about a year in USAID limbo, I was offered an Embassy in Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we move to your Ambassadorial assignment, in my
                        interviews I get, I won't even say a mixed impression, but at least a
                        tendency to cast down upon our efforts particularly in Africa on our AID
                        programs. There seems to be almost the idea that many of our endeavors,
                        either there is no follow through or else they are not too well conceived.
                        At least the results are very problematical. Have we made a positive
                        difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Absolutely, and unfortunately, not. Things are definitely worse in Africa,
                    economically, after 30 years of foreign aid. USAID meant well, but overall, they
                    have probably exacerbated Africa's problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I am talking over a long period, not just that one
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>RUDDY: USAID offers jobs to people, many of whom couldn't get a job any place
                    else, so it does some good, at least domestically. But in terms of making a
                    difference in Africa, absolutely not. We had spent fortunes on aid to Africa,
                    and the figures and results, or non results, speak for themselves. Western aid
                    to Africa over the past 30 years has totaled somewhere around $30 Billion, and
                    as enormous as that aid has been, Africa is more impoverished now than it was 30
                    years ago. The result of our aid has not only been zero, it has been a minus.
                    Like President Johnson's failed Great Society Program, US foreign aid in Africa
                    has created dependencies and discouraged initiative and private enterprise. We
                    have supported, kept afloat, African governments that should have been made to
                    pay the piper long ago. Sadly, despite the good intentions, foreign aid just
                    hasn't been a good thing. It has been government to government in Africa. We put
                    a lot of money into Africa, and it went to supporting African dictators' villas
                    in Geneva and other parts of Europe. Lord Bauer called foreign aid the poor
                    people in wealthy countries paying money to the wealthy people of poor
                    countries. From my experience, he had it about right.</p>
                <p>In Equatorial Guinea, to mention a particular country that I am quite familiar
                    with, they get $30 million a year in foreign aid for a country about the size of
                    Maryland with a population of 300,000. That is more aid per capita than almost
                    any country in the world except Israel and Egypt. I defy you to find any
                    difference that enormous amount of aid has made in that country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again from your vantage point at that time, were there any
                        examples of any program that seemed to be justified and any sort of horror
                        story where it seemed to be working the wrong way?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>RUDDY: The best thing I can think of if you want horror stories is Blaine
                    Hardin's book, Despatches From A Fragile Continent. Hardin was The Washington
                    Post's man in Africa, so he doesn't come at the issue of foreign aid with
                    anything like a Conservative point of view. He has a couple of tales of waste
                    and abuse, like the one about the Turkana Dam in Kenya, which are absolutely
                    true and point out more forcefully than anything I can think of, the arrogance
                    and insouciance of aid bureaucrats to the sufferings they cause. The Shaba power
                    line in Zaire is probably as great a waste of money as ever has been spent. It
                    was/is a tremendously expensive power line extending over about 1,000 miles from
                    one end of Zaire to the other, without providing power to any of the millions
                    along the way. These are not isolated examples, simply dramatic instances of
                    waste in a series of tremendously expensive and ineffective projects. Other
                    projects that might be mentioned if you were creating a hall of fame of waste in
                    foreign aid would be the cocoa projects in Ghana (the huge and costly cocoa
                    silos were still standing, rusting and never used, the last time I was in Ghana.
                    Then there was the brainstorm of turning Sudan into the breadbasket of Africa,
                    an idea that not only didn't work, it devastated Sudan. In Tanzania the
                    Scandinavians decided that what was needed were giant threshing machines to deal
                    with all the harvests to be forthcoming as a result of Nyerere's economic
                    enlightenment. (You recall that this saintly gentleman forcibly removed 10's of
                    thousands of Tanzanians to the countryside in his Ujamaa villages project. Of
                    course, it was a disaster, and, as a result of Nyerere's thuggery, Tanzania
                    ranked lower than South Africa on Freedom House's annual assessments of
                    countries' tolerance of political and civil rights. His economic strategy came a
                    cropper as well. He believed that there was as fixed amount of wealth in the
                    world. If the West was wealthy and Africa poor, that meant the West had more
                    than its share of the world's wealth. “You're rich because we're poor,” was a
                    famous rallying cry of his, and you can understand why he was such a favorite of
                    President Carter and Global 2000 types. He didn't understand that nations, like
                    individuals, can create wealth, and therefore looked to the international
                    community for handouts. The Scandinavian thresher program failed, of course, and
                    the giant threshers of Tanzania, like the cocoa silos of Ghana, just rusted
                    away.</p>
                <p>These kinds of patronizing and subsidizing have two very damaging effects: one is
                    what it keeps the people of achieving in a free economy where there are
                    incentives for ingenuity and risk taking. The Africans are great entrepreneurs,
                    the very active black markets throughout the continent demonstrate that, and if
                    they were encouraged by their government, or at least not stifled by it, they
                    would produce individual and national wealth. “A rising tide lifts all boats,
                    great and small,” as JFK said, and it's true. It's also true that if you allow
                    people to have economic power, you are allowing them political power, a reality
                    not lost on African dictators.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>A second damaging effect is the direct harm, literally making people worse off
                    than they were before, of aid projects by created by World Bank or USAID
                    “experts” who know better than the people they are supposed to help, what is
                    best for them. Blaine Hardin, whom I mentioned, cites in his book, the Turkana
                    Dam project in Kenya, and I can't improve on that one. The Turkana were a
                    nomadic people getting along just fine in northern Kenya, or so they thought.
                    The development experts came in from Washington or Geneva or wherever
                    know-it-all bureaucrats come from, and told the Turkana that as nomads and
                    herders they were not doing anything for the land or for themselves and that
                    they, the bureaucrats, had no choice but to change the Turkanas whole way of
                    living. They told the Turkana they would turn them into fishermen and begin by
                    creating for them a fish freezing facility, using fish from a nearby lake. What
                    the experts didn't realize was that this same lake dried up regularly every so
                    often. The freezer which cost $22-25 million to put up was in business for one
                    week! Part of the lake had dried up, as could have been anticipated if the
                    experts had asked, and the water which was available was too dirty to use. Ten
                    years the experts, I don't remember if it was the same experts or new ones, came
                    back and said: “Sorry. Our fish freezing idea was a bad one. What you ought to
                    do raise cattle as you used to do.” By that time, of course they had no herds
                    and were on relief. It is no mistake to say that foreign assistance and aid
                    experts ruined these people. The Turkana were devastated, but the aid experts
                    packed their Guccis and went home, to wait for another opportunity to enlighten
                    some Third World country.</p>
                <p>To get back a little earlier to what I said, Reagan's philosophy and my own is
                    that people are probably the best judges of what is best for them. Of course,
                    people can make mistakes or they can be taught to do what they are doing more
                    efficiently. There is an institute of tropical agriculture in Ibadan, Nigeria,
                    that exists to discover and disseminate better farming methods in Africa. That
                    is all to the good, and I have visited the institute and applauded its work.
                    Improvement is always possible, but you better have a care before you start
                    telling other people, Africans, for example, how to live their lives. They
                    probably are not only doing the best they can, they are probably, repeat
                    probably, doing something that makes economic sense. We have in law something
                    called a rebuttable presumption: a criminal is presumed innocent, but that
                    presumption can be rebutted with hard evidence. I think the Turkana Dam fiasco
                    argues petty persuasively for a rebuttable presumption in forcing aid down
                    Africans' throats. They are entitled to a presumption that their old ways make
                    sense unless an unimpeachable case can be made to the contrary. In this case the
                    experts went home and the Turkana were devastated.</p>
                <p>Turkana is one of the worse examples that I am familiar with, but there are a lot
                    of Turkanas going on around Africa, lots of experts with the “we know what is
                    best for these people” view, a variation of 19th century colonial views of
                    Africa and Africans. “ Africans are incapable of helping themselves. Someone, we
                    appoint ourselves, have to help them.”</p>
                <p>In yesterday's New York Times there was a review of Gertrude Himmelfarb's new
                    book. Do you know her?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No I don't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: She is an extraordinary writer. She is the wife of Irving Kristol. The
                    statement that she uses for her second volume is from Lionel Trilling “...Some
                    paradox of our natures lead us when once we have made our fellow man the objects
                    of enlightened interest to go on to make them the objects of our pity then of
                    our wisdom, ultimately of our coercion.” There is a lot of truth in that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In AID then I take it you were in a way basically acting
                        as a brake on doing things which in a bureaucracy is a kiss of death.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: A brake on some projects I thought quite wasteful. A dynamo (what is the
                    opposite of brake?), a force, a thrust for others that I found quite
                    sensible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because it wasn't just philosophy. Were you questioning
                        programs at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Oh, absolutely. And also trying to change some of the ways USAID did
                    business. Take, for example, something like language. I had had about eight
                    years of French in school, including Cambridge where I had to read all the
                    French philosophes in the original for my thesis. So my French was not bad to
                    begin with, and I had kept it up over the years by taking classes at L'Alliance
                    Francaise. No one would confuse me with a native Frenchman, but I wasn't bad.
                    When I got to USAID and had to deal with all the Francophone countries, I went
                    to FSI, the Foreign Service Institute, to get my French up to snuff. At FSI, you
                    need to qualify as a 3 out of a possible 5 (”0” is a non-speaker and 5 is a
                    native speaker) in speaking and reading to be certified as competent in that
                    language.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The working level of a language in both speaking and
                        writing.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Right. I made the grade pretty quickly. As a matter of fact, I did a
                    little better than that. I thought language competency was pretty important in
                    the field and made it a requirement to be a mission director. I made the rule
                    that nobody could go out as a mission director who could not achieve a 3- 3 in
                    the language of his or her country, and in Africa, at that time, that meant
                    French or Portuguese. I thought that was a rather modest standard and one
                    professionals would be ashamed to contest. Well, I was wrong. There was a big
                    to-do. You would have thought I had required people to take Ph.D. orals in
                    chemistry or physics. I merely insisted that mission directors speak the
                    principal language of the country they were working in. As well to be hanged for
                    a sheep as a lamb, I also required that mission directors be re-tested every
                    year to see how they were progressing in their language abilities. I happen to
                    think all AID officers who have to work with foreign nationals should be able to
                    communicate in the host country language and be tested regularly in that
                    language. That sounds like common sense, but let me assure you, it's a radical
                    idea. To return to the program I instituted, of all the people tested during the
                    time I was there, one officer, count 'em: one, in Mali, I believe it was,
                    improved. Nobody else had improved their language which, in most cases, was
                    French, not some exotic language like Arabic. I thought those results were
                    incredible, especially since, at that time when we were competing with the
                    Russians...the Russians who are wonderful linguists. I don't know if you are
                    shot if you are a Russian diplomat who's not fluent in the language of the
                    country the send you to, but I do know the ones I met are terrific
                    linguists.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think you get outside the country if you are a good
                        linguist.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>RUDDY: That may be, but whatever the incentive, the Russians I came across were
                    good. For example, in the Francophone countries where I was, the Russians spoke
                    French impeccably. In Equatorial Guinea they spoke Castillan Spanish. I could
                    not speak as sweepingly of the language skills of our own people. As a matter of
                    fact, I was frequently shocked by the language bumbling of some of our senior
                    people. I was in Ouagadougou one time visiting with our mission director. I
                    forget if we just got back to his office or met there prior to setting out
                    somewhere. Anyway, while I was waiting in his office, a group of officials from
                    the Upper Volta government (the country is called Burkina Faso today) arrived
                    ready for action. The poor mission director didn't have a clue why they were
                    there. It turned out the mission director had attended a meeting the week before
                    and agreed to sign a particular agreement. That's why the men from the
                    ministries were there. However, the meeting the week before had been conducted
                    in French, which the mission director didn't understand very well, and the
                    mission director didn't know he had agreed to sign the document or that the
                    signing was to take place on that particular day. That kind of language
                    incompetence is not only embarrassing, it is wasteful. Sadly it did characterize
                    USAID, and that day in Ouagadougou was one of the reasons I initiated my
                    language testing programs.This is not to say that there are not some wonderful
                    linguists in AID, there are. One who comes to mind was the Deputy Director in
                    Senegal, Carol Tyson, actually Dr Carol Tyson, she had a Ph.D. from Harvard.
                    Carol had a 4-4 in French, which is almost at a native speaker level. She also
                    was fluent in Wolof, which is one of the indigenous languages of Senegal and The
                    Gambia. And, of course, there were and are others besides Carol very
                    accomplished in languages. But facility in foreign languages isn't a
                    characteristic of AID. I remember the reaction of the FSI language teachers on
                    learning that they would be teaching French to AID people. It was like that
                    picture, The Cry, by Munch.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>The absurd part of all this is that you can't do business if you can't speak the
                    language, and we had a generation of AID officers who looked on language as a
                    nuisance. “Let them speak English,” was their attitude. Insisting on language
                    competency (after all I wasn't insisting they write poetry or op-ed pieces, just
                    to be able to communicate and do business) was just a matter of basic management
                    efficiency. To make the language pill easier to swallow, I experimented with
                    some things. I had one fellow scheduled to go to Niger go a language school in
                    Cannes or Nice, I forget which, and live with a family there while learning
                    French at a local school. I thought getting out of FSI, not that FSI is the
                    problem, might work for some, and the Cannes experiment did work with that
                    particular officer. Others were just plain lazy or incompetent. One affable
                    fellow, one of the AID good old boys network, wanted to go to Togo as the
                    mission director. Togo is French speaking. He had already had been tested at
                    2-2, so his stay at FSI should have been no more than a refresher and a little
                    new material. FSI courses are designed for people to go from a 0-0 in a language
                    like French to a 3-3 in 20 weeks. If you start at FSI with a 2-2, as this fellow
                    did, you are already more than half way home. After 20 weeks at FSI this fellow
                    never moved off 2-2. That's not easy to do. You almost have to resist learning
                    not to move from a 2-2 after 20 weeks of classes and language labs. I told him
                    he was not going. After I left AID, the whole language program was scrapped and
                    his friends got this fellow his francophone posting after all. I guess he and
                    the bureaucracy won, but why do people like this join AID and want to live
                    overseas when they're too lazy to learn the language?</p>
                <p>Sending people who couldn't speak the local language abroad was one of the many
                    USAID inefficiencies. Another was keeping track of foreign aid dollars. I worked
                    with the USAID Inspector General, Herb Beckington, to make sure that solid
                    accounting standards and procedures were in place to keep track of monies
                    distributed by USAID. The main cause with AID money disappearing in Africa, I
                    think, was not theft; rather poor accounting procedures. USAID has probably the
                    worst record of any federal agency when it comes to embezzlement and misuse of
                    funds, so I'm not saying AID was lily white. My own successor, a few times
                    removed, was sent to the slammer for fiddling with US Government funds, but in
                    most of the cases we investigated involving unaccounted for project money, the
                    consensus was (and I include the usual cynics, such as inspector general
                    investigators in that consensus) that the money probably was spent on AID
                    purposes, but the accounting systems were inadequate. Francophone countries
                    would use a French accounting system, Anglophone countries an English one,
                    Lusophone countries a Portuguese one, and we would use an American system. There
                    was no shortage of problems as you can imagine. I worked with our financial
                    people and the Inspector General to standardize the different accounting systems
                    so that US taxpayers' money could be accounted for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you become Ambassador to Equatorial Guinea?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>RUDDY: I got a call from the White House, from John Herrington's office. John was
                    then the head of White House personnel. He and other Californians like Bill
                    Clarke, the Interior Secretary who had been the Deputy Secretary of State...they
                    all knew what was going on over there. Anyway, I got a call from the White House
                    asking if I would like to be the Ambassador to Equatorial Guinea? My first
                    reaction was “Equatorial Guinea ! Oh no !” (I kept that reaction to myself,
                    fortunately.) I knew Africa pretty well, but I didn't know where Equatorial
                    Guinea was. I knew it was on the West coast somewhere, and I remembered from a
                    meeting with Peter McPherson that I attended with their ambassador, it had a
                    terrible reputation. I asked for some time to think it over, and I hoped I could
                    use that time to get a better embassy. I went to two people: Frank Shakespeare
                    and Bill Middendorf. Frank Shakespeare was back in town again as chairman of the
                    Board of International Broadcasting. I asked him what I should do and he said I
                    should take it. What I really wanted him to say was: “Frank, you don't have to
                    take that embassy. Let me make a phone call, and we will get you some place a
                    lot better.” He didn't say that. He just said, “Why don't you take it.” Then I
                    went to Bill Middendorf, who was our Ambassador to the OAS at that time. I asked
                    him the same question I asked Shakespeare, and I knew he would say he would take
                    care of this for me and arrange for me to get a better posting. Wrong again.
                    What he said was, and I remember this well: “Frank, sometimes the subway only
                    stops once, you had better take it.”</p>
                <p>So I called the White House back and spoke to Joe Salgado, a tough ex-cop from
                    Oakland, who was really a very kind guy and his support was, I am sure, one of
                    the reasons I got an embassy. I asked: “You know I speak French. Of all the
                    countries in Africa, why are you sending me to the only one that speaks
                    Spanish?” Joe said, “You mean they don't speak French there?”</p>
                <p>Anyway, to make a long story short, Teri (my wife) and I talked it over and
                    decided to go. When I told the children, David who was about 13 at that time,
                    said, “Dad, you have made some dumb decisions in your life, but this is the
                    worst.” That was about July. There were some funny incidents from then until we
                    arrived in Malabo (the capital of Equatorial Guinea).</p>
                <p>Since I didn't speak Spanish, I had to go to The Foreign Service Institute to
                    learn. Teri was allowed to go too since she would have to be at home in Spanish
                    to be effective in E.G. as well. FSI was a one of the great experiences of our
                    lives. For 20 weeks you study Spanish full time: classes 9-3 and first class
                    language labs after that. If you're a State employee, you get paid to do
                    yourself a tremendous favor: learning the second most spoken language in the
                    world (I'm not including Chinese). In Teri's case, she wasn't paid, but she got
                    to attend a 20- week Spanish language course that would probably cost $20 or 25
                    thousand dollars if Berlitz offered it. It was like going back to university,
                    and we both loved it. We even hired one of the FSI teachers to do a little
                    moonlighting and teach our sons David and Stephen a little Spanish.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>One of the things that happens while you are awaiting Senate confirmation as an
                    ambassador is that the President himself calls you on the telephone and asks you
                    to be his ambassador, in my case to Equatorial Guinea. It's all pro forma, but
                    it is still done. It is one of the special things about being an ambassador that
                    the President takes time out of his daily crises to play the game. He had to ask
                    “Frank, I was wondering if you would be my Ambassador to Equatorial Guinea.” And
                    I had to say, “Of course.” Well, on the appointed day I was at FSI, so The White
                    House called FSI and said The President of The United States would like to talk
                    to me. The FSI bureaucrat answering the phone told The White House operator that
                    they were too busy to find me for the President. For the President ! I found a
                    note, one of those “while you were out” yellow telephone slips on the students
                    bulletin board. “To Frank Ruddy. You were called by The President of the United
                    States.” The “please return call” box was checked. I returned the President's
                    call on a pay phone on the first floor. Returning the President's call would be
                    personal, the FSI lady, probably the same one who was too busy to bother with
                    the President's call, told me, so I couldn't use the FSI phone.</p>
                <p>Another interesting call came the day before I was sworn in...I can't remember
                    the exact date so let's say October 24...(1984) from Jim Lucier of Senator
                    Helms' staff, asking if I would support an ad to run in the country's major
                    newspapers endorsing the Senator. (My name was to be one of 20 or more U.S.
                    ambassadors supporting Jesse.) Senator Helms was in a tough race that year, and
                    the purpose of the ad was to show that a large number of U.S. ambassadors
                    supported him, and by implication, his views on U.S. foreign policy. As
                    political appointees we were not covered by the Hatch Act and could legally
                    endorse a candidate without violating any law. I said I would be happy to go on
                    record supporting the Senator for two very simple reasons: I agreed with him on
                    most things, and, on a personal level, when I needed his help in my battles with
                    McPherson, Helms had been there. He didn't hesitate or give me any of “on the
                    one hand...” business. He just delivered. So when he needed my help I said,
                    “Absolutely.” The ad ran in all the major papers, at least all the major east
                    coast papers. The ad itself and the participation of U.S. ambassadors in it were
                    roundly criticized by the usual suspects, The New York Times and The Washington
                    Post, and surprisingly by The Washington Times, a conservative paper. It turned
                    out that Bill Cheshire, a deputy editor of The Washington Times had played a
                    major role in Helms' '78 campaign, but had had a falling out with Jesse. The
                    Washington Times criticism of the Helms ad was payback time. After all I had
                    been through in the previous 4 years, the flap over the Helms ad was small
                    potatoes. I even thought of it as a badge of honor. I was pleased. There were
                    about 23 of us ambassadorial types, I think, who signed the ad. I liked Helms
                    then and I like him now. He is a decent man who has been terribly maligned. I
                    think there are few in Washington strong enough to stand up to the abuse he has
                    taken. With all the jokes about members of Congress who will take any position
                    to be re-elected, Helms stands out among U.S. senators like the Rock of
                    Gibraltar.</p>
                <p>One twist in the ad was that it appeared the day that I was sworn in as
                    ambassador. Of course, The Secretary of State, George Shultz, had apoplexy when
                    he heard about it. Did you know Nancy Rawls?</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I knew her name.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Nancy had been ambassador to several African countries, and I knew her
                    when she was ambassador to The Ivory Coast. Nancy was a good friend who had very
                    nice things to say about me when I was at AID. She telephoned me at one point
                    after the ad ran and said, “How could you do that? That was so, so...
                    unprofessional.” I said to her just what I said to you: the Senator was a friend
                    to me when I needed a friend, and I would do it again tomorrow. There is a
                    marker system in political Washington. When someone does you a big favor, he has
                    your marker. When the tide turns and that person comes to collect your marker,
                    you had better deliver. I thought everyone in Washington knew that, so it seemed
                    odd to be roundly criticized for doing what I thought was a perfectly
                    understandable act, supporting a friend, and it hit all the big papers in the
                    country. I suppose there is another tradition in Washington, in the press, at
                    least, which might be called the Captain Renault syndrome. You remember Captain
                    Renault from the movie Casablanca. He's the one who exclaimed he was “shocked;
                    shocked, to learn gambling was going on...” in Rick's place, and then accepts
                    his night's gambling take from one of the croupier's. I supposed The Washington
                    Post and other papers have to exclaim to be “shocked” when publicly forced to
                    acknowledge what they and everybody else knows goes on every day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of preparation did you get before going
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Not a great deal of formal preparation. FSI had a course in area studies
                    which explains the politics, economics, in short, everything you ever wanted to
                    know, about the area you are going to. In didn't work in our case for two
                    reasons: first, the area studies for Africa were scheduled when I had be in
                    Spanish class (African area studies were worked around Portuguese and French
                    language lessons.) Secondly, and I'll get into this later, because nobody knew
                    anything, really: nada, zip, nothing, about Equatorial Guinea. There was
                    something we called ambassador prep, a three day seminar for ambassadors going
                    out for the first time. It was a program run by Shirley Temple Black and David
                    Newsom. It was a worthwhile program, and Shirley Temple Black was excellent. She
                    had been an ambassador herself in Ghana, and, of course, she had a lot of
                    presence and charm as you know if you have ever, and you must have done, seen
                    her in the movies. A lovely person and very effective. If you could translate
                    the enthusiasm and professionalism she exudes, and tries to instill, into
                    out-going ambassadors, every U.S. ambassador would be a great one. Newsom was
                    your basic 7th floor, State Department guy. He looked like a house detective in
                    one of The Marx Brothers movies and was about as exciting. I suppose he was good
                    at something, or had been, but his picture appeared under boring in the
                    dictionary. The three days at ambassador prep covered basic things; some I knew
                    and some I didn't. Little tricks of the trade, like good techniques for getting
                    your cables around State without appearing as a prima donna, keeping track of
                    embassy silverware (Various committees in Congress went ballistic over
                    silverware issues) and making sure embassy financial records are squeaky clean
                    made relations with Washington and life at the embassy a lot more pleasant.
                    Covering these kinds of things was helpful, but by and large, I don't think it
                    would have been a catastrophe if I missed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today it is a longer one, two weeks, and there is a lot
                        more on management, fraud and problems like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>RUDDY: That makes sense. There are two kinds of ambassadors in a program like
                    that: someone like me and someone who was going to be a figurehead at a large
                    post, where the day-to-day management is handled by the foreign service resident
                    staff. In my class that would be someone like Bob Stuart, a former C.E.O. for
                    Quaker Oats, who was going to Oslo. There were career and non-career people, and
                    the career people rarely got the figurehead posts. That's changing, I think,
                    with President Bush. In any event, for those of us who actually had to sit down
                    with the admin officer and go over the books before the regional State
                    Department fiscal officer arrived, like a bank examiner, to check up on us, that
                    extra fraud, waste and abuse training would have been very useful. Fortunately
                    for me, my main admin officer was a lawyer, and he and I pored over the regs to
                    make sure everything was Kosher. We did the same with the procurement regs,
                    security regs, etc. We taught ourselves everything, well, almost everything at
                    the post. We could have profited from some help in those areas before we left.
                    It sounds like they're doing that now, and if they are, it's a good thing. The
                    other real gap we found at State, and if State didn't know, Shirley Temple
                    surely didn't, was information about Equatorial Guinea. Nobody in Washington
                    knew anything about Equatorial Guinea. We made it a point to cure that situation
                    by sending loads of material on the country to State and to FSI so that our
                    successors would know more than we did before leaving.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was going to ask if you were getting any support from
                        the Desk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: They were very helpful, as helpful as they could be, but they just didn't
                    know much. My predecessor in Equatorial Guinea, Alan Hardy, came home in the
                    summer of 1984, and was retiring. We had lunch, and he told me a lunch worth's
                    (we had lunch in the FDIC cafeteria across from State) about the country, and
                    that was it. Then he was off to his retirement life, and I am sure the desk gave
                    me whatever they had, but that wasn't much.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>I was a lawyer at USIA in the 70's, and I remembered the weird cables coming in
                    from Equatorial Guinea. It turned out there had been a murder there, but before
                    we knew that, the cables from E.G. were like dispatches from The Twilight Zone:
                    “Soviet troops marching through the streets,...the screams of victims being
                    tortured by the E.G. Government are driving us mad,....” These were the kinds of
                    details in the cables from E.G. What made them less unbelievable was the
                    situation in E.G. The country's dictator, Francisco Macias, was a mass murderer,
                    a poor man's Idi Amin. He called himself “The Divine Miracle” and massacred
                    people in the capital's soccer stadium to the accompaniment of Beatles music. He
                    once settled a Cabinet disagreement by hurling the dissenting minister out a
                    second floor window. Macias was certainly capable of the atrocities described in
                    the cables, so desk officers and cable watchers suspended disbelief for a while.
                    As the cables became more and more bizarre something had to be done. The
                    Department sent over two officers from Cameroon, I think, Lannon Walker and
                    another gentleman named Sherthoff or something similar. They finally gained
                    entrance to the embassy in what appeared to be a scene scripted by Francis Ford
                    Coppola and began a search for the communicator who was missing. The
                    communicator's wife eventually found his body behind a locked door. The Charg�
                    d'Affaires, Al Erdos, had killed him with a pair of those very long G.I. shears
                    you find in every mail room. It was the result of a spat during a homosexual
                    love affair as I later found out from Dr. Moran, the Spanish doctor who formed
                    the autopsy (sperm in the deceased's stomach, that sort of thing.) That was
                    about the sum total of what I knew about the country, and nobody I met at State
                    knew any more. So when we went out it was really to terra incognita.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>I arrived in Malabo, the capital of E.G., January 12, 1985. Teri (short for
                    Kateri), my wife, came with our two youngest sons, David and Stephen, February
                    9. I went from a very freezing cold Madrid, where I had spent a week meeting the
                    U.S. Embassy Madrid folks and waiting for the once a week flight to Malabo
                    (there was no other way of getting there at the time), into this lush, tropical
                    setting, right out of “Love in The Time of Cholera.” The capital city is Malabo,
                    emphasis on the second “a,” a once magnificent city when E.G. was “the
                    Switzerland of West Africa.” Maybe not Switzerland, but it was a slice of
                    Europe, with hospitals, casinos, fine hotels, a place wealthy West Africans went
                    to vacation, to gamble, or to get medical treatment, and Americans, like Peace
                    Corps types, went for R &amp; R. With independence in 1968, the country
                    destroyed itself, or, more accurately, the first President, the infamous
                    Francisco Macias, destroyed the country. Cocoa production virtually ceased, and
                    with it foreign income, and E.G. which had the second highest literacy rate in
                    black Africa (behind Uganda) at 87 % produced destroyed the school system and
                    produced a generation (from 1968-79) of illiterates. The city of Malabo decayed
                    visibly during Macias' years, and when he was overthrown (1979), a bankrupt
                    successor government was no more competent to restore the city than it was to
                    revive the economy. A return to law and order and economic normalcy would have
                    regenerated the country but attracting the necessary foreign and domestic
                    investment, but that would also have diluted the government's power, and that
                    was not an option the new dictator, who overthrew Francisco Macias, his nephew,
                    Teodoro Obiang, was willing to consider. In any event, as you drive around the
                    city and squint your eyes, you can see what the old Gothic cathedral, the
                    Moorish building that serves as defense department, the Supreme Court building
                    and 100 other magnificent structures must have looked like in their prime.</p>
                <p>Since 1980 when diplomatic relations between the U.S. and E.G. were established
                    again, the Embassy had been a set of rooms on the fifth floor of a seedy (but
                    the only) hotel in Malabo. My predecessor Alan Hardy would have done a fine job
                    if he only succeeded in keeping his sanity operating out of an office Sam Spade
                    would have turned down, but, in fact, he did a great deal more. He got us
                    started there, toured the country, got to know the government and its officials.
                    He got hit with a very unflattering portrait in a story on E.G. in the London
                    Sunday Times, but that was a result of his seedy, unairconditioned office, over
                    which he had no control and which by Malabo standards was Trump Plaza, rather
                    than his accomplishments. I still remember the articles reference to the
                    fly-stained portrait of President Reagan hanging behind Ambassador Hardy. The
                    irony was just as a real embassy was being completed (Hardy had negotiated for
                    two adjoining houses for the embassy and ambassador's residence respectively, it
                    was time for him to leave. He did get to move into the office, but he never had
                    the comforts of the new residence which he had acquired and modeled to his
                    specifications. Running the embassy when we got there was a young officer who
                    was on his first tour as an officer, and he was probably the Department's
                    youngest Charg� d'affaires. He had been in E.G. for a long time, and they were
                    beginning to get a little worried about him at State. His cables were showing
                    signs of strain (he had advised Washington that he was considering a major
                    confrontation with the Spanish ambassador over some minor parking matter), and
                    they thought, correctly in my opinion, he needed his long deferred R &amp; R. He
                    got it when I arrived.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>In the very first month that I was there I got quite an education in the
                    relationship between E.G. and Nigeria. Strange as it seems today, there was a
                    time when E.G., or Fernando Po as the main island used to be known, was much
                    more important than Nigeria. Nigerian workers used to come over to E.G. to work
                    the cocoa plantations, as many as 75,000 Nigerian workers at times. This led,
                    understandably, to tensions between the residents of the main island of E.G. who
                    simply rented out their lands to the cocoa developers and the Nigerians who
                    actually worked the land. As Nigeria became more powerful, this historical
                    dependency became an embarrassment, and the Nigerians starting talking about
                    Nigerian “slaves” brought over to harvest cocoa in E.G. Nigerian-Equatorial
                    Guinea animosity had simmered for generations, and I was about to see it erupt
                    again. A Nigerian cocoa worker was shot by a Equatorial Guinean policeman in a
                    bar in a slum called “Campo Yaounde” on Saturday night. (It's hard to visualize
                    a slum in a city (Malabo) which has itself become a large slum, but everything
                    is relative.) The shooting wasn't a political act or a statement by the
                    government of E.G. A policeman got drunk and shot someone who annoyed him. Did
                    the policeman decide to shoot the fellow because he was a Nigerian? Maybe. Who
                    knows. In any event, the important point is that the government of E.G. had
                    nothing to do with it. To get buried, as well as to do anything, in Equatorial
                    Guinea, you need a permit. Since the deceased was a Nigerian, the Nigerian
                    charg� went through the regular process to get the burial permit, but he didn't
                    succeed which is not surprising because the bureaucracy there doesn't do
                    anything well or efficiently, even when it concerns disposing of a body which is
                    putrefying in the equatorial sun. So he then went to the Ministry of Foreign
                    Affairs to get their help but still no luck. Now remember: The Nigerian was shot
                    on Saturday night at 10:00. It is very hot in E.G. There is no electricity and
                    no way of refrigerating or preserving dead bodies. The Nigerian Charg�
                    d'Affaires had tried unsuccessfully for over 40 hours to get his countryman
                    buried. On Monday afternoon, the charge arrives at the Foreign Ministry at 3,
                    just as it is closing for the day. He has the dead body angled in the back seat
                    of his Mercedes. He catches the Foreign Minister as he is coming out and says:
                    “I have the body here. You won't give me a permit to bury it, perhaps that is
                    because you would like to eat it.” He got the burial permit, as he gloated to me
                    over lunch one day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is known as diplomacy ?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Hardly. It was not only a bizarre incident in its own terms, it was even
                    worse if you knew the local history. There is a certain amount of cannibalism,
                    in the country, necrophilia really, even to this day. When Francisco Macias was
                    overthrown, the story was that he was executed and the executioner, including
                    the current president, had a picnic on various of his body parts (brain, heart,
                    etc.). American Indians used to do this same sort of thing to incorporate,
                    literally, the best qualities of their enemies. Whether this ever happened in
                    the case of Macias is not the point. The charge's was reminding the Foreign
                    Minister of the reputation for necrophilia just to give an extra twist. That
                    little story gives you an idea of the relations between the two countries. As I
                    mentioned, the charge got his certificate, but the following Saturday two gun
                    Nigerian gunboats arrived in the port of Malabo along with a giant transport;
                    two Hercules aircraft (the kind they carry tanks and troops in) arrived at the
                    airport, all without permission. Sunday morning Nigerian soldiers and sailors
                    scoured the cocoa plantations and Nigerian living areas to find and repatriate
                    all the “Nigerian slaves.” (That's what the giant transport was for.) Agence
                    France reported that Nigeria had sent an armada against E.G. and BBC World
                    Service reported it as dramatically. The Guineans, for once used good sense and
                    treated the planes, boats and Nigerian search parties as a non-event. There was
                    nothing they could do about, so they ignored it on the state controlled radio
                    and TV. The gun boats left within hours of their arrival since the Nigerian
                    commander who was in charge of the search parties must have realized very
                    quickly he was on a wild goose chase: the Nigerians he met were very happy to
                    stay where they were. Many were married and had families. The ship stayed but
                    nobody wanted to go except for 7 people who wanted a free ride back to
                    Lagos.</p>
                <p>We had no radio (I'm so used to saying it that I forget that it must sound like a
                    fluke or temporary abnormality for a U.S. embassy not to have a radio when, as a
                    matter of fact, it was routine for us to be totally isolated), so while the BBC
                    and Agence France were describing what sounded like Nigeria's answer to D-Day,
                    we weren't saying boo. Washington, which is used to dealing with embassies with
                    new-fangled inventions like radios, never considered the possibility that we
                    just could not communicate. They interpreted our silence ominously. We were
                    finally able to make a telephone call and alert the station chief that there was
                    nothing to worry about. That put our mind at ease, but Gimbel's doesn't talk to
                    Macy's, and our little chat did not get into State Department channels. While we
                    went whistling about our business, fat and happy, thinking all was well with the
                    world, the State Department truly believed we were under siege and unable even
                    to communicate. That sort of confusion that was always going on when, as usual,
                    we didn't have any communications. We came to realize, of course, that being out
                    of touch with Washington was not necessarily such a bad thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why didn't you have communications? I would have thought
                        that would have been a number one priority.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>RUDDY: As of the time I left Malabo (February, 1988), the embassy still didn't
                    have reliable communications. We had an old system which wasn't very effective
                    even when well it was working well, which was rare. And we didn't have any
                    reliable international telephone. Every once in a while, we did get a call
                    through, but you just couldn't rely on it. The telephone hours would be erratic,
                    and even when the phone was supposed to be working, it wouldn't. We went for
                    months without reliable communications, and sometimes without any communications
                    at all, except for what couriers would bring. Typically, we would have to
                    communicate routine matters with Douala (in Cameroon) by radio. Classified
                    material had to go out from Douala or be carried to us from Douala. It was not a
                    good way to run a railroad. For other things, like mail, we depended on Iberia,
                    the Spanish airline, which carried the diplomatic pouch, including letters from
                    home, from Madrid to us. Iberia was always in a snit with Equatorial Guinea, and
                    when things got nasty, as they frequently did, Iberia just suspended flights to
                    E.G. At one stage we went just about 4 months without any mail. That meant no
                    American Express bills, no Visa/MasterCard bills, and when mail finally resumed
                    there were some very nasty dunning letters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This all harks back to the 19th century consular
                        posts.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: It really does. It was almost like being an embassy in the days of the
                    clipper ships. It was hard to deal with people like American Express because
                    even their notices telling you that you didn't pay their last bill didn't get
                    there either. And there was not much you could do about it. You could send out
                    your bills, or whatever it was that came up and on other things you had to hope
                    you could find someone, a missionary, a Peace Corps volunteer, somebody going to
                    the States who could mail your letters there. Otherwise, you were on Mars. You
                    couldn't call, you couldn't be called. For long periods, you couldn't send mail
                    out; you couldn't get mail in. You couldn't get messages in; you couldn't send
                    work messages out.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>But, there was a good side. It meant we had to, repeat had to, send somebody to
                    Douala regularly on courier trips. That was the only way we had to get and send
                    important (classified) materials, and that being the case, State (as opposed to
                    the embassy) paid for these trips. Frequently we could only go by charter
                    because the national (E.G.) airline flights, such as they were, were
                    inconsistent and sometimes non-existent because they didn't pay their fuel
                    bills. Even Cameroon Airlines required payment from E.G. up front before they
                    would allow any passengers to board. On other occasions, where we had a great
                    many things to take to or from Douala (copiers, motors, booze and goodies for a
                    major reception like the 4th) a charter was actually a better buy. So we used to
                    get a charter every other week or so to take the mail out and bring back goods
                    from Douala, which is about 20 miles away across the channel, and a big city. We
                    rotated it among the Americans at post so that everybody would get a turn and
                    have something to look forward to. I know Teri and I didn't take our full turns.
                    I had no particular interest in going to Douala; I much preferred Malabo. But
                    for others, though, it was just a nice break. They would go over, stay at
                    Novotel or Le Meridien, have a few tasty French meals, swim in the topless
                    pools, do some shopping and return refreshed. It was a therapeutic break, and
                    everyone knew when his turn was coming up. The anticipation might have been
                    greater than the event, but it was very good for morale.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Morale must have been a major concern of yours.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, it was, but all things considered, we had surprisingly good morale.
                    In addition to the Douala trips, the embassy rented a house in a mountainous
                    region of the country, about an hour and a half away by car. It was called the
                    ambassador's guesthouse, but I guess we used it less than anyone. The house was
                    in a Swiss-like area (here the comparison with Switzerland was appropriate) or
                    in an area like the mountainous regions of Burundi, above Bujumbura. This part
                    of Equatorial Guinea, called Moka (no relation to coffee), is high, is pastoral
                    and cool. You actually need a blanket at night. We would rotate the house among
                    the embassy staff (American), so that every fourth week or so you knew you had
                    use of the house. The only exception would be if I needed it for some official
                    entertaining, and I did only once. The sea level part of Equatorial Guinea is
                    great for mosquitoes and tsetse flies, malaria and sleeping sickness. Cattle
                    can't survive there (sleeping sickness). But up in the higher regions you are in
                    Marlboro country. Fresh air, great areas for hiking, reading, and some serious
                    sleeping. Moka was a another very good thing for morale.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>One of the demoralizing sides of E.G. for some, i.e. those who didn't speak it,
                    was language. Spanish is the official language, but if you didn't speak Spanish,
                    you could get by in French. There were enough people in Malabo from the
                    continent (E.G. is in two parts: one part is an island (former Fernando Po), and
                    the other part is a pie slice between Gabon and Cameroon) that a foreigner
                    (American) could get by in French. Foreign Service officers did not have a
                    problem since they could all speak Spanish. Secretaries, communicators, the
                    non-coms, as it were were the ones who had language problems, and therefore, by
                    definition if they were young and single, problems with their social lives. I'll
                    get back to that in a minute.</p>
                <p>A real fear, and therefore a morale problem, for parents, was for the health of
                    young children. One of the officers and his wife had a small child at post, and
                    there was always the fear of illness, exacerbated because there was no real
                    hospital. There was a hospital, of course, but it would make you gag walking
                    around the grounds to smell the medical garbage and trash just thrown behind the
                    buildings. The U.S. Navy doctor who came to E.G. on a ship visit visited the
                    hospital and said that we would never be so sick to go to that hospital, no
                    matter what we had. They treated patients with contagious diseases in the bed
                    next to someone there for some internal problem. Patients brought their own
                    food; there was no electricity, therefore: no x-rays, no refrigeration, no
                    medicines requiring cooling, no whole blood supply. Another fear was trauma?
                    What do you do if you or your wife or child is in a motor accident, for example,
                    bleeding, internal injuries, if you could do anything? It was not an academic
                    question. During my stay in E.G. several ex-pats (a few Europeans and a South
                    African woman) died in different parts of the country as a result of car
                    crashes. In Malabo, at least, we, in the embassies had an agreement among
                    ourselves, to help each other in several ways. First, we listed those diplomats
                    who could be called on to give blood, on the hoof, as it were. (It was the honor
                    system; don't volunteer unless you're sure your blood is untainted.) We arranged
                    to have a plane from Douala, to come out when signaled, land at in Malabo, at
                    night if necessary, without airport lights (the various embassies' cars would go
                    out and provide runway lights...this was right out of a movie) and medevac the
                    injured person. Fortunately we never had to use that.</p>
                <p>We did have direct cable traffic with Europe through the Spanish Embassy and
                    their Foreign Ministry in Madrid. The Foreign Ministry could inform our embassy
                    in Madrid and arrange whatever kind of medical help the USG could provide us. We
                    could at least get the word out that way. There was a real medical risk, no
                    doubt about it. That's why E.G. was a hardship post, why everybody got paid
                    about 25% more to go there.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Language was also a great a problem. One of big mistakes State made, and probably
                    still does, was to send communicators and secretaries out to post without any
                    language training. The rationale, I guess, is that they don't need a foreign
                    language to do their job in the embassy, so why bother? The reason to bother is
                    that 16 hours of each day are spent out of the embassy, and if they can't relax
                    by shopping locally, dining out, having a drink, dancing, doing the things
                    people need language to do, they are going to become unhappy and depressed. In
                    some cases the non-coms, as I called them, would try to learn Spanish. We
                    offered language classes free, had native speakers come in, provided books and
                    tapes and did what we could. (I took Spanish all the time we were there, because
                    you can never be good enough.) But we always started classes for anybody who
                    wanted it....basic, “market” Spanish to let people mingle in town, order a
                    drink, be a little less self-conscious. But they weren't interested. They would
                    try for a while and then drop off. I couldn't understand that, especially since,
                    without Spanish, they knew they were too embarrassed to do simple things like go
                    shopping. They couldn't go to the bars and do the social things that they liked
                    doing. Nobody expects you to have perfect Spanish (the Guineans are so nice
                    about helping you along if you have any Spanish at all), but without any Spanish
                    you are playing charades.</p>
                <p>The married people were in better shape. For example, there was a communicator
                    and his wife, neither of whom spoke Spanish, but they were married and had each
                    other, and that solved a lot of the language problem. If you didn't have someone
                    to unburden to in English, it seemed to me you had a problem. But we had (to my
                    knowledge) no drinking problems,no drug problems, the kinds of problems you
                    would expect in so isolated a place.</p>
                <p>We did have some unhappy people, no question about that. I don't know how State
                    solves that, but if everybody, especially the non-coms, were given language
                    training, it would open up new worlds for them. One secretary, a lovely young
                    woman really tried to learn Spanish on her own but just didn't have much
                    success, although she was extraverted and gave it the college try. As a result
                    of being unable to speak Spanish, she asked to leave post early and, of course,
                    I said all right because she really had tried. But if she had had a couple of
                    months of Spanish before she came out it would have made things a lot easier and
                    State would have had a trained secretary in place for a much longer period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since Equatorial Guinea is a place that really does not
                        show up on the normal radar, could you explain a little about it
                        background?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Actually it is fairly well known among Africanists, but by the name
                    Fernando Po, the Main island. The Portuguese discovered, or in
                    political-correctese, encountered Fernando Po (Po rhymes with goo) in the 15th
                    century. Many people had sailed down the West coast of Africa, but few made it
                    back. They didn't have the technology to do so. The Portuguese developed the
                    corsair, the height of naval technology in those days, a technological
                    equivalent in its time to the nuclear subs we have developed which can sail
                    around the world under water. The corsairs, with their special sails and
                    Portuguese knowledge of the winds and tides, allowed them to get down the coast
                    of Africa and back again. That is how they were able to get around the Cape of
                    Good Hope, an achievement for those days equivalent to our moon landing.</p>
                <p>The Portuguese were the astronauts of the 15th century, and they explored
                    everywhere, including Africa. That is why so many places like Sierra Leone and
                    Cabo Verde have Portuguese names (Papua New Guinea in the Pacific was so called
                    because the native hair pieces reminded the Portuguese of a papal tiara).
                    Mozambique, Angola, Guinea Bissau were Portuguese colonies (they even landed on
                    The East Cape of Good Hope but used it only for a fueling and R &amp; R station;
                    they didn't think it worth colonizing!), and in their voyages they landed on the
                    island known until 1968 or so as Fernando Po. (No, I don't know who the
                    eponymous Fernando Po was.)</p>
                <p>There is a humorous story I tell on myself. The capital of Mozambique in the late
                    60's when I got to USIA was Louren�o Marques, named I guess, in Portuguese
                    fashion after some famous Portuguese. All the African cables I saw on arriving
                    at USIA had the notation: “Copy Lourenco Marques.” I didn't know it was a place.
                    I pictured some old colonial planter in a white suit, the kind of person
                    Fernando Lamas played in SOUTH PACIFIC, grown old but still very knowledgeable
                    about East Africa. I assumed he was on our payroll and the “copy Lourenco
                    Marques” was to keep him informed. Dumb? Yes, very.</p>
                <p>Anyway, there was a trade made between Spain and Portugal in the 18th century.
                    Spain ceded Portugal some islands off Brazil, and Spain was given Fernando Po in
                    West Africa. Thus, in a nutshell, is how Fernando Po became Spanish. It gained
                    independence in 1968, but it had exercised autonomy for some time before and had
                    its own representatives in the Spanish Cortes.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>The first President was Francisco Macias, and his accession to power was the
                    result of a power struggle in the UN Poland, of all countries, was influential
                    in gathering support around him. He was not Spain's first choice by any means,
                    but in one of the great underestimates of all time, they went along with him as
                    someone who couldn't do any harm. It is the vogue to say he was a madman. I
                    think he was just a very bad and very stupid man. He gave himself the title of
                    “Divine Miracle”, and woe to anyone who snickered on hearing it. He took
                    Equatorial Guinea which had the third highest per capita income in Africa, after
                    Libya and South Africa, right over a cliff. He destroyed the economy. E.G. had
                    the best cocoa in the world, and he destroyed its production and export. He made
                    it a crime to be an “intellectual,” the corpus delicti sufficing in owning a
                    single book. He drove out priests and nuns, and many others fled for their
                    lives. The schools, which the nuns had run with such great success, closed, and
                    for a decade young Guineans had no schooling whatsoever. He also murdered many
                    people, leading anyone with a brain and means to escape to flee. If someone drew
                    up a plan to destroy a country, he could not have improved on what Macias
                    actually did. When he was finally convicted... they had a trial for him of
                    sorts...they named 4500 people that he was responsible for killing, some as I
                    mentioned, executed in the national soccer stadium to the accompaniment of
                    Beatles music.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We are talking about a population of how many?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: The current population is roughly 300,000. That's probably a good working
                    figure. You know that records don't mean much in a country where many births and
                    deaths are not recorded. Add to that the great numbers that fled, obviously
                    without getting their passports stamped. There is no really accurate number of
                    those killed or driven out by Macias, but the number I heard frequently was
                    100,000 or a third of the population. Those who could flee went to Gabon, to
                    Cameroon, to The Canaries or to Spain itself, and probably other places as well,
                    such as Nigeria, but how many is just guess work.</p>
                <p>Those who were able to escape formed Guinean exile associations in the countries
                    in which they settled. I have seen the minutes of some of these groups. They
                    were, of course, all against the government of E.G. (you have to wait in line to
                    do that), but they reminded me of the Young Republicans: they spent all their
                    time trying to purge each other, half the group accusing the other half of
                    disloyalty, intrigue, etc. It didn't matter where the group was, The Canaries,
                    Paris, Gabon, the minutes always read alike.</p>
                <p>Their plight, of course, was anything but humorous. Families were separated
                    forever, many Guinean women became prostitutes to support themselves in places
                    like Libreville (the red light district there is largely Guinean), and all
                    because of Francisco Macias, who had done just terrible things, abominable
                    things, an Idi Amin without the publicity. Many people think he had to be
                    demented. I think he was just a bad person. He admired Hitler whom he used to
                    quote in his speeches. He used bhong, rhymes with gong, a kind of marijuana
                    which he smoked all the time. “The Dogs of War” if you have ever read that book
                    is about Equatorial Guinea.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: John Forsythe?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Fredrick Forsyth, I think. John is the actor. That book was not only about
                    E.G., it was written in Equatorial Guinea. If you want to know what the city
                    looked like that book will tell you. The description is just wonderful. Forsyth
                    was in E.G. during the Macias period, and the book is about a fictional attempt
                    to overthrow him. Forsyth, himself, did fund an aborted attempt to overthrow
                    Macias, but the Spanish Coast Guard intercepted the guns and mercenaries before
                    they could get out of Spanish waters, and that was the end of that. There has
                    been an recent book on E.G., and The New York Times rated it as one of the best
                    books of 1990. Written by Bob Klitgaard, it's called “Tropical Gangsters” and
                    treats Equatorial Guinea about the time when I was there. I knew Bob and
                    actually reviewed the book for the Foreign Service Journal. The title tells it
                    all: the tropical gangsters are the corrupt government officials (is that
                    redundant ?) in E.G., a tropical nomenclature headed by the President himself,
                    Teodoro Obiang, as gang leader.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is a coastal part too isn't there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, there is a pie slice really between Gabon and Cameroon which is also
                    part of Equatorial Guinea. Then they have an island called Annobon on the other
                    side of Sao Tome and Principe, at least 500 miles away from Fernando Po, and it
                    too is a part of Equatorial Guinea. Again these possessions are all the result
                    of trades, deals made centuries ago, by countries playing Monopoly with each
                    other.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>We actually went to Annobon one time by ship, the “national ship,” the Acacio
                    Mane, a gift from the Chinese who got it as a war reparation from the Japanese.
                    “ Getting there is half the fun” is Cunard's motto, and it could have been the
                    Acacio Mane's as well. There are no scheduled departures. You just hear that
                    it's sailing soon, and you buy a ticket and hope soon is within the next week or
                    two. Like all the African ships I have been on, there were nice cabins, black
                    hole of Calcutta cabins and deck space for people and their animals. Remember:
                    these folks didn't have bank accounts; their animals were their wealth, and they
                    carried them with them. Some on the deck slept on straw mats they brought;
                    others slept in their cayucos or in any unoccupied convex form on deck. There
                    were also convicts on the boat, en route to Annobon to spend a year or two, or
                    at least until the boat came back, as prisoners. They weren't dangerous or
                    violent. People in E.G. just are not violent. They probably stole some money or
                    insulted some official, and they are on their way to Annobon, as carefree as the
                    other passengers going to see family. Annobon isn't near anywhere; Gabon and San
                    Tome and Principe are too far away to reach by small boat, and no big boats ever
                    come there. There is no place for them to go until the government ship comes and
                    takes them back after a year or whatever period of time is involved. Since the
                    population of Annobon is 9 to 1 women to men, all the husbands and sons having
                    gone to Gabon or Malabo to find work, the prisoners may actually be looking
                    forward to a Club Med experience.</p>
                <p>All in all, the geography of E.G. is unusual. They have these little islands here
                    and there. One of them is just off the coast of Gabon, and it is, or at least
                    was, a hot potato because there is supposed to be a great deal of oil in the
                    area...or at least some form of hydrocarbons, in the water off shore. When last
                    I checked, Gabon and E.G. were disputing ownership of the oil rich island area.
                    In addition to hydrocarbons, there are quite a few other natural resources, gold
                    and wonderful timber, in E.G. It is potentially a rich country. They had a
                    wonderful cocoa industry and could have again, with some foresight and sensible
                    government policies. The cocoa plantations of E.G. used to produce the best
                    cocoa in the world, and some think they still do, but they are producing at
                    about 5 or 10 % of capacity. The cocoa trees would have to be cut back (many
                    haven't been pruned or attended to in 25 years), they are still hardy I am told,
                    and getting them back in production would certainly be do-able. The problem is
                    that nobody wants to invest in the country because bribery is not just a moral
                    issue it is an economic issue. The politicians of E.G. don't even meet the
                    Chicago definition of government ethics: a politician who once bought, stays
                    bought. Worse, the investors in E.G. don't even know whom to bribe. The
                    country's system of graft is as screwed up as the rest of the country. I had a
                    French businessman come in to see me one time and he said, “You know we paid off
                    the Minister to bring in the Peugeots we were importing, and now I have to pay
                    off the Customs guy as well. It never stops.” So no one is going to invest in a
                    place where costs, not even the payoff schedule, is predictable.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>Politically, and paradoxically, the government is stable. It may be that the
                    people are just too worn out by the travails of the last twenty-odd years, by
                    the memory of Macias' horrors or just think that things, bad as they are, can
                    never be as bad as the period before the coup, golpe de estado they say in
                    Spanish, which overthrew Macias.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: The coup happened in 1979. Macias' nephew, the one who overthrew him, is
                    the current President, and probably a fairly decent man, despite some of the
                    horror stories I've heard about him. He went to Zaragoza, which is the Spanish
                    West Point. He got through, with caballero's C's, I guess you'd say in Spain. He
                    is a very interesting person, a lot more complex and interesting than many of
                    the politicians I've met in Washington. When I got to E.G. Teodoro Obiang, or
                    Teodoro as he is called locally, spoke only Spanish and Fang. When I left he
                    spoke French quite well. He had worked hard at it and succeeded. It made sense
                    since to learn French since the French are moving into E.G. in a very big way.
                    They are replacing the Spanish in all the key institutions. Teodoro was also
                    trying to get a degree from Madrid (unlike President Doe of Liberia who was
                    getting a sweetheart deal from a university in Monrovia, Teodoro is going after
                    a real degree) and was working on that as well. He is a workaholic. Now that he
                    has French he may switch to a French university since the Spanish system is
                    incredibly bureaucratic and would probably love giving a head-of-state a hard
                    time. He is a physical fitness...I won't say nut, but more than an enthusiast.
                    He has a very pleasant way of dealing with people, and he is extraordinarily
                    effective in dealing with large groups of Guineans, whether he be talking about
                    monetary policy or keeping the garbage off the streets. He assumes a fatherly
                    role and is firm without being brusque.</p>
                <p>His faults as leader or dictator, because that's really what he is, are probably
                    the same, although on a smaller scale, as his dictatorial brothers, Mobutu,
                    Kaunda, Nyerere, Moi, Doe, et al. throughout Africa, but I have met almost all
                    the famous African dictators, and I would give Teodoro higher than average marks
                    on personal qualities like sensitivity, sympathy for the little man or, at
                    least, acting as if he did. Teodoro has the reputation of running something
                    called Black Beach, “Black Bich” in pidgin, a prison for Macias' enemies, real
                    or imagined, where, they say, Teodoro was in charge of torture and death. It was
                    like the Castro prison Valadares describes in Beyond All Hope or Idi Amin's
                    Psychiatric Institute. And yet, while it is possible to view Teodoro as a crook
                    with his bank accounts in Paris and Madrid, it is very hard to meet with him, as
                    I have many times, and believe he is a brutal or violent man, or one capable of
                    authorizing or participating in the atrocities committed with “Black Bich.” I
                    discussed this with a friend one time, an Agency fellow who had also met him. He
                    had an interesting comment. He said: “ Suppose Obiang did all the things they
                    say he did (and like me, my friend didn't know for sure whether he did) how
                    would he be acting now if he truly repented all the evil things he had done?”
                    Well, the answer to his question is that he would be acting exactly as he was
                    acting. So, I guess I think that if he ever committed the crimes attributed to
                    him, he has changed his ways.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>There is no violence in the E.G. which is extraordinary to anyone familiar with
                    West Africa. Lagos, an hour away by plane, is wild, and if you go across the
                    Bight of Benin to Douala, 20 miles away, and it is like New York City. That bad!
                    My son and I got mugged in Douala at 7 o'clock at night, in the main business
                    district, to the amusement of passers-by. Mother Teresa would get mugged in
                    Douala. It is just a very rough place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Douala is the capital of...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Douala is Cameroon's main city, its New York, as opposed to Yaounde, its
                    capital, its Albany. In contrast, in Malabo, if you can believe this, your wife,
                    if she were a beauty queen, could walk down any street in any area of the city,
                    in a bathing suit, at midnight and be perfectly safe. However, if she left her
                    rosary beads in a church pew to go to confession, they would be stolen. Theft of
                    every kind, was rampant, but there was no violence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must have made it quite doable for the staff
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, and the peace of the place gave us a lot of peace of mind about the
                    children. They could go wherever they wanted and explore, play with friends,
                    ride their bikes, go anywhere, and we didn't have to worry about them being
                    robbed, beaten or straying into the wrong neighborhood. Malabo was a heck of a
                    lot safer than D.C.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>Two of our sons came over with us. The third would come a little later. One had
                    just finished grammar school, and the other was about to go into seventh grade.
                    We put them both in an African school in Malabo, the Instituto Rey Malabo (King
                    Malabo was a famous Bubi leader). It was a good experience for them as far as
                    making friends, learning Spanish and being accepted by the Guineans was
                    concerned, but a complete waste of time in academic terms. The teachers called
                    in sick (there were no phones, so they sent a message some way), and then came
                    to school and played basketball and soccer in plain view of the administrators
                    and students. Other times they just didn't show. The good thing was that David
                    and Stephen learned a little Spanish at school. They played basketball, and I
                    put up a basketball court in the Embassy so they could invite the local boys in
                    to play. The Spanish Embassy opened up a grammar school in Malabo time for
                    Stephen to do his 8th grade there (David had gone back to board at Georgetown
                    Prep in Washington), but the next year they both went to school in Spain, to a
                    high school called San Estanislao de Kostka, a school many educated Spanish sent
                    their own children to, 20 K's outside Madrid on the road to El Escorial. They
                    were the only two anglos there, so their Spanish is wonderful. They speak
                    castellano castizo, as they say. When they were in Spain they would come back
                    for vacations at Christmas and Easter, as did many diplomatic children. The nice
                    thing was...you know the Spanish schedule is different, dinner at 10:00 and then
                    off to the disco at midnight...there was never a worry about their safety. They
                    would come home about 4 or 5 in the morning, routinely. If that happened in
                    Washington, we would be pacing the halls, calling the emergency rooms, but in
                    Malabo there was no worry. They could walk home if they had to (one end of the
                    town to the other in any direction was under two miles), and I guess they
                    usually did because they weren't driving at that time. But as I mentioned,
                    Malabo was just much safer than Washington or New York City. Other people who
                    had daughters and therefore might have been a little more cautious had the same
                    experience. It was so nice that they could go out and didn't have to worry about
                    them. The Spanish Ambassador (and you know the Spanish tradition of duennas and
                    extremely close scrutiny of daughters) was saying that in Madrid, if his
                    daughter wasn't home by 2 he would be frantic; in Malabo, he was sound asleep
                    when they came home at 3 or 4.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American interests in Equatorial Guinea? When
                        you went out were you told to do something in particular?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Probably the most important thing I could do was to keep the peace between
                    the French and Spanish. The Spanish were the colonial power, but their prestige
                    and influence in E.G. were waning. The French were shoving their way into
                    Equatorial Guinea, and there was, understandably, no shortage of tension between
                    the two countries. The United States opened the embassy in E.G. because
                    President Carter had made some sort of commitment to King Juan Carlos that we
                    would do something there, and that may have seemed at the time the best thing to
                    do. It wasn't the result of some geo-politician like Henry Kissinger saying: “To
                    keep the U.S. a world power, we've got to go into Equatorial Guinea.” I doubt
                    even Kissinger knew where it was. No, our being there was purely a political
                    favor to The King of Spain. Who knows, maybe Jimmy, who thought he knew Spanish,
                    was really like that mission director in Ouagadougou. Maybe he agreed to
                    something the King said in Spanish without knowing what he was agreeing to. In
                    any event, we had broken off diplomatic relations during Macias' time, about a
                    year, I think, after that murder, although not just because of the murder. It
                    certainly made sense to restore diplomatic relations with the country after
                    Macias was overthrown, but an embassy? State goes through these things
                    regularly. For a while, diplomatic relations are handled regionally; then they
                    decide on embassies everywhere. Then they decide they have to cut back. And on
                    and on. That happened in E.G. They reopened the embassy, and 8 years later they
                    were trying to close it again, this time for fiscal rather than policy
                    reasons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: A cynic would quote Parkinson and say work expands to the time allotted to
                    it. In fact, there were quite a few things to do. We had an AID project for one
                    thing. Since we did have an embassy there, things like dealing with the
                    government on some key UN votes was a major responsibility. I will be immodest
                    enough to say that during my stay E.G. went from the bottom to the top of
                    African countries supporting the U.S. on key votes. There was also another
                    semi-annual ritual: every six months we got a telegram from Vernon Walters, our
                    Ambassador to the UN, saying that the Marshal in New York was about to evict the
                    Equatorial Guinean embassy (embassy is the right word; E.G. was allowed to use
                    its UN Mission as its embassy; embassies as you know are in capitals, and I
                    never heard of this before.) E.G.'s embassy was in New York, and every 6 months
                    Vernon Walters would ask us to ask the Foreign Minister to pay the rent. Walters
                    could never call their embassy because their phone was cut off for non-payment
                    more than it was on. So we would go to the Foreign Minister who was always
                    shocked that this unseemly matter had arisen, especially as the check was in the
                    mail, etc. It was a little game we both played. He was lying. I knew it. He knew
                    I knew it. I knew he knew I knew it. We both pretended it was a horrible
                    misunderstanding.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>There was also a great deal of building going on; the embassy building itself was
                    being completed and quarters were being renovated for the political officer's,
                    the admin officer's and the communicator's house. Since we were a sho'nuf
                    embassy, we got on State's mailing list of issues to discuss with the government
                    of E.G. in order to get their support on everything from GATT issues to Law of
                    the Sea questions. Most of these communiques were never acted on since only two
                    people in the government would have the slightest idea what they were about, and
                    I had to save these 2 for special favors on key issues. Where possible we did
                    float informational papers on issues that we were interested in just to keep
                    them more or less au fait with issues that might become hot. We did a fair
                    amount of dealing with other embassies. We were very friendly with the Spanish.
                    They were really a class act, extremely professional. They had to speak two
                    languages well even to be considered for the diplomatic service. All whom we
                    knew had lived in English and French countries for a while, so it wasn't a
                    question of just going to FSI. Their English and French were excellent. They
                    usually went to places like Dublin. The Spanish Ambassador had gone to LSE
                    (London School of Economic) for a while. He had also lived in Paris. The French
                    had two ambassadors during my stay. The second one was extremely pleasant,
                    mainly so, I think, because he had spent so little time in France. He was a pied
                    noir, born and raised in Algeria. A very nice person and easy to get along with.
                    He had a wonderful sense of humor, and his wife had filaria, as did the wife of
                    the previous French ambassador who had no sense of humor. It proves, I think,
                    that filaria is not contracted from a humorous spouse.</p>
                <p>Different events broke the monotony. There was the 40th celebration of the end of
                    World War II which came up in 1985. Boris, the Russian ambassador, invited me to
                    celebrate May 8th, 1985 as part of a worldwide Russian celebration of their role
                    in ending WWII. We were under instructions not to attend, as were the French.
                    “But we were allies in World War II,” Boris protested when I said I couldn't go.
                    “Which part would that be, Boris,” 41-45 or '39-41 when you were allies of the
                    Nazis.” He was not amused. He said I was the rudest person in Malabo except for
                    the French ambassador who was even ruder.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>There were also be visits by the Fleet, usually our fleet, but sometimes the
                    French fleet and sometimes the Nigerian fleet. (Sometimes they were invited!)
                    There would be national days and special holidays, and all the embassies
                    supported each other by going. The Government, however, only went to one
                    national day per year at each embassy (that was their rule), so the idea was to
                    find some other pretext to get them there. Ship visits usually worked, but the
                    biggest success we had was Martin Luther King's birthday. I think we were the
                    first embassy in Africa that did a major program on Martin Luther King. I
                    personally wasn't in favor of his birthday being a national holiday, but I was
                    outvoted. My job as an ambassador was to represent the United States, and if
                    Martin Luther King's birthday was something our country had decided to
                    celebrate, I thought the embassy should do it up right. It was amazing to me,
                    and to all of us at the embassy, just how enthusiastically the Guineans
                    responded to our honoring Martin Luther King. Usually Guineans come to our
                    celebrations for the food. Not so with Martin Luther King. He was a hero in
                    Africa as well as in the U.S. We had a ceremony on Martin Luther King's birthday
                    in 1988, just before we left, and dedicated a small building on the embassy
                    grounds as the Martin Luther King's Reading Room. Even the Foreign Minister,
                    trained in Patrice Lumumba University in Moscow (You know the Russians
                    segregated the African students in Moscow! So much for the workers' brotherhood)
                    was there and cut the tape to open the reading room formally. The irony, of
                    course, is that many Guineans would still be afraid to be seen by government
                    people entering the U.S. embassy, if only to use the MLK Reading Room. The
                    Government of E.G. praised MLK because it was an opportunity for them to be seen
                    on the side of the angels, in favor of equal justice, one man, one vote,
                    democratic government, etc. The reality is that if Martin Luther King had tried
                    any of his non-violent resistance in Equatorial Guinea, if, for example, he were
                    to organize protests to oppose the discriminatory treatment of the Bubis by the
                    ruling clique of Fangs in the government, he would have been in “Black Bich,” or
                    among the missing, un desaparecido, in no time flat. They don't put up with much
                    dissent, let alone civil disobedience, in E.G. as the Jehovah Witnesses and
                    anybody who lived there soon found out.</p>
                <p>Although Martin Luther King enjoys a kind of secular sainthood, I would dare to
                    say, throughout Africa, there is no such uniformity among all Africans in their
                    views of American blacks. The point was best made by recently by an American
                    black. I wonder if you read in the Washington Post about two weeks ago...their
                    man in Africa was writing about his experiences there; he is black and the
                    successor to Blaine Hardin whom I mentioned earlier. He wrote, among other
                    things, about the reactions of Africans to him. Some were very warm and happy to
                    see him... “you are one of us,” they seemed to be saying. Others were very
                    condescending. “You are not one of us.” He said the first time he had ever been
                    called “nigger” was by a Kenyan policeman in Nairobi who looked down on American
                    blacks. In the 20 years or so that I have been going to Africa, I have seen
                    first hand both reactions by African towards black Americans, but I never
                    observed any hostility or superciliousness by Guineans towards American blacks.
                    If anything there was a little unrealistic hero-worship of American blacks and
                    their success.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>An example, by no means atypical. USIA has VIP tours where up-and-comers from
                    countries like E.G. spend a couple of weeks in the United States visiting cities
                    and places of particular interest to them. Technical people might visit the
                    Silicon Valley; finance types New York City, etc. USIA picks people who they
                    think are going to be running the government in a few years. Well, one of these
                    people, an economist and, I would have thought, a reasonably worldly young man
                    who had done university work in Russia and Spain, had gone on one of these tours
                    of the U.S. I was talking to him about his experiences and he said in all
                    seriousness: “You know, I was over there, and I was just so impressed by how
                    well all these black people are doing. In New York I saw this fellow who had a
                    very big hat, and big fur coat and all these rings on, a huge Cadillac and some
                    white girl friends.” What he saw, of course, was a pimp, but to the Guinean,
                    this was just the American dream come true for a black man. If I asked my young
                    Guinean friend what the gentleman he saw did for a living, he probably would
                    have said he worked on Wall Street or worked in a big office somewhere.</p>
                <p>By the time I left E.G. we had two big MLK celebrations, the second one being
                    bigger than the first. I suggested to my successor, Chester Norris, that he
                    really emphasize the Martin Luther King holiday. Guineans were so happy and
                    proud that the U.S. was honoring a black man, Martin Luther King, that our
                    celebration almost became their celebration. It was a natural for us, and all we
                    had to do was bring people together to talk about Martin Luther King, and even
                    that was no problem. Guineans knew as much about Martin Luther King as we did.
                    In a panel discussion on television (E.G. didn't have a newspaper, but it did
                    have a television station before most African countries) during our first
                    celebration of the MLK birthday, panelist after panelist gave different details
                    of MLK's life and various reasons why he (MLK) was a great man. It was like
                    listening to soccer fans discuss Pele. They knew everything about him. One of
                    the panelists was the Catholic Bishop of Malabo. Equatorial Guinea is 98 percent
                    Catholic, at least nominally. One of the questions asked the Bishop was, “Are
                    you (i.e. The Church) going to canonize Martin Luther King?” The Bishop wasn't
                    going to get into a discussion of the canonization process. I forget his answer,
                    but it was diplomatic. The interesting thing to me was the question itself. It
                    showed how the Guineans viewed MLK. He deserved to be canonized, whether he was
                    or not. Being associated with MLK simply by representing the country he did so
                    much to change was an enormous plus for us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said part of your marching orders was to keep the
                        French/Spanish dispute quiet. Did you get involved between them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Oh, Yes, indeed. E.G. changed currency from the bipkuele, its own
                    currency, to the West African Franc in 1985, a sign of things to come. The West
                    African Franc, the CFA, pronounced say-fa, was pegged to the French Franc on a 1
                    to 50 ratio, and that spelled the beginning of the end of Spanish influence in
                    E.G. Teodoro actually committed a pun in one of his speeches after the currency
                    shift. The economy was worse than ever, and he referred to the “CFA, or as they
                    say in pidgin “Sufa” (suffer). I guess you had to be there. The currency
                    business didn't happen in a vacuum. There were always problems between Madrid
                    and Equatorial Guinea on levels of aid, on Iberia (Iberia is a government run
                    airline and shows it), on insults real or imagined towards one or another, and
                    the French would capitalize on these frictions. One cartoon I saw in a Madrid
                    paper portrayed Teodoro as a cannibal biting or eating the hand (Spain) that fed
                    him. Vicious and racist as it was, it was not the Spanish government speaking
                    but a newspaper. These distinctions were not necessarily made. There were some
                    real racists among the Spanish: one of the rising young diplomats at their
                    embassy referred to the Guineans continually as monkeys, “monos” in Spanish, and
                    he meant it. In general, though the Spanish were not racist. They and the
                    Guineans were like a family. There were lots of squabbles and finger pointing,
                    but at bottom they liked each other, saw themselves as belonging to one another.
                    The French, on the other hand, were, man for man, the most racist group I ever
                    encountered in Africa. Surprising, perhaps, because of their long experience in
                    Africa, especially, West Africa, but they were there to use the Africans and for
                    no other reason.</p>
                <p>The French knew what they had to do to get control of a Third World country. They
                    would get into ministries such as Finance, Transportation, Communications, and
                    that is where they would put their experts with the aim of taking over
                    everything. While the French and Spanish didn't openly quarrel about French
                    maneuvering—the Spanish attitude was classic sour grapes: let them have the
                    place; it will be a great relief to us not to be burdened with all the
                    corruption—yet there really was a lot of animosity and hurt Spanish pride. I
                    tried to keep on good terms with both the French and Spanish to stop things from
                    getting out-of-hand. Spain was moving out and France was moving in. That seemed
                    unavoidable. What I wanted to do was to avoid any real outbreaks of bitterness
                    between Spain and France. Everybody knew the handwriting was on the wall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about our AID mission? Here you had come from AID
                        where you had sort of a jaundiced view and all of a sudden you had an AID
                        project in your lap. How did you feel about that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>RUDDY: I had a jaundiced view of aid in general, but not of every aid project.
                    The one that we had there was first rate. It was run out of Yaounde by what was
                    called a PVO, a private voluntary organization called The Cooperative League of
                    the United States or CLUSA for short. CLUSA was into cooperatives, not in the
                    Chinese sense, but in the Land-o-Lakes sense. USAID had been in E.G. before we
                    broke off diplomatic relations in the mid 70's, and when they left, they behind
                    a great many heavy duty trucks. When the U.S. came back, the trucks were still
                    there, many wrecked or rusted out, but there. What CLUSA did was to teach
                    Guineans how to rehabilitate the trucks by repairing those they could and
                    cannibalizing parts from trucks that were too far gone. This created a group of
                    pretty competent Guinean mechanics. Once the trucks were up and running again,
                    CLUSA worked with farmers to develop ways of using the trucks to take the crops
                    they had grown to the markets in the cities. This training stressed maintenance
                    since un-maintained trucks wouldn't last, and an entrepreneurial spirit since
                    access to markets via the trucks encouraged farmers to grow more to sell more.
                    They were also moving into exports. It tried to teach farmers how to organize
                    their products for export. I thought it was excellent idea. It didn't cost a lot
                    of money. Nobody could get rich on CLUSA, and there was nothing to steal. The
                    Guineans in the program came away with a skill and eventually would be running
                    the operation themselves. The government, of course, didn't understand what
                    CLUSA was doing, and put lots of stumbling blocks in their way, like hitting the
                    farmers with contrived export taxes when they tried to exports their products.
                    The idea of people making money on their own really bothered some of the Guinean
                    bureaucrats, and, instead of encouraging exports and the money they would bring
                    into the country, they did their best to stifle them.</p>
                <p>The Peace Corps was supposed to come to E.G. to work on these kinds of projects,
                    but as of the time I left, none of the volunteers had arrived. I had actually
                    arranged for the Peace Corps to come to E.G. although I have never been overly
                    impressed with them. I suppose getting all those young people who can't find
                    jobs out of the country and putting them on the dole in some foreign country
                    where they can't do too much damage is not such a bad idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any Soviets or Chinese involved there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes. The Soviets went from about 200 plus when we got there to about 50-60
                    by the time we left. The Chinese also had a very big presence, in the hundreds.
                    Many of the Chinese were on the mainland where they ran all the government's
                    telecommunications. They also ran the national ship. There was a Guinean crew
                    too, the captain might actually have been a Guinean, but that was all for show.
                    Once the ship got underway, the Guineans disappeared, and the Chinese took over.
                    The Chinese also did most of the things requiring technical skills. They also
                    avoided controversies and kept out of everybody's way. They went about their own
                    business. The embassy types were very pleasant to deal with, and everybody's
                    great hope was to be invited to the Chinese embassy for a dinner of endless
                    courses of wonderful food. Of their hundreds in E.G., many were manual laborers
                    whom we seldom saw. All the others, diplomats, doctors and other higher ranking
                    Chinese lived in town lived together in a large four-storied building in the
                    center of town. The Chinese were not very active politically in E.G.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that the Soviets were sort of a receding wave
                        or something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, indeed. I'd like to think I was able to arouse some very pro American
                    sympathies in the Guineans, and that was what cooled relations between The
                    Russians and E.G. Truth is, with SDI and al the extra costs it involved for the
                    USSR, they had to cut back around the world. E.G. had to be at the top of their
                    cut list. The Russians lent the planes that were the national airline, but when
                    they became too dangerous to fly, the Russians didn't want to pick up the tab to
                    repair them. The stories of flights on those planes were right out of Lawrence
                    Durrell.</p>
                <p>The Russian ambassador, Boris Krasnakov, was a Stalinist. He was really somebody
                    right out of a Dostoevsky novel, a nice man of the land, somebody who had worked
                    in a cooperative somewhere, had come up through the Party apparatus and, as a
                    reward or punishment, had been sent to this place. He was never going to go any
                    place else and was there for a long time. They called him el embajador
                    vitalicio, a joke meaning him the lifetime Ambassador to E.G. He was described
                    in an '84 article in the London Sunday Times as an “aging drunk.” He had
                    apparently rolled his car on the airport road on Sunday a.m., and the embassy
                    staff was called out to put it back on the road. Boris spoke reasonably good
                    Spanish although he would not speak to you in Spanish in any formal setting; he
                    would go through a translator. I don't know if that was because he was being
                    observed (Were the translators KGB?) or whether he just wanted the extra time to
                    think. The Russians were quite active. They were forever doing rotten things,
                    just like their counterparts Boris Badanov and Natasha. And not just nasty
                    things, but stupid things as well. We always had to be on the qui vive. Any
                    activity we had in the city, for example, always had to have fall back plans
                    because the Russians were capable of sabotaging our events. On one occasion the
                    power line was carefully cut, and the only ones who could have benefited from
                    that were the Russians. After that incident, we always had to have a generator
                    on stand-by in case the power went off.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>They also did some silly things. The level was just childish. Their ambassador
                    was out of the country, (that was when their embassy played), and I got a call
                    one night, at home by myself, from a Russian asking me to go to the Beiruth,
                    basically the only restaurant in town and Malabo's answer to Rick's in
                    Casablanca, to meet him and to discuss something important. So I went. When I
                    got to the place there were three Russians sitting at the table and I went over
                    and said, “I am here.” They said they knew nothing about it. So I went to the
                    owner and told him I had just gotten a call from somebody who said he was a
                    Russian diplomat. He said, “Yes, that man right over there. He just used the
                    phone,” pointing to the Russian I had just spoken to. Their idea of a joke was
                    to get the American Ambassador to come down there. In the 7th grade, that might
                    have been funny.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You can be basically relaxed about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes. As I said, Malabo may have had many negatives, but it was safe. The
                    day after we bombed Tripoli, I called Armengol, the head of the government's
                    secret police, and the President's brother, and said, “We are going to need some
                    extra support around here in case someone gets some ideas.” An Aeroflot plane
                    came from Tripoli to Malabo each week, and if you were looking for a place to
                    retaliate, Malabo was a soft touch. He said, “In case you didn't know it, you
                    have had police around your embassy since last night. We arrested one man in
                    back of the embassy. He didn't belong there, but we don't think he was a
                    terrorist.” So they were on the ball. The Russians in E.G. had descended to
                    pranksters, and we let it go at that.</p>
                <p>Before I leave the subject of the Tripoli raid, on April 16, 1986, the day after
                    the raid, our embassy cars were cheered in the streets of Malabo. It wasn't just
                    us. Qadhafi had put Teodoro on his death list (being on Qadhafi's death list was
                    a sign that you had arrived among many African leaders), so there was little
                    sympathy for him in E.G.</p>
                <p>The Cubans were in E.G., but they were so hard up...their ambassador had to
                    borrow money from the Spanish ambassador to go out to the Beirut. We know this
                    because the Spanish ambassador mentioned it, not critically but sympathetically.
                    The North Koreans were no better off. They took their duty free liquor and
                    tobacco and had what amounted to duty free garage sales every once in a while at
                    the Korean embassy. Totally illegal, of course. They also got mixed up in some
                    scheme to buy Guinean passports from some Foreign Ministry official, and the
                    government refused agr�ment to their new ambassador. They paid off the wrong
                    people. The East Germans were not there; they were in Sao Tome and Principe.</p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>It's fortunate that the country was as safe as it was because our security was a
                    joke. State's security people might do a fine job in some places, but the
                    security people who came over from Yaounde did not inspire much confidence. One
                    particularly bureaucratic security type announced, on his arrival, that the
                    entire embassy staff would have to assemble for a security briefing. With
                    everybody present, he demonstrated self-defense and in the process wound up
                    shooting himself with Mace.</p>
                <p>There had been an attempted coup, summer of '86, I was home, and the number two
                    was telling me that this same security fellow came to Malabo for three days
                    shortly after the coup attempt. As he was getting ready to leave and go back to
                    Yaounde and at the end of the third day, the DCM said, “Clarence, you have been
                    here for three days, and you are our security officer. You haven't asked one
                    thing about the coup attempt.” His reply: “What coup attempt?” That was the man
                    in whose care the State Department entrusted our security.</p>
                <p>The way it works, you know, is that State's security “pro” was supposed to come
                    over from Yaounde and do a security evaluation of our embassy. In fact, we would
                    do the evaluation ourselves and then give it to the security officer, and he
                    would sign it. Apparently, in at least one case, the security officer had a real
                    literacy problem and was not able to write the report himself. The irony was
                    that at one point we asked for a shotgun just in case we needed to protect
                    ourselves. We thought that if anything awful ever happened a shotgun would keep
                    people from coming up the stairs. The security people said, “No. On the basis of
                    the security evaluation we don't think you need it.” I found this sort of
                    interesting because we had done the evaluation. Anyway security was a joke.
                    Fortunately we never never had to rely on them. They didn't inspire
                    confidence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were running your own show but not much support
                        anywhere...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: No, that's not so. There was no support from Security, but they were the
                    exceptions. In general we got great support from Washington. Jim Moran, who was
                    the management chief for the Africa Bureau in State, was terribly helpful.
                    Anything we wanted that was reasonable, and a lot that wasn't so reasonable, we
                    got. We needed a truck one time, but he diverted a shipment already at sea, and
                    we got it in weeks. Now this is Africa, and to get a truck you usually wait
                    years. State people in general were as helpful as can be. And the Desk officers
                    couldn't have been more helpful. They tried to do whatever they could.</p>
                <p>That surprised me. Because of the Helms business I thought there would be a lot
                    of resentment, and I would get a cold shoulder at the State Department. I
                    couldn't have been more wrong. I found nothing but helpfulness there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think once you are in the system you are part of the
                        team.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Yes, that's probably right. All the State people I dealt with were
                    extremely helpful, extremely professional. There is no place I enjoyed more in
                    my entire life than working for the State Department, and, although I didn't
                    agree with many of my colleagues on politics, I thought the people there were,
                    as a class, the brightest and most interesting I had ever come across. And, as
                    far as I was concerned, extremely helpful. As I said security was an area where
                    I felt State wasn't too helpful, but security people really weren't State. They
                    were just Burns detectives without uniforms. There were bureaucratic reasons why
                    we didn't get better communications, but the people we actually dealt with tried
                    to help. Once they were there and saw the situation they really had to be
                    sympathetic. The Agency people were outstanding. I had expected them to all look
                    like Robert Culp with sunglasses and trench coats— they do all wear sunglasses.
                    That must be a requirement. What surprised me is that I thought they were the
                    best linguists in the foreign affairs agencies, better than the State Department
                    FSO's; they are the best educated, all with advanced degrees in one thing or
                    another. Very impressive group. They too were extremely helpful as the following
                    incident demonstrates.</p>
                <p>There was a USAID fellow, based in Yaounde, who used to visit the continental
                    part of E.G. frequently to oversee CLUSA activities. While there, it transpired,
                    he took time to go around the country paying Guineans for information on wages
                    and economic conditions in the country, identifying himself as a CIA agent. I
                    can tell you about this because it is, as you shall see, in the public domain.
                    One of the people he was paying for this information was a Guinean working for
                    CLUSA. The employee told or let it slip to the head of CLUSA, an American, and
                    he went ballistic. He came storming into my office asking: “What are you doing
                    to us? You are going to compromise CLUSA and ruin us with this government? I
                    know you are going to deny that he is a CIA agent because you will have to, but
                    this is an outrageous way for the government to deal with one of its own PVO's.”
                    I said, “Well, if he were a CIA agent, I guess I would deny it, but as a matter
                    of fact he doesn't work for the CIA. That I can assure you. If he were do you
                    think he would go around telling everyone he was a CIA agent?” When I talked to
                    the Agency people about it they were as embarrassed as anybody and confirmed
                    what I already knew. “Of course he is not one of ours.” I then had to go to the
                    government and see my friend, Armengol, because if I knew, I had to be about the
                    last person to hear about it. With E.G.'s police, and their sources of
                    information being what they were, they knew all about this guy . I had to make
                    sure they knew we were not sneaking somebody in on them. Armengol said he had
                    heard nothing of the story, but that was just the wily Armengol.</p>
                <p>To return to your question, I categorize the support we got as outstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1988. How did you feel when you
                        left?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>RUDDY: Sad. FSI gives you a course on how to work when you get there, but they
                    never say how to leave. It was very hard. We had made some good friends there.
                    It was the right time to go though because I was getting too close to the
                    country. I was getting too sympathetic and could see that I might not be
                    objective anymore. I actually stayed on six months longer than expected as a
                    favor to the State Department because of a screw up. There was a report in the
                    Washington Post in September, 1987 that State was planning to close some
                    consulates and an embassy. The embassy would either be in The Comoros or
                    Equatorial Guinea, according to the story. VOA picked up the Post story and
                    reported it as a news story in its Spanish service. The Minister of Defense who
                    lived next door to us heard the story on VOA's Latin America service and
                    reported it to the Foreign Minister who called me in. The Foreign Minister and
                    President didn't distinguish between the VOA's reporting news and an official
                    announcement. They reasoned that since the U.S. Government runs VOA, what VOA
                    says must be a pronouncement by the United States Government. If VOA reported
                    that we were going to close the embassy in E.G., it must be so. I had been given
                    about 7 minutes notice of that broadcast by our consulate in Douala which had
                    called to say VOA was about to broadcast the Post story. I telephoned Chet
                    Crocker and amazingly, got through to him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was Assistant Secretary for African Affairs.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: It was very, very rare that anyone was able to get through to the States,
                    my call might have been the first, not that Crocker wouldn't take calls but due
                    to technical reasons. I knew Crocker well; we used to testify together. I said,
                    “Chet, what the hell is going on here? I just got called in to see the Foreign
                    Minister over that VOA broadcast of the Post story. They are v-e-r-y upset. They
                    say that the way this closing was announced shows that it wasn't a mistake; it
                    was a deliberate attempt to embarrass the country.” He said something like,
                    “Frank, it is a preliminary notification of a possible decision, and while it is
                    by no means definitive, I can't say it's not true.” I said, “Chet, this is me.
                    Save the gobbledegook for your staff meetings. What is going on?” After some
                    more to-ing and fro-ing, he said he didn't know.</p>
                <p>What happened was that I had to go back to see the Foreign Minister again. I said
                    that he was absolutely right to be outraged at this, that I hadn't heard a word
                    before the VOA story, and that I felt foolish as well. I tried to convince him
                    that I would have given him a heads up if I knew the news story, and that there
                    was absolutely no percentage or advantage surprising them this way. I told him
                    he and the President deserved an apology for the way the whole matter was
                    handled. I apologized and said that as far as I knew no final decision had been
                    made.</p>
                <p>In retrospect, the flap over the VOA story was the best thing that could have
                    happened to keep the embassy. I wouldn't be a bit surprised if State proposed
                    the closing to pacify Hill demands for budget cuts and then leaked the story to
                    create such an uproar that the closing couldn't go through.</p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>In any event, An Assistant Secretary of State was sent to Malabo with a letter
                    from President Reagan to President Obiang apologizing for this mistake. But it
                    was a big incident so instead of leaving at the end of September as I was
                    expected to, I was asked to stay on until March.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To keep the continuity...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: To keep the continuity. The new ambassador, Chester Norris, was having a
                    rough time with Spanish at FSI, so the extra time allowed him more time to
                    practice the subjunctive. Unfortunately for him, the extra time didn't seem to
                    do much good.</p>
                <p>E.G. was an extraordinary experience. Consider this. In mid-life the government
                    swoops down and sends you somewhere to learn the most spoken language in the
                    world (after English). It's not only free; they pay you while you are learning
                    for the four months... Exxon wouldn't do that. They send your children to school
                    in Spain. The boys got their own special international experience. E.G. has
                    become a metaphor for our whole life. People who we met there, things that we
                    did there, are the basic common experiences of the whole family. As I said, the
                    two youngest boys are absolutely fluent in Spanish. One is reading Quixote in
                    the original this year at Holy Cross; the other one did it at Columbia last
                    year. Our third son is in NYU and is going to Madrid in January. He spent about
                    a year with us over there. Spanish has gotten into his blood too. It has been
                    just an extraordinary experience. It is like something out of Gabriel Garcia
                    Marquez ...a family transported to the other side of the world. We had to get
                    plague shots to go there. Plague shots. That tells you it's not Atlantic City.
                    Where everybody got malaria. Where we advised relatives not to visit because it
                    was so expensive to get there and were afraid they would get sick. And yet it
                    turned out to be the most extraordinary experience that any of us have ever
                    had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to thank you very much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RUDDY: My pleasure. This took longer...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no, this is just perfect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
