<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000636">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Kenneth L. Kornher </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>United States Foreign Assistance Oral History Program Foreign Affairs Oral
                    History Collection Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</p>
                <p>An interview with Kenneth L. Kornher</p>
                <p>Interviewed by W. Haven North</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 4, 1998</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'll start off, Ken, by asking you to give us sort of an
                        overview, a thumbnail sketch of your association with foreign
                        assistance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: My career with the U.S. Agency for International Development extended
                    from 1963 to 1990. I came into the agency under the Federal Junior Management
                    Intern Program. I had been interested in the U.S. Information Agency because of
                    my academic work, but in retrospect, I'm delighted that I ended up working for
                    USAID. I think the scope of USAID's work is broader and more challenging, though
                    USIA is also an important instrument of foreign policy. I stayed with USAID
                    until 1990, when I retired. I have retained a strong interest in international
                    development in various consulting assignments since then.</p>
                <p>My work was predominantly with the central technical bureaus of the agency in the
                    field of development administration. We can later go into sub-sets of that
                    specialty. I greatly enjoyed the roles that I performed, in partnership with
                    many colleagues, to provide research and development, to develop ideas about how
                    field programs could be done better or in a more focused way. The tools and
                    techniques that would help with that, and then field service, direct links to
                    USAID missions and host country people, often through contractors or cooperative
                    agreements or grantees who would help to plan and set up field programs, and to
                    implement field programs. Those relationships extended to over fifty countries
                    over the course of the years that we'll be talking about.</p>
                <p>My career with USAID has been very satisfying. It has combined a lot of learning
                    with services that I believe were often useful to the missions and countries we
                    were working with.</p>
                <p>Early years and education</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We'll come back to all that and get it on the record.
                        Let's go back to your early years. Where did you grow up, where did you go
                        to school? What in all of that experience and time, and your early work
                        experience, led you to be interested in international affairs, international
                        development?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Okay. My origins were on a farm in south Idaho. My father was an
                    immigrant from Austria shortly before the First World War. My mother was also of
                    Germanic stock. She was born in Nebraska, and chose nursing as her career. Both
                    parents moved to Idaho and established our family in a small town called
                    Gooding. We lived on a small farm outside of town and had a family business
                    consisting of a meat market and grocery store. My father was a butcher and
                    sausage maker, a successful entrepreneur. I had three siblings, one brother and
                    two sisters, and we all went to school in Gooding. I went on to the University
                    of Idaho where I majored in education with a social sciences bent. I also was in
                    Air Force ROTC.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there anything in your college experience that had
                        international flavor to it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Not specifically, but I had been interested in international affairs
                    early in life. I was in my early teens during World War II, and most of the news
                    was about the war in Africa, Europe and the Pacific. In high school I got
                    interested in public policy matters. I remember writing a paper on the big dams
                    of the Tennessee Valley and the Columbia River basin, what the tradeoffs were
                    between flood control and electric power generation, and so on. Then I began to
                    apply similar interests to international affairs. But I would say that it was
                    really during and after my two years of Air Force active duty that I got more
                    specifically interested in international affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was after college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your military experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I spent two years under an ROTC obligation in the Air Force and learned
                    about military operations worldwide even though I was based in the United
                    States, primarily at Otis Air Force Base, Massachusetts. In the course of my
                    work at Otis, I took a pistol team to Washington, DC, which was my second visit
                    to Washington, actually. I was very taken with Washington as the site of the
                    national government, international connections, a lot of history and culture —
                    the place to be. But, in thinking back, my interest in international affairs
                    just gradually evolved in reading and personal interest. I decided after
                    finishing my active duty that I wanted to go to Georgetown and study
                    international relations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you hear about Georgetown?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>KORNHER: I looked into the programs of some of the preeminent east coast graduate
                    schools for international studies. The Fletcher School, Johns Hopkins
                    University, and Georgetown were interesting possibilities. I wanted to go to the
                    East Coast to extend my horizons. So, I applied to Georgetown and, fortunately,
                    got in. I arrived in Washington in January 1956.</p>
                <p>I began a Master's Degree in international relations and meanwhile did some
                    teaching in DC high schools.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you teaching?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I was teaching social studies. That is, history, government, and an
                    honors class in world problems.</p>
                <p>One of the things I learned in that class, just as a quick aside, was that U.S.
                    youngsters, at least at that time, and I'm fairly sure its still true, know very
                    little about geography. These were very smart and able students, but they had to
                    learn where England and France were. Almost literally. The only student I had
                    that was really topnotch in geography was a German student who had immigrated to
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Interesting. Was there a major in your graduate
                        course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. It was a broad international relations major, but my research
                    interests ran toward the place of the U.S. Information Agency and international
                    exchange programs in U.S. foreign policy. So, in both my masters' paper, and
                    then in my doctoral dissertation, I studied the record of USIA in the array of
                    foreign policy tools, and pored over congressional hearings and policy papers
                    and studies of what USIS was doing and should be doing. Of course, this was in
                    the middle of the Cold War era, and quite a bit of it was cast even in the
                    domain of psychological warfare. But I became convinced that the real value of
                    these programs was their long-term contribution to building mutual international
                    understanding and the basis for a world community of democratic nations.</p>
                <p>The educational exchange programs, I believe, have immense value if you take a
                    longer-term view. And that works both ways, both in exposing the participants
                    coming from abroad to people and institutions in United States, and exposing
                    people in the United States to the people, politics and culture of other
                    countries around the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you do your doctoral work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Also at Georgetown. I finished that on a part-time basis after joining
                    AID, completing it in 1969.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get into USAID ?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, I came into the international job market in 1962-63. I first
                    looked into positions with USIA, which turned out to be most interested in media
                    specialists or area specialists. They were not hiring people of more a general
                    or policy cast, such as I. So, I took the Junior Management Intern Exam and
                    turned to AID, which was hiring at that time, in 1962-'63. I got into the intern
                    program in the summer of 1963.</p>
                <p>Begins international work with USAID in 1993; the Brazil program in 1964</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your assignment then, when you started off? This
                        was just after USAID was founded, formed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. This was a very interesting time because the Kennedy administration
                    had just recast foreign assistance programs and merged technical assistance and
                    loan programs. Congress passed legislation creating AID in 1961. (The preference
                    for “USAID” as the official acronym came along many years later.) One important
                    emphasis was the Alliance for Progress which aspired to greatly benefit the
                    people and transform the economies of countries in Latin America and the
                    Caribbean. So there was quite a spirited and upbeat agenda for international
                    assistance at that time.</p>
                <p>During the first year, I rotated through various positions in AID under the
                    intern program. I worked on the Nepal Desk; and then in the Economics Office of
                    the Bureau for Program Policy and Coordination. I worked for Curt Farrar, who
                    later became Assistant Administrator of the Bureau for Technical Assistance. And
                    then I rotated into the Institutional Development Office of the Bureau for Latin
                    America which included a public administration division. I then ended up in a
                    permanent civil service position in the Bureau for Latin America, Office of
                    Brazilian Affairs. I was recruited by Gerry Gower, who had been an Intern in the
                    class of 1962.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>Let me just mention a little bit about the Brazil Program, because it was a big
                    and important one in the mid-to-late 1960s. There were some changes in Brazilian
                    politics going on in 1964, and a left-leaning regime under President Goulart
                    took office. There was quite a bit of anxiety in Washington about whether that
                    new government would lead Brazil in a more socialist direction, and into a more
                    friendly relationship with the Soviet Union. A nonviolent revolution took place
                    — organized by some of the Brazilian States and the military — that succeeded in
                    ousting Goulart. And then U.S. assistance really poured in. I think that program
                    was, for its time, comparable with USAID's Egypt program of the '80s and '90s. I
                    remember, for example, that we had 16 different university contracts operating
                    at one time. I had backstopping responsibility for several of them.</p>
                <p>I worked directly for Shep Hollander who reported to Willy Feuerline, the senior
                    AID officer, who reported to Ralph Burton, the Office Director. It was a joint
                    STATE-AID operation. Burton represented both State Department and AID interests.
                    His successor was Jack Kubisch, later Ambassador to Mexico, who also came from
                    the State Department side. Now the staff remained separate; it was called a
                    back-to-back arrangement, and that was characteristic of the Latin American
                    Bureau during that period. The Alliance for Progress structure was back-to-back,
                    with joint State Department and AID offices, and that was the only bureau of
                    State/AID that operated in that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find it worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think it worked rather well. It was highly visible because there were
                    a lot of political considerations, State Department, Congressional and White
                    House considerations, related to the Alliance for Progress; and to Brazilian and
                    other country resource allocations, including the new sector loans. Fortunately,
                    the Office of Brazilian Affairs and the “country team” in Brazil had really
                    outstanding senior leadership and a creative, hard-working technical staff for
                    the years I was there. Lincoln Gordon was Ambassador, and he had a broad,
                    expansive vision of what needed to be done, along with a collaborative
                    team-building style that worked well. For example, he exercised personal
                    leadership in getting Brazilian private family planning activities started. We
                    had several other senior people with great energy and talent in the field,
                    including Mission Director Stuart Van Dyke, and in Washington as well. One of
                    the latter was Sam Lewis, who later became Ambassador to Israel. Hollander was
                    excellent in his oversight of all of the operating details in a very large and
                    complex program. He was also ingenious at crafting answers to the difficult
                    questions posed every year by Congressman Otto Passman, the Chairman of the
                    House Appropriations Subcommittee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a sense that there was a heavy political hand
                        on the USAID programming, and what we could and couldn't do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>KORNHER: No. It was much more that anything that would be useful, that fit within
                    the broad agenda of the Alliance for Progress and was endorsed by the Brazilian
                    Government, could get funded. There was a lot of money flowing for the Alliance
                    Programs. Also, I found our senior people very open and balanced in their
                    judgments about program and technical matters, as well as the political side,
                    and so that helped. In the field there was strong technical leadership by people
                    like Ed Rizzo in public administration, Phil Schwab, Rosson Cardwell and Al
                    Lackey in education, and Dick Newberg in agriculture, among others.</p>
                <p>So the strong leadership helped to balance White House, State, and AID interests,
                    as well as Congressional, technical, and country interests. I would refer any
                    interested readers to the interview that you did with Stuart Van Dyke, who was
                    Mission Director in Rio de Janeiro, and doubtless recounted — I haven't read his
                    interview yet — but doubtless recounted what programs were like in Brazil during
                    that period.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since you were mostly concerned with the university
                        contracts, what was that arrangement and how do you think it worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think those were generally excellent and influential programs. Based
                    on their work in Brazil, I became a big fan of U.S. universities' contributions
                    to international development work. In the field of agriculture, four U.S.
                    universities worked with counterpart Brazilian universities. Purdue had a team
                    at Vicosa, Minas Gerais; Wisconsin was in Porto Alegre; Ohio State in
                    Piracicaba, and Arizona in the State of Ceara. Vanderbilt was working with the
                    economics faculty at the University of Sao Paulo. Michigan State had a team in
                    business administration at the Getulio Vargas Foundation in Rio de Janeiro.
                    There was an elementary education team from San Diego State at the University of
                    Minas Gerais. All of them were extremely well received by the Brazilians. I
                    heard that the Michigan State field team members were honored with an
                    all-expenses-paid reunion in Brazil on the 10th anniversary of the completion of
                    their project.</p>
                <p>Some of the efforts had significant and visible impact. For example, the
                    Brazilian State of Minas Gerais generated a primary education reform that
                    affected the way the system was organized and the way teachers were selected and
                    trained, books distributed, etc. The reform was strongly influenced and
                    supported by the team from San Diego State. That work set a pattern for
                    constructive changes in elementary education throughout the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A good example. So how long were you in this
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: For three years, until 1967.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your rotation was there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The three rotations as an Intern ended before I joined Brazilian
                    Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you joined the office in what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: That was 1964. So it was from 1964 to 1967 that I worked in the Bureau
                    for Latin America, Office of Brazilian Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, in those initial years, what was your impression of
                        AID as an agency? What was your sense of what you were into?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I was quite impressed with AID, not only because of the scope and
                    challenge of its programs, but also because of the innovative and able people
                    that had been attracted to the organization. I found the people I was working
                    with, a broad range of people, very committed to getting things done and to
                    improving technical approaches, to working closely with host country people and
                    institutions. I've never changed my mind about that. Some of them were extremely
                    knowledgeable about the application of their specialties to international work.
                    In the field of agriculture, Milo Cox in the AID Latin American Bureau's
                    Agriculture Office was an amazing expert in all dimensions of agriculture in
                    Latin America, and a great human being as well. When I needed to learn something
                    about high lysine corn I'd go down and talk to Milo, who would patiently explain
                    all I needed to know. In general, I think AID succeeded in building up an
                    excellent staff.</p>
                <p>But it's a challenging job when you step back and think about what the agency
                    aspires to do. The resources and time frames are clearly inadequate to the
                    aspirations. Then you have to move through a series of actors both within USAID
                    and the contractor or grantee, and then to “ownership” and effective
                    collaboration with the host country people, their views and priorities versus
                    the views of the Mission and Washington, and then hope that something gets done.
                    If it gets done and lasts beyond the project period, it is because the host
                    country people are really committed to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a sense of any particular development policy
                        or development strategy or ideology?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: At that time?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What guided what you did and didn't do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Well of course I was working at with the Alliance for Progress, which
                    had an extremely ambitious agenda of trying to build the basis for new kinds of
                    benefits for the people of Latin America and the Caribbean—notably including
                    education, nutrition and health benefits. And for improved public
                    administration, economic development, and agriculture, among other things. When
                    you mount a huge program of that kind it is difficult to tell how efficiently
                    the resources are being used. But I was quite impressed in Brazil, that even
                    though the programs were built up fast, I think most of them worked quite
                    well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Well, after your three years there then you moved
                        on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Assignment in new Development Administration Division - 1967</p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. I think a great deal of my career hinged on a phone call that I got
                    when I was working on the Brazil desk one afternoon in the summer of 1967. It
                    was a call from a fellow by the name of Jack Koteen. Now Jack had been involved
                    in public administration training and then moved over to the new Development
                    Administration Division in the Office of Program and Policy Coordination. He had
                    been asked to build up a staff in an area that was called development
                    administration. Jack told me that this program would have a kind of new look,
                    since public administration assistance had a mixed record. Many critics
                    considered the ongoing programs inadequate as a means to reform public sector
                    management and get development moving.</p>
                <p>There was a public administration division under Bill Lawson, which was quite
                    effective in working with field missions and the regional bureaus and providing
                    the field with information to support public administration programs. But Bill
                    was going out to head the Brazil program, and PPC was looking for a new
                    direction for the public administration programs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is public administration? What is the scope of the
                        program, what do you do in public administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KORNHER: We have, of course, some semantic issues around your question. Public
                    administration at that time was focusing largely on civil service reform,
                    personnel and training, national planning, tax administration, budgeting, census
                    projects, capital projects, and decentralization. It was often “tool oriented,”
                    assuming, for example, that better use of the tools of planning or budgeting, or
                    personnel management would improve public sector performance. It was much less
                    concerned with sector program management or with fostering private sector
                    growth, which came along later. The critics of public administration at that
                    time asked, “What is the relationship between public administration and
                    development? It's not very clear to us because in many circumstances preparing
                    national plans or training civil servants or writing better job descriptions
                    doesn't seem to get the development job done.” Of course, in fairness, there are
                    many systemic problems that developing countries faced and still face that
                    prevent civil servants from being effective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there was what do you call it, a sort of an
                        anti-bureaucratic tone slipping into views about public administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes., if you ask what development results you get from civil service
                    reform, it's not too obvious. So there was a gradual shift in AID's perspective
                    toward deciding which public services were most relevant to development purposes
                    (like agricultural research, schools, health services, road maintenance and
                    banking laws and regulation), and concentrating more on them. We were spending
                    comparatively too much assistance money on building up or trying to reform
                    bureaucracies, rather than focusing on key development functions of government
                    and asking how those functions could be better managed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were working with Jack Koteen in the reorientation
                        of this program under the new title of Development Management, was that
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: It was usually called Development Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Development Administration. Well, what was the difference?
                        What were you trying to bring about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I came to prefer “Development Management” because it implies a more
                    proactive role than “Administration.” But the official AID name was “Development
                    Administration.” A simple definition would be the judicious choice and use of
                    means to get development results. It includes both public sector and private
                    sector roles, and the interactions between them.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>The years from 1967-1971 when the development administration programs got started
                    were an exciting period, a period of considerable learning and serious work on
                    strategy. I credit Jack Koteen with laying the basis for work that went on for
                    25 years afterward, much of which we can talk about later. When the Bureau for
                    Technical Assistance was created in 1969 Bill Siffin, a professor at Indiana
                    University was brought in by the new Assistant Administrator, Joel Bernstein, to
                    head up the Office of Development Administration. Bill was an expert on
                    institutional development and a keen student of the strengths and weaknesses of
                    public administration as a discipline, and its applications in developing
                    countries. Koteen was Deputy, but they worked closely together, and Siffin
                    contributed to and supported virtually all of the ideas we had been advancing.
                    When Siffin went back to Indiana in 1971 Koteen became Director. Siffin
                    continued to play an important role in institutional development research and
                    helped broaden it from the organizational perspective to include systems and
                    cultural perspectives.</p>
                <p>I might just recount the themes that we developed from 1967 to 1971. In the first
                    couple of years we did quite a bit of something you rarely have an opportunity
                    to do in the Federal Service. We did some serious mapping of promising
                    innovations, and laid out long-term technical strategies likely to have high
                    payoff. We studied and discussed the strengths and weaknesses of ongoing public
                    administration programs with people from the field, the regional bureaus, the
                    World Bank, the United Nations, and the universities. We talked with colleagues
                    in the Technical Assistance Methodology Division. We brought in consultants and
                    experts, one of whom I remember was a systems theorist. Others were experts in
                    public administration, planning, budgeting, and capital projects. We also talked
                    a great deal with sector people, agricultural people, health and family planning
                    people, and asked, “What are your program management problems, and what kinds of
                    approaches are needed to make your programs work better?” Ed Rizzo was a budget
                    and public administration expert who took a good deal of interest in health and
                    family planning programs. David Jickling was a public administration and local
                    government specialist. We talked extensively with Don Fiester, an agriculture
                    and coffee expert with much field experience in Latin America, and with Milo
                    Cox, whom I mentioned earlier. Later, Gerry Horne, an agriculture specialist,
                    joined our staff.So, exploration of sector management needs, particularly in
                    agriculture, was one emphasis.</p>
                <p>Another theme was implementation of government plans. In the 1960s government
                    planning was very popular in developing countries, and consumed a lot of time
                    and effort. But too many of the plans were nicely written, overly optimistic
                    shelf documents that seldom got connected to resource allocations or to
                    provision of specific government services. We worked with Al Waterston, who had
                    done a book on development planning for the World Bank, to try to define
                    remedies.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>These questions about the difference between public administration and
                    development administration were also being debated in academe, by members of the
                    American Society for Public Administration and ASPA's “Comparative
                    Administration Group” which had a Ford Foundation Grant. Also, a little later,
                    by members of the Midwest Universities Consortium for International Activities.
                    Bill Siffin at Indiana, Milton Esman at Pittsburgh (later at Cornell), Jack
                    Montgomery at Harvard, Frank Sherwood at the University of Southern California
                    (later Florida State), and Norman Uphoff at Cornell were among those thinking
                    and writing extensively about the question. In 1969 Esman and Montgomery
                    completed an influential paper commissioned by Koteen and published in the
                    Public Administration Review, “Systems Approaches to Technical Cooperation: The
                    Role of Development Administration.”</p>
                <p>On the business management side, H. Igor Ansoff was one of the first proponents
                    of strategic management in the early 1970s. He became Dean of the business
                    school at Vanderbilt University, which was working not only on strategic
                    management, but also on a range of other business management innovations like
                    organization development and team building. One important idea evolving at
                    Vanderbilt was the need for business and government to adapt to fast-changing
                    technology. This insight was prescient. If you think of the changes over the
                    past 30 years—the influence of production technologies in agriculture and
                    industry, health technology, certainly information and communication technology
                    — successful public management and business enterprise demand understanding and
                    effective use of these new technologies.</p>
                <p>Ray Goldberg at Harvard became well known in business management circles for his
                    work on agribusiness. He used the idea of “commodity action systems” as the
                    linchpin of his writing and consulting in agribusiness and export promotion. It
                    had the advantage of being very practical and easy to convert into operational
                    advice.</p>
                <p>Art Mosher's little book, Getting Agriculture Moving (1966), was a classic
                    contribution to sound thinking about agriculture as a sector and a system, as
                    well as a model of clear writing. Our approach to systems thinking and sectoral
                    management was greatly influenced by it.</p>
                <p>Another set of less sharply focused, but important questions centered on how to
                    improve grass-roots participation in development and the capability of local
                    action groups, for example, small farm families producing similar crops, or
                    local governments providing responsive services. Means to involve the people who
                    must put their labor and other resources together to provide key local services
                    and get local development moving. That set of questions and responses extended
                    later to private enterprise and public-private collaboration.</p>
                <p>AID was experimenting with large sector and reform loans at that time. We tried
                    to find out whether or not those loans were succeeding, and how improved
                    analysis and management might made them work better. These examples illustrate
                    some of the important ideas that were developed during the period of the late
                    '60s and early '70s.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't you describe this document, at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I actually have three documents. The first is a six-page memorandum
                    published in 1970 called Key Problems in Development Administration in the Low
                    Income Countries: An Agenda for Action by the A.I.D. Bureau for Technical
                    Assistance. It laid out four “key problems” we thought could and should be on
                    the agenda of the new Office of Development Administration. The first two were
                    designated for “priority attention.” They were: (1) The lack of managerial
                    capacity to meet programmatic needs, particularly in agriculture, health, and
                    family planning, at national, regional, and local levels. (2) The lack of
                    capacity for local action, particularly institutionalized delivery systems
                    involving public service structures to meet sector concerns.” The second two
                    “Key Problems” found to be of “considerable importance” were (3) The inadequacy
                    of project management, and (4) The need for improvement of key development
                    institutions: Institution Building.</p>
                <p>The Key Problem memorandum was accompanied by the second document — a Staff Paper
                    — also called Key Problems in Development Administration. It discussed the four
                    key problems along with other problems found significant in the course of our
                    staff work.</p>
                <p>A third document issued in 1973, after the Office of Development Administration
                    had launched its first four projects, was called Interregional Programs in
                    Development Administration. This document is of course more action-oriented,
                    since we had begun contract work and field work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Maybe we can capture some of these documents as annexes.
                        These were documents you worked on as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your role in most of these documents?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I made inputs in the institutional development problem area, because
                    Jack had assigned me to take the lead on looking into what was going on in
                    academic studies and research and Agency thinking about institutional
                    development. Also, I brought in some experience from the Latin American
                    programs, and helped with writing, packaging and editing. Ed Rizzo and David
                    Jickling were major contributors to the key problem paper and staff paper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, at that point in time what were the characteristics
                        of development administration that contrasted with public administration?
                        What was different?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>KORNHER: What were we trying to do that was different? I think one very important
                    difference was emphasis on development sectors and systems of action. Public
                    service delivery usually implies a functional responsibility. For example,
                    government agricultural programs often include research, extension, education,
                    irrigation, land titling, and facilitating the delivery of inputs. The private
                    sector usually handles input distribution, production, on-farm functions,
                    quality control, transport and marketing. You learn a good deal about how to
                    manage successful development work by disaggregating development into sectors,
                    and then asking what the public and private roles and management requirements
                    are. The same thing works for health, family planning, education, or
                    transportation. Our early programs targeted agricultural plan implementation,
                    agribusiness, and then health and family planning. These efforts laid the basis
                    for a great deal of important work later on. We considered both public and
                    private sector roles in all the sectors, and what the interfaces should be. So I
                    would say that one of the things that was new was sector management and systems
                    of action within sectors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: A second one was seeing projects in developing countries as vehicles for
                    producing development results over extended time periods. (This was later called
                    “sustainability.”) Projects are privileged particles of development that can
                    deliver lot of resources in a short period of time. The World Bank at that time
                    emphasized technical analysis, project finance and economics as the main points
                    of project development—all important, but incomplete. Projects work pretty well
                    when it comes to creating infrastructure: building bridges, roads, ports,
                    storage facilities or other physical assets. These are very appropriate objects
                    of a project form of management. But the more we studied developing country
                    projects, the more we realized that functions and services to support and
                    sustain their flows of benefits and to involve stakeholders weren't usually
                    built into project design. Projects are temporary, they are enterprises that
                    last one year, four years, whatever, but then end. Yet project payoffs unfold
                    over time, and there must be other organization and management structures built
                    up to help assure such continuing payoffs.</p>
                <p>One valuable resources for project work that we got started in about 1974 and
                    supported for 15 years was the Development Project Management Center (DPMC) in
                    USDA. The Center was led by Morris Solomon, and had a very strong staff. An
                    offshoot was the International Development Management Center at the University
                    of Maryland led by Marcus Ingle.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>We and DPMC worked on projects as such at first. But we soon began to link
                    projects to private sector capabilities, to team training, to accountability
                    needs, and to public sector program management. It's one thing to finance and
                    build an agricultural storage facility. That might be a private sector or a
                    combined public-private effort. But who is going to run the storage facility
                    afterwards, who is going to maintain it, where will the money come from for
                    those continuing functions, and is the enterprise going to produce a continuing
                    stream of benefits commensurate with the investment? The initial infrastructure
                    investment is not enough. The most common failures in road projects and many
                    construction projects in developing countries are failures to maintain. So it
                    increases payoffs if projects are treated more like long term development
                    ventures with benefits continuing well beyond the project period. Later on, this
                    wider perspective led us to change DPMC's name to “Development Program
                    Management Center.” I think that the emphasis on projects and programs as
                    instruments of effective development was a change that went well beyond
                    conventional ideas about public administration.</p>
                <p>And then, local action and participation. Helping create forms of organization
                    that can successfully involve people at the grassroots, in the villages or on
                    the farms, in mobilizing resources, starting development ventures, getting
                    needed inputs and services, and aggregating products for larger markets. This
                    program area began in about 1972, led by Jerry French and Keith Sherper.</p>
                <p>The agency made a major effort in community development from about 1950 to 1965,
                    and in the “New Directions” emphasis on benefits for the poor and rural
                    development participation from about 1974 to 1981. Sad to say, the conclusion at
                    the end of both periods was that there were no “quick fixes” for bringing poor
                    people into the mainstream of development, and that grassroots organizing hadn't
                    worked very well. And the grass-roots organizing, certainly in the rural
                    development participation era, was too often turned to political rather than
                    development purposes.</p>
                <p>Perhaps Tanzania is the classic example. Though it was not a heavy-handed
                    autocratic regime, the central government — using centrally administered
                    socialist ideas — got its fingers into the organization of every village. It
                    controlled the resources flowing to the villages mostly through public agencies
                    and foreign NGOs. The Government's purposes were much more political than
                    developmental. It didn't work. In fact, the whole era of rural development
                    participation from about 1974 to 1981 produced disappointing results, and the
                    effort was abandoned.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>But the questions about local action and the processes of participation endured.
                    What kinds of grassroots participation are important to development and
                    democracy? How should developing countries organize such participation? The
                    Office of Development Administration and its successors worked very hard to
                    understand how local action and participation could be advanced by donor
                    assistance. Much of the work was under a succession of contracts with
                    Development Alternatives, Inc. and Cornell University.You can see some of the
                    better answers that emerged in USAID's current support for more autonomous local
                    governments and systems of justice, microenterprises, small business
                    development, and local organizations of civil society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why don't we come back to that toward the end? Was there
                        another dimension to the development organization concept? You mentioned you
                        were working on the institution building part of this. What does that mean;
                        what do you mean by that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Okay. If you look at “institutional development,” in USAID's history,
                    you find two related, but different, sets of ideas and activities. The first,
                    and easiest to grasp, arose from the organizational sciences during the 1960s.
                    The underlying question is what are the conditions under which an organization
                    becomes successful, provides benefits to the people who are involved with it,
                    and can endure and become valued in a given social setting? Milton Esman, who
                    was originally at Pittsburgh and later at Cornell, was one of the leading
                    figures in academic work on institutional development from that point of view.
                    Many others made important contributions. By the early '70s, the ideas had been
                    well documented and tested on field projects. One convenient summary with many
                    references is called Institution Building: a Source Book. It was written by Mel
                    Blase in 1973 and updated in 1984. The source book contains excerpts and
                    references from many people writing on the subject at the time, along with handy
                    dandy checklists, that is, lists of important factors that field analysts can
                    use to tag specific dimensions of organizational effectiveness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you understand it to be, in the light of this
                        interest in development administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Institution Building — the organizational point of view, is practical
                    and useful, because most of USAID's work is with country organizations or
                    networks of organizations, both private and governmental. Of course, at the
                    outset a judgment needs to be made about whether an organization will work
                    better as a private entity (profit or not-for profit), or a public entity. Much
                    of the institution building work dealt with governmental organizations, and
                    there was a tendency to gloss over the question of whether an organization
                    dealing with economic markets would ever work efficiently under government
                    auspices. I remember one agricultural advisor in the Technical Assistance Bureau
                    in the early '70s who argued that AID support for government seed farms and seed
                    sales was misplaced, because they should be private. He was right. This kind of
                    bias was largely corrected in later years.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>Institutional development work from an organizational perspective moved gradually
                    toward concern for networks of organizations. Field research by Cornell
                    University and Development Alternatives, Inc. in the mid 1970s pointed to the
                    need for systems or networks of local organizations and also to the link between
                    successful organizations and tangible contributions by small farm families.</p>
                <p>Any organizational focus takes a lot for granted about the “rules of the larger
                    game” in the setting where an organization is trying to get things done. Think
                    of the frustrations of trying to run successful organizations in Nigeria or
                    Haiti over the last 30 years. By 1980, partly because of increasing field
                    research using political economy and new institutional economics, institutional
                    development came to be defined more often in terms of the rules of the larger
                    game and the structures of incentives that explain why individuals and
                    organizations behave as they do.</p>
                <p>This second approach to analysis and prescription for institutional development
                    emerged in development studies in the 1980s. The new approach included attention
                    to formal rules - the constitution, laws and regulations - and to informal
                    rules. It also emphasized institutional economics - incentives, transactions,
                    and “rent seeking.” This new line of thinking linked readily to issues of
                    sectoral reform, policy reform and even constitutional reform needed to improve
                    constructive rules and incentives. The approach is interdisciplinary; it draws
                    on political economy, the new institutional economics, and public choice theory,
                    as well as public finance economics, political science, anthropology, sectoral
                    knowledge, and other more traditional development disciplines.</p>
                <p>You can bring this broad perspective down to earth some by thinking about the
                    rules that govern market transactions or government service delivery in a
                    particular country, about appropriate governmental and nongovernmental roles and
                    functions, about interest group politics and individual self-interest, “rent
                    seeking,” political payoffs, about property rights and other rules of the game
                    affecting economic or service sectors, and about means of governance (including
                    land use markets and policy, and corporate governance) that work well or not so
                    well. When we get to the 1980s in our discussion I can talk a bit more about the
                    use of this broader institutional development perspective as applied to
                    decentralization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And this was integrated into the concept of development
                        administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. Lots of folks claimed the new kind of institutional analysis in the
                    late 1980s. The agency's economists, private sector people, policy reform
                    people, some sector people, and development administration people. That was
                    okay, because the reform agenda was a legitimate concern of all those groups,
                    and new money was mobilized by various offices to address an important problem
                    area. Two of our projects that were relevant came along in the late 1980s; one
                    was Decentralization, Finance and Management, and the other was Implementing
                    Policy Change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well let's come back to that in a minute. What was the
                        reception to the program idea of development administration in the agency
                        when you launched it in, what, 1970? What year was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Office of Development Administration in the Technical Assistance Bureau</p>
                <p>KORNHER: The Office of Development Administration was created in the Technical
                    Assistance Bureau in 1969. So that's a good time marker. By the mid 1970s the
                    sector management and systems ideas were accepted and having an important impact
                    on agricultural, health, and family planning programs. The local action and
                    participation ideas waxed and waned, but in general endured as a part of the
                    agency's agenda. The strategic management, and project and program management
                    ideas have been widely accepted. The integration of private and public sector
                    perspectives gained momentum and flourished in the 1980s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But when you launched this program, this concept, did you
                        get substantial resources to do something with it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: We got money for a staff of reasonable size, for new projects, and
                    usually for follow-on projects. The projects we started in this period were the
                    following: studies and dissemination in institutional development, agricultural
                    management, agribusiness management, and managing small farmer development. A
                    project called Modernizing Management, which began with an attempt to inventory
                    and understand promising business management approaches and techniques, was
                    revised to focus on project management. A second generation of projects included
                    health management, rural development participation, project management (evolving
                    to extensive work on public program management and reform), management training,
                    local revenue, agricultural marketing, organization and administration of
                    integrated rural development, decentralization, and implementing policy
                    change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a very substantial portfolio then?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>KORNHER: It was, but I'm describing a progression of projects that lasted from
                    about 1971 to 1990, so it was nearly 20 years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did these projects work? How were they used?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: May I also add this? My staying in a central bureau role working on
                    development administration over a period of 23 years helped produce continuity
                    and a succession of projects in this field. Its a classic example of what David
                    Korten and others call “learning process approach.” I worked with people in the
                    regional bureaus and missions, learned about field needs, and sold projects and
                    ideas to a succession of office directors: Bill Siffin, Jack Koteen, Nick Luykx,
                    Harlan Hobgood, Jerry French, Chris Russell, Eric Chetwynd. But all of them
                    welcomed the continuance of development administration projects that built on
                    field experience responsive to host country needs and agency priorities.
                    Projects based on solid research and development, testing of field relevance,
                    and refinement of “wholesale” field service mechanisms require long periods of
                    time. We were able to work in those longer time frames. So there was a stream of
                    projects that moved, for example, from modernizing management to project
                    management to public program management, to policy reform studies and to
                    implementing policy change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there a core behind all of these? What was the
                        difference between modern management and project management?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The modern management project and the project/program management work
                    were both dealing with strategies, approaches and techniques of management and
                    with means to achieve management improvement for governments and businesses. But
                    the key was to deal with intermediate level systems of action, not the smaller
                    tools like writing position descriptions that Bill Siffin had tagged as a
                    weakness of the old public administration programs. The Modernizing Management
                    project with Vanderbilt University began in about 1971. It was an attempt to
                    inventory and evaluate the ideas and approaches to effective management that the
                    Vanderbilt business school—H. Igor Ansoff and his faculty — were teaching at
                    that time. It was a business school, but with a strong concern for public
                    management. It was there in part that we learned how important it is that
                    business management be linked to technological change. Ray Radosevich, the
                    leader of the contract team working under our project, was also working with the
                    University of San Paulo, helping Brazilians decide what technological changes
                    were important to their business enterprises and public enterprises. We also
                    looked into things like organizational development.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which means?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Organizational development is a means by which a business or public
                    entity can mobilize external facilitators and inside leaders to decide what
                    changes in its way of doing business, and in its management structures and
                    processes, are needed to improve its effectiveness and efficiency. It includes
                    building consensus and commitment to implement the needed changes. It includes
                    team-building. It was originally quite behaviorally oriented, but has evolved to
                    include both “hard” changes like finance and choice of technology, and “soft”
                    changes like decision making, hierarchy, and quality of work life. One of the
                    important discoveries of organizational development that has been picked up by
                    USAID was that people can often work more effectively in teams, combining
                    talents and resources to get results.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Well, was this evolution, you said, in the context
                        of the other projects you were talking about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Let's come back to the specific projects in our next interview. But I
                    wanted to mention some of the other ideas that we were working with. I've
                    already mentioned organizational development technology. Sector management,
                    we've covered that, as well. Systems approaches. The latter may seem abstract in
                    theory, but its easy to illustrate in the real world. If you have a budget
                    system, but your accounting system doesn't tell you how much you've spent for
                    nine months after you've spent it, you don't have timely data to feed back into
                    your budget controls. That's a systems problem. The World Bank, went down to
                    Jamaica - I believe it was in the early '80s - to try to help Jamaica improve
                    its budget. But the Jamaicans didn't have timely data on what had been spent. So
                    they found very quickly that they had to improve the accounting system, along
                    with the budget system.</p>
                <p>Let me mention a little bit about strategic management, which was another thing
                    we looked into at Vanderbilt that has become very popular in business and public
                    management in recent years. I think most readers of this interview will know
                    something about strategic management, because of its wide use and the publicity
                    that it has gotten. I prefer the term “strategic management.” In the earlier
                    days it was often known as strategic planning, but strategic management is
                    better because it reminds us that we have to carry out what we plan.</p>
                <p>I remember an address given by Peter Drucker, before the American Society for
                    Public Administration, here in Washington back in about 1969. Peter Drucker is
                    one of the gurus of business management who has written about 10 influential
                    books. Someone from the audience asked him a question, saying, “Well, Mr.
                    Drucker, what can be more important than sound planning, because if you don't
                    know what your objectives are and where you are going, you can't get there.” And
                    Drucker said, “Only one thing is more important: carrying out your plan.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right, right.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>KORNHER: So, Igor Ansoff emphasized that you must not only understand the
                    environment in which your business is operating, define the business niche that
                    you are in, choose technology that is not obsolescent, and select operating
                    processes that enhance productivity, but also carry out the necessary changes to
                    get the correct “fit” between your business and all the success factors in your
                    outside environment and inside your business in order to assure profitability.
                    Anyway, that view of strategic management was built into this early work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is a fairly complex and comprehensive perspective on
                        what you mean by development administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, it is complex because you have to deal with both strategic and
                    tactical factors. You have to deal with short-term and longer term decision
                    making and implementation, with public and private management and their
                    different underlying values and assumptions, and with factors in the larger
                    environment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this period, what are some examples of how this
                        strategy and this concept of developmental administration were introduced
                        into the agency and how was it made use of during that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, again, I think that sector management provide a good illustration.
                    Sectoral team building within the agency was important. In agriculture we were
                    working with the best thinkers and field operators in the agency. People like
                    Gerry Horne, Don Fiester and Milo Cox, among others, and these people in turn
                    had substantial influence on how agricultural programs were being designed and
                    implemented out in the field. In 1973 Ed Rizzo developed strong links to the
                    Health Office, including its Director, Dr. Lee Howard, which later led to a
                    health management project in our office working closely with the Health Office
                    and various missions. Following his retirement in 1974 Ed also worked
                    extensively in consulting and contract roles with the Population Office. The
                    sectoral people were very open to use of our ideas, and we were equally open to
                    using their ideas based on their sectoral field experience.</p>
                <p>Milo Cox, for example, was telling Joel Bernstein, the first head of the Bureau
                    for Technical Assistance, that agricultural marketing should play a key role in
                    AID's programs. We knew he was right, and tried to help him make the case. But
                    it took some time for the agency to pay very much attention to agricultural
                    marketing in addition to its traditional emphasis on production. It probably
                    happened faster because of the interactions that were going on between various
                    people and offices in the agency. Incidentally, we later picked up the banner of
                    agricultural marketing ourselves. Tom Mehen in my division managed our
                    agricultural marketing project through the 1980s—a very successful and popular
                    project with a lot of field buy-ins.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ...and in development administration. What happened to
                        your own situation? You were in the civil service, and this was early on in
                        your career. What was your role in all this, what evolved over this time in
                        terms of your position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I was personally responsible for institutional development and
                    management improvement efforts, then project management. Let me just mention
                    some of the people who were involved in the team effort, and I will leave out
                    others, unfortunately. I mentioned Jack KoteeGerry Horne was a specialist in
                    agriculture, Ed Rizzo, who was a specialist in budgeting and public
                    administration programs was responsible for links to population and health
                    programs. Jerry French joined us in about 1972 after the Office became a part of
                    the new Technical Assistance Bureau. He transferred from the Title IX Office
                    which was concerned with political development; and Keith Sherper came, I
                    believe, from the same office. Keith had a background in agriculture and rural
                    development with field experience in Asia. And I've left out several others who
                    made important contributions, but we created a staff that was interacting with
                    each other and learning from each other and helping to build these projects and
                    programs that we got started by the early '70s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you introduce these approaches and concepts to the
                        field so they could get built into the Mission's programming?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I have to say that we learned to do this over time. And we made
                    mistakes. In the early 1970s we first started working with regional training and
                    research centers and a few national centers.</p>
                <p>We learned that some of these regional centers were not as strong nor as well
                    connected as we thought they were. There was a relationship problem because most
                    of the regional organizations were not directly linked with government policy
                    and programs, nor with business enterprises, and not necessarily with USAID
                    missions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember which centers these were?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, I remember most of them. They included the Getulio Vargas
                    Foundation in Rio de Janeiro, the Pan African Institute for Development in
                    Cameroon, the African Center for Training and Research in Development
                    Administration in Morocco, the Inter American Institute for Agricultural
                    Sciences in Costa Rica, the Central American Institute of Business
                    Administration in Nicaragua, and the Southeast Asian Regional Center for
                    Graduate Study and Research in Agriculture in the Philippines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the purpose of this was to help them?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, to try to create a multiplier effect by introducing these project
                    systems approaches and methods that had been developed by Vanderbilt and later
                    our Development Project Management Center in USDA, and the agricultural
                    implementation and agribusiness ideas that had been developed by Governmental
                    Affairs Institute and Harvard University.</p>
                <p>I came later to believe that this was, while not a bad idea, not as efficient as
                    working with national programs. In some cases, it worked fairly well. For
                    example, the Pan African Institute for Development (PAID) in Yaounde, Cameroon
                    built some useful capabilities. Unfortunately, the Deputy of PAID got put in
                    jail for a while for speaking out against some policies of the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did these regional centers work with national programs, or
                        not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Sometimes; for example, they trained people from national programs. But
                    the linkage was but not as close as would have been desirable. If you're dealing
                    with the Ministry of Agriculture in Botswana, you know you are dealing with an
                    organization that commands some continuing budget resources, has responsibility
                    for improving agriculture in that country, and so on. Whereas if you are dealing
                    with the Inter-American Institute for Agricultural Sciences, it doesn't command
                    resources from a national budget, and is at least one step removed from the
                    action of ministries or agricultural enterprises. So later we moved most of our
                    links from regional institutions to USAID Mission projects that were working
                    with the ministries or the ag marketing enterprises or the local governments,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>I don't wish to denigrate the work of some of these regional institutions. The
                    Vargas Foundation has an excellent reputation, as did the Central American
                    Institute of Business Administration, among other institutions we were working
                    with. The Pan African Institute for Development had a good program. I was out
                    there two or three times to see it first hand. But being one step removed from
                    the national action was not as good as working with country programs or
                    institutions via AID projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any of these national programs stand out in your
                        mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>KORNHER: As a generalization, government training institutions or management
                    support institutions were a disaster. There were exceptions. In Egypt for a
                    time, when they got really first rate leadership at one of the national
                    management institutes, it took off and did really good things, had an influence
                    on Sadat's programs, and so on. But, then, unfortunately, the leader of that
                    program had a heart attack and died and the center withered again. But most of
                    the national management institutes, government run, became dumping grounds for
                    bureaucrats that were kind of “on the shelf” for one reason or another. They did
                    not have a sufficient action orientation, they used lecture methods, and they
                    focused on the law rather than management, things like that. Most of them just
                    didn't work very well.</p>
                <p>There may be a resource threshold problem as well. I think management support
                    institutions in Europe and in the United States work in part because they have
                    enough money to hire full-time, able professionals, who have the incentives and
                    commitment to provide the assistance, and also have a strong client orientation.
                    No doubt, countries in intermediary stages of development move toward that,
                    countries like Korea and Thailand. Thailand's Institute of Development
                    Administration was better than most.</p>
                <p>So we gradually turned to more direct work with the field missions and to joint
                    funding of field activities. We used both contract and grant intermediaries to
                    work hand-in-glove with Mission and host country people on project development,
                    studies, evaluation, design, training and implementation. And that had a much
                    broader effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any Mission or set of Missions which seemed to
                        pick these up fairly quickly; do you recall of any you were involved
                        with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, but since there were other project officers, there were more early
                    field relationships than I will remember. Early field links of the local action
                    work included Kenya, Lesotho, Bolivia, Peru and Paraguay, and later the
                    Philippines and Sri Lanka. Central American Missions including Costa Rica, plus
                    the Kenya and Philippine Missions, were interested in the agribusiness work.
                    Cameroon, which was supporting some activities of the Pan African Institute for
                    Development, was one of our project management sites, and we worked closely
                    together. I remember some ag sector work in Ghana; I believe you were the
                    Director there in the late '70s when I was helping design the renewal of an
                    agricultural extension project. I worked on the redesign team and the people in
                    the Mission were very receptive to making adjustments in that project.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>We went out to Brong Ahafo and asked the extension agents located in that
                    regional center what they did about extension to the small farms away from the
                    city. They said, “we go out and provide advice and services to small farm
                    families. Then we sent our vouchers to Accra, and it took a long time to get any
                    money back for the trips we took. When we do get money back it was only after
                    they sent back the voucher saying explain this, explain that, we disallow this,
                    we disallow that.” It was a small example of how bureaucratic procedures get in
                    the way of doing a development job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well wasn't that a function of public administration
                        reform, to try to make that work? Or did it perhaps just make it more
                        cumbersome?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: From one point of view it was encouraging that there was some financial
                    oversight, but the delays and disallowances created disincentives for the
                    extension agents. Part of the problem was doubtless a shortage of money to
                    properly fund extension. I sometimes wondered if agricultural extension services
                    are worth their cost in the poorer countries. If ag research finds means to
                    increase production significantly, farmers usually find out soon enough. Ghana,
                    like most of the countries we worked with, had little money for agricultural
                    extension or any other services. The more I learned about most countries'
                    resource constraints and low salaries, the more I cringed when yet another donor
                    team came in and said, “Why don't you expand your staff by four or five
                    people?”</p>
                <p>Your training team in Ghana was also doing a fine job of getting out into the
                    small towns and rural areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We had a development administration specialist on the
                        staff there. Did you have development administration direct hire staff in
                        other Missions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, there were public and development administration staff in the
                    regional bureaus and in many missions through the 1960s and much of '70s. There
                    were large-scale public administration programs in a number of countries. Turkey
                    had an ambitious program led by Tom Thorsen. Korea and the Philippines had large
                    programs. In Vietnam there were literally hundreds of public administration
                    advisors as the program built up in the late 1960s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Iran, I think, had a big program, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, it did. Brazil - Ed Rizzo led the buildup of budgeting, revenue,
                    statistical and municipal development programs in the late 1960s. In many
                    countries similar emphases, along with civil service training and reform
                    efforts, were under way. Dave Jickling was involved in sizable programs in
                    Bolivia and other Latin American countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>In the 1970s, in most countries other than Vietnam, the public administration
                    projects began a gradual decline. One or two programs, like Egypt, grew larger.
                    And public administration projects of various kinds persisted. AID's legislation
                    specifically cited public administration as an area for continuing assistance.
                    AID Administrators reaffirmed the value of many of these programs in 1974 and in
                    a 1977 Policy Determination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there building, also, of institutions for training
                        civil servants?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: There were many training institutes around the world. Only a few of the
                    government personnel training units were very effective. I came to believe that
                    it would usually be better to contract-out government training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were they declining because the job was largely done, or
                        did people just lose interest?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: It was not that the job was done. The need for personnel training in
                    government and business is continuous. The life-long learning idea. Today, for
                    example, businesses and governments need to be doing a lot of training to keep
                    people up to speed on the information revolution. The institutes were sometimes
                    ineffective because they were dumping grounds for tired old bureaucrats who were
                    not professionally well qualified nor strongly committed to a dynamic,
                    pro-active, no-nonsense training function. Even those institutes that had
                    leadership were perennially short of money, and much of the money they had was
                    spent maintaining buildings and grounds rather than for training. Donor money
                    was put to good use in some cases, but that was not a long-term solution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the office you were in, how big a staff did you
                        have, and where was your position in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I was originally a project officer in the Development Administration
                    Division of PPC from 1967-69. The Division had about six people, including a
                    field information specialist (Carol Piper, succeeded by Dimetra Crassas) and a
                    secretary (Beatrice Graham). I had responsibility at first for institutional
                    development, management improvement and project management work.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>After President Nixon took office in 1969 the Bureau for Technical Assistance was
                    created and picked up the technical functions that had been in PPC. Our Division
                    was upgraded to become the Office of Development Administration with Bill Siffin
                    as Director for the first two years and Jack Koteen as Deputy. Koteen became
                    Director when Siffin returned to Indiana. Ed Rizzo left on a special assignment
                    for the Office of Management and Budget from 1970 to 1973, and then returned as
                    Koteen's Deputy. We recruited Jerry French and Keith Sherper to manage the local
                    action effort, and started up four new projects by 1973. But we suffered serious
                    staff lossewith the departure of Jickling for a field assignment, and the
                    retirement in 1974 of Horne, Rizzo and Koteen in quick succession. Jerry French
                    became Acting Director.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the Office of Development Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Right. The work we had been doing aroused considerable interest in some
                    parts of the agency, and Jack Koteen was a good salesman. Curt Farrar, the
                    Assistant Administrator of the Technical Assistance Bureau who had succeeded
                    Joel Bernstein, asked for a Work Group to find out whether there was growing
                    acceptance for the new ideas and approaches, and if so, how these programs might
                    be expanded and used in other parts of the agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: This was 1974, just after Koteen retired. The chairman of the Work Group
                    was the former Director General of the Foreign Service, Ambassador Bill Hall. In
                    addition to trying to keep a couple of projects going, I was Staff Director of
                    that group. I felt a bit frustrated, because the work in Washington inevitably
                    delayed project field work which I thought was of equal or perhaps greater
                    importance.</p>
                <p>I worked closely with Ambassador Hall and some senior members of the Work Group
                    to lay out the justification for an expanded program. There were quite a few
                    people who accepted these new ideas and quite a few who felt it was just a new
                    face on the old-style public administration programs. So the results of the Work
                    Group effort were officially supportive, but really inconclusive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it didn't lead to any change?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Not major changes. We were able to maintain a small staff, implement the
                    projects in the portfolio, and gradually increase field linkages. Sectoral
                    management approaches took hold in agriculture, family planning and health. And
                    we got a supportive policy determination in 1977. But there was no strong
                    reaction across the agency that development administration was the wave of the
                    future.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, then, what happened to the office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Jerry French left for a field assignment. If I recall correctly he went
                    to Tanzania as Mission Director. I became Acting Director for a year starting in
                    1976. Curt Farrar began a search for a new Office Director and came up with
                    Nicholas Luykx, who had been at the East-West Center. So Nick came in 1977. He
                    had a mandate for leadership, but didn't get additional resources. Nick stayed
                    in that position for a couple of years and then moved on to the Nutrition
                    Office.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he add any particular dimension to it
                        substantively?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Asian experience, which was helpful. And he embraced and was a good
                    representative of the ideas that we were trying to advance. He was very
                    interested in and supportive of the agribusiness project, and led a conference
                    at which Ray Goldberg and associates presented Harvard's end-of-project
                    findings. But Nick also was busy learning about AID, and as you can imagine that
                    took a period of time. So he basically was very supportive of the ongoing
                    programs, but did not attempt to introduce major changes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, he left, and then what happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Office mergers; becomes Chief, Development Administration Division, 1983</p>
                <p>KORNHER: Then we had a succession of career Office Directors through the '80s and
                    '90s. they were Harlan Hobgood, Jerry French, Chris Russell, and Eric Chetwynd.
                    All of these people were very experienced and kept our programs visible and
                    funded, even as resources declined and we came to rely more and more on field
                    funding, or “buy-ins” to our central projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this still under Development Administration, the same
                        office, or did they change it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: There was a merger of the Development Administration and Rural
                    Development Offices under Harlan Hobgood in 1979. The merged Office was called
                    “Rural Development and Development Administration.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In which there was a unit for Development
                        Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. The former Office of Development Administration became a division
                    of the merged office and kept the same name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were head of the Development Administration
                        unit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Norman Nicholson was head of the Development Administration Division
                    under Hobgood, and then when Jerry French succeeded Hobgood and Nicholson moved
                    to another position, I became Division Chief.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you became Division Chief in what year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: That was 1983.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you might want to elaborate on the evolution since
                        then of the office's name, so we get that story, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. Jerry French succeeded Hobgood, and there was a further merger with
                    the Office of Urban Development in 1982. The merged Office was then called
                    “Multisectoral Development.” Later the name became “Rural and Institutional
                    Development,” and then “Economic and Institutional Development.” That takes us
                    to 1993 when the Center for Democracy and Governance was created in the new
                    Global Bureau. The part of the combined office that prospered the most in the
                    mid to late 1980s was the Small Enterprise Division.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to the development administration unit?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER : My Division, which I called “Institutional Development and Management”
                    though it was still on the books as “Development Administration,” got a
                    reasonable share of declining central funding, and the field missions and the
                    Africa Bureau increased the levels of funding they were providing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's continue a little more about the evolution of the
                        office and the bureau during that time, because you had a nice overview of
                        that whole time period. Were the differences just name changes or conceptual
                        changes in what they were supposed to be doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>KORNHER: One key reason for renaming the central technical bureaus and
                    repackaging their agenda was political. When a new Administration came in,
                    especially with a change of political party, it always wanted to give the agency
                    and the central technical bureau a new look. So, there was a good degree of
                    continuity with the Technical Assistance Bureau during the Nixon/Ford years from
                    1969 to 1977. Then the Carter Administration recast it as the Development
                    Support Bureau from 1977-81. The Science and Technology Bureau lasted through
                    the Reagan-Bush years from 1981-1993. The Clinton Administration's Global Bureau
                    will presumably continue for eight years, from 1993 to 2001. You also asked the
                    question whether these programs changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there different emphases in these different
                        programs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The answer is yes and no. The central technical bureaus always had a
                    core of functions that didn't change very much. Those included the core sectoral
                    programs of health, education, agriculture, nutrition, population, housing and
                    urban development, and the multisector development areas. The latter included
                    rural, urban and regional development; participation; social soundness and some
                    women in development work, microenterprise, and development administration. Now,
                    those various sectoral and multisectoral programs were never cut out. Some were
                    pruned or merged from time to time, and all had to adjust to reduced operating
                    funds over an extended period. To take one example, education has waxed and
                    waned in the emphasis it has received over the years. Primary education and
                    educational technology were emphasized for several years, and then declined. One
                    education emphasis in the Global Bureau is girls' education, which I believe has
                    attracted some additional money.</p>
                <p>Multisector development changed more than the other sectors, partly because it
                    has more components. When the microenterprise development efforts were
                    successful, they were shunted off to get more visibility in the State Department
                    building under what was then the Bureau for Private Enterprise. So that was a
                    significant reduction in the sum of our office programs—a reward for success!
                    Also, as I mentioned earlier, programs like rural development participation were
                    very popular for a time, but then discredited, so there were ups and downs of
                    that kind. There have also been changes in external partners. Funding for
                    universities has declined in the '90s, while commercial contracting and grants
                    for NGOs have increased as a proportion of total program funding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about functions of the bureau in terms of research
                        and services, what was the function of the bureau not by sector?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>KORNHER: The names of the Bureaus had some significance in that regard. The
                    Technical Assistance Bureau was pretty balanced regarding its emphasis on field
                    services and research. The Development Support Bureau emphasized field services
                    and, given limited resources, there were cutbacks in research and development
                    [R&amp;D] funding. The Science and Technology Bureau, as the name implies,
                    tended somewhat more toward technology interests, such as the agricultural
                    research centers around the world. R&amp;D became more legitimate than it had
                    been under the Development Support Bureau.</p>
                <p>Let me mention a bit about the tug-of-war between R&amp;D on one hand, and field
                    service on the other. The regional bureaus and the field missions generally saw
                    central resources as competing with field resources. So their position was that
                    resources for technical assistance going to the central bureau ought to come
                    back to the field in the form of in-country work by central bureau staff and
                    contractors. Also that the work should address practical country issues and help
                    meet their operational requirements. Interestingly, they fairly often defined
                    their operational requirements to include studies, even applied research.</p>
                <p>The mission views on this were legitimate. If you dilute field resources by
                    allocating too much to the center you put pressure on field operations. On the
                    other hand, the central bureau position was that allocations to knowledge
                    consolidation and applied research are important so that you don't continue to
                    use old and inferior ideas and approaches in field work. So there tends to be a
                    creative tension between what the central bureau is supposed to do in R&amp;D
                    and what it is supposed to do in field service. In addition, whether explicit or
                    implicit, the central bureau is involved with cultivating USAID's U.S.
                    constituencies. During my years the interaction was mainly with universities.
                    Now it has shifted more to NGOs and commercial contractors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your view of what the bureau's function was in
                        terms of the things you were working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I believe it is vital for the central technical bureau to really know
                    what development is about at both strategic and tactical levels, and by
                    technical function. And to accumulate lessons of experience as you, Haven,
                    advocated in your leadership of the Center for Development Information and
                    Evaluation (CDIE). It is a sad waste of resources and a disservice to the
                    countries and people we're supposed to be helping if costly old mistakes are
                    repeated. So I think it is the responsibility of the central bureau to get it
                    right.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>One way to do that is to support the CDIE function of what we used to call a
                    memory bank, including evaluations and knowledge consolidation. The task is to
                    document what has worked and what has not worked in specific technical areas,
                    projects, and countries, and to define the processes of design, procurement,
                    implementation and evaluation that are more likely to produce good results.
                    Another way is to be able to deliver knowledge-based expertise when the missions
                    need it. When you have people in the field who are asking for help, they ought
                    to get really topnotch knowledge-based help. But to provide such help from
                    either USAID staff or external resourcerequires at least constant learning by
                    the field support providers, and better, involvement in research as well. I
                    think resources should be allocated to continuously review and document the
                    lessons of experience and achieve real depth of expertise. You can get such
                    expertise from experienced in-house staff, from firms, from universities, and
                    from some NGOs. But I am absolutely convinced that good field support has to be
                    based on a solid body of knowledge and experience relevant to the field
                    needs.</p>
                <p>So I think the creative tension ought to be continued. The central bureaus ought
                    to have money for systematic learning and applied research. But systematic
                    learning and research are useless to USAID if they don't get put to use in the
                    field. I should also mention that the buy-in idea helped out quite a bit in
                    matching field and central bureau interests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Okay. “Buy-ins” began to be used in the late 1970s and became more
                    important in the '80s. USAID missions would provide funds to get services from
                    central bureau projects. To some extent the central bureau budgets were reduced.
                    That produced kind of an automatic customer relationship. If you wanted to have
                    your Washington-based enterprise succeed and grow, you had to provide services
                    that the field people were willing to pay for. That was a good incentive
                    mechanism because the central bureau units that were entrepreneurial and
                    maintained good relations and high relevance to field activities got more
                    buy-ins than those that did not. They even got field money for country studies
                    and occasional applied research.</p>
                <p>But the more difficult question for me is how much serious research the central
                    tech bureau ought to do. To take an example, there were millions spent in
                    attempts to get a vaccination for malaria. That was real research. It turned out
                    to be unsuccessful, but some research isn't successful. So I didn't think it was
                    a mistake to try. In the social sciences it is much tougher to define the
                    boundary between knowledge consolidation and serious applied research. Quite a
                    bit of USAID's social science “research” is really inference from a very small
                    sample of cases. That creates a high risk for both validity and reliability. I
                    think that in my career I only had one project that was a serious, respectable
                    research project.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>KORNHER: The decentralization project in 1987. I thought it was necessary because
                    decentralization has several definitions, some of which are contradictory, and
                    the desired outcomes of assistance haven't happened in most developing
                    countries. USAID really didn't have a good grip on factor weights and causal
                    relationships in talking about successful “decentralization.” The approaches
                    offered by public administration as a discipline hadn't been sufficient. So the
                    project was intended to fund up to seven years of serious interdisciplinary
                    applied research drawing on political scientists, public-finance economists,
                    organizational specialists, new institutional economists and field operators to
                    develop a new and more powerful framework of factors to explain how successful
                    local action can be better supported. The intent for Phase II was to spend seven
                    more years working in specific countries that wanted to try to implement the new
                    formulas for success. The first seven years were funded, buPhase II was not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, do you want to take the time now to talk about what
                        you learned in that, that's a very key component of your work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Perhaps we should do the decentralization project in our next
                    session.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Let's just sum up before we go on to the projects in
                        the next session. Talk about your own career, what happened over this time?
                        You worked on the decentralization project. What were some of the other
                        things, without going into detail, that you were concerned with in that
                        process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Views on acquisition and competition</p>
                <p>KORNHER: I would like to touch briefly on the agency's acquisition mechanisms and
                    competition, and perhaps challenge some current norms a little. When we were
                    building up these projects in the early '70s, competition was not as much
                    emphasized as it is now. Competition was used in commercial contracts, but in
                    the case of universities, the acquisition regulations permitted non-competitive
                    selection. So in the agribusiness domain we selected Harvard because Ray
                    Goldberg at Harvard was one of the preeminent thinkers and consultants in
                    international agribusiness, especially on export approaches. Similarly, the
                    university contract with Vanderbilt was sole source. These contracts were
                    successful. So non-competitive procurement worked very well. Also, we later used
                    cooperative agreements with considerable success.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>What concerns me about over-emphasis on competition, which is now seen by many as
                    THE key to effective Federal acquisition, is first that the means are emphasized
                    much more than the end. The end is supposed to be excellent performance. For
                    USAID I believe the most important factors needed to achieve excellent
                    performance defined as development results are knowledge-based competence and a
                    relationship of confidence between the host country people and the service
                    providers. What you often destroy by repeated requirements for competition is a
                    continuing relationship of confidence. Sometimes, especially when USAID accepts
                    “low-ball” bids, you destroy competence as well.</p>
                <p>When I was working for a contractor of the ENI Bureau in 1996-98, I found that we
                    had to compete for the basic contract and then we competed for each task order.
                    The task order lasts a year or at most 18 months. And then you compete again. No
                    one on the U.S. Government side seems to be thinking about the administrative
                    costs to the contractors, to USAID, and to host countries, of these repeated
                    competitions. So in thinking back about some of these mechanisms, and
                    particularly the university contracts and cooperative agreements, I think there
                    is little to be gained in executing a contract instead of an assistance
                    mechanism - cooperative agreement. And there is more than excessive
                    administrative costs to be lost if, after you have selected a contractor and the
                    contractor has established relations of confidence with the host country
                    stakeholders, you require a new competition.</p>
                <p>One of the things we had going for us in some of these early projects was
                    continuity. And when we had a preeminent agribusiness specialist like Ray
                    Goldberg or a local revenue specialist like Roy Bahl orchestrating our country
                    linkages, they worked. They were handled beautifully.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of a contract was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: These were non-competitive or limited-competition university contracts,
                    which would probably be impossible today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you select somebody like that to be sure that
                        other people were confident that you were not just selecting your
                        friends?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well that's the dilemma of sole source procurement. Perhaps the best
                    procedure is to have an initial open competition for a commercial contract, or
                    use at least limited competition with justification for a cooperative
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But for long term effort?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Right.Once selected, as long as performance is good, why not a five-year
                    effort rather than one year, and why not allow administrative discretion in the
                    award of task orders under the umbrella contract?</p>
                <p>Views on development management projects</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's turn now to your views and descriptions of the
                        development management projects for the period from the 1970s up to 1990,
                        '95. Take each one, what is the project, and what was your role in it and
                        what did you think about it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: USAID projects always have to represent the policy and ideas in good
                    currency at the time they are developed. And, of course, policies and ideas
                    change over time. They reflect the policies of the current Administration and
                    the emphases of legislation. USAID has operated for many years on the
                    authorizing legislation of 1971, but it has been amended at frequent
                    intervals.</p>
                <p>So, inasmuch as programs and project development reflect the ideas in good
                    currency and the policies of the current Administration and of Congress, it was
                    no accident that humanitarian assistance was emphasized during the Carter
                    Administration and private enterprise during the Reagan years. So it's
                    important, I think, to understand the context in which projects are developed,
                    the context of policy, legislation and of technical ideas in good currency. As
                    to the latter, lessons of experience, evaluations, academic work and advocates
                    all have an important influence on the ideas in good currency that help shape
                    projects.</p>
                <p>I'd like to cite a source that is really excellent in describing the context in
                    which projects were developed in the field of development management from the
                    1960s up to 1987. It covers the changing policy emphases of Congress and
                    successive Administrations, as well as that of AID itself. The book is by Dennis
                    Rondinelli, and it is called Development Administration and U.S. Foreign Aid
                    Policy. It was published by Lynn Rheiner publishers in 1987. Dennis, along with
                    Ray Radosevich, was the co-leader of the work that we sponsored at Vanderbilt
                    University, which I mentioned earlier. This book was subsidized by one of our
                    projects, but I think we got a good deal more than we paid for in Dennis' effort
                    to lay out the evolution of some of these programs and context of policy and
                    ideas in good currency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in getting this book developed and
                        done?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. I was one of the people who thought it was a good idea, and so our
                    division provided a little seed money through a cooperative agreement we had
                    with the National Association of Schools of Public Affairs and Administration
                    (NASPAA). NASPAA paid Dennis to get started on the book. We also made the
                    publishing arrangements with a guarantee of a certain number of books.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in the development of the text, or the
                        substance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: No. I had discussions with your wife, Jeanne North, who was project
                    manager, with Dennis and others about the content of the book. But I was not
                    deeply involved in the writing or articulating the ideas. I would credit Jeanne,
                    Dennis and others that he cites in the book.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular theme that runs through the book?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. The projects that he cited were of two kinds. First, projects that
                    contributed to understanding of successful local action in developing countries
                    and second, projects that contributed to organization and management
                    improvement. Many of the themes in this book, lessons of experience reflected
                    there, are and remain very important for U.S. aid policy and internal
                    management, as well as the success of efforts to help developing countries
                    improve their management.</p>
                <p>Just to give one example of this. There was an exercise known as PBAR, back in
                    the late 1960s, which was very well intentioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Program Budgeting, Accounting and Reporting,
                        PBAR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think that's the right acronym. You have a good memory! It was a very
                    well intentioned effort by some very smart people to bring some order and
                    discipline into AID's project development and management process. But its
                    outcome was to require in the design process a very elaborate set of a priori
                    specifications as to what the projects were supposed to do. You know, trying to
                    predict how a project would unfold, and what the inputs needed to be and what
                    the outcomes were going to be. Well, Rondinelli's work, and other literature
                    that he cites, show that this does not work very well, especially in local or
                    rural development kinds of projects. For local action projects you have to go
                    out and learn on the ground, learn as you go.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>You have to get the advice of the local people, who are supposed to get the
                    benefits of the project, you have to develop local leadership and you have to
                    mobilize local resources. In the a priori or “blueprint” approach to project or
                    program development, you're missing the point thalearning with local
                    participants and getting them in the forefront of the action is really what it's
                    about. And that is not predictable before the fact, or certainly not precisely
                    predictable.</p>
                <p>So the PBAR idea, in other words, was too control-oriented. There are questions
                    being raised with USAID today, particularly by the non-governmental
                    organizations, as to whether the current reengineering approaches to project
                    development, intermediate objectives and indicators, may not have some of the
                    flavor of this control-oriented approach. So that's an example of one lesson of
                    experience that is well-documented in Rondinelli's work.</p>
                <p>It is also very useful for anyone who wants to understand the policy and program
                    emphases that affected development administration from the 1950s through the
                    mid-'80s. Now, while I said that there are constant changes in policy and ideas
                    in good currency, there are also themes that endure and recur in international
                    development. In our first interview I mentioned that public administration, or
                    at least the label of public administration, lost some of its popularity in AID
                    in the late '60s and '70s. But the New Directions amendments to the Foreign
                    Assistance Act that were passed in 1973 specified public administration as one
                    of the emphasis areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they called it Public Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, specifically, public administration. So there was a little
                    different view in Congress than there was in some circles of USAID itself. But,
                    it is also a fair question as to what people mean when they say “public
                    administration.” In our programs we were at that time emphasizing systems of
                    action and sectoral management and processes of program management and
                    management improvement, including training. Clearly the ministries of
                    agriculture have to get involved in providing services in any country we are
                    helping, but that is a little different twist on public administration than the
                    civil service reform programs of the '50s and '60s.</p>
                <p>Now, among the themes that endured and recurred among the ideas in good currency
                    were two that were very important for our projects from 1971 to 1990. Let's call
                    the first theme local action, and the second organization and management
                    improvement.</p>
                <p>Rondinelli's book, relying largely on a 1978 retrospective study by Lane
                    Holdcroft, points out that community development was a big emphasis of AID
                    programs during the 1950s and 1960s. So the theme of local action was not new in
                    the '70s, '80s and '90s. There was also, in these earlier eras, considerable
                    attention to decentralization, to local government and local revenue, and other
                    themes of local action. But in the 50s and early '60s community development was
                    the big one.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>By the mid '60s, community development was seen as soaking up a lot of resources
                    with outcomes that were disappointing in most cases. And so, as we were thinking
                    about assistance efforts in that era, we were thinking of other mechanisms that
                    could promote local action.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have an understanding of why the community
                        development approach wasn't getting the results people expected?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Part of it was that it did not build enough on indigenous people and
                    organizations and resources. There was some good research later that pointed out
                    that leadership and involvement by local people, plus their contribution of
                    resources, was important to successful local action. And community development,
                    as I understand it, was more coming in from the outside and trying to organize
                    people. That style of external management persisted through the New Directions
                    years, too. I believe I mentioned earlier that it was very evident in some
                    African countries in their internal politics and bureaucracy, as well as in
                    external assistance. The political party (usually unitary) and the central
                    ministries wanted to organize the villages, rather than helping the local people
                    to organize to do things they wanted to do. And that style simply doesn't
                    work.</p>
                <p>There is an excellent account of community development in the Lane Holdcroft
                    paper. I would recommend it to anyone who wants to delve into the community
                    development era.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were talking about local action?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. The labels of the '70s and '80s were things like decentralization,
                    small farmer organization, rural development participation, integrated rural
                    development, managing benefits to the poor. In the '90s local action themes
                    shifted again and became things like local government, governance, best
                    practices for local government, and organization of civil society. All of these
                    are easily accommodated, it seems to me, under the label of local action which
                    we came up with in the late 1960s.</p>
                <p>Similarly, organization and management improvement received much emphasis as
                    “public administration” in the 1950s and 1960s. In the '70s and '80s,
                    organization and management improvement continued to receive some emphasis but
                    under different labels like sectoral management, institution building,
                    organization and administration of rural development, project and program
                    management, policy change, and so on. In the '90s, important labels for
                    management improvement became policy implementation, governance, capacity
                    building, and best practices.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>So let's turn to some of the projects of the '70s and '80s that were sponsored by
                    the original Office of Development Administration and its larger successors.
                    These successor offices were the Office of Rural Development and Development
                    Administration, the Office of Multi Sector Development, which incorporated the
                    Urban Development Office. Then, it became the Office of Rural and Institutional
                    Development. And about 1991, it became the Office of Economic and Institutional
                    Development. One of the reasons for the economic designation was that there was
                    much more concern with small enterprise, private enterprise, and economic growth
                    in the mix, and also with the economic components of institutional development,
                    than there had been in earlier periods.</p>
                <p>I will have to leave out or only mention briefly in this interview the projects
                    which I was not directly involved with, which were developed by other divisions
                    in the office, even though some of them made significant contributions to
                    development management.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Such as?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Such as micro enterprise, urban development and regional development
                    projects. I shall also give limited time to Agricultural Marketing, one
                    important and successful project managed in my division by Tom Mehen. It was a
                    second-generation project in the category of agribusiness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: All right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: So, first let's talk about the organization and management improvement
                    projects. In our first session I mentioned the modernizing management project
                    with Vanderbilt University. That started in about 1972, and it explored new
                    methods for management improvement such as strategic management, and
                    organizational development. Another important knowledge building activity that
                    we supported in these early days was the Program of Advanced Studies in
                    Institution Building and Technical Assistance Methodology at Indiana University.
                    This long title was abbreviated to PASITAM. It was run by Bill Siffin, and if
                    memory serves, originally sponsored by the Division of Technical Assistance
                    Methodology. The program published books and monographs, and identified and
                    circulated summaries of current studies in a newsletter. PASITAM monitored and
                    reported findings in institutional development and management partly based on
                    U.S. experience, but increasingly from developing countries. It gave special
                    attention to the need to adapt managerial approaches and techniques to the
                    context of developing countries' politics and culture.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>I remember, for example, one very good study in Korea that described how
                    procurement practices there were much different than procurement practices in
                    the United States. And you really shouldn't talk about procurement in Korea
                    without understanding the cultural context, because it was so different from the
                    way it worked here.</p>
                <p>The Modernizing Management project with Vanderbilt was revised after a couple of
                    years to emphasize project management. It produced over its final two years,
                    1972-'74, a final report and set of learning materials for project management
                    improvement that emphasized the entire cycle of project benefits and managerial
                    factors in addition to the traditional technical, economic and financial
                    factors. The successor project was called Project Management.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the reasons for these changes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: At that time the approach to project development at the World Bank,
                    which set the standards for the development community, emphasized technical
                    analysis and economic and financial analysis. That is, getting it right at the
                    front end, being sure that there was going to be a viable technology, economic
                    payoff, that there would be a sensible flow of finances into the project to
                    achieve completion on time, and so on. Now this model was pretty good for
                    creating infrastructure, but as projects moved toward more service delivery and
                    people-oriented change, it proved to be incomplete. Also, it didn't pay nearly
                    enough attention to the downstream problems in implementing projects -
                    maintenance, renovation, service delivery and so on - that inevitably had a big
                    impact on the flow of benefits after the project period ended.</p>
                <p>So the Vanderbilt people, and a consultant to our office, Morris Solomon, were
                    saying that the approaches that the World Bank and to some extent USAID were
                    using had to be expanded with attention to the entire project cycle. What uses
                    are going to be made of the facilities, how are people going to be involved in
                    their use, how will benefits be assured over long time periods? Not just the
                    analysis in design stage but the implementation stage, the service-delivery,
                    maintenance and renovation stages, the whole project cycle. And, indeed, if one
                    looks at failures of projects they often come in the downstream failure to
                    maintain, or the failure to continue the flow of services contemplated in the
                    project's design.</p>
                <p>There were some criticisms of the work at the time because it was drawn largely
                    from U.S. business experience, not sufficiently informed by empirical study of
                    projects in developing countries. Nevertheless, I think it was an important
                    contribution to sound project planning and implementation.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>In addition to the work on project management, the Office of Development
                    Administration launched two projects that contributed a good deal to management
                    improvement in the early 1970s. These were agriculture sector management
                    efforts. The first was called the Agriculture Sector Implementation Project,
                    which was contracted to the Governmental Affairs Institute and led by Al
                    Waterston. Waterston had worked for the World Bank and had been involved in work
                    on planning — governmental planning, program planning, project planning. He
                    became a very strong advocate of one of the themes that emerged at Vanderbilt,
                    namely that implementation is at least as important as good design or good
                    planning. So this was also a finding of Waterston and his work at the World
                    Bank.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any particular theme in this context, of how to
                        carry out a project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The starting points, it seems to me, is to look at the whole project
                    cycle, at the downstream needs for continuing reliable service delivery and
                    maintenance, at the involvement of people in projects, and to figure out how to
                    do that. And I've already said that you cannot blueprint the way a rural
                    development project is going to work. You have to go out there and find out how
                    to make it work with local resources, local leadership, and local organizations.
                    Many of these themes were echoed by Waterston and built into his recommendations
                    as to how you had to move from planning into agricultural implementation,
                    reliable research, extension, credit, and other services, mobilization of local
                    resources delivery, and involvement of local people. So that was the work at the
                    Governmental Affairs Institute.</p>
                <p>And the second ag sector project which I mentioned earlier in our discussion was
                    also a significant contribution. It was Agribusiness Management contracted to
                    the Harvard Business School. That project lasted from about 1973 to about 1977.
                    I was pleased that we were ahead of our time, because shortly after that project
                    ended, agribusiness again became an important theme in USAID. A lot of the
                    materials, a lot of the ideas, that had been developed by Ray Goldberg and
                    associates at Harvard were quite useful in agribusiness projects, including
                    agricultural marketing projects.</p>
                <p>The basic ideas were fairly simple but quite powerful. Goldberg argued that the
                    way to look at agribusiness development is through what he called “commodity
                    action systems.” That means that an agricultural enterprise has to have a market
                    to be successful. So you have to trace the process from “seeds to consumer.” You
                    have to do what is necessary in a systematic sequence of events to be sure that
                    you achieve not only the production, which had always been a part of ag
                    programs, but also quality control, crops ripening in sufficient quantity at a
                    particular time, having the transportation to the market there when the crops
                    are ripe, being sure that you have refrigeration, a systematic link to markets
                    so that your produce or whatever you're producing gets sold and turns a profit
                    all the way back through the chain. Fairly simple, but I think powerful
                    ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A systems approach to it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Exactly. A systems approach.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It all sounds like common sense. But why do you think this
                        needed emphasis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, Ray tried this out in the real world. Mexico at that time was
                    exporting produce to the United States off-season market. But Central America
                    not very much, except of course for coffee. So the Harvard people worked in
                    Costa Rica and other places in Central America, trying to determine whether
                    there was potential for a substantial increase in off-season marketing from
                    Central America into the North American market, at times of the year that would
                    be even more favorable than Mexico enjoyed.</p>
                <p>But in the real world that they examined, some entrepreneurs grew produce in the
                    off season and they had contracted with refrigerated barges to take it north,
                    and they had market links in Florida. But, unfortunately, at the time the barges
                    were supposed to arrive, they didn't show up. The barge operators said, “Well,
                    you guys have ordered our services before, but you never had the produce for us
                    to haul at the time we were supposed to haul it.” It was a small disaster,
                    because all of the produce that had grown had to be sold on the local market at
                    giveaway prices or it simply spoiled.</p>
                <p>I guess it's fair to say that what this research pointed to was that you've got
                    to make all the linkages work. All of the linkages in that chain of commodity
                    action, from seeds to consumer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you go about that? Do you create a super-manager,
                        or what do you do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, there are broader institutional issues around that. The guy who
                    was supposed to deliver the barges didn't pay any attention to his contract. You
                    really should have enforcement and sanctions for contracts to make a chain like
                    that work. In the meantime you probably go back and say to the bargeman, “Look,
                    we really mean it. We are going to have that produce to you on such and such a
                    date, and you have to have the barges there. If not, we'll never do business
                    with you again.” So informal means to make the linkages work are useful, but
                    enforcement of contracts by law is more fundamental.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But doesn't that systems approach presume some sort of
                        overriding management structure, or individual or operation that keeps these
                        linkages connected? Or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. That was not what I was arguing against earlier. The individual
                    parts of the system don't necessarily have to be parts of one massive management
                    structure as long as the transactions, the links in the chain, are reliable. But
                    it is easier if one company or organization controls many of the critical links.
                    The more time-sensitive the requirements are, the more you need to be able to
                    control them. It is true that a driving force of very large, vertically
                    integrated agribusiness enterprises is the need to assure such control. The
                    nature of the enterprise governs the management structure needed to make it work
                    reliably.</p>
                <p>One of the problems, for example, that emerged in Goldberg's findings was that
                    the big producer who has 200 hectares or more can control the quality of the
                    export crop being produced. But how do you do that with small farmers, who have
                    three hectares, but want to participate in a marketing opportunity that requires
                    more scale? Answers to that question are difficult. Sometimes associations work,
                    or co-ops, but they only work when every farmer is committed to meet the
                    required standards of quality, delivery date, and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did this project, this development, emphasize? What
                        was it trying to focus on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The main focus was on export agriculture, especially for countries in
                    the Southern Hemisphere that could do off-season exportinto the Northern
                    Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the management approaches, techniques, that it
                        seemed to be emphasizing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think the most important ones I've already described, the systems
                    approach, the movement through transaction links in the whole chain from seeds
                    to consumer, and finding effective mechanisms to assure quality control, on-time
                    transportation, and marketing. In the background, of course, were the standard
                    requirements for finance, labor, etc.</p>
                <p>So these two sector projects were the pioneers. A third sector management project
                    that came along in the mid-'70s, was Health Management. The project was
                    developed jointly with the Office of Health and became important because it
                    introduced the idea that you had to have a strategy to optimize use of scarce
                    resources, systems approaches and strategic management in the health sector.
                    It's one thing to produce a new vaccine, but how do you deliver it, and how do
                    you allocate health sector moneys for hospitals versus vaccination campaigns, or
                    for hospitals versus clinics when providing routine health services?</p>
                <p>The health management ideas influenced the Office of Health in the Technical
                    Assistance Bureau and countries in Latin America and Asia, as well as the World
                    Health and Pan American Health Organizations. A lot of health ministries picked
                    up the idea of moving resource allocations from very expensive provision of
                    services through hospitals to much more use of local clinics, vaccination
                    campaigns, and other means to reduce unit costs of services.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was a major theme of the project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. As you know, in the United States, providing health service through
                    hospitals, when people come to the emergency room, is a very, very expensive way
                    to dispense clinical medicine, and it is financially impossible in rural areas.
                    So in health systems, it is vital to look at what health outcomes you get for a
                    certain amount of money using different delivery mechanisms. That is the main
                    reason that vaccination campaigns are emphasized. The benefits per unit cost are
                    large. But of course you can address only a limited number of health problems
                    through vaccination campaigns. And if you decide that a clinic is the way to
                    deliver the service, you can move down to that level to try to assure that the
                    clinic is efficiently run, to establish staffing requirements, patient load, the
                    logistics of getting medical supplies, and so on.</p>
                <p>Anyway, this systematic attention to return on investment in health and related
                    organization and management structures was at the core of the health management
                    work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the project have an approach to measuring returns on
                        investment in health? Was it calculating that sort of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. Every health organization that the project worked with was
                    encouraged to do benefit/cost analysis.</p>
                <p>Okay. I will next cover some of the successor projects. Our work on project
                    management was continued with a new project in about 1977, called Project
                    Management Effectiveness. That project supported two and later three U.S.
                    centers, which had responsibility for services to USAID Missions, and host
                    countries, and also had responsibility for producing good technical materials,
                    working papers, articles and books.</p>
                <p>All of these centers also helped us work closely with AID's regional bureaus. So
                    their relationships were not only with our office, but also with the offices of
                    the regional bureaus. We encouraged them to be entrepreneurs; you know, if they
                    could get funding from the African or Asian Bureaus, as well as ourselves,
                    great. We encouraged relations with the missions as well, but kept closer tabs
                    on those links, since the services were linked to our project budget.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>The first center was set up through a service agreement with the Department of
                    Agriculture. It created the Development Project Management Center, abbreviated
                    DPMC. The center was headed by Morris Solomon. Morris had a knack not only for
                    knowing what approaches state of the art work required but also for hiring the
                    right people and promoting teamwork among the people who worked with him. His
                    best-known personal contribution to development management was action training.
                    Action training is described in detail by Rondinelli and also in another book
                    produced under one of our projects called Management Training Strategies for
                    Developing Countries.</p>
                <p>The basic idea of action training was first that you train people in teams, so
                    that they learn to work together as well as learning what to do. You put the
                    training as close to the reality of the working environment as possible. So if
                    you wanted to train people to develop projects, you went into an organization
                    that had a responsibility for developing projects and helped the trainees
                    develop actual projects, and led them through the analytic requirements, the
                    packaging requirements. It is guided learning by doing. This kind of training
                    was discovered by others, as well as Solomon, and seems to have great advantages
                    compared to normal classroom training in getting people focused on how to make
                    things work in the real world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the idea spread quite widely?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. I think it has been picked up quite widely, and while you still
                    find a lot of boring classroom training, you also find a lot more management
                    training linked to real world problems and to team building and things like
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What, apart from team building, was the content of this
                        kind of training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The content drew on the kind of work that Vanderbilt and DPMC had been
                    doing, as well as on World Bank sources. Yes, you have to get your economics
                    right, you have to get your technical content and financing right, but you have
                    to look at the entire project cycle. You have to build in planning and action
                    provisions for effective implementation, provisions for maintenance of
                    infrastructure, provisions for systematic involvement of people. So the content
                    of the training was pretty much already on the shelf, which is not to say that
                    it was easy to do and easy to get people to learn in the poorer countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it related not just in general or in principle, but
                        related to a particular project? Was the training project or program
                        specific?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes it was. One good example where the use of action training worked,
                    and you are doubtless familiar with this because you were probably at the time
                    Deputy Administrator of the African Bureau, was called Sahel Financial
                    Management. Some of the Sahel Missions had gotten in trouble with Congress
                    because they were not able to account systematically for funds they had given to
                    local organizations. It was a little difficult to find out whether there was
                    leakage in these projects, whether people were making off with some of the money
                    or some of the goods, because they didn't have accounting systems, bookkeeping
                    systems. Everyone realized that these countries, and especially these local
                    organizations, could not install elaborate accounting systems, but they could
                    devise and enforce systems of basic accountability. If you bought this item,
                    where is the receipt? You know, things like that.</p>
                <p>So the Africa Bureau funded the Development Project Management Center to take on
                    training to remedy these bookkeeping/accounting deficiencies. It recruited
                    French-speaking as well as Anglophone trainers who went out and worked right
                    with the local organizations to install rudimentary bookkeeping and accounting
                    systems. Action training. It worked, certainly to the extent that Congress
                    agreed that they had achieved some reasonable accountability in these Sahel
                    country projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is a good example.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Now, I've spoken of the first service center that was created under this
                    series of projects, the Development Project Management Center in the Department
                    of Agriculture; later called the Development Program Management Center. The
                    second serviccenter was created in 1979, through a cooperative agreement with
                    the National Association of Schools of Public Affairs and Administration. I fear
                    that we had a tendency in some of our projects to deal with organizations that
                    have long and complex names. Like PASITAM. But we simply called this one NASPAA,
                    and almost forgot what the long version was.</p>
                <p>NASPAA provided a very nice umbrella organization through which we could draw on
                    faculty with relevant international experience from any of about 40 U.S. member
                    universities with programs in public and development administration. Successive
                    Directors were recruited from this network. They included Phil Morgan from
                    Indiana University, Rudy Klauss from Syracuse, and then Lou Picard from
                    Nebraska. The project lasted a long time, a full decade. So that there was a
                    nice continuity that evolved in the NASPAA Program as to botthe service elements
                    of the project and the research elements as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they focus on?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>KORNHER: They emphasized quality responses to USAID Mission requests for help in
                    development management, rather broadly defined. Helping assure that the Mission
                    design included strong attention to what the host country wanted, to the
                    organizations and management structures they were working with in the host
                    country, to mobilization of indigenous consultants and resource people, to an
                    understanding of what the local managers wanted and the local beneficiaries
                    wanted. Sometimes there was a little Mission resistance to pushing it that far,
                    but I must say that the Project Manager for most of these years was very
                    effective in persuading Missions that they needed to do this intensive work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give any examples that sort of typify what they
                        were working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, there were many examples from Africa. Oh, by the way, I should
                    mention that the long-term manager of this activity was a person you know rather
                    well, Jeanne North, your wife. She did an excellent job of combining the Mission
                    resources with the NASPAA resources and the host country resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of the Missions bought into this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. About 50 missions. She persuaded the field people that this was the
                    way that it needed to be done. One kind of activity that I was impressed with
                    was assistance to business schools in three countries. Part of the success of
                    that was due to the solid experience of Wendell Schaeffer, who was on the NASPAA
                    team through most of these years. He had originally been on the faculty at
                    Pittsburgh, and I think he was hired when he was working in Texas. Wendell was
                    an excellent broker between university authorities, who wanted to make some
                    changes and improvements in their way of getting things done, and the Missions
                    which were providing resources for it.</p>
                <p>This model of collaboration was built into university assistance in the Dominican
                    Republic, then picked up by Paraguay and Uruguay. I think the substantial
                    strengthening of three different business schools was significant in Latin
                    America, and will have a continuing multiplier effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Strengthening in what way?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, they were changing the course content, getting it more action
                    oriented, more business oriented. They were trying to develop their faculty to
                    use more market relevant approaches not only to business management education,
                    but also to consulting and involvement in actual business enterprises rather
                    than being only an academic institution. They were encouraged to go out into the
                    real world and work with business enterprises. And then there were a lot of
                    exchanges of materials, often in the Spanish language, that helped them do these
                    things.</p>
                <p>But that is only one example. NASPAA's country linkages were very numerous. They
                    were very strong in African countries, and mobilized several top-notch
                    consultants from three or four different countries. Activities included
                    everything from management training to railroad management; to improvement of
                    personnel systems, to auditing and prevention of corruption, to policy change,
                    and so on. So it was a multipurpose, demand-driven kind of a project that worked
                    in all regions served by USAID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And through NASPAA, the project was able to reach out to a
                        very wide area of institutions in the U.S.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Definitely, and I think that was another very successful dimension of
                    the project. It was a case in which an assistance mechanism — a cooperative
                    agreement — really worked to build U.S. capacity. In most of the larger
                    universities and many smaller ones there are some people who have an intense
                    interest in international work and do some of it, as time permits. But they are
                    driven by the university's requirement to teach lots and lots of bachelors and
                    MPA students basic American public administration, and to churn out
                    publications. They jump at the opportunity to get more involved in international
                    work.</p>
                <p>One good example was Rich Vengroff, who I believe worked at the University of
                    California, Santa Clara.But he had been involved in training programs in West
                    Africa and had a really strong commitment to do more of that kind of work. So
                    NASPAA was able to give Rich opportunities to do training in a number of African
                    countries and gain more experience, and spend more time doing this kind of work.
                    Eventually his work gained enough recognition that the University of Connecticut
                    hired him as Director of their International Programs. That kind of change in
                    career path happened a number of times for our NASPAA people. Almost all of the
                    long-term staff remained in international activities.</p>
                <p>There are other good examples. Rudy Klauss is working in Ghana these days. Lou
                    Picard has spent literally years on a full and part time basis in South Africa,
                    and is now a senior faculty member at the Graduate School of Public and
                    International Affairs, University of Pittsburgh. Ed Connerley, who came from
                    Eastern Washington University, did full-time field consulting for USAID and the
                    World Bank for several years after he left NASPAA. He then accepted an offer
                    from Pittsburgh to direct their International Management Development
                    Institute.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So there were a lot of domestic spin-offs and benefits, as
                        well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, absolutely. These staff members stayed involved in international
                    work and do it a lot better because of the experience they accumulated in these
                    projects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the NASPAA program produce any material, books,
                        research material at all, reports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. That was the second main function that complemented the extensive
                    record of field service. If I may, I'll talk about publications as the last item
                    in our discussion. It was a very rich program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, let's continue on some of the projects you were
                        talking about.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: We have covered reasonably well the organization and management
                    improvement theme and the resources we developed to respond to it. The second
                    theme that I wanted to talk about today was local action. I can abbreviate my
                    treatment of that because it is so well documented in the literature, including
                    the Rondinelli book on Development Administration and U.S. Foreign Aid Policy.
                    The lessons of experience are well documented, so I will only mention the
                    projects involved in the first part of my discussion, and secondly I will treat
                    one 1987 project in more depth.</p>
                <p>The projects of the earlier period included strategies for small farmer
                    development, rural development participation, local revenue, organization and
                    administration of integrated rural development, and managing decentralization.
                    Those projects spanned the period from the mid 1970s through the 1980s. It's
                    difficult to draw generalizations from that much work in many countries.
                    Experience ranged from a lot of rural development efforts in Asia, to local
                    revenue studies in a dozen or more of countries conducted by Syracuse under the
                    Local Revenue Administration Project, and to training programs for local action.
                    A wide range of activities were linked to agricultural production and
                    productivity, because that is what's out there in the rural areas. That was a
                    necessity of the so-called New Directions legislation calling for assistance to
                    the poor majority. In many of the countries AID was working with, the poor
                    majority still lived in rural areas, in spite of the fast growth in the numbers
                    of poor people emigrating to cities.</p>
                <p>The problem of poor people is cities was addressed more by the Urban Development
                    Office, the Housing Office, and the Urban and Regional Development Division in
                    our Office after the merger. So following the merger with the Rural Development
                    Office our Development Administration Division dealt more with rural
                    development.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>Involving local people and successful local action</p>
                <p>Let me try to provide some generalizations based on our findings in these
                    projects. First, you have to involve the local people and work closely with
                    them. USAID and other donor projects that attempt to link to the capital city
                    rather than to the local organizations and people aren't doing it right. Second,
                    blueprints in planning and lack of flexibility in implementation don't work.
                    They don't work whether they are tried by outside donors or NGOs; and they don't
                    work if they are programs of the national government, run from the capital city.
                    It's essential to work on the ground with local organizations, people and
                    resources.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let's take that one for a minute and then we can go
                        on to the others. There is sort of this dilemma between a situation where a
                        manager is supposed to get money, but be able to establish what the money is
                        going to be spent on, and what it's going to accomplish up front, before he
                        can get the money. Because otherwise why would they give him the money? On
                        the other hand, you're saying, well, you don't want to be too precise about
                        all that because you need to be flexible. How do you balance these extremes
                        of careful preparation and planning, which gives people confidence you know
                        what you are going to do, and the other side that's saying, well, we have to
                        learn as we go, feel our way, which some people say is very mushy? So how do
                        the lessons address that kind of dilemma?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think you've asked one of the classic questions about successful
                    public program management. You do have to have rigorous planning and
                    accountability, but you also have to have judgment and flexibility. Two of our
                    colleagues, Derick Brinkerhoff and Marcus Ingle, wrote a nice article about this
                    problem. It was called Between Blueprint and Process: Structured Flexibility
                    Approaches to Development Management.</p>
                <p>Onanswer, I think, is that you have to provide time for successful programs to
                    unfold. You use annual work plans with enough flexibility to change direction
                    some as you learn more. I think that USAID has been ill advised to abbreviate
                    what used to be five-year projects into one year, or less.</p>
                <p>There are good reasons to have a longer authorization. Often the one year
                    projects gets renewed, but there are administrative costs around the renewal and
                    there are certainly learning curve costs if you change from one agent or
                    contractor to another for the second year. We wrestled with this question in
                    NASPAA research in almost the same terms that you have expressed it. I think the
                    best answers were that there are indicators of progress that do not constitute
                    project outcomes, but do reflect interim milestones, persuasive indicators of
                    progress clearly pointed in the right direction.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>Now indicators of that kind might be something like the following: dynamic local
                    organizations have been identified which have leadership and resources for
                    subsequent implementation. Or, clients report that the services they receive are
                    useful, appropriate, and on time. So you're not saying you are going to increase
                    the wealth of this district in one year. As an outcome that may be the ultimate
                    measurement. But you can measure whether the organizations are there, whether
                    the service delivery pilots are working, whether you have a plan for replication
                    of successful pilot efforts. You can't do it without the intermediate steps, so
                    the trick is defining the steps that are the best precursors of the intended
                    outcomes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the actual management requirements with that
                        approach?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, part of it is continuity in field management. Some of the
                    successful rural development projects around the world had good professional
                    leadership that stayed on the job for extended periods of time. They also had
                    resource commitments from the local people. It wasn't just the outsiders dumping
                    goodies on us local people, but rather we have to match the goodies that they
                    are bringing with a contribution of our own. In that way the aggregate of the
                    resources that we provide, and that the outsiders provide, will permit us to get
                    ahead. The finding is pretty much universal that when people get freebies they
                    don't value them. When they agree to put up their own resources, they value the
                    effort a great deal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's go on to the next points you were going to
                        make.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: So the generalization I was making is that you have to involve the local
                    people and work closely with them and ask them to contribute their own
                    resources. Blueprints and planning that lacks flexibility in implementation
                    generally don't work.</p>
                <p>Let me mention another reason that outsiders have repeated difficulty with local
                    action. There was an economist named F.A. Hayek, who was one of the most
                    articulate enemies of central planners and vice versa back in the '40s and '50s.
                    Hayek had a little paragraph in one of his articles that is profound, once you
                    think about it. It was this: to carry out local action you need time and place
                    information. That is, information about what is going on here, in our town, in
                    our rural district. Time and place information is almost always inaccessible to
                    central planners or bureaucrats in the capital city, and that is a primary
                    reason that central planning or design doesn't work in local development. I
                    think it's a very powerful idea and puts a little different spin on the problem.
                    Hayek's criticisms were generally valid, and central planning of the kind he was
                    criticizing has been abandoned in most places in the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>Another factor is that participatory local organizations are needed to reliably
                    mobilize local resources. That's important because otherwise the work can't be
                    sustained. It's easy to find rural development projects where donors came in
                    with generous resources for the environments they were working in and made
                    things go for two years or five years. But the real question was, once those
                    exceptional external resources are withdrawn, what happens? Unless some
                    mechanisms have been established that provide for local mobilization and
                    prudent, parsimonious use of local resources, sustainability is going to be dead
                    every time.The Local Revenue Project</p>
                <p>The issue of mobilizing local resources takes us to a project we had with
                    Syracuse University for several years called Local Revenue Administration. The
                    project lasted about 10 years, from the mid-1970s to the late 1980s. Missions
                    around the world, such as Bangladesh, Chad, and Guatemala, called on the project
                    to send analysts and researchers from Syracuse to help find out what it would
                    take to mobilize local revenue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is one of the projects that you initiated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, elaborate on that. What did the project do, what
                        were some of the techniques? What were they recommending in their work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Syracuse University's Maxwell School has long been ranked in the very
                    top ranks of public administration programs among U.S. universities. It
                    developed special strength in public finance economics, and substantial
                    experience with international work. So it was a long-term resource that proved
                    very useful to AID. I think not only the continuity but also the knowledge base,
                    which was solidly grounded in the Maxwell School and grew from one study to
                    another, provided a very sound basis for supporting quality field work.</p>
                <p>We knew we could deliver very capable people to conduct those studies and also to
                    put them in the context of public finance economics, accepted by the World Bank,
                    regional development banks, and Ministers of Finance. The Syracuse people were
                    well connected to the network of public finance economists in those institutions
                    and in other U.S. and Canadian universities. The leaders of the project were,
                    first, Roy Bahl and then Larry Schroeder. We had a succession of contracts and
                    amendments, which were centrally funded at first, and later funded predominantly
                    by missions which wanted country studies of local revenue systems. So in over a
                    dozen different countries, the Syracuse people provided excellent local revenue
                    studies that were well received by the missions that had sponsored them.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to talk about the substance of this now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. Collecting local revenue cannot be separated from the system in
                    which it is being generated. In almost all countries around the world a major
                    source of revenue for local units is the central government budget. As soon as
                    you start talking about local revenue, you are also talking about relationships
                    between the national government and the local government. You are talking about
                    revenue sharing. You are talking about whether or not the local authorities have
                    taxing and spending power without going back to the center to get everything
                    approved.</p>
                <p>Now these are fairly complex systems and they are the reason that it is
                    essential, in my opinion, to have an experienced public finance economist
                    involved in analysis of revenue systems. Projects that try to focus on local tax
                    collection divorced from considerations of revenue sharing by the center, or
                    relationships with the Ministry of Finance, are tactical, not strategic. They
                    have not happened too often but when they do, it is often a mistake. You have to
                    deal with the systemic relationship between central revenue and its managers,
                    and local revenue and its managers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But why was the subject of local revenue generation fairly
                        narrow? Why was that selected as being important and then last such a long
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I would say simply the demand schedule. As soon as a field mission,
                    whether it be in the Philippines, or a small African country or Jamaica, begins
                    talking about a decentralization effort or giving more power to the cities or
                    maintaining local roads, whatever the problem set may be, they come up with the
                    fact that there has to be a revenue flow to provide for those functions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: So while the demand schedule shifted from one place to another at
                    two-year intervals, it persisted. There was enough business to use this
                    established resource to mount new field studies as the missions became
                    interested and were willing to pay for them.</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>They started with the reality that in most countries, developed or undeveloped,
                    much of the revenue allocated for local use comes from the center. Revenue
                    sharing is a fact of life and local jurisdictions need that revenue partly
                    because the mechanisms of taxation controlled by central governments produce a
                    more robust cash flow and it's harder both administratively and politically to
                    produce a robust cash flow from local sources. Okay, then, how can you assure
                    that that flow will be regularized? Partly that's a matter of central government
                    policy; it might even be a constitutional provision that there is some
                    percentage of revenue sharing with localities. Guatemala moved in that direction
                    in its reforms of the last ten years.</p>
                <p>That does not mean that local revenue is not also important. So the Syracuse work
                    helped identify what the more productive and readily-administered options for
                    local revenue are. It is sometimes property taxation, though administration of
                    property taxes is not simple. Idepends a lot on the ability of local authorities
                    to equitably appraise the current value of property. Of course they have to have
                    the authority, which some local governments around the world don't have, to tax
                    property. But if they can tax property, and if they can assign and enforce
                    valuations of the property, then they are in a much better position to have one
                    reliable revenue source.</p>
                <p>Local business taxes. Value added taxes. Local sales taxes, like Virginia which
                    has a State sales tax, and then the localities can add one or two percent. In
                    Zaire, fuel taxes were a robust source of money, which in that case were
                    allocated to national road maintenance. It would be possible, of course, to say
                    that 80 percent of the fuel taxes go toward centrally administered road
                    maintenance, and 20 percent go to locally administered road maintenance.</p>
                <p>In studying road maintenance the Syracuse people almost came to abandon their
                    usual principle that you put tax money from various sources in one pot and then
                    allocate it rationally to essential governmental functions. They found that road
                    maintenance is such an important government function that earmarking might be
                    justified. One simple, direct way of assuring a robust flow of revenue for road
                    maintenance is fuel tax earmarking. So, at any rate, the work was to study
                    systems of taxation; the relationship of central taxes and revenues and
                    allocation to local needs and the prospects and alternative means of raising
                    local revenue for local purposes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you do when in most of these developing countries
                        in the rural areas and in the villages, they are so poor you wonder whether
                        they have any money at all. How can they be paying taxes, or is there some
                        other approach to that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>KORNHER: One of the approaches is revenue sharing. But I think another one is to
                    realize, and we learned this from Akhter Hameed Khan, in East Pakistan (later
                    Bangladesh) back in the '60s, that however poor a family or a village may be, it
                    is always possible to save something, or to mobilize some resources. Even the
                    rickshaw puller can save a rupee a month for a hundred months, and buy his own
                    rickshaw. So the question becomes where is the money flowing in local villages
                    that could be tapped, and is the intended public use sufficiently important to
                    justify taxation of poor, or relatively poor people? It may be a modest tax on
                    businesses, and the more prosperous the business, the more robust the revenue.
                    We are not talking about large projects or large sums from taxation, rather
                    about how to maintain the village market, or how to get the streets in the
                    village to drain. Very practical, local things that people value.</p>
                <p>Let me give you an example from Egypt. One of the governors discovered that the
                    method of sewage disposal in the villages was very costly, messy and
                    inefficient. They had cesspools, which were periodically pumped out by trucks,
                    and the effluent hauled away for disposal. It was relatively costly, and the
                    people had to pay for this themselves. So some local leaders developed
                    small-scale waste water and sewage disposal systems. They implemented this
                    through an informal system in which village leaders would go around and say,
                    “Look, we want to change the system, but if we do you and all your neighbors are
                    going to have to pay so much a month. It will probably turn out to be less than
                    trucking away your waste, but everyone has to do it.” And they did, and most
                    people were satisfied with this changed structure of sewage disposal. So it is
                    partly a question of identifying local needs that people are willing and able to
                    pay for and then setting up a locally enforceable system to collect the fees or
                    taxes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the principle in this for control of the money?
                        When you raise it from local communities, I know, in some situations the
                        money goes back to the Ministry of Finance, and so on. What is the principle
                        that relates to managing the raising of tax income?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: First, local governments need authority to levy and use revenues that
                    don't have to go back to the central government. Second, in every effective
                    management structure, you have to have some kind of accountability. I think
                    there are lessons in the Sahel Financial Management effort. That is, don't make
                    it too elaborate. Make it transparent, practical, simple.</p>
                <p>If local people know how their money is being used, and ideally they should even
                    have the right to look at the books to confirm it, thievery is going to be
                    seriously reduced. But people have to know what accountability and bookkeeping
                    are, there have to be political and moral constraints on local authorities so
                    they won't give the contract to their buddies every time, not to siphon ten
                    percent off the top and so on. And it is not an easy problem. USAID is
                    sponsoring anti-corruption efforts in Latin America, and has done so for some
                    years. The World Bank appears to be getting more interested in anti-corruption
                    efforts as well. But there are no easy answers to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But what you're implying is that the management of local
                        revenue generation is local, the resources don't flow back to central
                        authorities and then are allocated out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. The usual workable system of local revenue is to combine revenue
                    sharing by the central government with revenue raised and kept locally. But that
                    raises additional questions. Is the system transparent? To what extent ought the
                    central government to audit the books of local authorities, what kind of
                    reporting mechanisms are necessary, what kind of sanctions for misuse of the
                    money? I think, most experts in finance would say that, yes, there should be
                    some kinds of central government auditing and oversight, and that is justified
                    not only by the revenue that comes from the center, but also by enforcing
                    accountability for local funds. Am I answering your question?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right. Well, it's a question of changing the role of the
                        central government in part from one of managing money and allocating it out,
                        and having it spent by agencies of the central government, to overseeing
                        responsible local administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: That's a good way to put it. In other words, don't prescribe in as much
                    detail how money is to be used, or don't think you have to hire central
                    government staff to perform village service functions. Instead, think of giving
                    matching grants to the villages to provide the services in their own way, but
                    with inspection of the books to be sure it is properly spent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And including, though, the local revenue that is generated
                        locally. Where do the central program services fit into this situation? How
                        do they relate to the fact that each village has their own pot of money that
                        they are managing? Where do the ag people, the health people, and so on, and
                        education people, fit into that structure?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Another thing that Hayek said is that local people need to handle time
                    and place information; central people are better equipped to handle scientific
                    information. You don't ask the local people to handle agricultural research,
                    though the researchers have to understand on-farm requirements. If you are
                    trying to develop a new breed of maize to serve several parts of the country, it
                    makes sense to do that through a central agency or organization. Perhaps the
                    Ministry of Agriculture or a university, or contracting out. In education, if
                    you want to supply standard textbooks to all the elementary schools in the
                    country, it doesn't make sense to have each jurisdiction do that [itself]. But
                    it makes a lot of sense for the individual jurisdiction to arrange housing for
                    the teacher. So, one approach to deciding what can and ought to be done
                    centrally or what can and ought to be done locally, is to apply that criterion
                    of time and place information, versus scientific information. Another is to ask
                    if there are economies of scale in the provision of a particular good or
                    service. Another is to simply ask practical questions about who can get this
                    done most effectively.</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>Often the central ministries overreach themselves. They aspire to get down and
                    organize the villagers, or help the individual farmer and they can't do that
                    effectively for two reasons. They don't have the local information and
                    experience, and they don't have the money.</p>
                <p>Take road maintenance again. It makes a lot of sense to maintain trunk roads by
                    central agencies, because you need heavy equipment, sometimes asphalt. You're
                    working on a large number of kilometers of road, and it's a technical task that
                    can be centrally administered, if you don't have someone stealing the money. On
                    the other hand, local roads in most poor countries cover such vast territory
                    that there is no way that central agencies can maintain them. You have to have
                    very low cost routines that keep them passable, but not aspire to maintain
                    highway standards or pavement, or anything like that. It turns out, when you go
                    out to muck around with local road maintenance, the biggest factor is drainage.
                    If rural dirt roads are well drained, they are useable. And if they're not,
                    they're not. And local people can handle drainage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Was there any other part of the Syracuse project
                        that...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: One more thing. We always used our projects as flexible vehicles for
                    constructive change. We didn't pay too much attention to boundaries and labels.
                    So I was very pleased that one of our local revenue projects became a reform
                    project.</p>
                <p>Roy Bahl, at Syracuse, had been working on local revenue problems in Jamaica,
                    with the Revenue Board there. And he hit it off very well with the Jamaicans
                    managing the Board and they began to tell him their real problems with national
                    taxation, as well as local taxation. So, in the late 1980s they came up with the
                    idea of reforming their entire national revenue system. Of course, Jamaica is a
                    small country, but, still, this was much more than local revenue.</p>
                <p>We provided a few pieces of help in formulating what they might like to do
                    through our project and through Jamaican Mission funding. But then we faced a
                    bigger issue. These relations of confidence had been established by Roy Bahl and
                    the Syracuse people. Now if the Mission wanted to support a significant reform,
                    and they decided they did, do you put it out for open competition? And the
                    Mission — very wisely, in my opinion, decided no, this is working, let's not
                    stir it up. Let's make it work with the actors that already have confidence in
                    each other. So they gave an exclusive contract to Syracuse to carry through the
                    reform with the Jamaican revenue reforms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were allowed not to compete it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, and it worked. It worked very well, because there were relations of
                    confidence between the Revenue Board and the Syracuse people. The work included
                    all the implementation, the computer processing of tax information, the
                    relationship to auditing, and so on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Over what period of time did this take?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: This was about a three year period. Probably something like 1986 to
                    1989.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't that long?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Interesting. Good example. Are there other examples that
                        come to mind?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: It's sometimes difficult to judge the intermediate term results of local
                    revenue efforts, partly because the first phase is simply finding out what is
                    going on. Is the existing authority for local revenue sufficient to do the
                    things that local jurisdictions are supposed to do and want to do? The countries
                    themselves—the Ministries of Finance—often don't know, or at least don't think
                    very much about what is going on in local collection of revenue. They're too
                    busy dealing with national budget deficits and the complaints of the ministries,
                    and the latest IMF package.</p>
                <p>Take Egypt for example. The United States spent billions on decentralized
                    activities in Egypt, which consisted of a lot of village projects and programs,
                    cold storage for agricultural products, fire trucks, and enterprises where local
                    women could sew clothing and hopefully market them. But it was only when Don
                    Wadley got there in about 1986 or so that he and the Mission began to ask, what
                    are the policy bases for sustaining this work in rural jurisdictions? And there
                    wasn't much basis for sustainability.</p>
                <p>Local project development was marginally illegal. There was no property taxation.
                    So for the first time USAID began to urge the Ministry of Finance and the
                    Cabinet Secretariat to think about whether the authorities of the governorates
                    (units of the central government) were adequate or not. Clearly they weren't.
                    I've lost the thread of that story, because I was last out there in '87 and '88,
                    and Wadley left thereafter, and the local government program declined in
                    emphasis. But there were at least, I'm aware, some discussions by the Cabinet
                    Secretariat and a contract team that worked on public finance issues, including
                    the relationship of local needs to national needs.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>The point I was making is that you have to find out what is going on in local
                    taxation and the relationship of local to national taxation. You have to have
                    willingness in the country to permit local authorities to collect revenue and to
                    allocate it to needs decided on locally, with central oversight on
                    accountability.</p>
                <p>I remember talking with Syracuse people about revenue collections in Latin
                    America. A lot of Latin American cities have the authority to collect property
                    taxes, for example. But they don't necessarily use that authority, or they set
                    very low rates for political reasons. And there is a lot of variance. Some
                    mayors say we need to do this and we've got to pay for it so you need to pay
                    taxes. Others say, I won't be re-elected if I collect property taxes, so I
                    don't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's universal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: There were two additional projects that came down the road in 1987 and
                    1990, one called “Decentralization: Finance and Management,” and one called
                    “Implementing Policy Change.” Let's take decentralization first.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, let's go to those.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Rethinking decentralization</p>
                <p>KORNHER: In the mid-'80s, we did a lot of work in the Office, then called Rural
                    and Institutional Development, on the state-of-the-art in decentralization. The
                    traditional definitions of decentralization include apples and oranges - both
                    administrative decentralization of central services and autonomous local
                    government. Some clear thinking was needed that didn't rely on confusing,
                    contradictory definitions.</p>
                <p>The Local Revenue project was in my division. Another division funded studies by
                    the University of Wisconsin and the University of California at Berkeley, under
                    a project called Managing Decentralization. We began to pay more attention to
                    functions and incentives. What functions should central government be
                    responsible for, and why? What functions should go to local governments, and
                    why. What incentives are operating in local resource mobilization, service
                    delivery, corruption or “rent seeking,” and what action could be taken? Do local
                    governments lack the authority to tax and spend? Why do they sometimes ignore
                    the powers they do have to mobilize revenue and improve important local
                    services? What alternative ways are there of getting things done through
                    contracting out or through NGOs or businesses, or public-private partnerships.
                    Under what conditions should these mechanisms be used? In other words, it was a
                    rethinking of local action, administrative decentralization and local
                    governance.</p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>Some of us in the Office, notably including Norm Nicholson and Ed Connerley,
                    began to take a look at disciplines in addition to public administration and the
                    organizational sciences that would tell us something about why local governance
                    did or didn't work. This had to be a multidisciplinary effort. Public
                    administration and development economics were relevant, but not sufficient. You
                    had to put some additional perspectives in the mix.</p>
                <p>What we gradually put together was public finance economics, especially as it
                    treated mobilization and use of local revenue, including both revenue shared by
                    the central government and [revenue] collected and retained locally. Second,
                    political science, asking whether local people have voice and choice in getting
                    things done through public mechanisms and whether the constitution, laws and
                    rules permit and encourage local action. Third, political economy, dealing
                    realistically with the incentives (including corruption and “rent seeking”)
                    presented by existing formal and informal rules, and by the interaction of
                    politics, governance, and administration. And fourth, an understanding of the
                    dynamics of specific functions of local governance. Education functions are
                    different [from] health functions or housing functions or agricultural or
                    transportation functions. Truly understanding the dynamic of specific local
                    governance functions requires extensive disaggregation and an extensive
                    understanding of local “time and place” information.</p>
                <p>If you want to maintain local roads, does the local unit, whether it be a
                    province or a city, have the authority to do it, or are you relying on a
                    national bureau of roads? What are the characteristics and patterns of use of
                    the local road? Are local people willing to pay taxes or tolls for road
                    maintenance? If taxes, should they come out of a pool of public resources or
                    should they be linked to, say, a fuel tax, which is earmarked specifically for
                    road maintenance.</p>
                <p>Some of us came to the conclusion that further interdisciplinary research was
                    going to be needed to get a better grip on the relationship between central,
                    intermediate, and local institutions and functions involved in local governance.
                    So in 1987 I convened a very able and enthusiastic project committee of regional
                    bureau and central bureau people, and located some missions that were
                    interested. I borrowed Ed Connerley from the NASPAA Cooperative Agreement to
                    help with design work and contracted some field work to Associates in Rural
                    Development. The objective was to design a serious framework-building and
                    research project. We called it Decentralization, Finance and Management. Now
                    that title does not tell you that this is a research project. Even though we had
                    strong support in the regional bureaus and a couple of Missions, it is not
                    usually wise to launch a central bureau project which is tilted too much toward
                    research. But this project was definitely research.</p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>The contract was won by Associates in Rural Development, teamed with Syracuse and
                    with Indiana University's Workshop on Political Theory and Policy Analysis. The
                    project set out first to create a framework for analysis and understanding, and
                    second to look at what really happens in two kinds of local resource
                    mobilization linked to specific functions. Missions we had canvassed were
                    interested in road maintenance and irrigation, so those became the functions to
                    be examined in depth.</p>
                <p>Issues on public choice theory and practice</p>
                <p>The first field research focused on irrigation in Asia and the findings were
                    quite interesting. Eleanor Ostrom at Indiana used many cases because she
                    believed that the case method most researchers used, that is, to study two or
                    three cases and then draw conclusions from them, is very likely to be invalid or
                    unreliable. So she took scores of cases and extracted factors in the success of
                    local irrigation projects. She found that the small irrigation projects, like
                    those in Nepal, were generally very successful. They mobilize tremendous
                    resources in time, labor, and collaboration from local farmers. I guess this
                    should be obvious because their livelihood depends on it.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, large-scale, bureaucratically organized irrigation schemes
                    tend to be inefficient, even ineffective. This poses a dilemma. If bureaucratic
                    forms of management don't do the job for local people, then you either have to
                    figure out how to make the bureaucratic form of service and resource
                    mobilization work, or you have to give up on the possibility of economies of
                    scale. Let the local people do their own thing, in their own way, and try to
                    figure out ways to help them around the edges. And subsidies, if any, have to be
                    very carefully crafted, because it's easy to destroy the existing incentives for
                    farm families to do things for themselves.</p>
                <p>The research in this project, I think, left us with these kinds of dilemmas.
                    There are certain kinds of public goods that you almost have to provide through
                    some type of government and bureaucratic mechanism. One good example is road
                    maintenance. The economic benefits are obvious. The utility to local people is
                    obvious. But bureaucratic forms of administration are tough to make work. Even
                    contracting out is only a partial answer. It's difficult to avoid corruption.
                    It's difficult to create incentives for the workers to get the potholes filled
                    promptly. Its difficult to get local people to pay for the local maintenance and
                    to find the best revenue mechanisms and so on. So there were no quick fixes
                    discovered in this project. There were some new analytic tools developed, that
                    are important, like public choice theory which helps us to understand what is a
                    public function and what is a private function.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did you think about the public choice theory
                        approach?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think it's helpful. Not necessarily in the esoteric form that some
                    academics like to use it. But it does calls attention to some very important and
                    practical questions.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Are these specific goods that are being provided by government public
                    goods that are available to everyone, like a streetlight, or are they goods that
                    are used only by some, like a toll good? If you go to a movie theater and pay
                    for a ticket to see the movie, that's a toll. If you have a toll road that you
                    use for a fee, that's a toll good. You can control access, you can charge for
                    the benefit, and you can maintain and continue the service based on the toll
                    revenues. Or is something else a private good, like a loaf of bread, where if
                    you pay for it, you consume it, and nobody else is involved?</p>
                <p>Now that form of analysis permits us to ask whether the city of Potesti in
                    Romania really ought to have a [government] bakery or not. And the answer is
                    simple - no. Because bread is a private good and it is both unnecessary and
                    inefficient to have the government involved in the provision of private goods.
                    Whether a local government should help poor people pay for bread is a separate
                    question, but if the answer is yes, the good can still be produced by a private
                    bakery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But how do you deal with a movie theater, which is a
                        somewhat private business. Where does that fall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: That's an example of a toll good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The toll road can be private?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Toll roads can go either way. One advantage of private toll roads is
                    that the taxpayers don't have to put up the capital or assume the risks. There's
                    a privately funded toll road here in Northern Virginia from the Dulles area to
                    Leesburg. So far it's not producing enough revenue. Entrepreneurs assumed the
                    risks because they thought they could make money on the venture. Even though
                    they are wrong so far, they may be doing well 10 years from now if the increased
                    traffic on other routes makes people willing to pay for the time they will save
                    by using the toll road.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about utility services? Where do they fit?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>KORNHER: That's a toll good. There are arguments for public involvement in
                    provision of utility services, and our thinking, even here in the United States,
                    is still evolving as to how much public involvement. Some consumers are confused
                    and annoyed at the number of telephone service providers and the many
                    telemarketing calls from alternative service providers. At the same time, our
                    costs as consumers are dropping, so that confirms that competition is having an
                    effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But where does the issue of competition come into this
                        picture? Certainly the bread is a private good and so on. You can have
                        competitive situations in some of these other services. In toll roads you
                        can't have a competition. Where does that fit into public choice?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The theory assumes competition in the production and sale of private
                    goods. The more difficult issue is whether competition to produce more
                    efficiency can be used for toll goods or public goods. In the U.S. we are
                    probably not thinking enough about competition in modes of transportation; we
                    have a fixation on roads. We are struggling with the issue of how to provide
                    effective competition in the provision of utilities. We have competition in
                    telephone service to a good extent, but in electric power, its just beginning.
                    Thnew mechanisms of competition require sophisticated forms of regulation to
                    assure a level playing field. There are natural monopoly issues with
                    distribution services, such as cable TV and power lines. In developing countries
                    there are policy formulation and implementation and other administrative
                    capacity issues. Competition has costs, as well as benefits. I'm not at all sure
                    that a small country ought to try to provide extensive competition in the
                    provision of electrical services. They might be better off to work very hard on
                    sound regulation of national or regional monopoly private utilities or an
                    efficient government utility, so consumers have reliable service, rather than
                    worrying too much about competition. Maybe later, after the bigger countries
                    have found formulas for competition that clearly work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the evolution of this project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: The project lasted for seven years and moved from laying out a framework
                    for analysis and case studies to comparative conclusions in irrigation and road
                    maintenance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the use of this project?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>KORNHER: The research products were delivered, and a number of Missions,
                    especially in Asia, sponsored studies of irrigation and road maintenance and
                    other local services. I am not aware what actions were taken by the Missions as
                    a result of the findings. In fact, my design for the project originally was at
                    least 14 years: seven years of finding out what to do and why, and developing
                    clients, perhaps Ministers of Finance in a couple of progressive countries, and
                    then, about seven years of an effort to help the client countries change the way
                    they deal with certain critical functions like irrigation, roads, or schools.
                    But the second phase of the project never happened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Probably because there was no champion or coalition to support
                    continuance in USAID.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Bureaus were not supportive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Not enough. You see, Bureaus, like everyone else in USAID, had been
                    faced with declining resources and tough tradeoffs. It is probably very
                    difficult for them to support a project that is on the research end of the
                    spectrum, even though it is linked to the field and ready for more pragmatic
                    action.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have thought that experimentation would have been
                        given some real practical utility. But they weren't supportive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I don't know the details of what happened. I only know the project was
                    not continued.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Remember as well that what had been the Research and Development Bureau
                    was abolished and the new Global Bureau Centers were created. The Center for
                    Democracy and Governance inherited some of the former projects, but had
                    different priorities. There were a lot of discontinuities in the view of what
                    should be done with declining levels of money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Implementing Policy Change project</p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>KORNHER: I was very pleased that one of the projects that did get continued was
                    Implementing Policy Change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you want to turn to that now?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: That's the last project I want to talk about.</p>
                <p>A very important thing happened in AID doctrine in the Reagan years, starting
                    about 1981. That was that political and policy interventions became an
                    acceptable part of USAID's agenda. We saw that in local revenue, for example,
                    because we used to talk about local revenue administration, not reform, and we
                    did that because AID senior management believed that the political questions
                    around reform were too sensitive to confront, so we'd work on
                    administration.</p>
                <p>Suddenly in 1981 economic policy reform became not only acceptable, but the thing
                    to try. That was one of the reasons that we were able to do the Jamaica tax
                    reform that I spoke of earlier. So NASPAA sponsored, with Jeanne North's and my
                    support, some probes into policy change. And the Missions were quite supportive
                    of that. For example, we got some money from the Honduras Mission for studies of
                    contracting out versus government production of services. We also worked with
                    two or three African Missions. We did some think pieces of our own and talked to
                    World Bank people and others about the issues with policy change.</p>
                <p>One of the things we came up with was that after economic choices are made you
                    will have the problem of organizing and implementing the organizational changes
                    needed to produce the intended outcomes. And so that fairly simple, but
                    important, idea lay behind the project that Jeanne North and Pat Isman, with
                    some help from NASPAA (especially Wendell Schaeffer), used in designing the
                    Implementing Policy Change project.</p>
                <p>In addition, the African Bureau was extremely supportive of it and provided some
                    money for pilot work even before the project got authorized. Management Systems
                    International won the contract, and the renewal. The project has continued for
                    eight years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your understanding of the core idea behind that
                        project?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>KORNHER: I believe there are three main ideas. The first is that most policy
                    decisions are not self-implementing, that it is necessary to move from policy
                    decisions to follow-up actions in order to assure that the intended benefits of
                    the change are actually realized. A change in official interest rates may come
                    close to being self-implementing. But that kind of change is the exception. For
                    example, a policy change such as Poland's decision a few years ago to transfer
                    responsibility for elementary education from central to local governments is
                    certainly not self-implementing. Indeed, it illustrates how a broad policy
                    change will require further decisions about linked policies, such as whether
                    teachers are to become local government employees or not. So the first idea is
                    working on the required follow-up actions after the policy decision is made.</p>
                <p>The second idea is that the approach and techniques represented by strategic
                    management can be very useful in the process of defining and accomplishing the
                    necessary follow-on actions.The third idea is that involving the stakeholders
                    affected by a policy change in the follow-up process (and, better, in the
                    original decision too) can ameliorate conflicts and increase the probability
                    that the constructive purpose s of the change will be achieved. A corollary of
                    this third point is that successful policy change has to be a host country
                    enterprise; it is something a donor may facilitate, but not do.</p>
                <p>I'm sure Jeanne could say it better and probably come up with a couple of other
                    important principles, but those three are certainly among them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the subject areas that implementing policy
                        change activities focused on? It's neutral in that sense, and I assume can
                        be applied anywhere in any sector or in any kind of policy, pretty much.
                        Where was it mostly focused?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: You are right, the methods are relevant to many different kinds of
                    policy. The specifics differed in each one of the 45 or so countries that the
                    project has worked with, mainlin Africa, but also in Haiti, Jamaica, El
                    Salvador, and Costa Rica, among others. One problem that was important in the
                    project's early activities in Africa was that economic reform policies moving
                    from a more socialist economy toward a more capitalist economy at first produced
                    serious adverse consequences for poor people. You can certainly see that
                    happening in Russia today. So, an important question in some of the work was
                    what to do to ameliorate hardships the policy change imposed on disadvantaged
                    groups. Later on, a good deal of the work in the Southern Africa and West Africa
                    regions related to relationships between governments and business enterprises,
                    specifically to government policies affecting the climate for in-country
                    business development and inter-country trade. In West Africa the project
                    supported the activities of the West African Enterprise Institute which helped
                    represent the needs and interests of business enterprises in dialogues with
                    governments of the region. In addition to work for similar purposes in East
                    Africa, the project helped facilitate the coordination of mutually beneficial
                    transportation policies among eight countries of Southern Africa.</p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But your presumption would be that you would have to
                        involve representation of the poor community in the process to get them to
                        be part of the decision to go that route?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes, involved in a way that provides for continuing two-way flows of
                    information. If the government can convince people that there is going to be a
                    lot of pain for one year, but a lot of benefits after that, it is easier to gain
                    acceptance than if they don't see the benefits coming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything more on that project?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: No. It was clearly a successful project, well received by the missions
                    and countries it has served. In fact a contract with Management Systems, Inc.,
                    is still active today, nine years after the original contract was signed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you want to proceed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The publications program</p>
                <p>KORNHER: The final thing I'd like to talk about is the publications program. I
                    think one of the strengths of the offices I worked for through these years, and
                    my division, is that we made a serious effort to get the word out in terms of
                    ideas, approaches, methods, and lessons of field experience. That was a
                    commitment of the entire Office. It was true in the micro enterprise division,
                    it was true in the urban, regional and rural development divisions, and it was
                    true with my division. It was easier to do because a lot of our work was with
                    universities and university people have career incentives to write, to
                    publish.</p>
                <p>In the Institutional Development and Management Division we took advantage of
                    that by devising a strategy of not trying to get out the longer technical
                    publications ourselves, but rather to get them distributed as journal articles,
                    conference papers, published books. Therefore, we didn't have to worry about
                    whether or not it would be lost in the archives or in fugitive materials that
                    nobody would ever find. Publications were often in the form of books, which we
                    subsidized, but to which the writers contributed a lot of their own time and
                    effort. It served their purpose nicely and it served our purpose nicely.</p>
                <p>Across the office, I never made a specific count, but certainly in a 20 year
                    period there must have been 60 books, a hundred good journal articles, 100
                    conference papers, and so on. I've already talked quite a bit about the
                    Rondinelli book, which provides some nice background and context as well as
                    specific descriptions of some of our projects. Let me mention just two or three
                    more.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>David Korten, who worked for NASPAA in the mid '80s, did a lot of writing on
                    learning process approaches and on people-centered development. One product was
                    a book is a book by Korten and the NASPAA Project Director, Rudy Klauss, an
                    edited volume of good pieces collected from various sources on people-centered
                    development. That was put out by Kumarian Press, whicspecializes in development
                    and development management books and gave us a pretty good deal on subsidized
                    publication of the books we sponsored.</p>
                <p>Another one, and this is a theme I have not emphasized enough in our discussion,
                    is management training. We had a project in management training. Then John
                    Kerrigan and Jeff Luke, for NASPAA, did a nice volume on management training
                    strategies for developing countries which covered approaches, assessing training
                    needs, and training methods. It was just a good overview of how to approach
                    management training.</p>
                <p>A third book was by Derick Brinkerhoff. This one was put out in the Lynn Rhiner
                    series. It wacalled Improving Development Program Performance, Guidelines for
                    Managers. This book was published in 1991, and provides an overview of the
                    thinking and experience that NASPAA mobilized in its program management work. It
                    also has an extensive bibliography.</p>
                <p>So these illustrate the extensive publications program. We succeeded, I think, in
                    documenting a lot of this work and therefore it remains available. I will
                    include in my written version of this session a list of many of the books that
                    my Division sponsored. And each of the books, in turn, has a bibliography or
                    reference list.</p>
                <p>We used to say in the old days, “AID doesn't have a memory bank.” Indeed it does
                    nowadays. The program you implemented in the Center for Development Information
                    and Evaluation provided the overall framework, and did - still does - a fine job
                    of synthesizing and publishing lessons of field experience. In addition to that,
                    the technical offices of the central bureaus and the regional bureaus and
                    missions have produced and distributed a great many publications, so that there
                    are many sources of good literature available to the public to find out what
                    USAID has done and what we have learned about international development
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Were there any special initiatives on how to get the
                        learning and lessons from these studies and books into the developing
                        country environments?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>KORNHER: We did not emphasize that as an in-house function. We did encourage our
                    contractors and cooperators to publish newsletters. CDIE does a lot of good work
                    on distribution and utilization. I guess our attitude has been that if good
                    things are published, people all over the world will find them. That is not
                    necessarily true; but I have been very pleased about the eagerness with which
                    scholars, government executives, management consultants and directors of
                    training institutes, and so on have gained access to the current literature,
                    used it, and carried it forward. At conferences of the United Nations, the
                    Society for International Development, the American Society for Public
                    Administration, I see people from all over the world who know as much about
                    this, or more, than we have been able to discover in years of work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did mention that, I guess, some of the regions put on
                        workshops in their country using this material. Is that correct? Where was
                        that happening mostly?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, I remember, for example, the Pan African Institute for Development
                    in the Cameroon had workshops. The African Center for development administration
                    in Tangier used to have frequent conferences. The annual conferences of the
                    American Society for Public Administration draw a lot of international
                    attendance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Based on a lot of this material?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. Our university people, and some USAID people, were on panels and
                    presented papers. The conference panels and papers draw on studies and cases
                    from all over the world. I don't know to what extent international technical
                    conferences are attended or supported by USAID these days. They certainly are
                    continuing under United Nations, development association, and professional
                    association auspices. When I was still with USAID, attendance of USAID staff was
                    criticized from time to time, and it became difficult to get travel money for
                    direct-hire staff to attend. Like anything, it can be overdone, but I always
                    found occasional attendance at such conferences stimulating and operationally
                    relevant.</p>
                <p>Concluding observations on development management and USAID</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling about the receptivity to these ideas
                        within the Agency and in the Missions? Of course it depends on the projects,
                        and you talked about many of them that were used by the Missions, but, in
                        general what was your feeling about the receptivity to development
                        management practices and policies?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>KORNHER: It was something that you always had to work on. People are very busy,
                    and they tend to ignore ideas they are not familiar with. Utilization of
                    development management ideas, approaches, and methods often arises from a form
                    of team building. Utilization improves as we learn better how to do our work, as
                    we learn to build collaboration among people and offices in Washington, and as
                    we learn to extend that collaboration to Missions, where you find someone with
                    some work to do who needs some help to do it, and respects your ability to help
                    whether directly or through intermediaries. So it became kind of modus operandi
                    over time to involve regional bureau people and Mission people in the planning
                    and the implementation of these efforts. I think everybody benefited from that
                    kind of working together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have a sense in general, or maybe in specific,
                        where some of the results, findings, conclusions of these projects over the
                        period of years, have permeated the thinking of practitioners of development
                        that they sort of became the conventional wisdom of the time, or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I think that's a continuing job, because each generation of development
                    people learns things partly from formal and self-education and partly the hard
                    way. There is a real question as to how fully, and in what ways, the next
                    generation picks up that hard-earned experience. I believe that's part of your
                    mission here in the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training, namely, to
                    make available a lot of the experience that can be picked up by new people so
                    they won't have to learn as much the hard way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure. But my thought was, and maybe this is too difficult
                        to pin down, because it gets kind of diffuse. Do you have a sense, in
                        picking any one of the concepts or ideas that was behind the results of this
                        work, that now is common knowledge or is being applied as accepted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. It's a little bit difficult to judge, and I don't want to be too
                    optimistic, but I think, yes. For example, I think anyone going through a
                    business school in the Dominican Republic, or certainly to INCAE in Central
                    America, or to a public administration institute in Korea or Brazil, is going to
                    be exposed to many of these ideas which we have been working on and contributing
                    to. But, we have to be modest. These aren't our patented ideas; they are ideas
                    that belong to many writers and university people and operators around the
                    world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but they were stimulated or encouraged, facilitated,
                        by your work.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Yes. I think, for example, that the ideas of a project cycle and of not
                    just planning things, but implementing them, which may seem obvious but happened
                    only over time, are now very widely accepted in part because we kept pushing
                    them. The ideas of sectoral management, systems of action, institutional
                    development, action training, learning process, strategic management, program
                    management, involving country stakeholders, are used more often because we kept
                    using them and selling them to others in USAID, other donor, and professional
                    circles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any other dimensions to that, you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I'm also encouraged about the continuing search for new knowledge. I
                    said before that I think development assistance has to be knowledge-based to be
                    effective. So building the knowledge base is a continuing challenge. A great
                    many people in recent years have gotten interested in political economy, the new
                    institutional economics, and public finance economics. I think these are
                    powerful tools for continuing an expansion of our knowledge about how
                    development and development management work. Some of the frameworks are a bit
                    too esoteric for field operations, but some of them are very practical.</p>
                <p>For example, one of the core ideas of political economy is that people do things
                    because they are in their interest. Norm Uphoff at Cornell might say that's
                    terribly reductionist if you carry it all the way. But still it leads you to ask
                    what incentives are affecting the countries and sectors and organizations and
                    individuals we are working with. Is an official in a poor country corrupt
                    because he wants to make a lot of money or because he can't make ends meet
                    without accepting payoffs? Realistic questions like that. So I think, yes, a lot
                    of the things we have worked on over the years are now well known and well
                    accepted, and new ones are coming down the pike.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is your feeling about the current acceptance of
                        development management, the subject area, and the focus point, among the
                        development community?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, one way to measure that is to ask whether, as USAID support
                    declines, other organizations are picking them up, using and advancing some of
                    these approaches? The World Bank definitely is. The Bank has emphasized
                    organizational capacity building in recent years. One of the editions of the
                    World Development Report, in 1984, was focused on development management. The
                    Bank has continued to pay much attention to a wide range of development
                    management issues, including those we were working on . So I am quite hopeful. I
                    don't think these arts and sciences are going to get lost, because I think they
                    are such a fundamental part of international development work.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>For public administration more traditionally defined, there is still a good deal
                    of skepticism as to whether the benefits of programs exceed the cost. I think
                    that skepticism is good, because this whole era of moving toward the private
                    sector, while it may have gone too far at times, really produces some good
                    questions. Like, is this a public function and what is the relationship between
                    public functions and private market functions? So, I'm quite optimistic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about not just in the development community, but
                        within USAID, itself, what is your sense of the interest and concern for
                        development management issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, one concern I do have is that you have to have a piece of the
                    organization that keeps up the work. As staffing declines, and as the champions
                    of this work within USAID retire, I'm not sure who is going to keep it going.
                    It's out there in the knowledge base, but how many advocates are there going to
                    be in USAID? I'm not sure. It would be too bad if USAID just ceded this
                    important area of work to the World Bank and the United Nations, and to
                    contractors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much of these concepts get picked up in the discussion
                        of “governance?” Is that just another phrase for the same sort of
                        business?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: It ought to be included in governance. The shift to policy change that
                    USAID made in the Reagan years includes institutions of representation, justice
                    and property rights, among other things—political and legal institutions.
                    Democracy and governance must arise from political and legal institutions. That
                    is all to the good, but governance must also include public programs, roles and
                    relationships among business, government, and the “third sector” of civil
                    society, functions of local government, and efficient delivery of public
                    services.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But is that another dimension of the development
                        management process?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I would say the reverse. Governance, as I conceive of it, first sets up
                    the institutional framework, and development management then helps makes it
                    work. But both are needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, let me just ask you some questions to bring it back
                        to you a little more directly. After this considerable career and
                        continuity, you were a point of continuity over the years in this whole
                        field of development management, how do you feel about your work all those
                        years, and your experience? What is your assessment of what you feel you
                        have been able to do?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Well, unlike some AID retirees, I have quite a good feeling about my
                    career with USAID and the contributions that were made in the projects and
                    programs that I was associated with. I had a personal inclination and commitment
                    to move from knowledge to action. The roles that I played always permitted that
                    kind of movement. I think we developed approaches, methods and teamwork over the
                    years that made us useful and relevant to the real world that USAID Missions
                    confront and to helping involve host country people to get things done. So, in
                    general I have a good feeling about this whole movement over the past thirtyears
                    and my involvement in it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the evolution of AID or changes, and so on, how did you
                        find the Agency as an environment to work in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Generally very good. One of the things I have always said is that most
                    of the people I have met and worked with in USAID are very bright and committed
                    people. In those kinds of interrelationships with able people, who want to get
                    things done, I have been quite satisfied. At the same time, I guess this is
                    characteristic of all bureaucracies, you get jerked around, sometimes, in ways
                    that are not very satisfying.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q:What do you mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: There were two cases when USAID decisions—one in Washington and one in
                    the field—suddenly got in the way of important field initiatives we had
                    going.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Like what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: These are debatable issues, of course. First Morocco. I met Mohammed
                    Birouk, a senior official in the Ministry of Interior at a conference in
                    Tangier. We got acquainted and eventually came up with — his idea — reforming
                    the training provided for local government cadre in Morocco through the Ministry
                    of Interior.</p>
                <p>The Morocco Mission at that time was doing demand-driven programming. If the
                    Ministry of Health wanted some help, they got it, and usually good help, and
                    they were usually enthusiastic about it because it was their idea. Dr. Birouk's
                    idea was another example of demand-driven programming. The Interior Ministry
                    said we want to improve our training of local government cadre and we have three
                    regional training centers to work through and the S&amp;T Bureau in Washington
                    said they would help us get mobilized, will you, the Mission, put up the money?
                    Yes. So we hired Dick Roberts, who used to be the Ford Rep in the Maghreb, spoke
                    fluent French, and had done management work at Denver University, a really good
                    guy, to provide this direct relationship and help the Moroccans revise their
                    training programs.</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>Well, I think we were eight or nine months into the program when the Asia and
                    Near East Bureau back in Washington said, “You Mission people in Morocco are all
                    over the map, you've got health projects, you've got local government training,
                    you've got this and that. It does not amount to a strategy. We are not going to
                    let you do that anymore. Oh, and by the way, we think that what the Moroccans
                    really need to be doing is dry land agriculture. They have run out of irrigated
                    perimeters so you need to help them mobilize the technology and the organization
                    and the extension to do dry land agriculture.” So, guess what, some of the
                    demand-driven projects, including ours, got killed, peremptorily, and replaced
                    with a strategic emphasis on dry land agriculture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which the government hadn't asked for?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Which the government had not asked for. I checked the program book about
                    three years later and there was nothing going on in dry land agriculture in
                    Morocco. There was also an incident in a Southern Africa regional public
                    administration training program we were involved with Rukudzo Murapa, the team
                    leader, was doing an outstanding job. But the regional USAID office insisted
                    that he work directly for them under a personal services contract, and he didn't
                    want that kind of direct identification with USAID. So he left to work for the
                    World Bank. But I have to say that, however memorable and disappointing those
                    events were, there weren't very many of them over the years. Collaborative
                    relationships among the missions, regional bureaus, and our central programs
                    required lots of attention, but they usually worked well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you judge the Agency for providing opportunities
                        for initiative and creative thinking?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Compared [with] other agencies of the U.S. Government, ten out of ten.
                    One of the nice things about USAID, as I saw it, was that if you are a
                    reasonably good salesman with a reasonably good idea or product, you could get
                    money for it. That was one of the great things about working for USAID: the
                    activist people, the advocates, got things done that they wanted to do, and
                    usually quite constructive things, because it was an entrepreneurial
                    organization. That was partly because of the project form of management. You are
                    always looking for a new project that makes sense and gets things done.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Getting even further back, taking a look at the programs
                        and your experience in foreign assistance, what are your conclusions about
                        its effectiveness and contribution to the business of development in
                        developing countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>KORNHER: Over the years, while there have been some failures, the achievements
                    have been substantial. We should not think that the main impetus is the
                    assistance, though. Rather it's leadership and commitment in the country we are
                    working with. When you find that leadership and commitment, and especially when
                    they are supported by a progressive set of democratic institutional
                    arrangements, the external assistance can support and advance the needed
                    changes. For example, in Poland since the fall of the Iron Curtain, the
                    development progress has been phenomenal. External assistance has been very
                    helpful, but an adjunct to the initiatives the Poles were taking themselves. The
                    same was true of Korea many years ago and of South Africa in recent years.</p>
                <p>Also, USAID has made both mistakes and correct decisions in program emphasis over
                    the years. Exporting tactical tools of public administration was a mistake.
                    Supporting the wrong kind of rural development participation for many years was
                    a mistake. But supporting policy reform and autonomous local governments was
                    correct.</p>
                <p>Overall, my judgment is that the taxpayers are getting a much better deal in
                    foreign assistance than they think they are. Assistance, exchange, diplomacy and
                    community-building elements of foreign policy are a lot cheaper than military
                    elements. They don't produce quick results, but they do support the evolution of
                    responsible, increasingly democratic countries over long periods.</p>
                <p>This meshes with my conclusions in my research at Georgetown. They were that
                    people-oriented investments - cultural and university exchanges, for example -
                    make a difference over time. The so-called slow media efforts of USIS, the
                    exchanges, today the Humphrey Fellows, the Eisenhower Fellows, and similar
                    programs make a big contribution to U.S. foreign policy objectives. But it is
                    not very visible and it is not very fast.</p>
                <p>I think the same thing is true of USAID. It is hard to say that the reforms in
                    Guatemala were brought about by USAID interventions. But at the same time, the
                    constant, gentle pressure to get away from the military dominance to a little
                    more democracy, a little more rational way of dealing with your development
                    agenda, of relating to your large Mayan population up in the highlands, makes a
                    difference. It's kind of an accretive strategy, because a lot of Guatemalans get
                    educated in the United States, and they say this traditional, despotic regime is
                    not what we want anymore, and eventually not what we're going to tolerate
                    anymore. So I think in that way USAID makes a major contribution.</p>
                <p>These are also opportunities, and I saw this very much in working on programs in
                    Central Europe since I retired from USAID. Countries like the Bulgaria, Romania,
                    Bosni- they want very much to be a part of Western Europe, the European
                    community. In spite of the hangers-on from the old regime, their reform agendas
                    are moving fast. So there are opportunities to help them do what they want to
                    do, and do it more quickly.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, as a last question. If some young man or woman came
                        to you and said, “Would you recommend that I go into an international or
                        global development business? Would you recommend that they work for USAID?”
                        What would you say?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: I would say by all means do it. But I would say you had better be well
                    prepared to get in the door - the bar is much higher than it was when I was
                    hired by AID. You need a relevant second language, you need some overseas
                    experience like the Peace Corps or development contract work, and you need both
                    technical and international credentials, background and experience. With all of
                    these you might make it into the International Development Intern Program. It is
                    very competitive. If you do make it, it's a great opportunity, and a satisfying
                    career. If you don't, it's still a very international world, so your preparation
                    will be very useful on other career paths.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good. Well, why don't we end it there and thank you very
                        much.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KORNHER: Okay. May I just say one more thing.</p>
                <p>I think the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training, and Haven North as
                    one of its leaders, deserve a real compliment for the time and effort that you
                    are giving to these interviews. Establishing a personalized history of what has
                    happened in diplomacy and international development over the years is worth
                    doing. From one point of view, it's a nice forum for old fogies to reflect on
                    what they used to do. But I think it is much more than that. I think that the
                    sharing of experience can be immensely useful, and I commend you for spending as
                    much time on it as you do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you for that comment. We'll press on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Selected Bibliography</p>
                <p>A. SELECTED WORKS SPONSORED OR SUBSIDIZED BY USAID'S CENTRAL DEVELOPMENT
                    ADMINISTRATION UNIT</p>
                <p>Brinkerhoff, Derick W. Improving Development Program Performance: Guidelines for
                    Managers, Boulder CO, Lynne Rienner, 1991 (Note: contains an excellent and
                    extensive bibliography.)</p>
                <p>Esman, Milton J. and John D. Montgomery. “Systems Approaches to Technical
                    Cooperation: The Role of Development Administration,” Public Administration
                    Review, Vol. 29, No. 5, 1969, 507-538.</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>Hage, Jerald and Kurt Finsterbusch. Organizational Change as a Development
                    Strategy: Models and Tactics for Improving Third World Organizations, Lynne
                    Rienner Publishers, Boulder CO, 1987.</p>
                <p>Ingle, Marcus D., Morris J. Solomon, Pierette J. Countryman, and Merlyn H.
                    Kettering. “Promising Approaches to Project Management Improvement,” Washington,
                    DC, Development Project Management Center, U.S. Department of Agriculture
                    (mimeo), 1981</p>
                <p>Kerrigan, John E. and Jeff S. Luke. Management Training Strategies foDeveloping
                    Countries, Lynne Rienner Publishers, Boulder CO, 1984.</p>
                <p>Kiggundu, Moses. Managing Organizations in Developing Countries, WesHartford, CT,
                    Kumarian Press, 1989</p>
                <p>Korten, DaviC. “Community Organization and Rural Development: A Learning Process
                    Approach,” Public Administration Review (September/October 1980) 480-511.</p>
                <p>______ and Rudy Klauss, eds. People Centered Development: Contributions toward
                    Theory andPlanning Frameworks, West Hartford, CT, Kumarian Press, 1984</p>
                <p>Koteen, Jack, Edward Rizzo, David Jickling, and Kenneth Kornher. “Key Problems in
                    DevelopmenAdministration , Washington: U.S. Agency for International
                    Development, 1970 (mimeographed).</p>
                <p>Ostrom, Eleanor, Larry Schroeder and Susan Wynne. Institutional Incentives
                    andSustainableDevelopment: Infrastructure Policies in Perspective, Boulder, CO,
                    Westview Press,1993</p>
                <p>Paul, Samuel, Managing Development Programs: Lessons of Success, Boulder,CO,
                    Westview Press, 1982.</p>
                <p>Rondinelli, Dennis A. Development Administration and U.S. Foreign Aid Policy,
                    Boulder CO, Lynne Rienner, 198(Note: Contains an excellent and extensive
                    bibliography.)</p>
                <p>______ and H Raymond Radosevich, “An Integrated Approach to Development Project
                    Management,” Report to the U.S. Agency for International development.
                    Washington: U.S. Agency for International Development (mimeo) 1974.</p>
                <p>U.S. Agency for International Developmen(Ambassador William Hall), “Report of the
                    AID Work Group on Management Improvement and Development Administration,”
                    Washington, USAID (mimeo), 1975</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>White, Louise G. Creating Opportunities for Change: Approaches tManaging
                    Development Programs. Boulder, CO, Lynne Rienner, 1987</p>
                <p>B. OTHER SELECTED WORKS RELATED TO THE EVOLUTION OF USAID'S DEVELOPMENT
                    ADMINISTRATION PROGRAMS</p>
                <p>Blase, Melvin G. Institution Building: A Source Book , University of Missouri
                    Press, Columbia, M1973; Revised Edition, 198(Note: contains an excellent and
                    extensive IB bibliography.)</p>
                <p>Holdcroft, Lane E. The Rise and Fall of Community Development in Developing
                    Countries 1950-65: A Critical Analysis and Annotated Bibliography. AID Contract
                    -CA3; Washington: Office of Rural Development and Development Administration,
                    USAID, 1978</p>
                <p>Moris, Jon R. Managing Induced Rural Development. Bloomington, IN,International
                    Development Institute, 1981.</p>
                <p>Morss, Elliott R. and David D. Gow (eds.). Implementing Rural Development
                    Projects: Lessons from AID and World Bank Experiences, Boulder, CO, Westview
                    Press, 1985.</p>
                <p>Mosher, Arthur T. Getting Agriculture Moving: Essentials for Development and
                    Modernization. NY: Published for the Agricultural Development Council by Praeger
                    Publishers, Inc., 1966.</p>
                <p>Owens, Edgar and Robert D'A. Shaw. Development Reconsidered. Lexington,MA, DC
                    Heath, 1972.</p>
                <p>Picard, Louis A. The Politics of Development in Botswana: A Model foSuccess?
                    Boulder, CO, Lynne Rienner, 1987</p>
                <p>Siffin, William J. “Two Decades of Public Administration in Developing
                    Countries,” Public Administration Review, Vol. 36, No. 1, Jan.-Feb. 1976, pp.
                    61-71.</p>
                <p>Thompson, James D. Organizations in Action. NY, McGraw-Hill Book Co.,1967.</p>
                <p>Waterston, Albert. Development Planning: Lessons of Experience, BaltimorMD, Johns
                    Hopkins University Press, 1969.</p>
                <p>World Bank, World Development Report 1983 Part II, “Management in Development”.
                    NY, Oxford University Press, Published for the World Bank, 1983.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
