<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000207">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Kathryn Clark-Bourne </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>KATHRYN CLARK-BOURNE</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p/>
                <p>Initial interview date: August 2, 1995</p>
                <p/>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's start at the beginning. Could you tell me where and
                        when you were born and something about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Sure. I was born on October 15, 1924 in Fort Collins, Colorado. My
                    father at that time was a math professor at Colorado State College of
                    Agriculture and Mechanical Arts, which later became Colorado State University.
                    He was also a baseball coach. My mother's family was from a town in northern
                    Wyoming, Gillette. They were Pennsylvania Dutch people who had come from the
                    East. She and my father met at the University of Wyoming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you're a real daughter of the high plains.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The town of Fort Collins is just at the end of the plains near the
                    foothills of the Rockies. It's a mile above sea level. While growing up, we
                    could hike across the fields, climb up into the foothills, and enjoy the
                    mountains there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you get your education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I went through primary school, junior high and high school there,
                    except for one year in high school. Oh yes, and one year in primary school, when
                    we were in Urbana, Illinois, where my dad was working on his Ph.D. And then, one
                    year in high school, was spent in Berkeley, California, where he finished up his
                    Ph.D.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>Then I had one year at what is now Colorado State University. I had received a
                    four-year scholarship when I was graduated cum laude from high school. We didn't
                    have any money. Professors didn't make any money in those days, and I could live
                    at home and that was great. At that time, the Second World War was in progress
                    and after my freshman year Boeing Aircraft Company representatives came through
                    Fort Collins trying to recruit young ladies to be trained as draftsmen to
                    replace men, who were going off to the battlefield. So, I signed up. At the end
                    of the training, which was given through the summer, they chose a few of the
                    better students to go to Seattle to work in their plant. So, I went back to
                    Seattle. I worked there for a year and a half, almost two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of planes were you working on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The B-29 was the XB-29 then. That means it was experimental.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the superfortress.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, but it had already been drafted. I started out in what they
                    call “master layout.” You work on long, low tables on sheets of metal that have
                    been covered with paint. Your drafting instruments are metal and you draft full
                    size. We were drafting the templates that would be used to cast the wings or the
                    body of the plane.</p>
                <p>We worked in downtown Seattle. One day, they asked me to go out to the plant at
                    Boeing airfield, and take something to somebody out there. I passed a door that
                    said “Top secret. Do not enter.” So, I entered, to see what it was all about and
                    started talking with a man who worked there. He ended up inviting me to work
                    there so I transferred out there.</p>
                <p>They were working on a fighter plane. They had models in the wind tunnel and we'd
                    go out to the wind tunnel and get the data and then come back and do the
                    calculations and draft from that data.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Boeing has always been known for putting out larger planes
                        and not fighter planes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's right. This fighter plane turned out to be too heavy. It was
                    never produced. It never worked out. While I was there one of the great days
                    came—I believe it was on VE day—and I ended up resigning from Boeing. By this
                    time I had gained residency in the State of Washington and applied to go to the
                    University of Washington. I did not want to go back to Colorado because by then
                    my father was Dean of Faculty of the University. You'd get an A and they'd say,
                    “That's because your old man is Dean of Faculty.”</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>While I was working at Boeing, I also worked nights as a soda jerk to save money
                    to return to school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You'd better explain what a soda jerk is. I know, but for
                        the others...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In those days, you didn't get your Coke out of a can. Coca-Cola
                    came in big barrels. They'd tap it and put it into the soda fountain. You'd put
                    a little bit of syrup in a glass and fill it up with soda. That's when I learned
                    not to drink Coca-Cola, by the way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, the tap—you know, they're chrome-covered steel—fell into one
                    of the barrels. We couldn't get it out until the barrel was empty. It was
                    corroded beyond belief. I figured that, if it would do that to steel, what was
                    it doing to my stomach?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're saying this as I'm drinking a diet Coca-Cola.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: And I've had my eye on it all the time!</p>
                <p>At any rate, I was accepted into the School of Journalism. Because I was at
                    Colorado for one year, I was there for only three years. They had something
                    called “J.J.”, Junior Journalism. That year, you did nothing but journalism. We
                    put out the school newspaper. We took turns having different assignments on the
                    paper. I was graduated in 1947 with a Bachelor's Degree. During all this time, I
                    had various jobs, usually in the school library, sometimes typing, etc., so I
                    could keep myself going through university.</p>
                <p>After graduation, I got a job as editor of the West Seattle Herald, which was a
                    small weekly newspaper. While I was doing that, I noticed an ad in a newspaper
                    asking for typists to work in Japan, in the Army of Occupation. I wanted to see
                    the world, so I applied and was accepted. They sent us over to Japan on a
                    military ship. I was assigned to G-2 under General Willoughby.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: G-2 being the...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Intelligence, military intelligence. All the Japanese who had been
                    prisoners-of-war in Manchuria had been brought back to Japan. We had
                    interpreters who were interviewing them for any kind of information they could
                    tell us about Manchuria—about how many buildings were in the camp they were in,
                    for example.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>I was a research analyst. I had to take that data and put it together into
                    understandable reports. If I had questions, I could call back a certain
                    prisoner-of-war and, through the interpreter, ask questions. When I first got
                    over there, I was just a typist in a typing pool. But, within a week, they
                    discovered that I had a college degree. That's why I was shifted over to
                    research analysis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived there, what was your impression of Japan
                        in 1947?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: When I first got there, some of the city had been bombed out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Tokyo?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I was in Tokyo, in the NYK building, the Nippon Yusen Kaisha
                    building, which was just across the street and down a little bit from the
                    railroad station, which had been bombed.</p>
                <p>The Japanese were very nice. For we American civilians, practically everything
                    was off-limits. We were not to go into any of the restaurants. We were not to go
                    into any theaters or movies. On trains we were to go only in a car that had a
                    white line painted on the outside. Well, of course, I wanted to see Japan—most
                    of us did—and travel and do things. So, we were off-limits a lot of the time.
                    For instance, we'd go into a movie theater and, in the middle of a movie, the
                    MPs would come in with their flashlights looking for Americans. The Japanese
                    were very nice about hiding us in the projection room. On the trains, they'd
                    hide us in the baggage cars, so I managed to travel all over Japan that way. In
                    this way, I got around a lot.</p>
                <p>I hiked a lot. The Japanese like to go out for cherry blossom viewing or autumn
                    leaf viewing, so we'd take a train out to the mountains and spend the whole
                    weekend on all the trails. There would be lovely inns or rest places where we
                    could stay overnight. I took the train down to Hiroshima, which had been
                    completely bombed out. I left there in '49; the next time I was back was in '75.
                    I could recognize nothing, except the Palace and the moat around it. Even Frank
                    Lloyd Wright's original Imperial Hotel was gone. It was sort of sad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With this intelligence, what was your impression of what
                        we were after at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It was obvious that we were after any information we could find
                    about the Soviet Union, and also China, because these were Communist countries
                    at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for the rule of General MacArthur as
                        it pertained to what you were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: General MacArthur was not very much liked. He was quite imperial. I
                    had a boyfriend who was in the military. He was a German Jew, had gotten out of
                    Germany, come across Siberia to Japan before the war. Then, when the war came,
                    he and his family were sent to the United States. He went to school at the
                    University of Michigan, but as he had the Japanese language, he was sent back to
                    Japan when he joined the Army. By this time, his father was working for a big
                    company here in the States and he'd come to Japan and visit occasionally. They
                    had a house up at Lake Chuzenji in Japan, so we used to go up there a lot.
                    MacArthur and wife had a place nearby and they would come up, too. There was no
                    fraternization of any kind.</p>
                <p>There was a tennis court down in Tokyo, near the Palace, and whenever MacArthur
                    would come to play, his guards would come with their machine guns pointing and
                    get everybody off of all of the courts. Not one person was allowed on any court,
                    except MacArthur and whomever he was playing. The one thing I remember about him
                    is that his guards—bodyguards, I guess you'd call them—were all very tall. When
                    I would walk down from where I lived to the NYK building, I would pass by his
                    office building. Usually about that time, his limousines would pull up and the
                    guards would form lines along both sides from his car to the entrance, and he'd
                    march through. That's all I ever had to do with him. I can't tell you anything
                    more than that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any State Department presence there at all that
                        you were aware of?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not in Tokyo. In Yokohama, I think there was some presence at that
                    time. When I left Japan, I had to get a passport.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Alexis Johnson was running the place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, I think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1949, is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I left in 1949.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What further?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, I wanted to see the rest of the world. So, three other ladies
                    and I booked onto a freighter that was to take us first over to China and then
                    to the Philippines and then down to Singapore and then let us off in Calcutta.
                    Well, the Bamboo Curtain rolled down before we finally got on it, so we didn't
                    get to go to China.</p>
                <p>We went to the Philippines where we picked up lots and lots of pineapple in every
                    form imaginable: chucked, juiced, sliced, you name it. As they were loading, we
                    went out and hiked in the forests and rented outriggers and went swimming. Of
                    course, there were still bombs in some of the waters down there so we had to be
                    careful. We left, finally, for Hong Kong. South of Iloilo, in the Philippines,
                    we ran aground on a charted coral reef. There were 12 women passengers on this
                    ship. Evidently, one of the ladies had been with the First Mate while he was on
                    duty. The crew first shifted cargo and tried to get the ship off. Fortunately,
                    there was no break in the hull. While they were doing that, we ladies did the
                    housekeeping. After several days with no luck, they radioed the Philippines for
                    a salvage master. They didn't want to do that because the salvage master takes
                    50% of the value of the cargo and the ship.</p>
                <p>The salvage master came down with a small plane and a diver. The diver went down
                    and discovered that we were stuck on a soft reef at about a 45-degree angle and
                    that the only way they could get us off was to bring barges down, unload all the
                    cargo, and pull us off, which they did. Then we had to go back to Iloilo to go
                    into dry dock for the insurance company. So, we gals played some more: went
                    hiking in the Philippines and things like that. It was fun. We went on to
                    Singapore where we went to the Raffle's Hotel. By the way, it took two weeks to
                    get us off the reef and, during that time, we were eating pineapple out of the
                    cargo. The seaman were out fishing and we'd eat whatever they'd catch. So, by
                    the time we got to Hong Kong, all I wanted was a chocolate ice cream sundae. By
                    mistake, they brought me a pineapple ice cream sundae. I'll never forget that. I
                    never wanted to see pineapple again in my life!</p>
                <p>We went on past Calcutta. Because we'd missed so much time and the freighter's
                    sister ship was coming in the opposite direction and would stop in Calcutta,
                    they told us to go to Karachi and offload our Calcutta cargo onto the sister
                    ship. Of course, we were there without visas because we did not know we were
                    going to Karachi. So, we were interned in the airport. We had visas for India.
                    There was a sandstorm and it took us several days before we got out to
                    India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was just about the time of the partition, wasn't
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Just after the partition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a feeling of hostility between...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, not at all, not that we had too much contact with anybody to
                    get that feeling. Remember, we were literally just put in a hotel at the airport
                    and had to stay there until we could get out.</p>
                <p>We stayed in a hotel in Old Delhi for a couple days. We had gone down to Agra, of
                    course. We wanted to see what that was all about. One night, I was in the dining
                    room and my three lady friends had gone back to the room. There was only one
                    other person in the dining room, an elderly gentleman. He sent the waiter over
                    and asked if I would like to join him for a coffee and I said, “Sure.” By the
                    way, we were having real problems. I wanted to go to Egypt because, when I was
                    studying in Seattle, one of my boyfriends was an Egyptian working on a Ph.D. and
                    he'd invited me to come and visit with him and his friend. We couldn't get
                    visas. Supposedly, the US wasn't talking to Egypt at that time. Well, this
                    gentleman wanted to know who we were and what we were doing and where we were
                    going. I told him how badly I wanted to go to Egypt, but couldn't get visas, so
                    I'd probably have to go to Europe. He said, “Come to my office tomorrow. I'll be
                    able to help you.” It was the Egyptian Ambassador!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, my goodness!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: He just closed his eyes to the fact that we had American passports
                    and gave us visas. So, we flew to Egypt. My friend with three of his male
                    friends met the four of us, so we saw Cairo and the Pyramids—had a wonderful
                    time.</p>
                <p>Then, my ladyfriends decided they wanted to go home. So, they decided just to fly
                    to Paris and London and home. Well, I wanted to see Europe. I was out to see the
                    world, so I took a bus up to Alexandria and got myself on a ship crossing the
                    Mediterranean—third class, in the hold, with an Egyptian belly dance team. It
                    was a rough crossing. I was the only person who didn't get seasick. I remember,
                    one or two of the dancers got sick, and so they asked if they could teach me and
                    if I'd fill in. I said, “Sure,” but then, the last night when they had the
                    farewell party, so many people were under the weather, the officers asked if I
                    would act as emcee. So I did that instead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's like the classic story of Rebecca West learning how
                        to belly dance when she was in Yugoslavia.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I did not know that one! I don't remember too much about that
                    because I didn't actually perform. At any rate, I wandered around Europe by bus,
                    the cheapest way I could. I had been saving money all the time in Japan to get a
                    Master's degree. Well, I used all of that money to travel. I figured that it was
                    well worth it. I wandered around up through Italy and Switzerland and over to
                    France. By this time, I was down to about 10 or 20 dollars. I met some
                    University of Washington ladyfriends who had gotten jobs in Germany and France,
                    and we all met there. We all got one little room because none of us had any
                    money. We took turns sleeping: some slept in the daytime and some slept at
                    night. I went to the American Embassy there, to the Military Attach�, because
                    the government had promised me round-trip transportation. As I had not taken the
                    return transportation, I went to him and said, “You owe me this.” They also
                    still owed me some salary. So, he got me a berth on a troop ship crossing the
                    Atlantic, leaving from Belgium. After arriving in New York, I went to a fort
                    near New York City to try to get the rest of the salary they owed me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Camp Jolmer(?) or Fort...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't know. They sent a telegram to someplace and they got the
                    money for me. With that, I figured I had enough to explore the United States a
                    little bit by bus. My sister was at the University of Ohio and I went to see her
                    and stopped in several places and went home broke—home being Colorado.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was about 19...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: 1949—almost 1950. I still wanted to get a Master's Degree, so I got
                    in contact with one of my university professors at the University of Washington
                    and said, “Do you know of any place I could go where I can get a fellowship?”
                    Well, he had a pal at the University of Minnesota. They gave me a teaching
                    fellowship. So, I went in January 1950, that spring term, on a teaching
                    fellowship, to get a Master's Degree in mass communications.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mass Communications? What does that mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It covers not only newspaper and writing, but radio—by this time,
                    TV had started to come in. All kinds of communication. So, I went for the spring
                    term and summer term and really worked very hard, getting my Master's in two
                    terms.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>In the summer or spring, a recruiter from USIA came to the University of
                    Minnesota. I thought, “Wow, I'd like that. I could get back overseas.” So, I was
                    interviewed and they sent me to take a physical. I finished my work at the
                    University of Minnesota and they said they would get in touch with me. I went
                    back to Colorado to visit my family for a few weeks and heard nothing from
                    anybody and thought, “Well, I'll go to Washington, DC”. I got to Washington and
                    this was just the time when USIA was being taken out of the State Department and
                    nobody could find where any of their files were. So, I quickly went to the Civil
                    Service Administration, took a typing test, and got a job with the Panama Canal
                    Company as a typist.</p>
                <p>They soon discovered that I had some education and asked me to help balance the
                    company's accounts with the US Treasury. While I was doing that, I went to the
                    State Department and applied for a job and was offered one in the Office of
                    Intelligence Research, in DRS, the Division for Research for the Soviet Union
                    and East European Countries. Stan Wilcox was head of it at that time. I was
                    brought on as an editor for the NIS, the National Intelligence Survey. I did
                    that for two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what the National Intelligence Survey
                        was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It was by country. People wrote these reports with all the
                    information they had on their particular countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was sort of an encyclopedic thing: personalities,
                        geography, landing beaches...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's right. Anything and everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The idea being that, if a country came up, somebody could
                        sit there and say, “Well, this is where we'll invade and these are the
                        people we should contact.” It was a huge undertaking.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, it was. I did that for two years. Then I was offered a job
                    with a step increase—this was under Civil Service, you understand—in DRF:
                    Division for Research for the Far East. Of course, I'd been in Japan for a
                    couple of years and they wanted me to be Division Editor. That means editing all
                    reports that were written. I did that until '56.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These reports, what was your impression of the information
                        that was coming in, how these things were prepared and...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, it was stuff that came in from post. The subjects would be
                    whatever were requested from the various bureaus in the State Department. The
                    bureaus would say, “We would like a report on such and which,” and you would
                    gather all the information you could and put together a report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find them useful?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: To be very honest, I wouldn't know. I hadn't worked in the Foreign
                    Service or in the State Department. I had just worked there in Intelligence. So,
                    I had really not too much knowledge of what went on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this intelligence side of the State Department when you
                        were there, could you give a little feeling about how it was constituted and
                        what was the atmosphere of the people that you were meeting there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It was all Civil Service and, in those days, we were in State Annex
                    One—that was before New State had been built. It was an apartment building on
                    the corner of E and 23rd. The people with whom I worked in DRS were all college
                    graduates, some with higher degrees in their various areas of specialty. For
                    instance, for Finland, there was a Finnish guy who was the analyst. Hungary had
                    a guy whose parents had come from Hungary. He had been born in the States, but
                    he spoke Hungarian very well. They all knew the languages, by the way, in which
                    they were working. This was true with all of the East European countries. In the
                    Far East, it was more or less the same thing. Most of the people that I remember
                    did have the languages. I worked just with them and their reports. I did not
                    work with the outsiders with whom they may have worked.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In DRS from '52 to '54. In DRF from '54 to '56. In '56, I was
                    Wristonized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what the Wristonization Program
                        was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It was named after a gentleman named Mr. Wriston, who suggested
                    they bring civil servants who could qualify into the Foreign Service as a way of
                    expanding the Foreign Service. We had to take written and oral exams. I don't
                    remember too much about the written exam, except that it took all day. The oral
                    exam I remember for one stupid thing only. I was told to meet with a panel of
                    people, walked into a room—it was a big room—and the people were seated at a
                    table at the far end, near a window. I went in and sat down. I was smoking in
                    those days, and I wanted a cigarette. I looked around, but didn't see any
                    ashtrays. I thought, “Well, I'd better ask,” so I said, “Is it all right to
                    smoke here.” One of the guys said, “Oh, yeah,” and he brought out an ashtray
                    from the window sill behind a curtain. I'll never forget that one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the stories that used to go around of the test for
                        the Foreign Service—this was when people were smoking a lot—was that they'd
                        say, “Sure, you can smoke,” and then there wouldn't be an ashtray. They
                        wanted to see how you responded.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's right. That's exactly what this was about. At any rate, I
                    was accepted and my first post was Tehran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Tehran from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '56 to '58. It was during the time of the Shah, during the time of
                    Soroya. He was still married to Soroya.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Mrs. Pahlavi.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: By the way, I had to fight to get into that job, because the
                    Foreign Service did not think women should go to Islamic countries. I must have
                    been difficult enough that they decided I could go. I was at the bottom of the
                    totem pole in the Political Section. I was the only woman officer, not only in
                    our embassy, but in the entire Diplomatic Corps. The only one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Talk a little bit about, as you saw it at that time, in
                        1956, about women officers in the Foreign Service. How did they treat you? I
                        mean, you've already alluded to part of this, but maybe you got even more
                        coming in and the whole thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, not when I was coming in. In the Civil Service, of course,
                    there was no problem. This was the first inkling I had that there was
                    discrimination against women, and I fought it. As we go along, I'll tell you the
                    experiences. I have run into a lot of them. But let's keep it in chronological
                    sequence.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, absolutely. To start this off, could you tell me, who
                        was the Ambassador and how did he operate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The Ambassador was Selden Chapin. Selden had his ward there, Hope
                    Cooke, who became the Maharani of Sikkim. Hope was in high school, just
                    finishing up. As the only woman, I sort of ended up a lot of the time as Hope's
                    nanny, if you will. Being the only woman had its good points, too. The Iranian
                    men are very gallant. They're sort of the Frenchmen of the Middle East. In no
                    time at all, I got to know a lot of them. The Ambassador was very shrewd: he saw
                    that I had entree that the men officers did not have. I would go to the US and
                    European office in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and there would be two or
                    three Ambassadors sitting in the waiting room. I would not even have an
                    appointment but when the head of the office would open the door and somebody
                    would walk out, he'd say, “Kay, come on in.” I'd go in and deliver my message. I
                    had absolute entree. Two of the other junior officers, the one in the Egyptian
                    Embassy, the one in the Indian Embassy and I formed a Junior Officer's Club.
                    They were all men, except me. We had meetings once a week and we also met with
                    various friends we'd made in the Foreign Ministry and the other ministries. That
                    helped broaden my contacts also.</p>
                <p>Being a woman there in other situations, of course, I did not have the entree
                    that men had. Such as, for instance, visiting a mosque. One of my good friends
                    was the wife of a member of the Parliament and we soon solved this. She'd been
                    educated in Russia and Europe. I borrowed a chador and slippers from my
                    housekeeper and I'd go with this lady and her friend. We'd go into the mosque or
                    wherever I wanted to go. They always said, “Keep your mouth shut and don't talk
                    with anybody” because they'll find out you're a foreigner. But these gals would
                    be wearing regular saddle shoes and bobbie socks, so everybody thought they were
                    the foreigners. The whole thing was quite amusing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the political situation at the time? What were
                        you and the Political Section interested in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: For me, it was a tale of a thousand nights. It was fantastic. We
                    were very friendly with Iran. We had a huge Armish-MAAG set up there. I at one
                    time had a lady visitor who was an American foreign correspondent, and the two
                    of us were allowed to go with a Armish-MAAG battalion on a two-week trip out to
                    the northern part of the country, where we camped out. They gave us our own tent
                    and let us go off and do our own thing. That was interesting.</p>
                <p>The first week I was there, it was just unbelievable. There were many social
                    events. That week, Adenauer and a son or daughter came to visit the Shah.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the Chancellor of...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: West Germany. They invited the Diplomatic Corps to all receptions
                    and they often would be followed by dinners (at 10 o'clock at night) for the
                    Ambassadors and the big shots. And it was practically every night. I had not
                    received all of my air freight and did not have a long dress. In those days, you
                    wore long dresses. So, from the Ambassador's wife's secretary, I borrowed a
                    dress. She was a little bigger than I was and, as it was strapless, I had to pin
                    it on. The first or second night I was there, we drove to the downtown palace
                    which was walled in. There was a big, circular drive in front of it. We entered
                    the gate and the entire drive was covered with Persian carpets, so you drove
                    over the Persian carpets up to the front door. Then, when you entered, there was
                    a circular staircase that went up to the second floor, to where the peacock
                    throne room was. The reception was held in the peacock throne room, which was
                    about a block long, covered with a carpet that had been specially woven for that
                    room. All of the walls were covered with pieces of mirror and there were huge,
                    gorgeous crystal chandeliers from Europe. At the far end of the room was the
                    peacock throne, covered with gems, and two smaller thrones, one on either side.
                    This was where we were served drinks.</p>
                <p>While this was going on, the Chief of Protocol came up to me and said, “I
                    understand you've just arrived. You should be presented to their Royal
                    Highnesses.” So, I put out my cigarette, rolled down my gloves, and trotted down
                    the hall after him. He took me into a room first where Soroya was sitting,
                    surrounded by young courtiers. I was introduced and I knew I had to curtsy, so I
                    grabbed my dress at the top and curtsied. She looked at me disdainfully and
                    turned to one of the young men beside her. She never said a word. So, then I was
                    taken down to another room where the Shah was, who was perfectly charming. We
                    must have chatted for 20 or 30 minutes about all kinds of things. His English
                    was excellent. He was a very, very nice person. We just talked about things
                    generally—about where I was from, etc.</p>
                <p>It was either parties down there or parties up at his summer place in the
                    foothills in Shimron, where I had my house, or at all of the various embassies.
                    It was something continuously—all the time, morning, noon, and night.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a political officer, what were your
                        responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Mostly, at first, when I was assigned there, I was supposed to be
                    the Biographic Officer. I was supposed to collect all the information on 100 big
                    families, first families, and write reports. But as soon as the Ambassador
                    discovered that I had entree to everybody, then my job mostly was, when he
                    wanted to give them information or wanted to get information, to go back and
                    forth between the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and then writing the reports.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Mossadegh period was over by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Oh, yes, that was in '52.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, we're really talking about the aftermath of this. What
                        was the impression that you were getting from the other officers in the
                        political section and what you were observing about the stability of the
                        Shah?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: At that time, he seemed to be fairly stable. His twin sister,
                    Ashraf, was thought by everyone to be quite venal. According to the rumors, she
                    took 10 percent from any foreign business person who wanted to do business. She
                    got 10 percent of the profits.</p>
                <p>He, however, turned over a lot of the Pahlavi lands to villagers. In other words,
                    at that time, he was thought to be quite good. The women, a lot of them, seemed
                    to have more freedom. They were driving, some of them. Not all of them were
                    wearing the chadors all the time. We in the Diplomatic Corps were often invited
                    to affairs that the Shah had out in the desert, such as horse racing. He had a
                    large stable of Arabs and he allowed us to ride them all, to keep them
                    exercised. So, very often, I went riding out in the desert on one of the Shah's
                    Arabs.</p>
                <p>A friend of mine, as I mentioned before, was a member of Parliament, and his
                    family owned a village south of Tehran and we often went down to the village.
                    Every time they'd go, they'd take piles of gifts. When we arrived at the
                    village, the elder would be sitting in the center of the square with all of his
                    people behind him, and the member of Parliament would be there with the elder
                    and would be passing, as people came by, out the gifts. We were allowed to see
                    all of this. It was quite benevolent is what I'm trying to say. I did not feel
                    that there was any rancor against the Shah or the Pahlavis at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the political section have any connection with—I've
                        never served in Iran, but I've heard about it—what was sort of the Bazaari
                        class, the merchants?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I think some of the economic section people did. I don't know
                    whether I should say this one or not. We had a large CIA Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At that time, particularly after Kermit Roosevelt and all
                        that, Iran seemed to be a place where the CIA had a great deal of
                        influence.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: We had a big section. There was a Colonel in charge. I don't
                    remember his name. It was an East European name. They had contacts with all of
                    the tribes such as Bakhtiari and the Qashqa'is. The Colonel would ask me, as the
                    only woman officer in the Embassy, often to go with him to meetings with the
                    Bakhtiari in their tents, where sometimes they would sit around smoking opium
                    pipes. I've never used drugs in my life, but as part of my job, I had to
                    participate in this. I'll never forget that. After we left there, I was walking
                    down the street and everything was sort of hazy!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm just trying to catch the atmosphere. Were the Mullahs
                        anybody that we targeted as far as trying to get information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not that I know of. As far as the political section was concerned,
                    I don't think so. What CIA was doing, I don't know, other than contacting the
                    tribes. They may well have been targeting Mullahs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time, '56 to '58, it was what one would call a
                        rather tranquil time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: It was quite tranquil, yes. We could get around quite easily. The
                    Shah had a ski area in Ab Ali, which he let us use. When he'd come out to ski,
                    everybody was forced off the slopes. He was a fantastic skier. He'd only stay
                    about 30 minutes or so. He had a lodge out there that he stayed in. Then we'd
                    get back on the slopes.</p>
                <p>We were allowed to drive all over the country. I remember driving south to
                    Isfahan and Shiraz, although there was hardly any road across the desert. There
                    were military checkpoints and the Ambassador told us to always stop and check in
                    at every military checkpoint. At the time I was there, there were some AID
                    people who were lost or stranded in the mountains. I remember that, but I don't
                    remember much about it. I do remember once driving south with a friend in the
                    embassy and his wife and little boy. We got down to Shiraz and there was a tomb
                    out away from the city we wanted to go see. I was driving—it was my car. When we
                    arrived at the tomb, the wife said that she would sit in the car with the little
                    boy and Dick, my friend, and I went over to see it. But in no time at all, she
                    was there with the little boy and it turned out that she had locked the car
                    doors and I'd left the keys in the car. Here we were, out in the middle of the
                    desert. But we had passed a Qashqa'i encampment, so my friend Dick hiked over
                    there to see if he could get an implement of some kind so we could jimmy a
                    window open and get into the car. Well, he did and all the Qashqa'is followed
                    him back. We got into the car and when I got back to the Embassy, I told the
                    Ambassador about our experience. He said, “Kay, do you know what you just did?”
                    I said, “No.” He said, “You just taught a whole tribe of Qashqa'is how to come
                    into Tehran and rob all the cars!” But they were very friendly. It was a
                    peaceful time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the feeling there at that time towards the Soviet
                        Union?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: By the Iranians?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And by the American Embassy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: By the American Embassy, there was obviously a certain tension. The
                    Russian Embassy had a huge, high wall around it. I can remember, at that time, a
                    son of one of our officers, a high school kid, climbed over that wall. The
                    Ambassador sent the entire family out within 24 hours, as fast as he could. So,
                    you can see that there was some tension.</p>
                <p>I probably was the only person in the Embassy who ever got inside that compound
                    because of our Junior Diplomats Club. We took turns hosting and they did once,
                    so I got inside then. I can't tell you anything about the Irani-Soviet
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '56 to '58, did the Israeli-Palestinian business impact
                        at all? There was the Suez Crisis during this time. Did it have any
                        reflection in Iran at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Within the country itself, I don't remember. As far as we were
                    concerned, in traveling in and out and getting around, it was a problem. I had
                    taken a trip at one time, I think over to Bahrain, and bought a chest. I brought
                    it into the port in Iran, in the Gulf, and decided to leave it there until I
                    left, to have it shipped out when I left. I remember having horrible problems
                    with that. I remember that, by plane, sometimes we'd have to go round about to
                    go home. But, as far as the Iranians themselves were concerned, among my
                    immediate friends, I never heard too much about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1958, right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And where to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I was sent to The Netherlands. In those days—I imagine it's still
                    the same now, I don't know—all officers had to have consular officer training.
                    Although I was a political cone officer, I was sent to the Consulate General in
                    Rotterdam as special consular affairs officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: From '59 to '61. Bob Wilson was CG then. In those days, we had a
                    lot of American shipping and Rotterdam was the biggest port in Europe. The
                    captain of every American ship that came in had to report to the Consulate
                    General and had to leave his papers there. They were given to him only upon
                    departure after he had paid the port fees and fulfilled everything required.
                    There were a lot of ships that came in all the time. Seamen and shipping was one
                    of our basic jobs.</p>
                <p>Of course, American citizen welfare was involved. And there were lots of American
                    tourists in Europe, as you know. I'll never forget one day. A little old lady
                    came in and said that she'd lost her sister. They'd been traveling, I believe,
                    up in Scandinavia, and had come down to Holland. She wanted to come to Rotterdam
                    and her sister wanted to go to someplace else—Amsterdam, maybe. So, they split
                    up and were supposed to get together in Rotterdam. The sister never arrived.
                    Fortunately, I knew the manager of the biggest hotel there. He was one of my
                    boyfriends. I called him and told him to keep his eye out and called other
                    people and reported it to the police. A day or so later, this hotel manager
                    friend called and said, “She's here. I've got her.” She'd arrived, so we got the
                    two little old ladies together. I remember, they came in bearing a cake to show
                    their appreciation. But, mostly, problems were with younger people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Rotterdam and Holland...Later, it had the reputation
                        of being sort of the sin capital of Western Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Oh, really?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I mean, Amsterdam more than Rotterdam. Rotterdam was
                        a little more business. Was this a problem? I'm thinking, particularly at
                        this period, it was a pretty straight time for Americans. Were young people
                        getting into trouble?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not at all in Rotterdam that I can recall. Outstanding things that
                    happened to me had nothing to do with the young people. One of the ship captains
                    who came in asked me out to dinner one night. We went out with the
                    administrative officer and his girlfriend. After dinner the captain and I
                    decided to leave early. The other two were going to a movie. We got into a taxi
                    and the gentleman collapsed on me. While we were riding the taxi, he said, “Oh,
                    we've got to stop someplace. My left arm has no feeling. I'm having a heart
                    attack.” We got out of the taxi, got into a building, where I was trying to find
                    a phone, and he passed out on the ground. By this time, I'd gotten the hospital
                    and said we were coming over and a couple of Dutchmen said, “Here, we'll help
                    you get him into a taxi, and we'll go with you.” So, they were in the backseat
                    with him. We got to the hospital and, at the hospital, they said he'd died. We
                    had to stay there until the police came. The police interviewed the two Dutchmen
                    first—by this time, it was three or four in the morning—and let them go.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>Then, they interviewed me and said, “Who is this gentleman? All his pockets are
                    empty.” The Dutchmen, obviously, had fleeced him while they were sitting in the
                    backseat. I let them know this. I said, “The gentleman had a billfold and
                    everything when we were in the restaurant.” Then, I told them who I was. They
                    obviously didn't believe me. The Dutch at that time had no women in their
                    Foreign Service. We're talking about 1960. So, I said, “You come with me over to
                    our Consulate General and I will get you his ship's papers and all the
                    information you want.” So, they did. They escorted me over there, at five in the
                    morning. We were in a building up above a store that had apartments in it. Our
                    Administrative Officer was living in one of those. I woke him up to let us in
                    and to help me get the safes open and get the information. But, other than that,
                    it was fairly routine.</p>
                <p>One problem that comes to mind that I had with younger people was a young
                    gentleman, who was a transvestite, I guess. His passport had a lady's name in it
                    and he was in some trouble with somebody there about that.</p>
                <p>It was a good place to be. You got to travel around Europe quite a bit on the
                    weekends. You know, you can drive around Holland in one day. So, I got to see a
                    great deal of Europe when I was there. But I hated the weather—it rains all the
                    time. And the culture was sort of dull, after Iran. It was too much like US
                    culture. I was supposed to be there for four years. After two years, a telegram
                    came around, asking for Hindi-Urdu language training volunteers. I immediately
                    applied because I knew the sun would shine in India—right? So, I did that for
                    the next year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you take your Hindi-Urdu training?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: At FSI.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've often wondered, when they have Hindu-Urdu. A little
                        later, almost at the same time, I took Serbo-Croatian, but these two are
                        very similar languages. It's the same alphabet and a few different words.
                        How about Hindi-Urdu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: There are similarities, but they're different also.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're quite different, aren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Quite different, yes. This class was mostly Hindi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did they do, concentrate on Hindi?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, and we had an Indian teacher. There were only four or five of
                    us in the class. One was from the military. They were not all from the State
                    Department, I remember. It was very difficult for me. I was still smoking in
                    those days and I'd been driving home one day and heard on the car radio that the
                    Brits had come out with this study showing how dangerous it was. I decided to
                    quit. I'd been planning to stop and buy a package of cigarettes. I only had, I
                    think, two left. I got home, put the package of the two cigarettes on my
                    cocktail table and they sat there for a year. But, for the first month or
                    so...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes! I remember, about this time, I quit, too. For a
                        lot of us, it was not easy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Oh, no, not at all. But I think it was more difficult on my
                    classmates than on me because I had to have my hands doing something all the
                    time, I was playing with keys and everything like that. But it worked.</p>
                <p>It was Hindi. I don't remember any Urdu. Urdu is more closely related to Farsi.
                    The point being that, although I did not have an onward assignment, I think most
                    of the others did, and they probably were going to India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting anything from your training about India,
                        either from the teachers or from area studies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, I don't remember being given any area studies. We were
                    full-time in Hindi language. The instructor, frankly, was very obnoxious. I
                    found later that the urban Indian very often act in a superior manner. He feels
                    that he knows a great deal more than those stupid Americans. This was sort of
                    his attitude. We felt he was looking down on us all the time. The crazy thing
                    about all of this was that, after spending a whole year at that, I was assigned
                    to Bombay, where I never used it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was so often the case. You were in Bombay from when
                        to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '62 to '67.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '62 to '67.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Our Consular District included Gujarat, Maharashtra, Madhya
                    Pradesh, and Goa. In Gujarat, they speak Gujarati. In Maharashtra, they speak
                    Marathi. In Goa, it's some South Indian language. In Madhya Pradesh, they did
                    speak Hindi but it was so far away that I only got over there once or twice a
                    year. So, I just didn't get to use it. Most of the city people all spoke
                    English. It had been an English colony. So, it didn't matter that much, to be
                    very honest. If I needed an interpreter, my local employees could interpret.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From '62 to '67, you were in Bombay. What was your
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The first two years, I was a consular officer, head of the Consular
                    Section. Then, the rest of the time, I was a political officer, head of the
                    Political Section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Consul General at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I spent last night trying to remember names. Milton Rewinkel was
                    the first one and Dan Braddock was the second one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your perspective, what were American relations with
                        the Indians during the '62 to '67 period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Oh, very good. There were no problems at all. We had Peace Corps.
                    We had AID. We had everything there. We were experimenting on increasing
                    production of wheat in, I believe, the Philippines, and we were bringing the
                    results over for India. We helped them really increase their production of
                    wheat. In fact, I'll never forget it, because there was an Indian woman who
                    wrote a book. In it, she had interviewed a farmer and she said, “Now that you're
                    getting twice as much produce to sell, what are you doing with all the extra
                    money?” He said, “Well, I don't need any extra money. I have a bowl of rice for
                    breakfast, a bowl of rice for lunch, and a bowl or rice for dinner. What do I
                    need money for?” I'll never forget that. It's so different from the average
                    American outlook on life.</p>
                <p>But the relations were good. I had no problems whatsoever. I had many, many
                    Indian friends there. As a political officer, I was also a labor officer. I met
                    with the major labor union officials in Bombay, who were socialists, but I was
                    taken in by them. They confided in me on everything.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time, I guess, Nehru was still the Prime
                        Minister, wasn't he?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, I guess so. Chester Bowles was Ambassador part of the time,
                    and John Kenneth Galbraith was Ambassador part of the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were two of the stars of the Kennedy period in
                        particular. Did you have any reflection of these two strong
                        personalities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Chester Bowles was really liked by the Indians. He had two
                    different tours there. Galbraith was something else. I remember, as consular
                    officer, I was always the control officer for ship visits. And COMIDEASTFOR,
                    Commander of the Middle East Forces...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was stationed in Bahrain.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: ...in Bahrain, would drop by quite often. I remember Galbraith
                    coming down once by train. I think he took over seven cars on the train for all
                    of his friends and relatives. He arrived in Bombay and the COMIDEASTFOR had come
                    down on his flagship. Then there was a destroyer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a seaplane tender or something.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: You're right, it was a seaplane tender.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Large Bay, I think, was one of them. I served in Dhahran
                        at one time and we had these two rather small ships.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Galbraith announced that he and his wife were going to stay on the
                    captain's ship during the visit. In that day, a woman staying overnight on a
                    ship was practically unknown. The captain wasn't very happy, but felt that he
                    had to acquiesce to the Ambassador. My problem was that Galbraith was almost
                    seven feet tall and the bunks on ships were short. I remember sending a junior
                    officer down to the bazaar to find big cushions to pile up at the end of a bunk
                    so that he could sleep on it. But he absolutely insisted. That's the kind of
                    person he was. And yet, he wrote magnificently. We loved to read his cables and
                    his telegrams. We'd look forward to them. He really was very talented. But there
                    were two sides to the character.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there during the assassination of President
                        Kennedy. How did that...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That I will always remember because I had set out in my car with a
                    bunch of friends to drive up to Kathmandu. That's quite a drive, let me tell
                    you. I was driving a Mercedes 190 in those days, which are pretty sturdy cars,
                    and I remember stopping along the way for servicing. To get up over the border,
                    AID at that time was building a road that went from the border and over the
                    mountains into Kathmandu. I remember that the road en route to the border went
                    out of existence at one point. We tried to cross a stream and got stuck and had
                    to hike to the nearest village to get them to pull us out. Somehow, we got in
                    contact with AID. They sent a Jeep down to get us out. We got over the border up
                    to Kathmandu. While there in the hotel, I came down one morning for breakfast
                    and was met by one of the employees, saying, “Your President has just been
                    assassinated.” So, of course, we dashed over to the Embassy to find out what it
                    was all about. I was up there for another week before I returned to India.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were also there during the China-Indian War, weren't
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes I was and this was a problem, although the troops were over in
                    the East and we were in the West. We had a blackout and I was ordered to get all
                    the Peace Corps people down out of Gujarat and to Bombay to be evacuated. I
                    remember going up to Gujarat to find them and arriving back in Bombay during a
                    total blackout. But they managed to land the plane. My former husband—my fianc�
                    at that time—came out to the airport to meet me. We had to drive back to Bombay
                    without headlights. But that didn't last for too long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In a way, that was sort of a high point, wasn't it, of
                        Indian-American relations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, I think you're right. It probably was, at least at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a consular officer, did you have any particular
                        consular problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: This is where we did have trouble with young people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the height of what we'd call “the Hippie
                        Movement,” of young people going off as far as they could and running out of
                        money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: What they were doing was taking cars into Nepal and exchanging them
                    for drugs and then bringing the drugs down to sell in India. They'd often camp
                    on the beaches near Bombay. I remember working with the Brits trying to get it
                    under control.</p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>As consular officer before I became political officer, we had shipping problems.
                    I'll never forget one involving one of the big shipping companies, a Greek
                    company named Kulakundis employing mostly American seamen, had gone bankrupt.
                    When they arrived in Bombay port, they couldn't leave and their ships were
                    stalled in several ports in the Middle East. The Consulate General was told one
                    night, at about 10 or 11 at night, that the seamen on the ship were revolting.
                    They'd locked all the officers up in the saloon. I found out about it and called
                    the Consul General. The Consul General said that, as a woman, I couldn't go out
                    on that ship. And I said, “I certainly can,” but I promised him I'd take my
                    fianc� with me. We got out and had to climb up the Jacob's ladder to get on. By
                    the way, I had learned in The Netherlands that seamen are respectful of women,
                    but not necessarily of men. This is something that the Foreign Service learned
                    and started assigning women these jobs. I got to the saloon and climbed up on a
                    table and addressed these people. I said, “Alright, you guys, we want you to
                    come ashore. I'm going to find a place for you to stay and then I'm going to
                    find a way of getting you home by air. I want you to let the officers alone.”
                    And they went right along with it. There was a YMCA where I put everybody up.
                    Many telegrams went back and forth and we got a chartered plane and finally got
                    them out. They were most grateful. I got letters from unions for months
                    thereafter, thanking me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What had been the problem on the ship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: They hadn't been paid for two weeks. Kulakundis had gone bankrupt
                    and couldn't pay them. So, that was one of the high points as a consular
                    officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about with the young Americans? Were you having people
                        in jail and things of this nature with drugs? How did the Indians handle
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't remember them being in jail. I do remember having consulted
                    with the Indians on how to get them out of the country. That's what they mainly
                    wanted. I spent time and effort contacting relatives and Heaven knows what,
                    trying to get them out. It was a long time ago. Some of them may have been put
                    in jail. I just don't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a political officer, what were your
                        responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: As I mentioned, reporting on labor, as well as political affairs.
                    For instance, they had elections when I was there. I traveled to all the four
                    provinces to interview people from the various political parties and sent in
                    reports. We predicted the outcome of the elections in our consular district and
                    were 100 percent accurate.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of the Indian political system
                        from the perspective of Bombay?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: At that time, it seemed to work. The parties were there. They were
                    all allowed to operate. It was what we would call a democratic setup. They had
                    their elections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that you had pretty good access to the
                        political leaders in the area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes. There was no problem with that at all. Good access with
                    Indians of all kinds. They had, of course, a big movie industry. The
                    Ivory-Merchant Production Company had its studio there and I was very good
                    friends with Jim Ivory and Ismail Merchant. So, I got to know all the movie
                    colony people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Indian movie is so different than the American movie.
                        Bombay, of course, probably turned out more movies than Hollywood, I
                        guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I would not doubt it. They were horribly long and they had to
                    include everything. We'd go occasionally to them. But, of course, the
                    Ivory-Merchant films were made for Westerners, so they were not that way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever get involved in anything equivalent to turf
                        disputes? Were American movies coming in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I never saw anything like that, no. Maybe up in Delhi, they ran
                    into something like that, but I didn't see anything like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any other major events?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I traveled around quite a bit. I mentioned that, while I was in
                    Tehran, Hope Cooke was there. In fact, when I was there, she had her coming-out
                    party, which was a fantastic evening. I'll never forget it. It started at 10
                    o'clock at night and they had fireworks at midnight. At the conclusion of the
                    fireworks, there was a display of a peacock spreading its tail, with her name
                    written across the sky. She and “Aunt Mary,” Selden Chapin's wife, had gone up
                    to India and obtained the fireworks. I think that's where she met her future
                    husband, the Maharajah of Sikkim. We partied and danced all night and then had
                    breakfast and swam in their swimming pool. It went on most of the next day. Hope
                    was married in Sikkim while I was in Bombay and I was invited. I remember flying
                    across India and up to Sikkim—was quite an experience.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>But, back to the Consular District, I can't remember anything really
                    outstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were engaged there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't know whether you want to know about this or not. I was
                    engaged. My former husband was an American businessman. His family company is
                    the Singer Sewing Machine Company and he covered the whole Middle East. We went
                    back to the States to get married. I took leave and wanted him to come to
                    Washington to meet the India desk officer. Carol Laise was the India desk
                    officer and she said, “Kay, are you crazy?” I said, “Why?” She said, “Don't you
                    know women officers aren't allowed to be married?” I said, “No, why?” She said,
                    “They feel that a husband would not follow his wife around the world.” I said,
                    “My husband has more foreign office posts than we do!” She said, “That's beside
                    the point. You'd better get out of town fast, before they pick up your
                    diplomatic passport.” So, we dashed off back to India.</p>
                <p>Milton Rewinkel was still Consul General and he said, “Kay, why would you want to
                    keep working when you're married?” Well, the memos went back and forth, because
                    I was fighting it. Milton said I could stay on only as a local employee. They
                    kicked me out of my apartment, which was no problem, because my former husband
                    had his apartment. Of course, I received no allowances. Then Milton left and Dan
                    Braddock came on as CG. Dan was very nice and very understanding and tried to
                    back me up. He sent cables, but didn't get very far.</p>
                <p>Washington then said that I could stay on for another six months if I went to
                    Delhi as consular officer. Well, I was a political cone officer by then and I
                    did not want to ruin that, so I absolutely refused. I told Dan, “I'm going to
                    take leave” and gave him my leave addresses and went off to visit my brother in
                    California. While I was there, an old friend of mine from Tehran who was in the
                    Personnel Department—the same guy I went down to Shiraz with—called and said,
                    “They're taking up your case and they're suggesting that they'll keep you on in
                    a Civil Service position at the lowest rank possible in the Department,”
                    although I would still be a Foreign Service officer. I went back to DC and tried
                    to fight it out but didn't succeed. So I had to leave the Department.</p>
                <p>I went up to New York, where I had a second career, first with Coopers and
                    Lybrand, one of the big eight accounting firms. They had acquired an employee
                    benefits company. As they had hundreds of offices around the States and abroad,
                    they wanted to sell their accounting clients on employee benefits: stock-sharing
                    plans, health plans, retirement plan. Connected with that would be letting the
                    employees know what their benefits were. As I had majored in communications,
                    they interviewed me and said, “We don't really know what's going to be involved
                    and we don't know anything about you. We'll take you on for at least six months.
                    After that, we'll review the whole situation. We want you to figure out how to
                    set up an employee benefits communication operation.” They gave me a fairly low
                    salary, but said, “If everything works out after six months, we'll reevaluate
                    your salary.”</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>I decided to take Coopers and Lybrand's benefit plans to write my first employee
                    booklets. They had five or six and I studied all of the technical documents for
                    their plans. Then, I hired somebody to design the booklets. We did a booklet for
                    each plan and boxed them. In six months, I took that in and said, “This is what
                    I intend to do for your clients,” and they loved it. So, they immediately raised
                    my salary to more than I'd been making when I left the State Department. I hired
                    a staff and we went to work. We had big clients such as Coca-Cola. I traveled
                    around the country getting their business. Computers were in by then and we
                    started a computerized employee benefits statement for employees that said, “If
                    you retire by age 65 this is what you get. If you are disabled at such and such
                    an age, this is what you get.” It had the logo of the company and I sold it to a
                    lot of companies. Coca-Cola, I think, was the first one to go for it.</p>
                <p>Then, George B. Buck, which was involved just with employee benefits, stole me
                    away from Coopers and Lybrand. They gave me a lot more money.</p>
                <p>All this time, I'd been keeping in contact with the State Department. I had left
                    in 1967. In 1972, a letter came to all the women who'd been forced out, saying
                    that we could come back in at the grade and salary that we had when we left, or,
                    if we had since been working, they would match that. Well, they couldn't match
                    mine, because I was making more than the Secretary of State. There were lots of
                    letters and cables going back and forth. I had to have my security clearance
                    updated. Three years later, in 1975, they still had not updated my security
                    check, which only involved living in two places 10 blocks apart, and working in
                    two offices five blocks apart. Carol Laise was then assigned to be Director
                    General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Director General.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I remember sending her a letter, congratulating her. I said, “P.S.:
                    could you-” Two days later, I got a telephone call, saying my security clearance
                    was ready. They'd been hoping that I'd go away. So, then came the battle with
                    the Department. They finally said, “Well, we'll bring you back only at the top
                    of an FS-01.” They were not going to bring me into the Senior Service, which, if
                    they were going to match my salary, they should have done.</p>
                <p>But, I liked the Foreign Service. I liked the way of life. I liked traveling. By
                    this time, my former husband and I had split up, although we were still very
                    good friends and still are. I got married when I was too old. I was 40 and
                    wanted to do my own thing. And he understood. He was very nice.</p>
                <p>I got back in the Foreign Service. First, they brought me in, in 1975, to the
                    Task Force for Resettling the Indo-Chinese, which was headed by Julia Taft. I
                    was the liaison with the press and Congress. That was while they were trying to
                    find a job for me.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about that for a minute. What was the situation
                        that caused this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: A lot of them were coming and, as I remember, most of them went
                    down around the Gulf. A lot of them were fishermen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're really talking about the end of the Vietnamese War,
                        where South Vietnam had collapsed. There were many people coming out by boat
                        and all this. The problem was resettling. We felt we had an obligation to do
                        something about this. You say you were working as a liaison. What were the
                        problems of dealing with the Congress? What were the issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The issues were primarily that a lot of these people were
                    fishermen. They were settling down around the Gulf and the American fishermen
                    down there objected to them. They didn't want them around and they would go to
                    the Congressmen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we respond?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: As I remember, we were still trying to get them places to live down
                    there. That's where they wanted to be. I wasn't there very long. This was only a
                    temporary job until they found me a place in the Department. I don't think I was
                    there for more than four or five months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Then I was brought in to OES—Office of Oceans and International
                    Environmental and Scientific Affairs as Deputy Director of the Office of
                    Fisheries Affairs. The DAS at that time was Roz Ridgway. This was one of the
                    most fascinating jobs I've ever had. I didn't know the front end of a fish from
                    the back end when I got in there. I was there for only four days when Roz
                    Ridgway came in and said, “Kay, we've got a problem. We've been trying to
                    renegotiate our North Pacific Fur Seal Treaty.” (This was the oldest treaty we
                    had. It was from the early 1900s - 1906 or so.) She said, “We started last
                    spring. This treaty involves four countries: Japan, the Soviet Union, Canada,
                    and The United States. After several weeks last spring, we were deadlocked. We
                    have to get this renegotiated by the end of this year, or we've lost the treaty.
                    Next week, we're meeting again. The Japanese delegation came in and said they
                    would not participate unless there were an independent chairman for the
                    negotiation. In the spring, the chief of the US delegation had chaired the
                    negotiations and the Japanese did not like that. So, I would like you to chair
                    it.”</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>As I say, I knew nothing about fish. I had never been in a negotiation before. I
                    didn't know anything. I got a book of Robert's Rules of Order and all weekend I
                    read everything I could in the files of past treaties. I worked night and day.
                    The negotiation was held in one of the main negotiating rooms in the State
                    Department. The four delegations were seated around a big, circular table. To my
                    left, fortunately, was the Secretary of the North Pacific Fur Seals Committee,
                    which had been set up to run things in the interim. Above me were the
                    translators in their booths and there were microphones on the table.</p>
                <p>So, I started out. I'll never forget—the Japanese delegation was straight across
                    the table from me and the Japanese Ambassador kept smiling and nodding his head
                    in encouragement. Whenever I had a question, I would say to the guy next to me,
                    the Secretary, “What should I do now?” I soon learned that the most important
                    negotiating tool is absolute silence. I learned a lot of things. At the first
                    coffee break, one of the guys from the translating booth came down and said,
                    “Will you please signal to us when you want the microphones opened. Fortunately,
                    this morning, when you first started, they were closed but we got them open.” He
                    told me a little red light on the table signaled whether they were open. Well,
                    we accomplished our mission. At the end of two weeks, we had a new treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did we want and what did the Soviets and Canadians
                        and Japanese want?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: All everybody wanted was one, conservation of the species and, two,
                    to be able to harvest the species. The seals migrate from off of Southern
                    California up to the waters off Alaska. Both the Japanese and the Russians were
                    fighting to take larger catches. Our concern was more for preserving the
                    species.</p>
                <p>I learned a lot out of it. There were several interesting things. One is that
                    this species of fur seal is found in only one other place and that's off the
                    coast of Namibia. The second is that those seals that are harvested are skinned
                    in one place only—I believe it's in South Carolina. The Namibians send theirs
                    there. Then, the pelts usually go off to European markets. The meat goes to mink
                    farms in the US to feed the mink. The Namibians were starting to harvest and
                    wanted to send their animals to our plant. We said they had to prove that they
                    were harvested humanely. For the members of the treaty, “humane” meant the young
                    seals were hit on the head and stunned and then their throats were slit. This
                    way, they don't feel anything. It ended up that we sent Aleut fur seal hunters
                    from Alaska down to Namibia to teach them how to harvest humanely. They then
                    were approved to send their animals here to be skinned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that the people you were dealing with
                        were...I'm thinking that, often, the Canadians prove to be the most
                        difficult people to negotiate with.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, it depends upon the particular subject. On this one, they
                    were no problem at all. I had other people doing the North Atlantic Treaties,
                    where the Canadians were much more involved. For instance, you take salmon. The
                    salmon species in our rivers were practically nil by this time. We had a
                    fisheries operation in New England where we were breeding them and planting them
                    in the rivers to try to regenerate the species. They would then migrate out to
                    sea and go up along the coast of Nova Scotia. Then the Canadians would get them.
                    Of the first bunch that we put in, I think only seven ever came back because
                    they harvested them all. So, this was one of our big battles.</p>
                <p>We also had battles on our Great Lakes Treaty on harvesting. Eels was one of our
                    problems up there. I also sat on the North Pacific Fisheries Council. We worked
                    very closely with NMFS, the National Marine Fishery Service, over in the
                    Department of Commerce. We've got these Fisheries Management Councils in New
                    England, the Gulf, etc. I also worked on tuna fisheries. They were a major
                    problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Ecuador and that area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, the South Pacific. Our major problem, by the way, was with
                    American fishermen—not other countries. I flew around the world with Roz Ridgway
                    on various treaty negotiating missions. Every time we would start a negotiation,
                    we'd get together with our own team, which comprised all the fisheries, such as
                    seiners and the trawlers, canners, and frozen food companies, as well as the
                    American Indians in the Northern Pacific because we have treaties with them that
                    come first. We've had them since the 19th century. Of course, there were also
                    representatives from the Commerce and Interior Departments. Everyone of our
                    teams comprised 50 or 60 people. We'd spend more time negotiating with our teams
                    than we ever did with the other countries.</p>
                <p>American fishermen are pirates. Right now, you're probably reading about how so
                    much of the fishing in the North Atlantic has been decimated. The American
                    fishermen claim that's not true because they want to keep fishing. In about 1975
                    the Law of the Sea Treaty joined, and that's when we went out to the 12-mile
                    limit and 200-mile economic zone. The tuna fishermen would take their boats
                    inside the 12-mile limits of countries in the South Pacific and often they would
                    then be confiscated. Then the American taxpayer had to pay a lot of money to get
                    them out. Most of our treaties limit fishing on the various species to certain
                    windows and then only certain numbers could be taken. It was a continual battle.
                    The fisheries management groups tried very hard, but the fishermen always won
                    out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did the fishermen have such a strong lobby?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: This was their sustenance. This was where they made all their
                    money.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean, they were a fairly small proportion of voters or
                        something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: But then look at all the business people who were involved with
                    fish, such as tuna canners or salmon canners. There are lots of business people
                    involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume that the Congress people from California and
                        Washington, Oregon, and New England would be on you all the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Absolutely. But it was an interesting time. For instance, we had
                    our meetings on fur seals in Moscow and in Tokyo and in Ottawa and in the
                    States. We got to do a lot of traveling and I enjoyed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Roz Ridgway operate as you saw her there? I've
                        heard the story that, every time she got into trouble and something
                        happened, they kept throwing her back into fish all the time. I think she
                        ended up dealing with fish a number of times in her career.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: She may have, I don't know. When she was stationed in South America
                    or Central America, I think she had something to do with fish there.</p>
                <p>She was a marvelous person to work with. In all of our various negotiations, she
                    always led the delegation. I think I mentioned the complexity of our own
                    delegation, where everybody had to be represented. She could mediate beautifully
                    among all of them. She'd let everybody say their thing and get on to other
                    people and somehow she made everybody happy. We always came to an agreement on
                    our position before we went out to negotiate with the other countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about in dealing with other countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The same way—just really top notch. Everybody respected her very,
                    very much. The countries that I worked with were mostly Canada, Japan and the
                    Soviet Union. We traveled together to all of these places. It seemed like my
                    entire tour was spent mostly abroad. All the other countries highly respected
                    her. We never had any problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find that in these negotiations, did the other
                        countries have sort of their professional fish people, or were they usually
                        Foreign Ministry?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, they had the same kind of delegations we did. Their
                    professional fish people were represented as well as members of their
                    government. Ours was complicated a little bit, in that, as I mentioned before,
                    we had the 19th century fisheries agreements with various Pacific Northwest
                    Indians. Those all had to be taken into consideration. But that was primarily in
                    setting up our position on our side, not in dealing with the other countries. I
                    told you about the very first one that I was involved in and how supportive the
                    Japanese were. It was an interesting time. As I say, when I got in, I didn't
                    know the front end of a fish from the back end, but I sure learned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left fisheries when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '77.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In '77, I was assigned to Lagos, Nigeria as Political Counselor.
                    That was a fantastic time to be in Nigeria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Lagos from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: From '77 through '79 — three years. At that time, General Obasanjo
                    was head of state. It was a military government. He made the decision to step
                    down and to set up an elected government. He sent representatives to a number of
                    countries in the world to look into the types of government they had. They were
                    mostly oil-producing countries because that was and is the greatest source of
                    Nigerian income. They liked our form of government the best so he set up a
                    committee to draft a constitution. They were meeting down the street from our
                    Embassy. They came and used our library continuously and were always coming in
                    and asking questions and asking for advice. I'll never forget one night. I was
                    awakened at two in the morning at my home and one of the guys from the committee
                    said, “Kay, we've got a real problem. You've got to help us.” I said, “What's
                    that?” They said, “What happens in the United States when the House of
                    Representatives doesn't agree with the Senate?” So, I explained the joint
                    committee system and after they left, it dawned on me that none of this is in
                    our constitution. Our constitution's very general, but they had to have every
                    single detail put into their constitution. They decided to have two legislative
                    branches in each of their states—they had at least 12 states at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they were going to have a Federal Republic as opposed
                        to a unified...Of course, Nigeria is a vast country. Were they going to keep
                        a federal system?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: They asked me to bring in experts to go around the country and
                    explain to the people in all the states how, in our country, the states related
                    to the federal government. So, we did. We brought in professors and people like
                    that.</p>
                <p>When it came to forming parties and having elections, other problems arose. Large
                    numbers of the population in Nigeria were illiterate. They ended up with five
                    parties and decided to have symbols for each party. The voting mechanism was a
                    problem. They did not have electricity in a large part of the country. So, we
                    brought in a firm from Chicago to erect voting machines that were mechanical
                    that could accommodate the party symbols. The elections went on fine. The
                    elected government went into office. Obasanjo stepped down and retired to his
                    farm. I left shortly thereafter the election. After I got back to the States,
                    before going on to my next assignment, I went skiing in the Rockies. We stopped
                    at a rest stop and I picked up a newspaper. There it had the news on the front
                    page that the Nigerian elected government had been overthrown by the military.
                    There would been a military coup. All I could think of was, “What did we miss?
                    What did we do wrong?” I came to the conclusion that we didn't stress that the
                    chief of our military is a civilian—the elected President. However, I don't
                    think that would have made any difference. They've got the problem of too many
                    ethnic groups.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think this is one of the problems of the Americans.
                        Here, Nigeria has a coup, and you as the American representative say, “What
                        did we do wrong?” You can build these things, but it really took a couple
                        centuries for our system to develop and it's still going through the
                        process.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Could you talk a little about American representation there? Who was the
                    Ambassador? Did we have any Consulates and any other programs going?</p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: During the three years I was there, we had two ambassadors: Don
                    Easum and Steve Low. One DCM was Parker Wyman. We had consulates in Ibadan,
                    Kaduna, and one out in the East. One of the officers in the Political Section,
                    not too long after I arrived, asked to be sent up to Ibadan as Consul. Of
                    course, you know, now they've closed most of those and the capital has moved to
                    Abuja. They were working on having the capital in Abuja when I was there, but
                    years went by before it was actually moved up. But I believe our Embassy is
                    still in Lagos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got there, it was a military rule. Did you feel
                        that the country was going to be able to move into a new mode, into a
                        civilian role again? What was our way of looking at the situation in
                        Nigeria, that the military seems to step in a lot?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Of course, when the Brits had moved out, they'd had civilian rule
                    for a while before the Obasanjo government came in. We firmly believed they
                    should try again. Nigeria, as you know, is the largest country in Africa. One
                    out of every four Africans is a Nigerian. It has a number of universities,
                    whereas many of the other states in Africa don't. So, although there were lots
                    of uneducated people, there were lots of educated people too—very knowledgeable.
                    And the Nigerians, in general, reminded me of Americans. We used to say when I
                    was there that, at any given time, 50 million people would be selling something
                    to the other 50 million. They were all entrepreneurs. The feeling was that this
                    was what the people wanted and this was why Obasanjo did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we view the ethnic divisions of Nigeria? Did we
                        see this as something that could be, as a system, made to work? What were
                        the prime causes of trouble over ethnic...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The same as in all African countries. The same as in Yugoslavia.
                    The same as in Ireland and England. These people each had their own customs and
                    religions and felt that they should be the ones running the country, or at least
                    their areas. It's a chronic problem. I think there were over 50 different ethnic
                    groups. The three biggest ones were the Northern Muslims, the Yorubas in the
                    west, and the Ibos in the east. Of course, you know about the war with the
                    Ibos?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Biafran War, yes. When you were there, had the Biafran
                        problem been more or less resolved? Was it something that everybody
                        remembered?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Of course everyone remembered it, but they were at peace. They
                    allowed us to travel every place. There were no daily confrontations and
                    everyone was going about their own business.</p>
                <p>Dealing as a Political Officer with the Nigerians was very interesting for me. I
                    had government quarters and I had a guest house, which most of the other
                    government quarters did not have. So, when we had distinguished visitors, they
                    usually stayed in my guest house. If I wanted to have a reception for them, a
                    Nigerian would not accept an invitation just because I was a political officer,
                    or First Secretary in the Embassy. They only accepted invitations from people
                    they knew. So, I learned very soon that, when this would happen, to hand-carry
                    my invitations to the invitees. Of course, at the beginning, I didn't know all
                    the people that were on a list. But, in no time at all, I got to know them. Even
                    then, I'd tell them to think about it and I'd come back to see what their answer
                    was, so I could see them again. This way, I could assure attendance. But you
                    could not assure attendance just by the person you asked. He might show up with
                    five grandkids and two uncles. You never knew. I don't care what kind of a
                    function it was. So, you had to learn to adjust for that. And we had lots of
                    distinguished visitors when I was there. People such as Mohammed Ali stayed in
                    my place.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The world champion boxer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes. Vice President Mondale stayed in my place. Charlie Diggs.
                    Remember Charlie Diggs?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, he was a Congressmen from Chicago.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes. They were all interesting in their own way. The Nigerian
                    ladies went mad over Mohammed Ali. Every time he'd step out of the compound or
                    walk down the street, he'd be surrounded by women. It was interesting. Because
                    of the Nigerian personality, I got to know an awful lot of people and they
                    became very good friends of mine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a political officer—you were mentioning that you had to
                        sort of get to know people—how did this...I'm interested in not just
                        Nigeria, but how would a political officer, a Political Counselor, work in
                        Nigeria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The same as in any country. You get your directives from the
                    Department: go in and tell them what our position is on such and such an issue
                    in the United Nations; go in and tell them what we think about South Africa. Or
                    we would get telegrams in, saying, “We need more information on some of these
                    topics,” so you'd go talk with people, chat with them, invite them over, go out
                    to dinner, and try to get the information as easily as you could.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find it a pretty open society?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, very open. In Nigeria, like most African countries, women sort
                    of run everything. They run the markets. You do see some men in the fields, but
                    they were mostly women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about in the ministries, newspapers, universities?
                        What was the role of women there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't remember. I don't think there were very many in the
                    newspapers or universities, although there were some university teachers and
                    professors that I knew. I'm sure there were not as many as men. Still, the role
                    in business is what sort of fascinated me as an American. At that time, women in
                    the United States did not have that kind of a role. Of course, this was
                    reinforced when I lived in other African countries after Nigeria.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American prime concerns during the time you were
                        in Nigeria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In the late ''70s, I don't remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was South Africa playing in those times?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Nigeria played, and does to this day, a major role in inter-African
                    problems. When organizations or committees were established, Nigeria was always
                    very prominent and took charge. That was another reason why I was spending so
                    much time in the ministries, trying to get information on African subjects.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have much contact within the Nigerian
                        military?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I think we did. We had an Attach�. Of course, I had nothing to do
                    with that at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was wondering whether you would be in contact with the
                        Attach�, since the military had a tendency to come in and out of running the
                        government? From the political point of view, whatever we could get about
                        the military should be shared, I would think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't remember that as happening. As I say, I had not been there
                    very long when they decided to have the civilian form of government, so we
                    didn't pay any attention to the military. I met Obasanjo from time to time and
                    he was very easy for us to deal with and to work with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the Carter Administration most of the time you
                        were there, wasn't it? Did human rights play any particular role at that
                        time in Nigeria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not that I know of. As I say, women had fairly strong roles and I
                    never found a Nigerian who was anti-white. However, we had, occasionally,
                    Afro-Americans in the Foreign service or one of the government agencies, and
                    some of them were prejudiced against the Africans. This was really eye-opening
                    to me, to see this happening. In fact, one person had to be transferred due to
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it easy to get into the Foreign Ministry?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, I had no problems. I could walk in without an appointment. In
                    no time at all, I knew everybody. I could go wherever I wanted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the UN vote? This always was a problem. Was
                        Nigeria a problem as far as we were concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not generally, no. Of course, they usually voted with the African
                    countries on a lot of the subjects. But they were always receptive if I had a
                    position to give them. They would always say, “I'll take this up with the
                    Minister of Foreign Affairs, or I'll take this up with so and so.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did Easum and Steve Low operate? How did you find
                        working with them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Both of them were just terrific. They were very cooperative and
                    they gave me carte blanche to run the Political Section and to do the job that
                    they wanted me to do. They both were liked by the Nigerians. They both
                    entertained nicely. I remain very close friends with both of them. Don is up in
                    New York now and Steve is here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the impression of not only you but your officers
                        in the Political Section about the viability as a democracy of Nigeria
                        during this time, in the late ''70s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I think everybody felt that it was only a matter of time before it
                    would fall, because of the ethnic groups. This was Africa. This was the history.
                    It depended upon who managed to get voted in and what the supporting ethnic
                    groups would think of that person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any concern about the survivability of Nigeria
                        as a country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Oh, no. As I say, the Nigerians are entrepreneurs. They're very
                    strong people and they are in the majority in Africa. There is no doubt that
                    Nigeria will survive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't see a splitting up of Nigeria?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, not in any way, although we know that they tried to at one
                    time, but that was gone. There have been problems recently, of course, among a
                    smaller tribal group down in the Biafran area. They claim that Mobil oil is
                    ruining their environment and damaging their sustenance down there. But these
                    incidents are going to occur all the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the British playing much of a role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not at all. The Brits as colonists were great after they left. They
                    pulled out completely. Only one Brit remained in the country. That was up in the
                    North and he was a judge. He was just there for a couple of years and then he
                    retired. They pulled out of all the jobs completely, whereas the French did not.
                    They left thousands of Frenchmen in C�te d'Ivoire. They filled practically all
                    of the ministry jobs— the big government jobs. After they pulled out and Ivory
                    Coast started educating its own people, the young college graduates couldn't get
                    jobs in the government because they were all filled by Frenchmen. Finally, the
                    Ivorians told the French they had to leave. Because these Frenchmen had lived
                    all their lives there, they didn't want to go back to France. They didn't know
                    what to do with themselves. We had a large influx of them into Guinea when I was
                    there and I know they went into some of the other surrounding countries. You
                    didn't find that in any of the former British colonies. The Brits just left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Nigeria when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '79.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Back to the Department to become Deputy Director of the Office of
                    West African Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '80 to '82.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was in charge of African Affairs at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Some of the time, it was Chet Crocker, and some of the time, it was
                    Dick Moose as Assistant Secretary. But the Director of the Office of West
                    African Affairs first was Bob Bruce and then Parker Borg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What countries did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: All of the West African countries, both Anglophone and Francophone.
                    When I left, I was replaced by two people, one for the Francophone and one for
                    the Anglophone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your main concerns?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I don't remember any main ones. They were all the little nitpicky
                    things that were always going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Reagan came in in '81. I was wondering whether you saw any
                        particular change at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, not at all. You know, Africa basically, in American foreign
                    policy, was not at the top. It never was. Many of the problems we had when I was
                    in Africa and in the Department concerned American businesses who wanted to do
                    business in various countries. They might have problems in the various countries
                    where they were operating—oil companies, or bauxite or diamond mines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In one of the West African countries, I can't remember
                        exactly when it happened, but in Liberia when there was the violent
                        overthrow of...Were there any...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I can't remember any big problems of overthrows or changes of
                    government at that time. Most of the countries were still under dictatorships,
                    such as Guinea and Sekou Toure—he was a civilian. You have Houphouet-Boigny in
                    C�te d'Ivoire. Most of these were people who'd been around for quite a while and
                    most of the overthrows came after the time I was there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In '82.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And where did you go then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I went to Guinea as DCM.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Guinea as...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Guinea, Conakry. There's Guinea Bissau and Guinea. Conakry is the
                    capital of Guinea. It was Francophone. Guinea-Bissau was Portuguese. This was
                    over on the West Coast, near Senegal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the Ambassador at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I had two of them: Alan Davis and Jim Rosenthal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you got there, how did they use you as the DCM? Every
                        Ambassador sort of has their own...?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, Alan was the first one. He wasn't there too long. I was the
                    usual: running the place on the inside. But he did have me go represent our
                    government in the ministries. But, as I say, he wasn't there too long.</p>
                <p>Jim Rosenthal came in and Jim just sort of turned everything over to me. He'd
                    been DCM in Philippines, I believe, before he came there. He said, “Kay, I never
                    got to travel in the Philippines. I never got to do anything because I just had
                    to run the Embassy. So, you're going to run the Embassy here. I'm going to get
                    out and meet people and travel.” That he did and I had some of the greatest
                    challenges in my life while I was there, let me tell you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: On one occasion, he went off to visit his friend, Bill Miller, who
                    was the Ambassador in Ivory Coast. As Charge, I was awakened at four one morning
                    by the duty officer. A cable came in from the Department, saying that the King
                    of Saudi Arabia had sent them a telegram, saying that his pal, Sekou Toure, the
                    Guinean Head of State, had had a heart attack and he wanted to send an airplane
                    in and have it take Sekou Toure to the Cleveland Clinic in the United States,
                    which was evidently used by the Saudis. The State Department asked me to check
                    this out and see if it were true. So, I first went to his downtown residence.
                    There were military guards around, but they all said that Sekou Toure wasn't
                    there. Nobody would help me. The Foreign Minister lived just down the street
                    from me. By this time, it was five or so in the morning. The Foreign Minister
                    was not there and his wife said she did not know where he was and she did not
                    know where Sekou Toure was.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>Well, time was fleeting and the duty officer caught up with me and said that a
                    Saudi plane was on its way with doctors and that the King of Morocco, who was
                    also a friend of Sekou Toure was sending a plane. Would I please tell the
                    Guineans, because neither of these planes had permission to enter the airport.
                    So, I dashed out to the airport and ran up the flight tower. They said, “We
                    can't do anything. You'll have to get the Prime Minister to give us the okay to
                    let these planes land.” So, I dashed back downtown again, went to the head of
                    the military guarding the President's home, and said, “This is the situation. I
                    stopped by the Prime Minister's house and he wasn't there. Where can I find
                    these people?” Finally, he said, “I'll send a soldier with you.” First, we went
                    to the Prime Minister's home even though I said, “He's not there.” Then he took
                    me to a villa on the outskirts of town, which was used by the government for
                    visiting dignitaries and left me sitting in the car outside the gate for a
                    while. Finally, he came back and said, “Okay, we'll take you downtown to the
                    Prime Minister's office and you can meet with the Prime Minister.”</p>
                <p>So, we went down to the Prime Minister's office. The duty officer caught up with
                    me again and said that the planes had been turned away and had gone to Liberia.
                    I explained the situation to the Prime Minister and he said, “Well, there's
                    really no need for them to send these planes in. But I'll have the airfield
                    notified to allow them to land.”</p>
                <p>So, I went back out to the airfield. They finally came in with lots of doctors
                    and nurses. We all went back to the villa outside the city. By this time, they
                    had Guinean doctors there and the Saudi and Moroccan doctors went in. I was also
                    allowed to go in—In fact, I had to interpret for some of them. They said the
                    Secretary had had a heart attack and agreed to medevac him to the clinic in
                    Cleveland. So, people were rushing around to pack up. We set out in a caravan of
                    cars. By this time, it was late afternoon or evening. When a big caravan goes
                    through the streets of Conakry, people usually stop and stare. But there were no
                    flashing lights or police cars preceding the caravan. It was very quiet and
                    nobody took much notice of us. We got out to the airport and they had to decide
                    which plane to take. Just as we had thought that everybody was on, one of the
                    doors burst open and four or five people came dashing down the stairs of the
                    airplane. It turned out that Sekou Toure's suitcase had been locked up in the
                    hold. So, they had to get it out and get it up to where he was. They finally
                    took off. Of course, by this time, it was the middle of the night. I went back
                    to the office and got off all my cables to everybody. Of course, nobody had
                    visas or passports and New York and Cleveland and the State Department had to be
                    warned. I went home and collapsed for a little while.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>But then the cables started coming in. The first one said that, soon after Sekou
                    Toure got there, he died. Then they said that the plane that was bringing his
                    body back was coming in at a certain time. And then the cables came in that the
                    leader of our delegation would be Vice President Bush and the Secret Service
                    people were going to precede him and set everything up. Well, I lived in the
                    Embassy for the next week. Fortunately, we had a commissary in the basement and
                    I had a couch in my office. The Secret Service, after looking things over, were
                    not very comfortable with security in Guinea and decided they would not let Bush
                    stay there overnight, although I had arranged for a cottage for him. They'd
                    bring him in the morning for the funeral and take him out as soon as it was
                    over.</p>
                <p>On the day of the funeral they first had a ceremony in a big sports stadium and
                    then the entourage went to a mosque that had been recently built by the Saudis.
                    They put all of the dignitaries, such as Vice President Bush, on an ancient, old
                    bus, where they had to stand hanging on straps. So, as the entourage went down
                    the streets, our Secret Service were running alongside this old bus. They got to
                    the mosque and, as non-Muslims were not allowed inside, they had to wait
                    outside. Finally, they returned to the Embassy and got Bush out of there. I got
                    all my cables off and went home.</p>
                <p>Early the next morning there was a military coup d'etat. I was awakened by the
                    duty officer and wanted to get down to the Embassy. I set out in the middle of
                    the night and none of the street lights were on. There were military guard posts
                    on all the roads. The first one stopped me and said, “You can't proceed.” By the
                    way, this was on July 4th. I told them who I was, showed them my i.d., and said,
                    “This is our national day and I have to go to my Ambassador's.” They were very
                    sympathetic about things like that, so they took me to a nearby police station
                    and I was told I would have to be escorted and a civilian who happened to be
                    there was told to escort me. He had been out of the country for 30 years and
                    said he was a newspaper reporter. He took me over to the Ambassador's, talking
                    me through many stop points.</p>
                <p>When we arrived at the Ambassador's, we were told he had already left for the
                    Embassy. My escort agreed to take me to the Embassy because he wanted to go
                    downtown to file a story. He was carrying an infrared camera and was taking
                    pictures of everything in the dark. We got down there and, of course, our
                    concerns were the welfare and whereabouts of American citizens. There were not
                    too many in Guinea— about 40 or 50—and most of them were missionaries out in the
                    countryside. There were also some business people because there was a big
                    aluminum extraction operation there. We tried to get in contact with as many of
                    those as we could and to get off messages to all of their relatives in the
                    States, saying that they were okay. It was a bloodless coup d'etat, by the
                    way—there was no shooting.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>The new military colonel took over as the new head of state. Sekou Toure had
                    taken over as head of state when the French left in 1958. He was, in a way, a
                    dictator, and most everything was nationalized with businesses being run by the
                    government. Well, the new guy wanted to denationalize business. People, for the
                    first time, felt they could talk freely and openly on the streets. Little
                    businesses were sprouting up and it was a very good time. He was very open and
                    friendly to us—we had good entree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were American concerns in Guinea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: When we first got there, when Sekou Toure was still in charge, it
                    was primarily his relationship with the Russians, as were our concerns in most
                    countries. He was friendly with them. After he took over he had come to us for
                    help to develop his country. As we had no interests there at that time, we
                    weren't really interested so he turned to the Russians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there, we're talking about what, '80,
                        '82?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, we're talking about '82 to '85.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the role of the Soviets at that point?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: You didn't see them around much. They had an embassy and they were
                    giving monetary support to Sekou Toure.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any strategic elements to Guinea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, not at all. As I say, it was very undeveloped—backward. We had
                    no interest there. There was one American aluminum company and that was about
                    it. And about 40 missionaries. For instance, we had to ship in all of our food
                    from Denmark. You could buy fruits and vegetables and that was all.
                    Occasionally, you'd go to a market and you might see a carcass of a chicken
                    covered with flies hanging from a stall, but not too often. There just was
                    nothing there.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>When I first went there, there was one French hotel that had a restaurant in it.
                    There were one or two restaurants in town and that was basically it. The first
                    month I was there, I decided to take three friends out for dinner one night to
                    this one restaurant. I wanted to see what it was like. I was told, “Bring your
                    own wine because they'll charge you $100 for a bottle of wine,” so I brought
                    wine. Well, they had no choice on what to order. They served us chicken in
                    peanut sauce on rice and some salad and, for dessert, a big piece of pineapple
                    cut up in pieces. They didn't even have coffee. Well, it cost me over $300 for
                    four people.So, social life was just among ourselves, primarily, and the other
                    embassies. Of course, we had social affairs and invited Guinean officials, but
                    they didn't entertain very much. They couldn't afford to. They didn't have
                    anything to entertain with, let's put it that way. So, it was a simple life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have the usual thing, of trying to get the
                        Guineans to vote correctly at the UN, or was it sort of a lost cause?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Very often, the Ambassador and I were received by Sekou Toure and
                    he would listen to us, but generally he would side more with the USSR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any other elements there, like the Libyans or
                        did anybody really pay much attention?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, Sekou Toure had his personal friends, the King of Morocco and
                    the Saudi Arabians. He talked the Saudis into building a very nice mosque.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the country play any role in the African context?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Not too much, no. They interacted with the other Francophone
                    countries in various meetings occasionally, as they still do today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the French? Was there much French influence
                        there at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Interestingly, not too much. But, as I mentioned before, half way
                    during my tour there, a lot of French people came in from C�te d'Ivoire looking
                    for jobs. By this time, of course, we'd already had our coup d'etat and there
                    were jobs opening up. There was a Francophone school. My first Ambassador's wife
                    was a French woman and she taught in the school. French was the major language
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there...?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In '85.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: First, did you find any change in our relations after
                        Sekou Toure died?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, our relations improved immensely because the new head of
                    state, as I said, was trying to cancel out whatever Sekou Toure had done with
                    regard to nationalizing businesses. He was trying to privatize everything and of
                    course, he would ask for advice on various things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In '85, where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I went to Cameroon, to Douala, as Consul General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '85 to '87. That was interesting because the capital of Cameroon is
                    Yaounde, which is up north in the mountains. Douala is a seaport and is far
                    larger. The capital is almost a country town in comparison. All the businesses
                    are in Douala, which is the economic center. The only international airport at
                    that time was in Douala. I think they now have one in Yaounde. So, anybody who
                    wanted to go to Yaounde would have to come to Douala and then transfer to
                    Cameroon airlines for Yaounde. They had offshore oil and a good-sized seaport,
                    as I've said. We and the Brits had banks and businesses of various kinds.
                    Equatorial Guinea was next door and our Embassy there had a representative, a
                    local employee, in the consulate general. Everything that came over for their
                    capital came in through that port, so he took care of all that kind of stuff.
                    All shipments for the embassy came in through Douala, so he took care of
                    transferring them to Malabo. All shipments for Cameroon, Chad, and Central
                    African Empire, also came into the port of Douala, so much of our time was spent
                    handling those shipments</p>
                <p>We had a commercial attach� but did not have an economic officer. The economic
                    officer was stationed in Yaounde. So, I sort of covered the political and
                    economic scenes. I had an administrative assistant and a good-sized Cameroonian
                    staff. But, as far as consular activities, there were not really that many and
                    there were not that many Americans around.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Half way through my tour, it seemed a waste of resources to keep this as a
                    consulate general. I thought it should be downsized to a consulate, unless they
                    were willing to transfer the economic section to Douala where all the economic
                    activity was, which they weren't. Well, Washington agreed with me. This was
                    interesting because I made the same recommendation in Rotterdam when I was there
                    and nobody would listen to me. So, I spent my last year there downsizing the CG.
                    I managed to find a position for every local employee that I let go.
                    Fortunately, new American businesses were coming in that needed staffing.</p>
                <p>I had another challenge shortly after I arrived in Douala. I was exploring the
                    building, trying to find out where everything was. I noticed a ladder going up
                    into the attic and climbed up the ladder to see what was up there. The building
                    was an 'L' shape. We were at the bottom part of the L and the leg up had several
                    apartments that Cameroonian citizens lived in. This attic was open over both
                    areas. I was appalled at the security risk and wondered why it had been allowed
                    all that time. So, I immediately went in to the Department recommending that we
                    take over the other wing or move. USIA had an office downtown and
                    coincidentally, they were looking to move at that time. So, we got them to agree
                    to move in and got the tenants out. We remodeled it the way USIA wanted it. As
                    we did not have a good motor pool or parking area, we took advantage of the
                    remodeling and got walls put up for that. So, that was a nice challenge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of a government did the Cameroons have when you
                        were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, as in Guinea, a civilian government, but sort of what we
                    would call “dictatorial,” not absolutely open. We were so involved in working
                    with all of the shipments that came in and the business scene that I did not get
                    too much involved with political things.</p>
                <p>Also, the Ambassador, Myles Frechette, was not too cooperative when it came to
                    reporting. For instance, when I had been in the Office of Fisheries Affairs, I
                    had worked very closely with people in NOA and NMFS. One of the guys over there
                    had said, “By the way, when you go to Cameroon, we would very much like a report
                    on their port and fishing activities. Could you do that for us?” I said, “Sure,
                    let me get a chance to get settled in.” Well, I did, and the Ambassador
                    reprimanded me for sending in the report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was who?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: He was the Ambassador in Yaounde. He said, “You should have asked
                    the Economic Officer to do that.” Well, I had been told the Consulate General
                    had a certain amount of leeway in reporting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course it does.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: And I sent copies of everything to him. In this instance, he sent a
                    cable to the Department telling them that he was withdrawing that report. Of
                    course, Commerce already had it and I got a nice cable from them thanking me so
                    much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there problems of corruption and theft and all that
                        in the port? One hears that sometimes getting things into ports of some
                        countries are quite difficult. Here you had quite a volume of things coming
                        in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: We had a lot of things coming in and we never had any problems.
                    That doesn't mean that there might not have been problems. Maybe they respected
                    embassies.</p>
                <p>The very first week I was in Cameroon, I had an interesting experience. I
                    received a cable saying that a representative from the Smithsonian was coming in
                    with a large shipment of antiquities from one of the kingdoms up in the
                    Northwestern part of Cameroon, which the Smithsonian had borrowed for an exhibit
                    that had been shown around the States. In fact, I had stopped in New York City
                    and had seen the exhibit on my way to Cameroon. I was asked to make arrangements
                    for her to get everything returned. Well, this was quite a challenge. We, of
                    course, had to get trucks. There was a lot of stuff. There were barely one-lane
                    dirt roads in some places. I'll never forget the first night when we stopped to
                    stay overnight. I had to rent a room just for the antiquities, because she would
                    not leave them outside. She was too afraid something would happen to them. We
                    got them up in the mountains to their owners, who were very kind to us. It was
                    good for me because I got to see some of Cameroon before I got stuck in my
                    routine in Douala. It was an interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left in '87?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And where to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Back to the Department, to the Office of the Inspector General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: '87 to '89. I was forced to retire in '89. I'd reached age 65.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the Office of the Inspector General, who was the
                        Inspector General at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: The guy that just left before Jacqueline Bridger came.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sherman Funk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Sherman Funk, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did he operate? He was the first non-Foreign Service
                        Inspector and his coming and the new creation of this office was rather
                        controversial.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: We didn't have much to do with him. His office was in the
                    Department of State. We were out in Rosslyn. He gave complete authority to the
                    Director of the Office of Inspections. Sure, when we'd come in and write our
                    report, we'd go and present it to him. He was always very nice to deal with. We
                    always had good meetings. We'd have, of course, other people who were interested
                    sit in on the meetings, give us whatever suggestions they had before we
                    finalized the report. As all the reports were sent to Congress, we had to be
                    careful. If there was anything that we felt should not go into the report, we
                    would put in a separate, classified memo.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Bob Barber was team leader. I was on teams inspecting Saudi Arabia,
                    Bahrain and England, all of which were fascinating—especially Saudi Arabia, and
                    especially as a woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of looking at the operations in
                        Saudi Arabia or in London? I mean, these were not your areas of dealing, so
                        you often, you might say, had a clearer eye of how things were being done.
                        What was your impression of how the Foreign Service operated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Well, the first impression was that they were badly overstaffed.
                    They all could have been reduced in half. People sitting around without anything
                    to do. In England, a secretary came up to me and said, “I've been here almost a
                    year and I haven't had a thing to do. Can't you do something about that?” So,
                    you go to the boss or the Ambassador and they don't want their empire cut down.
                    They refused to take any suggestions. Even when we wrote them up, they wouldn't
                    do anything about them.</p>
                <p>When you're on an inspection team, you're given a certain responsibility. Mine
                    was, as a political officer, always to inspect the political section. Of course,
                    you look at what they're putting out and how the people are being utilized,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of how the political reporting
                        function was being carried on where you inspected?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: I thought they seemed to be doing a good job, except for the fact
                    they were often underutilizing their personnel. But they were getting out the
                    stuff that was needed and wanted.</p>
                <p>Saudi Arabia, I suppose, would have been a real problem for any woman officer
                    there. I, as a woman officer in another Islamic country (as I mentioned before,
                    in Iran), had no problem whatsoever. But Saudi Arabia was different. I couldn't
                    believe it. I'm used to getting out and walking and I wanted to walk from my
                    hotel over to the embassy. Well, a woman was not allowed to walk down the street
                    alone. Women could only ride in the last two rows of the bus and they had to be
                    accompanied by somebody. Women could not drive cars unless they were accompanied
                    by a husband, father, or son.</p>
                <p>The Saudis were such hypocrites about everything. When we were there, the
                    Ambassador's wife was sponsoring an art show of an American woman artist, which
                    was set up in the embassy, and she invited a lot of ranking Saudi women to a
                    reception. As they came in the door, there was a closet just inside and they
                    took off their chadors. They had on the latest Parisian fashions. You'd go into
                    a restaurant or, a hotel dining room and there would be a bar that looked just
                    like an American bar, with bottles behind the bar and wine glasses hanging from
                    the ceiling. But, of course, the bottles did not contain any alcoholic
                    beverages. There would be a bucket at the entrance, with ice and what looked
                    like a champagne bottle. Of course, it wasn't champagne. It was some
                    nonalcoholic drink. But why pretend that it was alcoholic? I couldn't understand
                    the thinking that went on there at all.</p>
                <p>But the embassy, I felt, was doing a very good job. I was impressed. It was so
                    different. We went from Saudi Arabia to Bahrain which is also an Islamic
                    country. The Saudis after work on Thursday night all get into their big
                    limousines and go over the causeway from Dhahran to Bahrain. There, they took
                    over the hotels. They had all of their various wives and many kids. They were up
                    all night getting drunk. We learned, while we were in Bahrain, to stay off the
                    streets at night and on the weekends. They'd careen around town. The hotel was
                    awful because their doors would all be open and they had T.V. and radio blaring
                    loudly and they'd all be running up and down the halls on their drinking binges.
                    Then they'd go back to Saudi Arabia for the week! Bahrain was quite liberal,
                    obviously.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in Dhahran back in the late '50s. There wasn't a
                        causeway and, actually, there weren't relations between Bahrain and Saudi
                        Arabia at the time, but we used to cover Bahrain from Dhahran. So, we'd fly
                        over. You could go to the one hotel there, the Speever House, and get some
                        beer, which you couldn't get anywhere else. Also, we'd stock up on booze,
                        which we'd take in footlockers. Everybody knew what we were doing, but we'd
                        wave our diplomatic passports and bring booze back for the Consulate General
                        and sometimes for the Ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: In Dhahran, did you have this experience of drinking in secret?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I didn't. There might have been this, but it certainly
                        wasn't apparent. The big money had not hit. It was still pretty fundamental
                        where we were. We would drink with non-Saudis. There probably was a little,
                        but not much. But, when you get really big money and sophistication and all
                        that, it's pretty hard to sit on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>How about London? I imagine that that's always a place where you might say the
                    morale isn't that great, it's too big an Embassy and people were lost..</p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: That's true. I think there were over 600 people when I was there.
                    The morale was not good. As I say, a lot of it was because people didn't have
                    enough to do. The reporting that I looked into was good. They had good entree to
                    anybody that you would expect in England and were covering everything the way
                    they should. But, as I say, we recommended they really cut down and nobody did
                    anything about it. They never followed up on our recommendation. That makes it
                    sort of discouraging, being in the Office of Inspections, to make
                    recommendations and not have them taken.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in any sort of emergency inspections
                        because of crises or problems?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No, those were the only two inspections that I had. Then I had to
                    retire. But then they kept me on for two years after I retired to edit all of
                    the inspection reports. As I say, they had to go to Congress and we had to be
                    very careful. My major in university had been mass communications and I had
                    edited a newspaper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we concerned about going to Congress? That this
                        might be used against people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: Yes, especially if there were any recommendations involving certain
                    individuals, and there may well be. These were the kinds of things that were
                    personal things, which shouldn't get out.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there Congressional offices that we were particularly
                        concerned about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>CLARK-BOURNE: No. It was just, as I say, certain things I had to keep an eye out
                    for. Sometimes maybe you'd have an Ambassador and a DCM that didn't get along
                    together. You might want to recommend that somebody be replaced or transferred.
                    You don't want things like that to go into the report itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly if it can be used by a group that are really
                        trying to get at the Administration or something to cause trouble and it has
                        nothing to do with anything outside of the normal working.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>All right, why don't we stop at this point?</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
