<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001288">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Victor Wolf Jr.</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>VICTOR WOLF, JR.</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: July 31, 1986</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>[Note: Mr. Wolf was killed in an accident on December 16, 1986 and did not have
                    the chance to edit this transcript.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Today I am interviewing Victor Wolf, Jr., who is managing
                        director of the Foreign Service History Center of George Washington
                        University. Our subject is the movement of peoples which refers to
                        immigration and refugees as done by the United States Government over the
                        past 30-odd years since Victor Wolf has been an officer and a participant in
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Wolf—I'll call you Vic—I note that you entered the Foreign Service in 1952,
                    after having taken both an undergraduate program at City College of New York and
                    government and history, and at Columbia University, where you got your Master's
                    in Central European politics. It appears that you had the Foreign Service on
                    your mind in your academic preparation.</p>
                <p>WOLF: Yes, actually that's right. The way I got interested in the Foreign Service
                    was, I went into the Army in 1944, where the Army decided they were going to
                    train me in engineering at Princeton University. I would have told them that was
                    a mistake, but Privates didn't argue with Captains and Majors and Lieutenant
                    Colonels. You did what you were told. So I staggered through nine months of
                    engineering training and got something out of it, but it was perfectly obvious I
                    was not making any large engineering contributions to the U.S. fight against the
                    Axis.</p>
                <p>At any rate, the war ended just as I was ending basic training, which followed
                    engineering training which happened at Princeton University. My basic training
                    occurred at Fort McClellan, Alabama, and the last day, as I said, was just at
                    the end of the war; in fact, the day that the atomic bomb was dropped on
                    Hiroshima.</p>
                <p>I went on home leave or on what they called in those days “delay in route,” and
                    reported to Fort Meade, Maryland, just about V-J Day. And then because they at
                    that time were not sending any more troops to Europe, the German war having
                    ended four or five months before, we were sent out to the Pacific, and I was
                    then shipped to Japan. I was on the first transport that arrived in Japan
                    directly from the United States, rather than coming up from some of the islands
                    in the South Pacific.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>When they were looking at my record, my files, as to where I should be assigned,
                    they discovered that I spoke German. The reason I spoke German as well as I did
                    was that both of my parents had been born in Germany, and we were essentially a
                    bilingual household. So because I spoke a foreign language, I was assigned to
                    military government in Japan, which may sound curious unless you know something
                    about how the military works.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds very normal.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Anyhow, in the course of my duties in military government in Japan from '45
                    to '46, I encountered something called the diplomatic section of SCAP. SCAP
                    stood for Supreme Commander Allied Powers—that is to say, General MacArthur. The
                    diplomatic section of SCAP was, basically speaking, manned by American Foreign
                    Service officers who were the channel through which foreign policy instructions
                    were passed to the Japanese Government by the Allied powers, which, in effect,
                    really meant, basically speaking, the United States and the other U.N. powers,
                    with the exception of the Soviet Union. Needless to say, SCAP did not pass on
                    any particular instructions that the Soviet Union agreed with. It was very much
                    slanted to what the Western United Nations powers wanted, rather than the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>The head of that organization was, if I remember, a Foreign Service officer named
                    George Atcheson. Not Dean Acheson. I think it would have been spelled Atcheson.
                    Anyhow, George Atcheson, in the course of his duties, encountered a rather
                    young, eager staff sergeant—that is to say, me. I had occasion to go to the
                    diplomatic section quite frequently. I asked him, “What is the Foreign Service?
                    What is it all about?” And over the course of the year, he very patiently and
                    with great kindness gave me a lot of details about the American Foreign Service.
                    Knowing that I was not interested in technical things, I wasn't particularly
                    good in technical things, I was more interested in the social sciences, I
                    decided that that was for me. It is for that reason that I sort of developed my
                    college educational plan to equip me to pass the Foreign Service exam. That
                    obviously had to be the first step.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see you entered the Foreign Service in 1952. Did they
                        ask you what you wanted to do? Did you have any career goal at the time in
                        any areas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I was very interested in political work. I was also interested in, I guess,
                    what would now be called human rights, although as a separate term or a separate
                    concept of work inside the Foreign Service, human rights as such didn't have
                    that label. But the content of that issue was certainly in U.S. foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>I also said that I was interested in the Near East, although it is true I had
                    taken my university training basically on Central Europe and NATO affairs. So in
                    the mysterious ways of personnel, I was assigned to Baghdad in Iraq.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your training, before you went to Baghdad, did they
                        touch on immigration or refugees policy? Or was this more or less discounted
                        as being an importance?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: No, I won't say it was discounted. It was touched on—a little more than
                    touched on. They gave a certain amount of attention to the mechanics of how
                    visas would be issues and should be issued and various types of visas.</p>
                <p>In those days, the McCarran-Walter Act, the Immigration Nationality Act of 1952,
                    had just passed. Actually, as you may remember, that Act didn't go into effect
                    until the first half of 1953. Before that, they had other laws that govern visas
                    and passports and nationality. The McCarran-Walter Act, although it had many
                    features which I think we now recognize were discriminatory and had certain
                    obnoxious characteristics to it, had the virtue of pulling together a whole
                    number of other laws that previously had governed visas. Before the
                    McCarran-Walter Act, consular work and particularly visa work for the United
                    States was governed by as many as 15, 20, 30 pieces of legislation and their
                    related regulations. This, of course, made it extraordinarily cumbersome to do
                    visa work overseas in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Particularly, I would imagine that most of this type of
                        work was often handed to a rather junior officer at an embassy, who would
                        have little time to master all these laws before moving on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Not only that, but he would have comparatively few people to refer to, to
                    give him guidance and counsel among his more senior colleagues at his post of
                    assignment, because all of these laws came into operation successively over a
                    15-year period, roughly just before the McCarran-Walter Act was passed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of the McCarran-Walter Act, I note that when it
                        came into effect, you had then moved from essentially a position as special
                        assistant.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I was special assistant to the AID director in Iraq. I then moved on to
                    head the consular section, which was not a very large one. It was basically me
                    and two Iraqi local employees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was 1953-1954.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>WOLF: Yes, it was. It was a normal little consular section, some visa work,
                    passport work, protection work, and the like, even consular invoices, where that
                    was in the days when it was still necessary for consular officers to accept and
                    process the certifications of exporters of products to the United States as to
                    what was in the shipment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Turning to the problems of movements of people, in the
                        first place, was there any regular migration from Iraq to the United States
                        in those days, what I'd call normal Iraqis going to the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: There was a small number of Iraqis who were immigrating, not very many, and
                    a somewhat larger number of people going to the United States principally as
                    students or to visit their relatives in the United States. And there was a very
                    interesting third category. This was the category of Iraqi Jews. This was 1952.
                    This was rather shortly after the coming into existence of the state of
                    Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was in 1948.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: That was in 1948. The Iraqi felt very, very strongly about this. They had
                    the typical Arab position that you would expect on anything having to do with
                    Jews, Israel, Zionism, and the like. I would even go so far as to say that the
                    way Iraqis discussed this question was unusually hysterical. I suppose that
                    meant because they were far away from the borders. They were not what now is
                    called front-line states.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They had sent a military contingent during the 1948
                        war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: They had sent a military contingent during the 1948 war, which was done
                    unusually badly. As a consequence, I think they were more than unusually
                    neurotic or psychotic on the subject of Israel and the like. They had, to be
                    perfectly frank, treated their own Jewish population rather badly. According to
                    all of the information available, the small Iraqi Jewish community wasn't the
                    least bit interested in Zionism and Israel, except what I would call a certain
                    normal sympathy with their co-religionists. But there was no evidence at all, at
                    least that I ever heard of, that there was any truth in the claims of the Iraqis
                    that the Jewish community represented a massive fifth column in Iraq and that
                    they were engaged in spying and the like.</p>
                <p>In 1948, there had been some rather nasty lynching going on, in which prominent
                    Jewish merchants were lynched, literally lynched. Their enterprises were taken
                    over by the organizers of the lynch mobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the British have any control in Iraq in those
                        days?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: No. By that time, the British mandate had really ended before World War I,
                    although the British influence was, comparatively speaking, still high. But the
                    Iraqi, as so many Middle Eastern countries, always credited foreigners with more
                    influence than the foreigners always had. Middle Easterners, Arabs sometimes
                    have a tendency to be much less introspective than is warranted or is
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>Anyhow, as a consequence of the mistreatment of the Iraqi Jewish community, the
                    Iraqi Jewish community was extremely insecure. The newspapers were full of
                    anti-Semitic and anti-Zionist statements and articles, and Jews in Iraqi were
                    very prudent, very careful, and really kept a very, very low profile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you have any idea of the approximate number and where
                        they were located?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Most of them were located in Baghdad itself. I don't know, there might have
                    been as many as—well, by that time, it had been considerably reduced, because in
                    1948, there had been an airlift to take a large number of Iraqi Jews out of Iraq
                    and relocate them in Israel. That had been arranged somehow. So what you had in
                    the Iraqi Jewish community was a considerably smaller number than had been in
                    existence before the founding of the state of Israel in 1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Are we talking about several thousand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tens of thousands?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I would say we're probably talking perhaps 5,000 to 10,000 in those days.
                    It's much, much less now in 1986, because everything that has happened since
                    that time has made it even more difficult for Jews to stay in Iraq.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the embassy's role in helping these people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: We didn't have a role as such, but we had a terrible dilemma. The dilemma
                    arose from the fact that large numbers of Iraqi Jews tried to visit the United
                    States, and we, normally speaking, found that very many of them qualified as
                    non-immigrant visitors or as non-immigrant students. They went to the United
                    States.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>At that point, a curiosity in Iraqi nationality law came into existence. Iraqi
                    nationality law had a provision which I guess you would call blatantly
                    discriminatory. It said that any Iraqi Jew who did not renew his nationality
                    specifically before an Iraqi consul abroad by going to that consul and saying,
                    “I wish to remain an Iraqi citizen,” was immediately denationalized, and that
                    meant he could not return to Iraq. If he couldn't return to Iraq, and he was in
                    the United States, he was in the United States, and there he would stay.</p>
                <p>The result was, as this pattern became more and more visible to us, we began to
                    have real qualms as to whether, in fact, Iraqi Jews who were going to the United
                    States or were proposing to go to the United States to visit or to study or what
                    have you, were simply using this as a device for disguised immigration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you finding any of these students or visitors going
                        to Iraqi consuls and making an attempt to stay nationalized?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: A small number were, but the largest number were not. On the other hand, we
                    were receiving a significant amount of pressure from university administrations,
                    from Jewish communities in the United States, and from congressmen who said, “We
                    don't want you to discriminate against Jews by issuing them an unduly low
                    proportion of visas and denying their applications in an unduly high number of
                    cases.” It was a very, very complicated thing.</p>
                <p>The additional problem was that from time to time, the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service would come to us, would ask the embassy to get the
                    authority of the Iraqi Government to receive as deportees some of these
                    overstaying Iraqi Jews. The Iraqi, in every instance, refused to accept them.
                    The dilemma was that there was a section of the Immigration and Nationality Act
                    which said that if a foreign state refused to accept U.S. deportees, it was
                    possible to deny all visa facilities to all citizens of that state. About the
                    time I was leaving, the United States was grappling with whether it would bring
                    that section of the Immigration and Nationality Act into operation or not.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about these Iraqi Jews? They did have another
                        nationality, which was Israeli, and the law of return. Were they taking this
                        into account?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>WOLF: Not really, because the law of return only applied if you were in Israel
                    and made specific application before an Israeli authority or an Israeli officer,
                    a person authorized to receive applications for the law of return. And it would
                    have been anomalous for us to say that an Iraqi Jew in the United States, in the
                    jurisdiction of the United States, simply because he was a Jew and had not gone
                    to Israel and applied, was therefore an Israeli citizen under the Israeli law of
                    return. I think the United States has always been unwilling to act as an agent
                    to enforce the laws of another state. That's a very dangerous precedent to
                    start.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were mentioning the pressure on you. How did the
                        pressure come? There you were issuing visas. What did the ambassador tell
                        you or recommend to you? What sort of instructions did you get from the
                        Department? How did you get these instructions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: With regard to visa applications as such, the Department did not instruct.
                    The people who ran the visa office in those days availed themselves of that
                    section of the law, the Immigration and Nationality Act by that time, which said
                    that the consular officer is responsible, not the Department. The Department can
                    only give guidance and interpretations. So the Department of State basically
                    stayed out of the whole issue. They didn't want to get involved in the
                    issue.</p>
                <p>As far as the ambassador, Berton Y. Barry, was concerned, the ambassador said,
                    “If you find a person qualified to issue a visa, you issue it to him. If you
                    find a person not qualified, you do not issue it to him. You have to make that
                    decision yourself, but I will support you in whatever decisions you make on
                    individual cases.”</p>
                <p>The deputy chief of mission was a man named Philip W. Ireland. I never got very
                    much counsel and guidance from Philip Ireland, because I think he was not really
                    interested in consular work. I think he took the view that consular work was
                    non-substantive. Now, anyone who's done consular work for the United States
                    Government understands what the words “substantive” and “non-substantive” mean
                    and how, in some instances, non-substantive is pejorative. Philip Ireland was
                    interested in political work; that's all he was interested in. He wasn't
                    interested in anything else. In some respects, that was good, because although
                    he was interested in political work, he made political officers very unhappy by
                    getting involved in details which DCMs should not get involved in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get a lot of congressional correspondence?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>WOLF: We got a fair amount of congressional correspondence. Curiously, the member
                    of Congress who was most interested in this and who basically wanted us to
                    virtually automatically issue non-immigrant visas to any Iraqi Jew who applied
                    was John J. Rooney. John J. Rooney, among other things, was the Chairman of the
                    House Subcommittee of the Ways and Means Committee, I guess it was, that handled
                    the State Department appropriations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was considered the most powerful man as far as the
                        State Department was concerned, because he controlled the State Department's
                        purse strings.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: That's correct. I, fortunately, never had a real crisis or run-in with him,
                    because for whatever reason, I never had very much in the way of kickbacks on my
                    decisions. In some cases I issued, in some cases I did not issue. But this was
                    an ongoing problem.</p>
                <p>The one other element with regard to this was the question of the reaction of the
                    Iraqi Government whenever we asked them to accept an Iraqi Jew who we wished to
                    deport. Because they were not citizens, we asked them, nevertheless, to accept
                    them. As I said, in every instance they refused to accept them.</p>
                <p>The problem that we had was, every time I would go down to the Foreign Ministry
                    and talk to an Iraqi official, who usually was the under secretary who, among
                    other things, dealt with consular matters, the reaction I got from him was not
                    what I would call a very adult or disciplined one. The reaction was about 15 or
                    20 minutes of an anti-Jewish, anti-Semitic, anti-Zionist tirade, attacks on the
                    United States for helping the Jews against the Arabs, anger that we were even
                    concerning ourselves with people like this, and then he would say, “We refuse
                    your request.” But I always had to go through this temper tantrum of about 15
                    minutes to half an hour. I knew what the result was going to be. And so finally,
                    I simply would go down, hand over the note, in effect shut my ears, contemplate
                    my navel, and think of something else. When I heard them say no, I would get up,
                    go out. I would go back to the Department of State, and I'd do the reporting
                    message on it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Besides this rather unfruitful business, did you have any
                        other specific types of problems dealing with the movement of peoples?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Yes, we had one other. In 1953 or '54, I believe, the United States
                    Congress passed the Refugees Relief Act. Now, the largest proportion of the
                    operations of the Refugees Relief Act had to do with refugees and other
                    categories of people principally in Europe, but there were several small
                    programs involving persons outside of Europe.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>Among those programs was a provision that 2,000 Palestine Arabs displaced from
                    their homes could be admitted to the United States as refugees. Now, there were
                    a comparatively small number of Palestine refugees in Iraq. There were, I think,
                    400 or 500 of them in a not particularly attractive suburb outside of Baghdad,
                    principally. And we thought it wouldn't be a bad idea to use the 2,000 numbers
                    to move that whole group to the United States and get this irritation out of
                    Iraq.</p>
                <p>Now, the problem was that the Congress had said that the country where they were
                    sojourning had to issue a readmission certificate. That was a certificate that
                    said if after all the refugee processing was finished, within six months after
                    their arrival in the United States as refugees, it developed that there was some
                    ineligibility, the country that had issued the readmission certificate would let
                    them come back if they were found ineligible to stay. And no one at the time
                    thought that this would be any problem at all. Here it was simply a pro forma
                    document, because the investigations were going to be so careful and so detailed
                    that there wouldn't be any slip-ups. This was long before the days of the
                    Palestine Liberation Organization or Arab terrorism or anything like that. This
                    was just a mechanical procedure, because, if I'm not mistaken, this requirement
                    was laid down for all persons admitted under the Refugees Relief Act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Now, the problem was that many of the Arab governments were unwilling to
                    issue such things, and the reason was they didn't want the Palestine refugee
                    question settled. They refused to issue these. I remember I was struggling with
                    the Iraqi Foreign Ministry for about a year, trying to get this. It must have
                    been in September or October of 1954, shortly before I left Baghdad, that I
                    finally received an instruction from the Department saying, in effect, “Look,
                    you've been doing this now for a year with the Iraqis. Let's have them fish or
                    cut bait. Let's really get a position from them. Will they or won't they issue a
                    readmission certificate?”</p>
                <p>So I called on the under secretary of the Foreign Ministry who dealt with
                    consular affairs, and he told me, quite candidly, that they would not issue it
                    simply because they did not want the Palestine refugees resettled anywhere else.
                    He said something like, “We want this running sore to continue. This running
                    sore is a good way of keeping the Palestine question alive, and ultimately we
                    hope that this will serve to destroy the Zionist state.”</p>
                <p>When I went back and I reported that, I remember there was some discussion in the
                    embassy as to whether such a telegram reporting such a thing should even be sent
                    out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: . . . to send out a rather straightforward
                        informational-type telegram such as this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>WOLF: Because isn't it true that many embassies do not like to report things that
                    make their host government look not very constructive and helpful? There is
                    always pressure on an embassy to make the government to which it is accredited,
                    if at all possible, look good rather than bad. And also, no one likes to report
                    an inability to follow instructions from the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving from the rather unprofitable, uncomfortable time in
                        Iraq, I notice that you became an Iranian specialist, having taken language
                        training and serving in political positions for the most part in Tehran,
                        Khorramshahr, and Tehran again. Your next significant consular assignment
                        was as a vice consul in Istanbul from 1957 to 1959. Could you describe the
                        position of the consul general in Istanbul and what you were doing
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: First of all, you must always bear in mind that the people in Istanbul
                    never really were pleased with the idea that from the time of the republic, the
                    capital became Ankara. Istanbul was and still is, really, an imperial city, and
                    there was always an underlying resentment on the part of the people in Istanbul
                    that they were no longer at the place where decisions were made about Turkish
                    life—real decisions made about Turkish life. This is, of course, quite correct.
                    The political headquarters of the country was Ankara. Now, a lot of the economic
                    control and a lot of the economic decisions were still made in Istanbul, because
                    that's where the banks were, that's where the money was, that's where, I guess
                    you'd call it, the sophisticated management structures and staffing were
                    located. But as far as political decisions, as far as political power was
                    concerned, this, by that time, had all been shifted very largely up to
                    Ankara.</p>
                <p>This being the case, the people in Istanbul were always looking for ways, if you
                    will, to make themselves bigger than the political reality was. We, in a sense,
                    acknowledged that position, because in those days we had a rather large staff in
                    our consulate general in Istanbul. The consul general was a very senior officer,
                    he was usually an old FSO-1.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there, who was the consul general?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Robert G. Minor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were doing what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I was the head of the consular section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How large was the consular section?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>WOLF: One officer, myself, plus some part-time help from another section in the
                    consulate general. That was usually one of the CIA officers assigned there, who
                    did actual consular work when I had a real glut of work. Then I had an American
                    administrative assistant and eight local employees, eight non-American
                    employees, because they were not all Turkish citizens. One of them happened to
                    be an Austrian citizen who had lived virtually all of her life in Istanbul, and
                    another one was a Greek citizen who had lived all her life in Istanbul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the main areas that you were dealing with in the
                        time you were in Istanbul concerned with movement of people, refugees,
                        visas, and the like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The real problem that we faced were really immigration or disguised
                    immigration problems. These were centered almost exclusively on two of the three
                    minority communities in Turkey. One was the Greek community, the other was the
                    Armenian community. The Jewish community was the third community, but there
                    wasn't much immigration there, and the Jewish community was, frankly, quite
                    content in Turkey. There was no enormous pressure on the part of Turkish Jews to
                    leave. They were in a pretty good situation.</p>
                <p>The situation with Armenians and Greeks was quite different. The Armenian
                    attitude toward living in Turkey had been largely shaped by the massacres and
                    deportations of the Armenian community during World War I, when, as you know,
                    many hundreds of thousands died, were displaced, what have you. From that time
                    on, the Armenians loathed the Turks, the Armenians loathed Turkey, and they were
                    quite willing to express their detestation of Turks and Turkey. The fact that
                    this exacerbated an already difficult situation was not considered by the
                    Armenians. They were so distressed and angry and full of hate for Turks that
                    they did not bridle their tongues and exercise a certain sensible discretion.
                    We've seen this pattern continue and expand, so that now you have Armenian
                    terrorist organizations going around, blowing up, and shooting Turkish diplomats
                    and consuls all over the world, including the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did the Armenians fit in the community of
                        Istanbul?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: They were shopkeepers, small merchants. They treasured, as much as they
                    could, any kind of a link with a foreign community, with the British community,
                    with the American community, with the French community, and the like.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your organization, as head of the consular
                        section, become involved?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Because they all wanted to immigrate to the United States, but there
                    weren't enough numbers available.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say numbers, what do you mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Immigration numbers. In those days, we had a certain number of immigrant
                    visas that would be issued per country based on place of birth. This is the
                    so-called national quota.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they would come under the Turkish quota, but no
                        Armenian quota.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: They would come under the Turkish quota. I think the numbers were 500 or
                    1,000; I don't recall. Something like that. So what the obvious solution was to
                    go as a non-immigrant and figure out a way of staying once you got there. In
                    those days, the rule was that if a person was registered for immigration, he
                    could not get a non-immigrant visa, because registration for immigration
                    indicated that the intent was to immigrate. You had to demonstrate that when you
                    got a non-immigrant visa, that you would return from that trip. It became
                    extremely difficult for Armenians to show that this was the case, because in
                    actual fact, it wasn't the case. We had all sorts of problems.</p>
                <p>The classic way this problem worked itself out was, I would have to deny a
                    non-immigrant visa, and there would be an immediate appeal to the consul
                    general. The reason why that was done was that Bob Minor, the consul general,
                    had lived many years in Istanbul as a teacher at Roberts College, and was
                    married to an English-Italian woman whose family had lived in Turkey for many,
                    many years as members of one of these foreign Levantine communities. So the
                    Minors, Bob and Nettie Minor, were very well known to all of the people of
                    Istanbul. So when this young punk of a vice consul would turn the visa down,
                    they would immediately have recourse to the Minors, husband and wife.</p>
                <p>So almost as soon as I got to Istanbul, when I was invited to dinner with the
                    Minors, they both said to me ahead of time, “Look, we are not going to get
                    involved in these cases, if at all possible, but from time to time, we may ask
                    you. That doesn't mean we want you to change your mind if your judgment tells
                    you you shouldn't. It's simply because of our relationships with all of these
                    various people in Istanbul, we have to go through some motions.” And I must say,
                    Bob Minor not once put any kind of pressure on me to change a decision in these
                    cases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting much pressure from the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Well, a little bit in Armenian cases, but rather more in Greek cases. The
                    Greek situation was, again, different. The Greek situation stemmed from the fact
                    that relations between Greece and Turkey had never been all that good, of
                    course. There was the memory of the Greek adventure in Asia Minor in the early
                    1920s.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The burning of Smyrna.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The burning of Smyrna and all of that, the massive invasion by the Greek
                    Army into Asia Minor. But the real problem came over Cyprus. The curiosity about
                    Cyprus was that in those days the Turks had a sense that for once they were on
                    the right side of a minority issue. The Turks have had a certain reputation in
                    the world as being very bad in their treatment of minorities. In Cyprus, it is
                    the Turkish community that is in the minority, and the Turkish Cypriots were
                    frightened that if there was a union with Greece, which is what many in the
                    majority Greek Cypriot community wanted, they would be discriminated against and
                    persecuted by the Greek majority in a province of a Greek state. So they
                    appealed to their brothers on the Turkish mainland to protect them, and the
                    Turks were very glad, for once being on the right side of a minority issue, as
                    it were.</p>
                <p>The problem culminated in 1956, when Greeks in Salonika burned the birthplace of
                    Ataturk in Salonika as an anti-Turkish protest. The result was almost
                    immediately widespread anti-Greek manifestations principally in Istanbul. Now,
                    there are all sorts of stories about how many Greeks were killed, whether Greek
                    women were raped, and all that sort of business, in Istanbul. The fact of the
                    matter is that there was no real recorded case of killing or raping. There was a
                    lot of burning, there was a lot of looting, and there was a fair amount of
                    disorder, and there is some evidence that the then-Turkish Government was behind
                    some of these anti-Greek manifestations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the burning of Ataturk's place, was the Greek
                        Government involved in that, do you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I don't know the answer to that question, but I wouldn't be surprised. I
                    wouldn't be at all surprised, because my impression is that neither of the two
                    governments were beyond staging things that would be useful for their particular
                    purposes, whatever those purposes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Given these riots and all, what happened to the
                        consulate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Then the Greeks wanted to get out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many are we talking about, the ones who wanted to get
                        out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: It's difficult to tell. The whole Greek community probably was between
                    50,000 and 100,000.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was a sizable community.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: That was approximately the size of the community. I could be wrong, but my
                    impression was 50,000 to 100,000. And a significant number of those Greek Turks,
                    meaning citizens of Greek extraction, were also registered for immigration, and
                    we had the same kind of problem that we had with Armenians, that they wanted
                    non-immigrant visas, we weren't able to give them non-immigrant visas if they
                    were registered, unless they showed that they really were not intending to stay
                    behind in the United States on that trip in a permanent way.</p>
                <p>We had much more pressure from the state because there were a number of states or
                    constituencies, districts within the United States where there was a large Greek
                    community, and the Greek lobby, the Greek community, was very well organized in
                    the United States, in many respects much more organized, at least at that time
                    than the Armenian community. You have a Greek-American organization called
                    AHEPA, I believe. I don't know what that stands for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think it's American Hellenic . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Ethnic Protective Association?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: At any rate, AHEPA. They were very interested in seeing that as many visa
                    applications of Greek ethnics in Istanbul were approved, and we got a fair
                    amount of attention from AHEPA. The congressman who was very interested in this
                    was John Brademas, a Democrat of Indiana.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who is of Greek extraction.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Who is of Greek extraction. There were also some districts in Massachusetts
                    where there was a lot of interest. In Maryland there was a lot of interest, in
                    Delaware.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We're really talking about places where there was a large
                        American-Greek community.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Yes. This was the kind of pressure that went on, and there was a fair
                    amount of that. I would say those were the movement of peoples issues that I had
                    to deal with.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you resolve the Greek problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: You didn't resolve the Greek problem. All that you could do was deal with
                    it on a case-by-case basis. I always took the position if there was any possible
                    explanation, if in an individual case one could plausibly assert that a person
                    was coming back, I tended to issue the visa, simply because why look for
                    trouble? It's going to come anyhow on cases where you can't, really can't issue
                    the visa. So if there was any possible justification in coming to the conclusion
                    that the person would come back from a non-immigrant trip, I would issue the
                    visa.</p>
                <p>I have to say, in fairness, that a significant number of Greek ethnics to whom I
                    did issue non-immigrant visas did, in fact return, and many of them would call
                    me up at the consulate general or come to see me at the consulate general and
                    say, “See? You weren't sure whether I would return. Here I am. I want to prove
                    to you that I was an honorable man.” Because I would always ask them to swear
                    the oath, the oath that the statements they made on their visa application were
                    true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which you included the statement that they were
                        returning.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Which you would include a statement that they were returning or the period
                    that they were going to be there or the purpose of the visit. My own impression,
                    frankly, is that one of the reasons why a number of these people did come back
                    was that they were very impressed in those days by the concept of an oath before
                    God.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Turning from Istanbul, you had a series of assignments
                        which had little relation to movement of peoples, until you became the
                        principal officer, the counsel in Cebu in the Philippines. The Philippines,
                        within the last few decades, has been a major source—in fact, the major
                        source of migration from the country to the United States. You were in Cebu
                        from 1968 to 1971. Did you have much in the way of migration from that
                        particular area of the Philippines?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Yes, we did. We had a fair amount. The problems that we encountered
                    involving movement of peoples were two, and this is where the whole issue of
                    fraud really began to arrive, at least in my experience. The first category of
                    problem in movement of peoples that we faced in the Philippines was the movement
                    of very large numbers of people with medical training—physicians, nurses,
                    medical technologists—to the United States for training, exchange visitor visas,
                    training in the United States, and then that which we learned from statistics,
                    that many of them were trying to figure out ways of staying on in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One thing that interests me here is Cebu is far removed
                        from the capital of Manila and Luzon Island, it doesn't look like a very
                        wealthy area. To have trained medical personnel coming out of not a very
                        rich country, from a provincial area, seems rather surprising. Why were you
                        getting so many?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: First of all, you must understand that Cebu is the second city of the
                    Philippines. Greater metropolitan Cebu had half a million people. Secondly,
                    although it is a poor country, it is a country that places a great store on
                    education, so very large numbers of people have university degrees. Many of
                    those degrees are not really worth very much, because many universities in the
                    Philippines were—I do not know about now—run as family businesses. So we had
                    three or four large family business-type universities in Cebu city, the
                    University of the Southern Philippines, the University of Visayan State
                    University, and so on and so on and so on. These were run by families, fairly
                    prominent well-to-do families, and this was a large income. This was a large
                    income source for these families. I mentioned the word Visayan. I should say the
                    Visayan are the central island group in the Philippine Archipelago, that island
                    group between Mindanao in the south and Luzon in the north.</p>
                <p>Because these universities ran as businesses of families, and because the concept
                    of educational standards is not as strong in the Philippines as it is in other
                    countries, what that meant was if you had the money, you would be admitted. If
                    you had the money, you would get your degree. That meant large numbers of people
                    were processing through these diploma mills and they came out as physicians,
                    they came out as nurses, they came out as medical technologists. Now, it is true
                    they also had to go through a licensing procedure by the Philippine Government.
                    You will not be surprised if I tell you that corruption is also a significant
                    characteristic of Filipino society. And so many people were able to get
                    certified as physicians, nurses, medical technologists when, frankly, they were
                    unqualified. How did they do it? They paid bribes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with this problem, both unqualified
                        people and people who wanted to go to the United States as non-immigrants,
                        but actually were, in fact, immigrants?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The question of dealing with the unqualified medical technologists was
                    really sort of a difficult one. We were not in a position in those days to
                    challenge a physician, a nurse, a medical technologist who came in with a degree
                    and who came in with an appointment from an American hospital as an intern, as a
                    nurse intern, as a medical technologist trainee. If they produced the
                    documentation indicating that they had completed the education, if they came in
                    with a Philippine Government license or registration to practice their
                    profession, and if they came in with the appropriate form that was issued by the
                    hospital, I believe it was the form—I don't recall what the number was—it was
                    authorized by the Immigration and Nationalization Service. There was nothing we
                    could really do.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>What we did was, we went to the Department and asked the Department of State to
                    begin to investigate the qualifications of these people by going to the
                    hospitals and acquainting the hospitals with what the educational situation in
                    the Philippines was, that many of these people were not adequately trained. The
                    curious thing was that many of the hospitals said, in effect, “We know that.
                    We'll train them ourselves. The problem is we are so short staffed,” because
                    medical training institutions were not producing enough people in the United
                    States to fill all of the positions of nurse and medical technologist spaces
                    that were available. It was really, while I was there, a losing battle.</p>
                <p>Sometime thereafter, there was an act passed by the Congress that tried to
                    address the whole question of medical standards and the whole ECFMG examination
                    process was considerably tightened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: ECFMG?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The Examination for the Certification of Foreign Medical Graduates. All of
                    these people, at least the physicians, had to pass the ECFMG, but that whole
                    procedure had been fairly loose. One of the things that I think was done by the
                    act of Congress, which happened after I left the Philippines, was to tighten up
                    the whole certification process. You had to meet much stiffer standards if you
                    were going to be admitted as an exchange visitor physician, exchange visitor
                    nurse, exchange visitor medical technologist. But that was the first issue we
                    had.</p>
                <p>The other issue was the issue of wives, foreign marriages. There were in
                    California, particularly, a large number of American citizens of Filipino
                    extraction, Filipino ethnicity, living. These were people who, when the
                    Philippines achieved its independence in 1946, had been able through certain
                    aspects of the treaty between the Philippines and the United States and the laws
                    that were passed and enforced to implement the treaty, were able to become
                    American citizens.</p>
                <p>What happened with many of these people was they went to the United States, the
                    men would go to the United States, work hard, make a lot of money, and then when
                    they were in their fifties or sixties, they wanted to get married. What they did
                    was send back to their home village, and there was a certain amount of fraud
                    going on in the matching up of the men in the United States and the young women
                    in the Philippines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the fraud?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>WOLF: The fraud was that in some instances, a man would have his first wife come
                    in, not for a wife, but to facilitate her immigration. It was a marriage in name
                    only, and after a period of time, the divorce would occur, the guy would get
                    something because he had gone . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He would be paid.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: He would be paid, and the broker got a percentage. He got a percentage from
                    the man and he got a percentage from the woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The broker being somebody in the Philippines or in the
                        United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Usually in the Philippines. We were constantly trying to find out how this
                    fraudulent matching of phony brides with phony husbands was going forward. It
                    was a very, very difficult thing to do. My guess is that for every ring that was
                    broken, another two came into existence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving from the Philippines to what would seem a much more
                        benign consulate situation, you were assigned to Copenhagen as the consul
                        general there. Did you have any problems there in the movement of
                        people?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: We had two kinds of problems. One of them was the problem of the Asian and
                    African visa shopper. Copenhagen is off the normal travel routings when you come
                    from the Third World into Europe. Usually when you come from Africa, you come
                    from the Middle East, you come from the Far East, you enter Europe at Rome or at
                    Paris or London or Frankfurt. You don't get up to Copenhagen very much.</p>
                <p>In the period that I was in Copenhagen in '71 to '74, a number of things were
                    going on. You had the expelling of Asians from Uganda by Idi Amin. You had the
                    Nigerian civil war or one of the periods of civil strife in Nigeria. So you had
                    a large number of these people fleeing, and they were displaced. Now, the first
                    problem that we encountered was the Asians from Uganda. For a variety of reasons
                    having to do with British politics and British nationality law, the Asians did
                    not have British nationality, neither did they have Indian nationality or
                    Pakistani nationality, which would have been the two countries in Asia where
                    naturally one would have thought returned to. But many of these people had no
                    idea about India or Pakistan. They'd never been there, they knew very little
                    about it; they were simply part of the Asian community in Uganda. They were then
                    expelled. So they couldn't go to England, they couldn't or wouldn't go to
                    Pakistan or India. They wanted to go elsewhere, and what more natural
                    destination than the United States?</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>These people would then arrive with a Ugandan passport, which was still valid,
                    and they would shop all over Europe trying to get a visa into the United States.
                    And we had literally hundreds of these people rotating through all the different
                    posts in Europe, and we received a very large number of these.</p>
                <p>Interview Number Two with Victor Wolf Date: August 5, 1986 Interviewer: Charles
                    Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you handle this Ugandan problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Unfortunately, it was a very difficult problem, because large numbers of
                    them simply could not show that they were qualified to enter the United States
                    as non-immigrants. They had been expelled from their home country, even though
                    in many instances they were still carrying these Ugandan passports. The British
                    wouldn't accept them. The Indians and the Pakistanis either wouldn't accept them
                    or were very reluctant to accept them. And yet they would come in and say, “I'm
                    simply going temporarily to the United States.” Well, on the face of the
                    situation, it wasn't very credible. So the visa officers were required to deny
                    the visas. It was not a very happy situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By any chance did any of these qualify for visas to go to
                        Spartanburg, South Carolina? I know that South Carolina had a minor program
                        trying to help these people. They took about 50 families in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: No, they did not. I'm frankly not aware of the Spartanburg program. That
                    would have been somewhere between 1973-74. I don't know when you encountered
                    that program. When would that have been?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I heard about it when I visited Spartanburg in about 1974.
                        Moving on, did you have any other refugee types, particularly from behind
                        the Iron Curtain countries?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Yes, there was a trickle then. The largest number were Poles. There were
                    two kinds of Polish refugees or potential refugees. The first were Polish Jews
                    who were expelled from Poland or placed under very harsh pressures to leave by
                    the Poles. I suppose that would have been in the very, very late Sixties. Many
                    of these Poles were members of the Communist Party who had been fairly loyal to
                    the regime, but about that time, the Polish authorities required scapegoats, and
                    Polish Jews are very convenient to be scapegoats in Eastern Europe.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>So many of them finally got the message that there was simply no future for them
                    in Poland, and they were permitted to go out illegally. The Poles did not
                    actually issue them exit visas, because they didn't want to really get involved
                    in the handling of Polish-Jewish documentation, but they facilitated, in effect,
                    the illegal flight of Polish Jews.</p>
                <p>Among the more notable ones was a man named Julius Katuski. Julius Katuski was
                    the Polish U.N. representative in the very late forties and very early fifties,
                    and he was a loyal member of the party, and he was one of the more vitriolic
                    anti-American orators in the Security Council in the General Assembly. I saw him
                    there when he was teaching at one of the Danish universities, and he was still
                    in shock that the regime had turned on him.</p>
                <p>We didn't get involved with those very much, because the Danes simply accepted
                    them and they ultimately became Danish citizens.</p>
                <p>The other category were people who, one way or another, found an occasion to get
                    out. For example, cruise ships. The Stefan Batory was a cruise ship that
                    periodically stopped at Copenhagen for tourism, and every time that ship
                    stopped, maybe 30, 40 of these people would jump off. So we always had braced
                    ourselves for the influx of these people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this work? Were many given visas to the United
                        States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: No, none of them were given visas to the United States there. The
                    arrangement was the following. One of two things happened to them. The Danes
                    accepted them, or whatever country they jumped off accepted them. The other
                    procedure was that we would contact our mission in Geneva, and our mission in
                    Geneva would, in effect, introduce them into the refugee processing system,
                    which was based on a series of refugee camps in West Germany, in Austria, and I
                    think there was one in Belgium. The only task we had was to get transit or
                    temporary visas from the Germans, the Austrians, or the Belgians, to permit them
                    to go to that country, enter the camp, and in effect, be processed by the
                    refugee voluntary agencies, the Immigration and Nationalization Service, and the
                    other refugee resettlement countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving from Denmark, very much a friendly country, I note
                        that your next assignment was as consul general in East Berlin, in which you
                        were there when the post was opened. I wonder if you could tell us something
                        about opening a post in a hard-line Communist country.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>WOLF: Well, it ain't easy. The East Germans were pretty much on their good
                    behavior as far as we ourselves were concerned. We were treated with courtesy
                    and politeness and all of that. When it came, however, for me to do my official
                    duties, which were such things as negotiating a consular agreement, starting the
                    process on claims by Americans against the East Germans, and most particularly
                    uniting divided families so that members in East Germany could emigrate to their
                    relatives in the United States, I cannot describe the East Germans as
                    cooperative. They were anything but.</p>
                <p>Just getting a consular operation started was very, very difficult, because the
                    East Germans didn't really understand that. They didn't understand the idea that
                    one of the things a consul does is to provide services to citizens of his own
                    country and citizens of other countries that wish to visit his country for
                    whatever purpose. This is something that is really quite alien to the East
                    Germans in any sort of deep philosophical sense.</p>
                <p>So one of the things that we had an enormous difficulty with was establishing a
                    medical examination process. If a person is supposed to emigrate to the United
                    States, he's got to get a medical examination to see that he doesn't have an
                    infectious disease. Usually, in most countries, you go to private physicians,
                    you contract out with them, and the procedure runs, and the government isn't
                    really the least bit interested in that. East German—nuh-huh. You couldn't go to
                    a private doctor; there were no private doctors. You had to go to the state. So
                    I wrote a note to the East German Foreign Ministry, explaining what it was that
                    we needed, and they didn't understand. They simply didn't understand really what
                    it was I wanted. So I had to explain this several times to them in personal
                    conversations, where I'd go in myself and talk about it. Finally, they
                    understood that this had to do with emigration. Emigration was something they
                    were completely disinterested in, so they were disinclined to be very
                    cooperative.</p>
                <p>Finally, it went to the point that Washington was getting after us to get an
                    immigrant visa processing capability established, and I went to the ambassador.
                    At that time the ambassador was John Sherman Cooper. I asked the ambassador to
                    go and talk to the foreign minister about getting a consular department, the
                    main consular department, as the bigger administration was called, to establish
                    a procedure for medical examinations, with our being told who the doctors were,
                    making arrangements for the appropriate forms to be delivered, making
                    arrangement for a German-language translation of the medical manual to be
                    delivered to all of these doctors, and then, in due course, the people would go
                    there, the examination would occur, and the results would be sent to us. Simply
                    getting started as a consular operation was a great difficulty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many people are you talking about for emigrating from
                        East Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>WOLF: The only emigrants you could get were people who had reached the age of
                    retirement and pensioning. The East Germans were indifferent as to whether they
                    left or not. And specific divided family cases where, with great pain and agony,
                    we persuaded the East Germans to let this person go to emigrate to a relative in
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: About how many people were getting immigrant visas,
                        approximately?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I can't give you a precise number at this time. I do know that on the
                    initial representation list which we insisted on presenting to the East Germans,
                    there were about 84 people, possibly divided into about 55 or 60 cases. We had
                    made it a condition of establishing relations with the East Germans that, one,
                    we would give them the initial representation list; two, we insisted on the
                    right to discuss these in a continuing way; and three, we insisted on the right
                    to present and discuss with them any new divided family cases that arose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How successful were you on divided family cases?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: In the three years that I was there, which was the first three years of the
                    post, or less than three years, we resolved, I think, all but two of the cases
                    that were on the initial representation list.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Talking about 80-ish.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Eighty people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: In addition to that, we resolved about, I think, one-third or so of a new
                    100 cases that arose after we opened.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you resolve the cases? What was the process in
                        resolving the case?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>WOLF: The process of resolving the case was when we were informed that a case
                    existed, usually we learned of it because an immigration and nationalization
                    petition approved would arrive. Thus for one of the preferences, a fianc� visa,
                    an immediate relative petition, and the like. We would contact the person and
                    call them in, ask them to come in, and they would immediately be worried could
                    they walk into the American Embassy without getting into trouble. We had an
                    assurance that they would not be hassled if they came into the American Embassy,
                    but we could not, of course, assure them that that was really going to happen
                    when they returned to their homes.</p>
                <p>In effect, we always had to say to these people, “Look, if you want to leave,
                    you're going to have to have contact with us, and you're going to have to decide
                    are you prepared, do you want to leave that much and join your loved-one
                    overseas to take whatever risks are involved in doing something that this regime
                    doesn't want.” They all, of course, ultimately agreed, but you had to talk them
                    through it. They would come in, we'd explain to them what the procedure was,
                    and, in effect, say, “The next step is for you to apply for exit permission, and
                    when that happens, the chances are pretty good that your life will begin to be
                    difficult, changing all the way from dismissal to a job, to hassling, to
                    pressure on leaving your housing, to abuse on the street, to abuse in the police
                    offices where you applied for this, to all sorts of trouble. You'd better
                    reconcile yourself. And you should also reconcile yourself,” we told them, “to
                    the fact that this is not going to go quickly,” although in some instances,
                    curiously enough, it did.</p>
                <p>They would go back, they'd do their application, and we told them that they
                    should just keep us in touch, write us a letter, call us up, and then when the
                    first refusal for inordinate delay, we decided that eight weeks was an
                    inordinate delay, I would go in and say, “Now, Mr. So-and-so, about the case of
                    Hans Schmidt, for example, he came to see us. He has advised us that he has
                    applied for application. He's heard nothing, and he's been denied. I want to
                    tell you the embassy is interested in the case. We are prepared to process him
                    for an immigrant visa,” and so on and so on.</p>
                <p>Their response, inevitably, would be, “It's none of your business. This is the
                    internal affairs of the German Democratic Republic,” and so on and so on and so
                    on. We would always say, “We beg your pardon. It is our business. One, when we
                    established relations with you, we said—and you agreed—that we would be
                    discussing these cases as cases that involved your citizens and involved our
                    citizens. And we assume that you intend to live up to the communique that
                    accompanied the establishment of relations between the two countries.” Secondly,
                    we said to them, “Additionally, you signed the Helsinki Accords in the summer of
                    1975, in which the signatories agreed that they would process, consider cases of
                    humanitarian concern involving immigration movement, what have you, in a
                    charitable and helpful way. We think you are obligated, one, to get involved in
                    these cases, to process these cases in a decent way, and we think it establishes
                    our right to discuss it with you.” We'd go back and forth and back and forth on
                    this, on again, off again, on again, off again.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>Usually cases were resolved for a number of reasons. One, they simply got tired
                    of the case, it had lasted long enough, and they decided they had made the point
                    they wanted to make, and they would grudgingly give the person the exit permit.
                    We would then process them for an emigrant visa out.</p>
                <p>Another way something would happen would be if they were getting ready to a
                    particular political or economic thing that was really important for them, there
                    would always be a certain resolution on a certain number of cases shortly
                    before. Thus, before the Leipzig fairs which occurred in spring and autumn,
                    there always were several of these cases resolved. Whenever a fairly important
                    American visited, there were several cases resolved. Whenever they were going to
                    send someone to Washington, several of these cases were resolved. If a
                    particularly significant congressman and senator had made an intervention in
                    Washington with the ambassador or the deputy chief of mission, we would be
                    notified about that, because the arrangement was that Congress would always let
                    the Department of State know. It would be reported to us, and from time to time,
                    there seemed to be a correlation within a few weeks after such an intervention,
                    they would break a case loose.</p>
                <p>Finally, there were what I call the curiosity cases. We had from time to time,
                    when the East Germans wanted to do something that we wanted, but at the same
                    time do it in a way that created problems and difficulties for us, they would
                    release them in a curious way. Once, for example, they took a person who was on
                    a list, who we had been trying to get out, and instead of giving them an exit
                    permit so they could come and get an immigrant visa for us, they simply drove
                    them to one of the borders with West Berlin and pushed them across into West
                    Berlin. Suddenly, we would get a telephone call from our mission in West Berlin,
                    “Hey, we have So-and-so from your office. Is he one of yours?” I'd check my list
                    and I'd say, “Yes, he is one of ours. What happened?”</p>
                <p>Another time someone was pushed across the border into West Germany, and I got a
                    call from our embassy in Bonn saying, “This has happened. Does this mean
                    anything to you?” And I'd say, “Yes, you will be receiving our telegram.” And we
                    would make the reporting on that.</p>
                <p>One other reason why they sometimes sent people over into West Berlin was they
                    perhaps thought of this as a way of asserting some sort of four-power rights
                    over the Western sectors of Berlin, and they figured this did something like
                    that. I think that's really all that I could usefully say about these divided
                    families cases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I note that after language training, you went as consul
                        general to Warsaw, where you served from 1977 to '79. Could you contrast
                        dealing with the East Germans with the Poles, both being rather hard-line
                        Communist regimes?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>WOLF: Well, it was in many respects easier to deal with the Poles than it was
                    with the East Germans. The reason for that is that although the problem was of
                    greater magnitude in Poland, 1,000 cases involving perhaps 3,000 people in
                    Poland, as I mentioned, we only had maybe at the most 120-odd cases at any one
                    time in East Berlin. Nevertheless, the Poles were smoother, they were not so
                    hard-linish, they were not so, if you will Stalinist as the East Germans were,
                    who, every time Moscow had a cold, East Berlin sneezed. This was not the case as
                    far as Warsaw was concerned.</p>
                <p>One of the other problems was that there was a certain amount of movement of
                    Poles out to Western Europe and the United States that was quite acceptable to
                    the Polish authorities. Indeed, there were some that was acceptable to them and
                    not particularly acceptable to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What types were these?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: For example, large farm families in southern Poland, where traditionally
                    much of the emigration to the United States originated from, would visit
                    relatives or want to visit relatives in the United States, in Buffalo and
                    Detroit and Chicago and Pittsburgh, wherever there were large Polish
                    communities, and they simply said they wanted to visit their auntie or their
                    cousin. The Polish-American community is 10 million people. The Polish
                    population at that time was probably 35 to 37 million people. So you could say
                    every three, three and a half Poles had one Polish relative in the United
                    States. That's an enormous proportion between a national population and what I
                    would call an expatriate emigrated community. Then if you add to that how many
                    Poles there were in Germany, in Canada, in England, in Australia, in South
                    Africa and the like, you would say that every Pole had a relative outside. It
                    was a huge expatriate community.</p>
                <p>Some people who were related to Americans of Polish extraction would go to the
                    United States on visitors visas, work in menial jobs for two, three, four years,
                    which was illegal under the Immigration and Nationality Act, save up $10,000,
                    $20,000, bring that money back into Poland. In a certain sense, that money was
                    available to the Polish community, to Poland. They could live very, very well on
                    these savings. The Polish Government condoned that, assisted that sort of
                    emigration, that sort of movement of peoples.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Since our laws prohibit the issuing of tourist visas to
                        potential immigrants, how did you deal with this problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>WOLF: We had to refuse a significant number of them. But at that point, we ran
                    across concerns of the American-Polish community, which was represented in
                    Congress by numbers of Polish Americans. I would point out to you that there are
                    congressmen named Rostenkowski, there was a congressman named Nedzi, there was a
                    congressman named Derwinski. All of these men were, of course, representing the
                    interests of the Polish American community. Right now you have a senatorial
                    candidate in Maryland, Barbara Mikulski. There's a large Polish American
                    community in Baltimore. All of these people would be quite concerned, at least
                    they had to appear concerned to their constituents, if it was thought that the
                    refusal rate, as it's called, was too high.</p>
                <p>Now, there is no such thing as a formal refusal rate. No consular officer says,
                    “Okay, we're not going to issue more than 67% of applicants.” You issue on the
                    basis of whether a person is eligible to go, or whether a person is not
                    eligible. Nevertheless, many people try to calculate what the refusal rate is by
                    looking at statistics, and the statistics require reporting of applications,
                    reporting of issuances and reporting of refusals. These statistics are generally
                    public knowledge. On the basis of these published statistics, as statistics that
                    become available to the public, they calculate a refusal rate. What is the
                    refusal rate? Simply by doing the appropriate numerical calculations.</p>
                <p>If they perceive that the refusal rate was too high, then you'd hear about it.
                    Now, I found myself that most of these congressmen were really quite
                    understanding. I even had congressmen say to me, “From what I know in my
                    district,” they would say, “aren't you being too permissive as far as issuances
                    are concerned?” And they would immediately explain, “The reason I'm asking that
                    question is that I've got, comparatively speaking, a high unemployment rate in
                    my district, and these people who are not American citizens are coming in and
                    taking jobs away from American citizens, even though they both may be Polish
                    Americans.” So they were fairly understanding about that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is in person, not in their correspondence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: Well, one or two of them even put it in their correspondence. Let me see. I
                    think Lucien Nedzi said it to me personally, but I think he alluded to what he
                    had said in correspondence to me. In effect, what he said was, “Look, you are
                    here. I know you have no prejudices. You're going to have to enforce the law the
                    way you see it.” Now, mind you, this was in '77, '79, when things were
                    comparatively easy—comparatively. A Pole had just been elected Pope, all Poles
                    felt good about it, even members of the regime. It was before Solidarity came
                    into existence, and obviously before solidarity was suppressed and marshal law
                    was declared. So the atmosphere was a lot easier. What the atmosphere would be
                    now if you had a high refusal rate, I do not know the answer to that question,
                    because I don't know the way American Polonia would react to that sort of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much in the way of visa fraud other than a Pole
                        saying they were going to visit, when they actually intended to stay? But
                        beyond that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: No. Poles did not do that sort of thing. The only thing that would happen
                    would be what you described. He would dissemble about what his essential purpose
                    was.</p>
                <p>Another interesting curiosity about Polish movement distinct from the situation
                    in other countries in Eastern Europe, comparatively few Poles who went to the
                    United States to work for a couple of years, earn $10,000 and $20,000 and go
                    back, ever even considered staying in the United States. No matter how rough
                    things are in Poland, that's home. Poles abroad have an enormously strong sense
                    of identification with their country. So they don't abandon their country all
                    that easily once they have a country. The tendency more is to figure out clever
                    ways of resisting the system or transforming the system, but the Poles do not
                    leave. At least while I was there, they didn't do that. I have a feeling,
                    comparatively speaking, large numbers of them still go back, even if they go
                    overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many visa offices did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I had one full-time immigrant visa officer, I had one full-time
                    non-immigrant visa officer, I had one full-time American services officer. I had
                    the services of about three-quarters of another officer from other sections of
                    the embassy if we had a problem, and myself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any difficulty with these officers, whom I
                        assume were relatively junior officers, in how they handled this rather
                        difficult problem with sorting out the tourist from the immigrant?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: And even from the genuine immigrant and how to handle the whole question of
                    divided family cases, which was another issue that I'll get to in a moment. Not
                    too much. I tried to rotate officers off the non-immigrant visa line. The
                    hardest duty was non-immigrant visa duty, and I made it a practice to rotate
                    officers out of the non-immigrant visa job every four, four and a half months,
                    because I think if you kept an officer there too long, there was a tendency to
                    burn out, and there was a tendency to be really rather harsh, and a tendency to
                    become so terribly cynical that they were unable to credit any explanation at
                    all. I didn't really want that to happen.</p>
                <p>We did have a necessary task of establishing and maintaining good relations with
                    the American-Polish community, and if you had a non-immigrant visa officer who
                    was burned out or made excessively cynical or . . .</p>
                <p>[End Tape I, Side A. Begin Tape I, Side B]</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>WOLF: As I said, if you left a young visa officer doing non-immigrant visa in
                    Warsaw for too long a period, then he might burn out or he would get too hard or
                    too tough or too cynical. Then he might find himself interacting with the
                    applicant in a way, when it was reported to the American relative or the
                    American-Polish community, incredibly complicated and detailed contact between
                    Poles in Poland and Polish Americans in the United States, then the embassy
                    would be perceived as being unsympathetic, hard, and all that sort of business.
                    Frankly, we didn't want that. So I tried to deal with it by rotation and by
                    ongoing process of monitoring to see that these people kept a sense of
                    proportion as to what they were dealing with, people coming out of a very
                    complicated and difficult situation in that country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were some of the other movement of people problems
                        that you had in Poland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The big one, the one that I spent, I would say, the largest majority of my
                    time on was the Polish counterpart to the East German problem of divided
                    families. In Poland, as I think I mentioned earlier, the problem was much, much
                    bigger. There in Poland you had at that time, in the latter part of 1977, 1,000
                    cases on our representation lists. That was the total of all the cases we sent
                    in that were unresolved when I arrived, were about 1,000. You averaged three
                    people per case, you're talking about 3,000 people who were the beneficiaries of
                    approved petitions from American citizens or legal permanent residents of the
                    United States who came within the appropriate priority category—fathers,
                    mothers, sisters, brothers, husbands, wives, sons, daughters.</p>
                <p>In every one of these cases there was a congressman or a senator, or sometimes
                    both, interested. They had to be kept apprized of what was happening. We had to
                    massage the Poles to release these. They had the same objection to our inquiries
                    that the East Germans did—namely, “It's none of your business. This is our
                    internal affair. Emigration is traditionally a domestic matter.” We used the
                    same arguments to them, their signature of the Helsinki Accords, a certain
                    tradition of dialogue between the United States and Poland on these cases. And
                    they having made their point and my having answered that point, we then got down
                    to business.</p>
                <p>It was possible to be much more businesslike with Poles. The Poles had a series
                    of things that they were very specifically interested in. They were not uptight
                    about their national identity the way the East Germans were. They were generally
                    more interested in doing whatever they could to maintaining a certain distance
                    between themselves and the Soviet Union. This is not to say that the people that
                    we dealt with were not members of the Communist Party, were not loyal to the
                    principles of Marxism and Leninism. Nevertheless, they were Poles, and that
                    affected the way they handled carrying out what they perceived to be the
                    requirements of the state and the party.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>There was a certain amount of flexibility. It was really possible to negotiate
                    with the Poles about these kinds of things. The whole thing was done in a more
                    traditional diplomatic sense. There were more traditional diplomatic exchanges
                    with the Poles on this issue than there were with the Germans. The Poles never
                    did anything to interfere with what I would call traditional diplomatic or
                    consular practices of a foreign mission in Poland. The Poles never would have
                    dreamed of obstructing the creation of a medical panel the way the East Germans
                    do. The Poles didn't care about that. The key issue to them was not whether
                    there was going to be a medical panel; the key issue was whether they gave exit
                    permission. And if they gave exit permission, they had no problem if the person
                    took a medical examination or not. If they didn't give exit permission, there
                    was no point in taking a medical exam. So I sensed the Poles were rather
                    pragmatic, and they were much easier to deal with.</p>
                <p>We resolved a relatively large number of those 1,000 cases while I was there,
                    although on the other hand, it is also true that new cases came into existence
                    subsequent to the time I arrived, or during the time that I was there.</p>
                <p>A comparatively large number of cases were solved in the autumn of 1977 as a
                    prelude and, in a certain sense, a postlude to the visit of President Carter at
                    the very end of December in 1977. That was a pretty good visit from the
                    standpoint of movement of peoples, except for one gaffe that was made, and that
                    was a senior American official said to a senior Polish official, in effect,
                    “We're basically satisfied with the Polish performance in living up to the
                    obligations of the Helsinki Accords.” Well, we were not satisfied. So we had a
                    problem of about six months to straighten it out, because after the three-day
                    visit, the Poles kept saying to us, when we would go in and complain that we
                    wanted more cases released or we wanted this case released, they'd say, “But
                    we're confused, because So-and-so said to us.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was So-and-so?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I don't remember who it was, but it was one of the very senior officials.
                    We said, “He wasn't fully briefed on the subject, but we're here to tell you we
                    keep getting word from Washington that they're not satisfied with what's been
                    done.”</p>
                <p>Then there were a series of other sort of batches of people who were released.
                    Frankly, I think we were successful in getting this comparatively large number
                    of people out for one other reason, and that was we had really first-class
                    ambassadors while I was there. The first ambassador we had who was there for the
                    first four or five months of my stay in Poland was Richard T. Davies, who was
                    just winding up a five-year tour in Poland, spoke Polish perfectly, knew Poland,
                    the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe intimately, and really was very, very good as
                    far as dealing with these kinds of topics. He personally devoted a lot of time
                    to the whole divided families question, because it was a principal irritant in
                    Polish-American relations.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>He was succeeded by William Schaufele. Bill Schaufele had originally been
                    assigned to go to Greece, but there was a problem in his confirmation hearings.
                    The Greeks chose to misinterpret something that he said, and then, in effect, he
                    wasn't sent to Greece, because a lot of Greeks made a lot of complaint about
                    whether he was anti-Greek or pro-Turkish or something like that. He was sent to
                    Poland. For someone who had comparatively little professional contact with
                    Eastern Europe, he was a remarkably quick study. He mastered the complexities of
                    Polish-American relations and the Polish situation as speedily as I think anyone
                    could have. He was personally also very, very interested in the whole divided
                    families issue, among other reasons, I think, because he found personally
                    offensive anything that separated families. He had a very strong and good family
                    life, it was a very warm, close family, and he didn't like the idea of relatives
                    being kept apart artificially by regimes. So he personally involved himself.</p>
                <p>I have to say that there may be consular officers who didn't get ambassadors and
                    DCMs very interested in consular problems of this type, because sometimes
                    ambassadors considered them as non-substantive. Any consular officer has heard
                    that phrase. Both Dick Davies and Bill Schaufele clearly understood that when it
                    came to Poland, divided families, movements of peoples, this was as substantive
                    as anything could possibly be. The fact that they were with me every step of the
                    way, and all I had to do was ask them to do something, and when I could explain
                    to them why I wanted to do something, they would weigh in at the ambassadorial
                    foreign ministry level. I think that contributed significantly to success.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you left Warsaw, you continued to be dealing with
                        problems of movement of people. You became the Director of the Office of
                        European and Near Eastern Refugee Affairs, where you were there from 1979 to
                        1980. What sort of organization was this? Was this a new one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: This was a new one. You may remember that in the middle Seventies, the
                    Bureau of Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs came into existence, and one of
                    its components was the Office of Refugees and Migration. The Office of Refugees
                    and Migration had a rather large amount of money, indeed, had the lion's share
                    of the money that was appropriated for that bureau, and was very operationally
                    involved in moving people around and assisting people in place and all of that.
                    This also was just at the time of the initial outflow from Vietnam in the
                    mid-Seventies was occurring, and refugees was very much on the forefront of the
                    mind. I suppose by the end of 1978 it was recognized that the refugee function,
                    frankly, was being shortchanged, at least in terms of administrative attention
                    span, executive attention span, by being part of this other bureau.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>So they broke it out and created a new bureau which ultimately was called the
                    Bureau for Refugee Programs. That bureau was headed by someone who for reasons
                    I've never quite understood, was not called Assistant Secretary for Refugee
                    Programs, but the Director for Refugee Programs. The deputies of that director
                    were called, however, deputy assistant secretaries. I cannot explain to you the
                    reason for such an irrational choice of nomenclature, but I do think it was
                    irrational, because it simply didn't accurately represent the chain of
                    command.</p>
                <p>Above that senior State Department official, however, was a U.S. Coordinator for
                    Refugees, who really was supposed to be part of the executive office of the
                    President. The first such man was defeated Democratic Senator Dick Clark from
                    Iowa, the man who introduced the Clark Amendment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the Clark Amendment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: The Clark Amendment had something to do with what would be provided racist
                    regimes or what should not be provided racist regimes in Africa, primarily, I
                    think, directed against South Africa.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of work were you doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>WOLF: I was organizing the Office of European and Near Eastern Refugees, which
                    meant primarily the following programs: the outflow of Soviet Jews from the
                    Soviet Union, the outflow of Soviet Armenians from the Soviet Union, the outflow
                    of Poles and Czechs into Western Europe and their resettlement, the small
                    program to deal with Syrian Jews, the feeding in place of Afghan refugees, the
                    struggle about what to do about Iranians after the revolution. The Congress
                    wanted and some of the religious minority communities in the United States very
                    much wanted to have a refugee program, but the Department of State felt that a
                    refugee program for Iranians would sort of function as a self-fulfilling
                    prophecy. It would simply stimulate the Khomeini regime to persecute the very
                    people we wanted to help, and that was not our intention.</p>
                <p>Indeed, at that time we began to hear from members of the Jewish community in
                    Iran—we're now talking summer of 1979, before the hostages—that they didn't want
                    at that time a refugee program, because they were afraid that that would kick
                    over into more intense, more organized persecution of members of the religious
                    community, minority religious communities in Iraq.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>Then when the hostages were taken in November of 1979, that confirmed us that we
                    were not going to do anything about Iranian refugees, because obviously the
                    first priority then for this government had to be to get our people out. And
                    anything which was going to irritate the religious authorities in Iran was going
                    to hurt the prospects of getting our people out and certainly not help them.</p>
                <p>It was a difficult program to organize for a variety of reasons. I mean, all of
                    these things that I was talking about that came under my office's purview. One
                    reason was that a few months after I arrived, Dick Clark left. Dick Clark left
                    because he decided he was going to back Teddy Kennedy for the presidency in
                    1980, and he couldn't do that if he was a Carter appointee. So he walked out,
                    basically, on three or four days' notice, which was really not very good. So the
                    job of acting coordinator was taken over for a short period of time by the
                    director of the bureau, who was John Baker, who was a first-class career officer
                    with a lot of experience in Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>Then a month or so later, two new personalities came on the scene. The U.S.
                    refugee coordinator was a man named Victor Palmieri, and the director of the
                    refugee bureau in the Department of State was Frank Loy. Now, Palmieri came out
                    of the private sector. He was a man experienced in pulling troubled companies
                    that had gone into receivership out of difficulties. I suppose they figured what
                    they needed was a Democrat who was pretty good at damage control, because the
                    whole refugee program was in great difficulty at that time. Frank Loy was a
                    close friend and legal associate of Victor Palmieri. He had been Assistant
                    Secretary for Economic Affairs, I think, in either the Kennedy or the Johnson
                    period. So he came back seconding Palmieri directly in State.</p>
                <p>The final complication was all of the work that was done on the new Refugee Act
                    of 1980. Up until the Refugee Act of 1980, refugees were brought into this
                    country, as you know, under a variety of programs, the Displaced Persons Act,
                    Refugee Relief Act, Hungarian Refugee Acts, special provisions, parole
                    provisions for Vietnamese and so on and so on and so on. It was a very
                    complicated mixed-up procedure. The Refugee Act of 1980 proposed to unify all of
                    these various procedures under a single act of legislation which would operate,
                    essentially, as follows. Each year the President and the Congress would consult
                    on the numbers to be admitted into the United States as refugees of different
                    categories, and then once those categories were agreed to and the numbers were
                    agreed to under the process called consultation, the refugee bureau, together
                    with the Immigration and Naturalization Service and other concerned entities of
                    the United States Government would develop procedures and regulations to
                    actually carry it out.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>We were therefore functioning under the old mix of laws and regulations while, at
                    the same time, trying to participate in the creation of new legislation and
                    prepare ourselves for the first round of consultations which were going to take
                    place within 45 days after the legislation was passed. So we, in effect, had two
                    processes going simultaneously. We were understaffed. While I was there, the
                    bureau was not adequately staffed, it did not have all of its table of
                    organization filled, and the money position was quite indefinite because no one
                    knew whether they should appropriate money for the old group of laws or whether
                    they should appropriate as if the program was going to be run under the single
                    new law, because no one knew when the new law was coming in.</p>
                <p>Then just about that time, I retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much. I appreciate this interview.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
