<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000608">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mary Kidd </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>MARY KIDD</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Tina Squire</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 12, 1989</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's the twelfth of October and I am at Mary Kidd's in
                        Jaffrey, New Hampshire, starting an interview with Mary who is interesting
                        to us not only as a Foreign Service spouse, but she was herself a Foreign
                        staff officer before meeting Coburn Kidd in Vienna in 1951.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mary, will you start in talking about this time in Prague which was of such
                    interest to us all, and tell us how you happened to go into the Foreign Service,
                    how you happened to go to Prague, and the situation in Czechoslovakia when you
                    arrived. What year did you arrive?</p>
                <p>KIDD: January of 1949.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you happen to go into the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well, it's funny. I've always wanted to go into the Foreign Service. I was
                    interested in political things. Because of foreign affairs, my parents having
                    been brought up in Austria, and they were very much affected by the things that
                    were going on, and I absorbed that in many ways. I mean this was part of my
                    life. And then I worked during the War for the Czechoslovak consulate in New
                    York City. And then in 1948 when the Communists took over, I resigned. There was
                    no way I was going to work for a Communist government.</p>
                <p>I sent in my notice of resignation because I had to file — as an American citizen
                    working for a foreign government, I had to send in once a year to the State
                    Department, you know, that I am an American citizen working for the foreign
                    government. And then I worked at various jobs. And I submitted an application to
                    the State Department to go into the Foreign Service and I heard nothing. While I
                    was in the consulate there was a young woman who had been there with me and she
                    had married a flight officer, a Czechoslovak flight officer. And after the War,
                    she flew out to meet him, and on her way to meet him, he had been killed in the
                    air. She went and convoyed. He was killed in a flight of some sort. So she
                    landed in England, a widow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A Czech?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>KIDD: She was an American citizen of Czech ancestry as I am an American citizen
                    of Czech ancestry. So I don't know how it happened, but she then became attached
                    to the Czech delegation in London and went with them all over through Carpathia,
                    into Prague and so forth. She worked for the American embassy there. She then
                    became a local employee at the American embassy in Prague. She was ready to
                    re-marry and was leaving and apparently somebody had asked her if she knew of
                    anybody who was an American-born citizen who spoke Czech who would be interested
                    in... So apparently she told them about me. Then I got a letter from the State
                    Department asking me if I would be interested in joining the State Department.
                    “Yes,” I wrote back, and I sent in an application. They sent me another one in
                    the meantime. And then I didn't hear anything for a long while. And the next
                    thing I heard a friend of mine saying, “Mary, the FBI is investigating you.” “I
                    don't know. What have I done?” (laughing) I didn't tell anybody about this
                    because I don't like to tell anybody something's going to happen and then it
                    doesn't happen.</p>
                <p>And lo and behold, I think it was in September, I had a telegram from the State
                    Department asking me if I'd come down for an interview at my own expense. I was
                    living in New York at the time. And they interviewed me and then I didn't hear
                    anything else for a long while. And then in November I got another telegram
                    saying that everything went fine with the interview. If you'll come to
                    Washington for training or orientation, whatever they called it in those days —
                    I can't remember now — I would be sent Prague. I mean this was in the telegram
                    which I kept — maybe I have it somewhere, I don't know, but when you move
                    around, you throw away a lot of things.</p>
                <p>So I went down and I was there from November and came up for ThanksgivinAnd I was
                    a little worried about this because my parents — my mother was a widow at the
                    time and we owned an apartment house. And she was the worst landlady in the
                    world. (laughs) I said, “Mummy, I can't go because I can't leave you.” My sister
                    was away, my brother was away. “Mary, you go down and when you come back, I'll
                    have the house sold.” And she did. I mean at a tremendous loss, but she sold it
                    and she moved out to Illinois.</p>
                <p>And then I was supposed to sail on Christmas Eve on the SS Washington, I think.
                    And that was canceled. I was glad because I wanted to be home for Christmas at
                    least. So then I sailed on January 9th, I think it was. I'm not absolutely
                    certain. And that's how it started. I mean those were the beginnings. This is
                    how I got into it, the zigzags that happen in a person's life.</p>
                <p>I got to Prague and they didn't know what to do with me. (laughing) I mean here I
                    could speak Czech and do all sorts of things, so first of all I was on reception
                    and then gradually I got into work with Milton Fried who was in the
                    Political/Economic Section so I was his secretary for a while. Then there was a
                    cut.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, now explain a little bit. How many people were there
                        when you arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>KIDD: This is where I'm a little hazy. I'm not sure. I always think it was about
                    180 or something like that. I'm not completely certain because there were
                    various trials of local employees. This was in a very sticky time, you know,
                    what they call the Stalinist Period. And because of this the Czechs then asked —
                    this would have been then in 1950, early 1950, spring of 1950 — that we had to
                    cut our staff two-thirds. So we had to cut our staff from whatever it was — I
                    don't remember the exact figures. Those would have to be verified by somebody
                    else. I think we were left with about 35 at that time. Then we said, “Okay. We
                    cut two-thirds, you have to in Washington cut two-thirds.” And that left them
                    with twelve. When the Czechs cut their staff two-thirds, it left them with
                    twelve. So then they came back and said, “Man for man.” So all of us — the
                    ambassador was not included in the twelve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Twelve plus one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Twelve plus one or else it was eleven plus one. Anyway, whatever it was I'd
                    have to look at something where I have a list of all of the people who were
                    there at the time. So then we ended up with that nucleus, that very small core.
                    There was no security guard. We all had to pull guard duty, those who were on
                    the staff. The wives weren't included in this at that time. I think later on
                    they had to be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, we didn't.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Never? Anyway, it was these officers except the ambassador again. Of
                    course, why should he pull it? (laughing)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But he said once, “I would have, but I wouldn't give them
                        the satisfaction.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Of course he would. He was one of the best ambassadors I ever had. (laughs)
                    And he would have of course. So then we were doing our regular work and then
                    bundled up and went up to — what did they call it — the Code Room. And
                    barricaded ourselves in there with them. It was a great big door and we were
                    given a Carbine. I didn't know how to use the darn thing. It was just there on
                    the table. Probably I would have used it if I had to. And we spent the night.
                    And when the first American officer came into the embassy, then we could go
                    home, take a shower, and come back to our regular stint. (laughs) It wasn't very
                    troublesome except when the code machines went off or, somehow the Czechs always
                    knew when I was on guard duty and the phone kept ringing practically all night
                    long because they knew that I could speak Czech. And they kept hassling me I
                    guess would be the word. Anyway, Pat, it was a time when those of us who were
                    left there just banded together. We were all working together at it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't you pack everybody up, they had 36 hours or
                        something?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes because, I forget, there was a 48-hour period, I think it was about 48
                    hours, and so everybody had to chip in and everybody did. It was a sad time
                    because a lot of your friends left. I had a friend who shared an apartment with
                    me and it was sad because they were all sad, everybody was sad to leave.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. What was your maiden name?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Harak which could be translated as “mountaineer, miner”, whatever. But I've
                    got sort of a mixed parentage. My father's mother was German, her father was
                    Czech, my mother's father was Austrian and her mother was Czech. So it's on both
                    sides. And my parents met in Vienna. This was one of those things. Anyway, where
                    do you want me to go?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I'm interested in the trial. This was such an
                        important time in Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well that was in 1951.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this after Bill Otis?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, that was the Bill Otis trial. There were several local employees of the
                    American embassy who had been put on trial at the time. Then at the beginning of
                    July when Bill Otis, who was an AP, Associated Press correspondent with the New
                    York Times was put on trial. He had been picked up on all sorts of charges of
                    espionage and he was the most innocuous-looking man I've ever seen in my life.
                    But whether he was a spy or not, that's immaterial.</p>
                <p>Then there was a vice consul who was — Dick Johnson at the time — who was allowed
                    to come to the trial. They didn't allow lots of other people, but the vice
                    consul could. And also I guess because I could understand, I was also given a
                    permit to. So Dick Johnson and I were at the Otis trial which lasted about three
                    days. We had to be at the trial at 8 o'clock and then until 6. And in the course
                    of this trial, they were asking all sorts of questions and this was brought out
                    in one of the books that was written either by Bill Otis later or Ellis Briggs,
                    I can't remember which book it was in, where it mentioned that — because I was
                    taking down notes all this time, translating from Czech into English and into
                    shorthand — mental acrobatics anyway you want to look at it! And I'd come back
                    to the embassy with a steno book, sometimes two, full of notes and have to
                    transcribe that after the trial so they could send these things back to
                    Washington. I was finished sometimes at 10 o'clock and the next morning I'd have
                    to be at the trial.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>There was one point — there were several points in the trial that were peculiar.
                    One was when the... They had to translate all these things for Bill Otis from
                    Czech into English and English into Czech. And sometimes the translator got
                    ahead of his testimony, so you knew the whole thing was rigged, even the
                    answers. Unless you knew what the answers were, you wouldn't know. And that was
                    the only time, you know. I could catch it because I could get the first and then
                    I got the second and I could see that Bill hadn't said that yet. It came in at
                    the next... And then the next thing was, it must have been the second day of the
                    trial, Bill was asked to mention all the people who were spies in the embassy.
                    So, you know, he went down. Some who were the obvious ones, let's put it that
                    way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were Czechs?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No American spies. And then he mentioned my name. And I just sat there
                    transcribing all this into shorthand and I suddenly realized, “He's talking
                    about me!” And then I continued. I simmered down a bit and then I continued. And
                    the day went on and I transcribed these notes. When I got to the point where I
                    mentioned it, I couldn't read my notes! I mean I had a mental block and somebody
                    else had to come and do it for me. Just that one section and then afterwards it
                    was all right. In the meantime, the ambassador knew that this was going to not
                    be well for me. I wasn't a spy! I was just an employee of the embassy!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But still.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: In the meantime things had been arranged so that whatever effects I had
                    would be packed up and the day after the trial I left. The funny thing is that
                    you have to submit a list to the Foreign Office of every single item you own. If
                    you had twelve handkerchiefs and you ended up with thirteen, you couldn't take
                    that thirteenth one. And so everything had to be very carefully entered down the
                    list.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Such an inventory!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well, I didn't have much in those days so it wasn't all that bad, but you
                    know — twelve handkerchiefs against thirteen — one I had to leave behind! Then
                    the ambassador wouldn't let me leave alone. I had to...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Ellis O. Briggs, one of the best men that I've ever served under. He
                    arranged a convoy to go with me. So there was a car in front of me, my car, and
                    then there was another car.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you drove out...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: As I drove out of Czechoslovakia. Leaving the country I was stopped twice.
                    And all of us very carefully followed the rules. If it said 40 kilometers, we
                    went 40 kilometers, even 39 so we wouldn't go over. (laughs) But they stopped
                    me. And one time one of the officers (said), “Well I see you're a careful
                    driver.” But they kept this up until I got to the German border. And then that
                    was the end of that.</p>
                <p>But while I was in Prague, there were one or two other things, but those are
                    incidental. The first DCM was Jim Penfield. He was very, very good. And so was
                    his wife Anne. One time I had to go to — I don't know whether this should be
                    said or not. He received a letter from someone who was concerned about a Czech
                    relative in Cardober Vary in the Cazbat. And he asked me if I would be willing
                    to deliver this letter. He didn't want me to go alone, so I asked one of the —
                    we called them flyboys because he was in the Air Force — what was his name? Jim
                    Macalroy, something, whatever. So we drove to Cardober Vary to deliver the
                    letter. This woman was in the hospital. I mean those were little things that we
                    were doing to help the American citizens who were concerned about their own.</p>
                <p>And then after he left, Tyler Thompson was the DCM. I'd always wanted to go to
                    Vienna. I mean after my posting. Technically I should have left in February, but
                    because all these different trials were coming up, I... And they also couldn't
                    find a replacement who had so-called “qualifications.” So I didn't leave until
                    July. But Tyler was on vacation and my transfer orders came in. And I was
                    supposed to go to Frankfurt. So I thought, well Vienna. I'll save that for next
                    time, maybe.</p>
                <p>And he came back and was going through all the telegrams. And he called me in and
                    said, “Mary, I thought you wanted to go to Vienna.” “Yes, I do, but Vienna isn't
                    offered, Frankfurt isn't such a bad thing.” Now maybe you'd better turn this
                    off. All right, he said, “You want to go to Vienna,” and I said, “Yes I do.” And
                    so he said, “Why don't you go to Frankfurt and then go to Vienna and see which
                    one of those posts you like.” So I flew to Frankfurt and I was interviewed by
                    Walt Stoessel at the time. Then there was another funny officer there. His name
                    begins with a D and I can remember being intrigued because he had his shoes
                    under the table and he had house slippers on. I believe he had corns or bunions
                    or something, I don't know. And then Walt Stoessel interviewed me, and he was
                    very nice and everything was nice. And Blanche Thompson was there at the time.
                    She been one of the girls who had PNG'd out, well, went out with the cut.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From Prague.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>KIDD: From Prague. And she was in the peripheral section there at the time. And I
                    stayed with her. And it all seemed very nice. Then I flew to Vienna and I talked
                    to [inaudible]. I didn't talk to Coburn in those days. It wasn't he. I talked to
                    someone in the peripheral section. I can't remember whether it was Fred Salter
                    or whoever it was. I can't remember. Anyway, I came back and he says, “Have you
                    made up your mind?” I said, “No question. I want Vienna if I can get it.” So
                    apparently he wrote back to someone in Washington and instead of assigning me to
                    Frankfurt, assigned me to Vienna and that's where I met my husband, Coburn
                    Kidd.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you served there. You were not married while you were
                        in Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No. I arrived in Vienna, it was the end of October.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was Coburn then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: He was chief of the Political Section at the time. And I really didn't meet
                    him until the Dowlings — he was the DCM I guess, Walter Dowling was the DCM at
                    the time. And they had a party for all the new people who came into the
                    Political Section, Economic, whatever. And Coburn was at that party and I
                    remember talking to him, but I mean nothing...</p>
                <p>And then at Christmas Tully and Anne Torbert were giving a Christmas party for
                    all of the people in the Political Section. And Coburn at that point had planned
                    to go to Greece so I didn't meet him then. I was supposed to go to this party,
                    but I was living in a flat and it was uphill. You had to walk uphill to get to
                    the Torberts, so I couldn't drive. Throads were glut ice, you know that black
                    ice as they call it here. And I kept going up two steps, sliding down one, going
                    up one, sliding down two. And finally I slid all the way back and I called up
                    Torberts, “I can't make it.” So I never got to the party. So I didn't meet him.
                    And he wasn't there either.</p>
                <p>Then there were a group of about five of us girls who decided in February of 1952
                    to give something called a “Gay Twenties” party. And we all dressed as flappers
                    and everybody else dressed as whatever the style was. And Coburn was at this
                    party. Well he didn't put on anything except a false nose. He came in a tux. He
                    didn't have anything except a false nose and that was his concession to the “Gay
                    Twenties.” And he taught me how to play roulette, you know this sort of thing.
                    And then he was talking. And I remember it just hit me. He was special. And we'd
                    go, we went there and things of that sort.</p>
                <p>And one time he asked me to get a list of the masses at a church that I hadn't
                    gone to. I went to the Catholic church and he did too, for that matter, when he
                    did go. It was Maria Algastada and so I asked for it. I was living at the
                    Bristol at the time. First of all I lived at the Cottage Hotel or something. And
                    it was a broom closet. I mean I was there only two or three weeks and then they
                    moved me.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well the Bristol was filled with Americans, wasn't it?
                        Foreigners?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, yes, it was requisitioned by the Americans. And so after the two or
                    three weeks in which I lived in this broom closet, then they moved me to the
                    Bristol which was a slightly larger broom closet that I lived in. (laughs) And
                    anyway, he asked me to get the list of masses for the Maria Algastada church in
                    Vienna. And so I asked the porter to get them for me. And Coburn that evening
                    came to pick me up for dinner. And the porter handed him this list. Coburn had
                    asked me by telephone, so you knew that everybody was being bugged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even in Vienna.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Even more so. I mean just as much as in all the others. So that was one of
                    the funny things that happened in the Service. And then Coburn was transferred
                    to Washington in May and I had to resign from my post. And I didn't leave until
                    after July. Donnelly was the ambassador at the time. Then we got married in
                    September of 1952 and lived happily ever after. (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back in Washington.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well we were back in Washington until....</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were married in...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: ...in Lisle, Illinois because my mother had moved out to Illinois and my
                    brother, being a priest, was out there, too, and he married us. And Coburn and
                    his mother and brother and sister-in-law came. So that was in September of 1952
                    and then we went immediately back to Washington. Coburn, because he was not yet
                    a full Foreign Service officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: He had been working in the State Department, you see. And when he came back
                    he wasn't entitled to home leave so we never had a honeymoon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was not a Foreign Service officer. Was he
                        Wristonized?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>KIDD: He wasn't exactly. There was one thing, it wasn't the Wristonization. It
                    was something where you were able to transfer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cross-laterally into the Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Exactly, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he do that in Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, in Prague, no not in Prague, in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After Vienna.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, yes. So you see when he came back he wasn't entitled to home leave.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what was he doing in Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: He was [chief of the] political [section]. We didn't have an embassy at
                    that time, it was only a mission. He had been on the Vienna desk in Washington
                    and he was sent out to Vienna for two years. He had been there from '48 to —
                    well I guess from '49 until then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well he certainly had by the end of his career a
                        reputation as one of the leading legal authorities on Germany.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, yes, that was his specialty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even at that time it was his specialty. When you were in
                        Vienna?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, yes, it was Germanic things. And he having had a career... First of
                    all, he started out as a philosopher and got his degree in philosophy at St.
                    Andrews in Scotland. And then he came back and his father said, “Can you earn
                    your living at this?” And he said that there was the Depression. And he said,
                    “No.” So he went to Georgetown University and got a law degree. So he became a
                    member of the Washington Bar. And he also worked in the Archives in the day
                    while he was doing that. And there were a couple of other things. He worked on
                    Wall Street for a while. And was called into the Army at that time. Then during
                    the War he was in the OSS. When he left the Army, then I think he worked at the
                    Archives then. I can't remember the sequence, I'd have to look up his
                    biography.</p>
                <p>How he got into the State Department at that point I'm not 100 percent sure. If
                    he were here he'd tell me. And then in the State Department he was sent to
                    Vienna.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So this was at the time that you met him? During this
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes. And he was not yet a Foreign Service officer. I think it was the first
                    few months that we were in Washington after we were married or early the next
                    year I guess, when he was accepted into the Foreign Service. It was not exactly
                    Wristonization, but there was an in-between when there was a crossover.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And there were people who came in, a lot of people who
                        came in after. Well I can find that out.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: I'm not certain about that. And then he became a Foreign Service officer
                    and went on to three or four... Because he was a Foreign Service officer three
                    Reserve when he was in Vienna, that's what it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A Reserve officer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: And then he became a regular Foreign Service officer. And he went in as a
                    three and when he left the Service he was an FSO one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Consul general in Hamburg.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I want to have you describe Coburn Kidd. You just said he was a Renaissance
                    man.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>KIDD: Well someone here in Jaffrey Center after having met Coburn described him
                    as a Renaissance man and he really was. He was a philosopher, he was a lawyer,
                    he was a diplomat, he was well-read, music. I mean, you name it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He published a book.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, he never published a book. Well, he did make A Portrait of a Village of
                    Jaffrey Center which was photographs of the various houses within the village.
                    The village isn't all that big. And then his last thing, just before he died,
                    was something called Streets and Roads of Jaffrey which was really definitive
                    and it's been really useful for the town. He was involved very much in town
                    affairs on the legal side of things before he died. Assistant Town Counsel,
                    that's what he was. And he enjoyed that. And he did that almost until the month
                    that he died.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You retired from Hamburg and came here to live.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well that was another story. I mean we'd traveled all around to find a
                    place to live and we ended up here which we love. And it was really marvelous
                    because the community here at that time was composed of a lot of retired
                    professors, very erudite. I mean in all fields whether it was English, whether
                    it was philosophy, whether it was history, whatever. And he joined a reading
                    group and he'd come home sometimes and say, “Mary it's like going to a college
                    seminar. I mean all these smart people.” He didn't realize he was that way,
                    didn't think that he was smart enough. It was just perfect for his retirement
                    years. But it wasn't enough so he went back to his legal things. And he enjoyed
                    that immensely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And passed the Bar exam again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, yes. He had to pass the Bar exam here in New Hampshire. He did that the
                    first year we were here. He was a member of the Washington Bar, the New York
                    Bar, and then the New Hampshire Bar. He had to pass that before he could do
                    anything in the legal field.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You know I want to take you back a little bit to after you
                        served in Washington. Where did you go after you were married and lived in
                        Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: We were there until 1956 and we were supposed to go to the Imperial Defense
                    College in London. This was in December. We were on the boat, we had closed down
                    the apartment, separated things that we wanted to take with us from things that
                    had to go into storage. We were in New York, we had put the car on the ship,
                    excess baggage, and just kept a few things. We were going to be there for two
                    days.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>But you know we all have to take medicals before we left. And he had had his
                    medical and I had had mine. And while we were in New York — I remember it was
                    the Henry Hudson Hotel — when we checked in, after we had put the car on the
                    ship and all the excess stuff, the State Department wanted him to telephone. So
                    he called back, called the State Department. They said they weren't completely
                    satisfied with his medical reports. But if he wanted to go to London and then
                    had to take another medical and all this sort of thing. Then he could do that.
                    But we decided no, the wisest thing to do was for him to go back and straighten
                    this whole thing out.</p>
                <p>Well, the upshot of this was that we didn't sail. He called me from Washington,
                    “Mary get the car off the ship, get everything else. We're not sailing.” He flew
                    up the next day and then told me the whole thing. They had found a spot on his
                    lungs that they weren't completely satisfied with. And so we didn't want to go
                    back to Washington. This was just before Christmas. And they were slightly
                    [understaffed].</p>
                <p>But this was the holiday period. So what we said, we've always liked to go to
                    Rehoboth for the holidays, especially when it was out-of-season because the
                    beach was empty, we could walk back and forth and collect shells and whatever.
                    So we decided, “We'll go to Rehoboth and take our chance and we can get a flat
                    somewhere or a cabin or whatever.” We were lucky, we were able to get something.
                    So we stayed there until after New Year's and drove to Washington. Coburn went
                    into Bethesda and some very good friends of mine, Jeff and Betty Lewis had me
                    stay with them in Virginia. He was there about a month.</p>
                <p>They said at that time that it was TB so then we got in the car and drove out to
                    Colorado to Simmons Hospital. We got there in February. I got a small efficiency
                    flat. Coburn was in the hospital. And they kept taking tests. And finally they
                    decided to do an exploratory and when they did the exploratory they decided it
                    wasn't TB at all, that it had been lung cancer, and they took out one of the
                    lobes of his lung. And then everything turned out well, thank God. I mean he
                    recovered fairly well, fairly quickly. And we left for Washington in June. And
                    Coburn went into the State Department and everything was fine.And then we sailed
                    the following December for London, just a year later than we would have gone.
                    And then we were in London from 1957, '58 and '59. One year at the Imperial
                    Defense College, that was fun, and then he was assigned to the embassy as
                    liaison officer with the Parliamentary Labour Party. Mind you, he was more of
                    what I would say a Conservative than a Labourite. (laughs) But this was all
                    right. It was marvelous because you met the most interesting people at that
                    time. And then we went to Japan.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was he in Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: A political counselor at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you like Japan? This was new for both of you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Oh, I just felt we weren't there long enough! We were there only two years.
                    And that isn't long enough. You're just beginning to absorb... This is such a
                    different culture. I mean in Europe it's easier to assimilate things. But in
                    Japan it takes time. And first of all to get yourself organized and everything
                    else. I went to classes every single day that I could to take Japanese lessons.
                    You know I hate to get up in the morning, early that is. But I'd go there and
                    the classes started at 9. I had about an hour or an hour and a half. I'd go home
                    and do whatever homework. But it helped me to at least speak some Japanese. Many
                    Japanese ladies at that time didn't speak English so at least you could ask,
                    “How are you? How many children do you have?” And if they asked me, I would be
                    able to answer. That was about the extent because Japanese is an ongoing thing
                    and you never say, “Oh, I know it all.” You never do. (laughs). It's just like
                    many other places.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you made the effort which was...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well it was so fascinating. I mean any country. If you make the effort.
                    Fortunately I was able to speak Czech so I didn't have to worry about that. I
                    did have to brush up on my German because we grew up speaking Czech and German.
                    But I had to brush up on that. So I did lessons there. Well, when we got back to
                    Washington I didn't have to worry about that. There was not a language problem
                    there. And in London, no problem there. But Japan was a world that was so
                    completely different.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were there for two years and then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: We were there for two years and then we got a telegram from the State
                    Department that he was being assigned to Bonn, Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what year was that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: '59. So we were in Bonn for six years. We had two home leaves I think in
                    that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And what was he in Bonn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: He was chief of the Political Section. And then he was assigned after that
                    to Hamburg so altogether we had nine years in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that was when he was the consul general in
                        Hamburg?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: In Hamburg.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where he became a legal authority on Germany.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well he's always been a German expert. He had some of his schooling in
                    Tubingen. When he was at St. Andrews he'd go down to Tubingen in the summertime
                    between semesters or whatever it was. His interest had been German affairs so
                    that I think he might have felt that he was out of his depth in Japan, I don't
                    know. (laughs)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I can't believe he ever was anywhere. (Pause)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: ...on holiday. The attitude was, “I can't wait to get back. What else was
                    doubling.”</p>
                <p>Because we were doubling already. And then somebody else taking your duty while
                    you were away. We just couldn't wait to get back. Even though it was a stressful
                    time. I will admit that it took me a long while to get over what I call the
                    “neck twitch,” you know, to see who's behind me or who's listening. And you
                    never talked over the phone, I mean anything that was important. I had Czech
                    friends and we always arranged to meet. And if they said, “Come on Wednesday,”
                    it meant come on Tuesday or whatever. We changed the code from week to week so
                    there wouldn't be a chance of being followed. I would always get into the least
                    American clothes.</p>
                <p>There was one incident when I was in Prague before... I thought I had on the most
                    innocuous clothes. Unfortunately I had a red shoulder bag. I got into a trolley
                    car and I was going from one place to another — I was going to a museum I think
                    at the time. And there were two women sitting across from me. They had their
                    shopping bags and cabbages, mostly cabbages because you couldn't get very much.
                    We were allowed one egg a month at that time. I think officers had two or three
                    depending on their family. But we only had one egg a month. Anyway, they were
                    sitting there talking and finally one of them looked at me, up and down. And
                    then she sort of whispered something to her neighbor. I couldn't hear the
                    whisper. The other neighbor, her friend, looked me up and down and in a voice I
                    could hear in Czech, “She's not pretty, but she's interesting.” (laughs) These
                    are little vignettes that really have nothing to do with the Foreign Service but
                    have affected the people who have been in the Foreign Service in the foreign
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course. You were completely cut off by that time,
                        weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>KIDD: Very much so, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Other Americans were not allowed in the country.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Because I wanted my sister in 1950 to come visit me because we were going
                    to drive to Rome — it was the Holy Year in Rome at the time. She couldn't get a
                    visa so I had to meet her in Frankfurt. Then we drove from Frankfurt to Rome.
                    She stayed with a friend of mine who was one of those who had also gone in the
                    cut in Paris. And then Anne and Lucy drove to Frankfurt and I met them there and
                    she drove to Rome. She couldn't get in!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While Bill Otis was in prison. Wasn't that the reason that
                        we broke off everything but diplomatic relations with...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes. They kept manufacturing all these things. It's all coming out now.
                    Even when they manufactured things against their own people. Oh, what was the
                    name of the man? It began with a G. It's been so long ago that I haven't even
                    thought about. He was subsequently hanged. It was that very rigid Stalinesque
                    period. They were more papal than the Pope, you know, that sort of thing. More
                    Communist than the Communists. And they still are to this day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, yes. (Pause)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD:..to my mother. And she said, “Aren't you Mrs. Harak? And she said, “Yes.”
                    “I have all these clippings.” She knew my mother, I don't know from where. And
                    she gave my mother all these clippings of me. Mummy hadn't even seen them. I
                    think they were in the Daily News or Tribune or whatever.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During the trial.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: There was one sharp reporter came. And you see in the meantime of course
                    Mummy had moved out to Illinois so she wouldn't have seen the New York papers. I
                    had originally been listed as coming from New York City. And so they
                    interviewed...</p>
                <p>—</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's 1990 now, nearly a year later, and we're sitting on
                        my porch. I am talking with Mary Kidd on my porch in Rindge, next door to
                        Jaffrey. Mary has been back to Prague since all the happenings in
                        Czechoslovakia. She went back in May and I think it will be very interesting
                        for her to add some of her impressions of Czechoslovakia today as a
                        second-generation Czech who has been going back to Czechoslovakia since she
                        was a young girl. Mary, when did you first go to Czechoslovakia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: In 1929 the whole family went to Europe and was there for the whole summer.
                    We went in June and we didn't come back until the end of September, I guess it
                    was. And so that was my early days there. And then as I think about how I felt
                    then, it was a happy time for me of course, being young. I didn't know anything
                    about politics or anything like that. I could sense the happiness and the
                    atmosphere. People were gay and happy, fairly happy.</p>
                <p>Then the next time I went there was in 1949 when I worked at the embassy for two
                    and one-half years. And that was a grim period. You were followed everywhere.
                    Pat will know. And people were afraid, that's it, they were afraid and you never
                    made eye contact with anybody unless you knew somebody personally. And even then
                    you tried not to do it. They scurried along. They always had these little
                    suitcases walking around with that shuffling walk. As a matter of fact when I
                    was there one time I even bought a whole outfit of Czech clothes so I'd blend
                    into the crowd. And people still recognized me as a foreigner. And I asked my
                    Czech friends, I said, “What's wrong? Is my Czech bad?” And they said, “No,
                    there's nothing wrong with your speaking language. It's the way you walk.”
                    Because I walked straight and I looked around and was curious about things. And
                    they all scurried around like little turtles.</p>
                <p>Then the next time, it was in 1964 when I went back with my mother. And that was
                    still in the pretty grim period, although in the countryside it wasn't so bad.
                    Then in '69, Coburn and I went there and we had about two weeks in
                    Czechoslovakia. And that was just at the time, it was in June and July of '68,
                    it was just at the time that Dubcek was starting that “Prague Spring”. Everybody
                    was gung ho to get... You know, “we're going to do something, we're going to be
                    free.” And of course right after that, it was right after the Russian-Czech
                    soccer game that had been in September or October, I guess. The Czechs won over
                    the Russians and of course the streets were just crowded with young people
                    particularly in jubilation and everything else. And that was the end of the
                    uprising. Because it started then — and it had been beginning — but it
                    snowballed until that time, until the Russian tanks came in.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>And at that time a young student, I think it was at... I forget now which
                    university it was. Was it Charles University or ... ? Well, whatever. He burned
                    himself right in front of the statue of St. Wenceslas on the main street and to
                    this day there is a memorial. It's really a living memorial started out by
                    people burning candles in his memory. And what has happened in that time is that
                    about a foot-high circle now has formed of wax drippings and into that people
                    still keep adding new candles and they're different colors. They're different
                    colors, it's not just black or white. And flowers are always there. And there's
                    a picture of him that used to be there right in the middle, just him alone. But
                    now since the Velvet Revolution, they've added a couple more of the old-timers
                    like Tom�sha and Benes and a few others, I can't remember who they are. There
                    are some women there and I can't remember their names.</p>
                <p>And the spirit is so different. You couldn't tell the Czechs from the foreigners.
                    It was crowded. Everybody was walking out, laughing, music. Stores are always
                    crowded. Of course you can't always get everything. You still have to get in
                    line. If you want to buy a couple of rolls, you stand in line to buy a couple of
                    rolls, and when you get there, they're sold out. (laughs) Or else you go into a
                    shop and you see a hat you like and they don't have it in your size. Or you go
                    there the next day and they don't have any hats left. (laughs) And they're not
                    stocking either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They don't know when they're going to get them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: One thing I remember. That the city is now so beautiful. Fortunately we
                    only had one day of rain and we walked and walked and walked. That old town
                    square is just magic. It looks like all the icing on a lovely birthday cake or
                    wedding cake. I mean it just looks like a great big wedding cake, the whole
                    circle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they are beginning to really restore?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well they must have been doing it for a long time. It's a city that really
                    has to be constantly...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because when we were there in '85, it really looked like
                        nobody cared. People put trash in places.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>KIDD: But you see they burn that soft coal and within a few years all these
                    things dull. But it was interesting when you went up to the castle and then,
                    just to the left of the castle as you're facing the castle is the Archbishop's
                    Palace. Well, you've never seen anything more glorious. Of course we thought
                    maybe they had done it because the Pope was coming. But this had apparently been
                    in the works to have it re-done. It was beautiful. Pink and gold, all the gold
                    picked out, all the seals and everything else. The castle itself — everything
                    looks splendid. What you notice again if you have been there before is you don't
                    see soldiers with guns. Now you do occasionally see two — maybe they're the
                    local militia, I don't know. I couldn't tell...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, like in London.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Like the police. But they don't have guns. One of them might have a gun.
                    But the other one has a walkie-talkie. But none of these tommy guns and none of
                    these horrible battle fatigue type of things. They dress very smartly. Their
                    uniforms are nice and neat and tidy and well-fitted, too. Handsome young boys,
                    too. But it was interesting. No guns, even in front of the castle!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No military guns.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No military. The feeling of being watched over by the military is
                    completely gone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you were there just before the elections.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes. I left on the 7th, the election was on the 9th. So that was another
                    interesting thing, listening to my Czech friends and listening to television and
                    watching Havel speak. The spirit of the people was something that was so
                    overwhelming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was interesting to me to hear about your friends, three
                        sisters — two Communists and one not.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>KIDD: Yes. My friend is married to a pediatric surgeon who should be retiring
                    soon because he's about 78 now. But he's still going strong. She's my friend.
                    She's about four days younger than I am, that's all. She had an older sister and
                    a younger sister. And I knew all the three girls when we first went there in
                    1928. I hadn't seen those other two sisters in a long time because one of them
                    was married to a doctor of philosophy, a very strong Communist, as was this
                    older sister. The youngest sister was married to a secretary of the Communist
                    Party, a strong Communist, and she, too. Then he became a Czech ambassador in
                    Rome. He's since died, but the two sisters and one of the brothers-in-law is
                    still living. I didn't get to see them because there isn't much going back and
                    forth especially at this time because my friend...</p>
                <p>We don't talk about politics because I don't want them to say, “See I told you
                    so.” I mean this is her way of looking at it. I couldn't contain myself. I'd
                    certainly go out and say it. (laughs) But their children, the children of the
                    two sisters who had been strong Communists, are very resentful of their parents
                    now. They're blaming them for what they have caused and they're saying it's
                    their fault because they were the ones who were part of the whole
                    establishment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mary, do you think they were Communists because of the
                        situation in Czechoslovakia or were they Communists like so many of the
                        British were in-between the wars. In the '30's, if you had a heart, you were
                        a Communist.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, this I think was part of the way they grew up. Because at the time when
                    Tom�sha Masaryk was re-building the republic, he believed very much in what they
                    called the “free-thinking” individual. I think that was part of the whole period
                    of bringing Socialism to the forefront rather than anything else. And that
                    stayed with those... As a matter of fact, my friend was not a particularly... I
                    mean, she came from a Catholic family, but she'd fallen away from the Church,
                    and you know, was shaky about it. But then I guess it was in 1950, one of her
                    children died and she suddenly realized her little girl was going to go to
                    Heaven and she wasn't and she'd never see her, that was her attitude. (laughter)
                    Then her husband — both of them are friends of my parents, their parents were
                    friends of my parents — he was always a strong Catholic. And because he never
                    joined the Communist Party, he never got to the top job of the medical
                    profession because he wasn't a Communist, card-carrying. However, anytime there
                    was a Communist who had a child who was ill and needed an operation, they always
                    had him do it, not anybody else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So they didn't suffer as much as some.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: They didn't suffer. This is what my friend said — Emma. She said, “We
                    didn't suffer. True, there were restrictions that we lived with.” But to say
                    that they suffered under that... She said that you couldn't say that. And I can
                    believe that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a form of discrimination, but it didn't...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Exactly. Well, as you know, they had the degrees of shops. When you went
                    shopping, if you were the ordinary man on the streets, you had to take what
                    there was. And whether the head of cabbage was the size of an apple or whether
                    it was the [size of a cabbage], you still paid the same amount for either one.
                    Then they had what they called a lower-grade Communists shop that was tucked
                    away where nobody could see it. They had to have cards and they could shop
                    there. Then they had the ones [for] the Number One Communists. When I was there
                    with my mother, Emma took me to one of the Number One ones because of her
                    sister. I was appalled. I mean every luxury that the average man on the street
                    couldn't get, never had. And the meat when you could get it was all fat, you
                    know that sort of thing, whereas in the Number One and Two stores...</p>
                <p>And now the shops had a lot of food. Of course, by our standards, it didn't seem
                    expensive. But then our income is different. For them, certain things, they
                    still had to worry — not worry, but think about whether they should spend it on
                    this or on that. Necessities like milk they can get, and that sort of thing.
                    Fresh vegetables are still chancy because they haven't opened up the free market
                    yet for them. Farmers come in and bring in their produce. It's coming in slowly.
                    We saw a few around Prague at the time.</p>
                <p>But what is plentiful are these smoked meats. Any variety of frankfurter. I mean,
                    you have to know — those from Arabia and those from... And they had a lot of
                    those shelves. Again, I can't talk about the prices because I'd make the
                    comparisons. To me it didn't seem expensive, but for them, yes. The interesting
                    thing, though, is if you saw something in the shop that you liked — I remember
                    going in and I bought a small pewter owl for a friend of mine who likes them.
                    And I went another place and I saw exactly the same thing and I thought, “I
                    wonder if I paid more or less?” It was the same price.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Still.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Still. They still haven't gotten on to the free economy. The restaurants —
                    they are few. They are good, but you have to make reservations days in advance.
                    You can't just walk in and say, “Do you have room for two?” Not just that day.
                    Days in advance. And they're always crowded. The theaters are full. Of course,
                    they always were. That was always one of the things — that was their outlet,
                    too. And while I was there I went to see one of the Capek plays — “The Insects”
                    — did you hear about it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>KIDD: It's a sort of metaphysical sort of thing. I think that's what they call
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw Mother Teresa.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: And my highpoint is meeting Mother Teresa. Oh that was exciting. One of the
                    daughters of my friend called and said that she had heard that Mother Teresa was
                    going to be at the Church of St. Anthony in a working-class neighborhood and
                    she'd be there at 6 o'clock. And I was exhausted. I had just put my friend on
                    the train and she was gone and she'd walked my feet off and I was going to put
                    my feet up and do nothing. But when this came up, oh there was no way you could
                    keep me away! So we got into the Metro, then we took a streetcar, then we walked
                    some more, so it took about an hour and a half or a little bit more. And we got
                    there and the church was packed. It was the last day in May, I remember that
                    now.</p>
                <p>And low and behold, before the mass actually began because it was the last of the
                    services that they had for her, Mother Teresa came in with her entourage. She
                    had about five or six young women with her who wear white veils and white
                    dresses and a blue band around them. And Mother Teresa, who is tiny — I mean she
                    just got lost in the crowd because everybody was towering over her — she came in
                    and greeted everyone. She speaks in English. She's Yugoslav by birth, but she
                    speaks in English. And I almost had a chance to translate for her and I — well,
                    somebody else got in and I will admit, I could have done a better job.
                    (laughter) That's not bragging, that's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, Mary, they want you to come and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well, they did ask me, but again you see, it's something that everybody
                    wants to learn now. The English — they have to learn now. Many of them didn't
                    bother to learn English because their attitude was “we'll never need it.” They
                    kept thinking this suppression, this domination by the Russians was going to
                    continue forever. Well, they had to learn Russian and the parents did urge their
                    children to have private lessons [in English]. “No, we'll never need it.” Now
                    they're regretting it of course. So one of the granddaughters of my friend is
                    studying. And when I was there, she was reading, she could read quite well
                    already. [To Tina] I've got to ask you about some books that I could send to her
                    that are in English.</p>
                <p>And now that the interest is everything towards the West, you can't buy a
                    Czech-English dictionary there. You can get stacks of Russian ones if you want,
                    but you can't buy them [Czech-English dictionary]. They're not in any bookstore
                    in Prague. One of the men who was serving — somebody came in asking for it. And
                    he said, “I'd like to have a Czech-English dictionary.” This was in Czech. And
                    he said, “They're not to be had. And when they come in, I don't know.” I mean
                    everybody wanted them as soon as they came in, you know.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>They have good book shops, though, and they're good books, relatively cheap, too.
                    But that's one of the things that they can get there in that subsidized
                    printing. My friends were surprised when I came in with paperbacks to read.
                    “Why? Don't you have hard[backs]?” Of course paperbacks are the best thing for
                    traveling. (laughs) You finish it and you can give it to somebody. I just left
                    all the paperbacks I had with them. Except the trouble with that is, the print
                    is small.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and hard [to read].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Anyway they're good to travel. So that was wonderful. (pause)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, it's the young people who started this. It's the
                        young people who...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes, they're the ones who started it and they're keeping it up, too. The
                    fascinating thing is when they're campaigning the way we do for our elections
                    because they had about 23 parties running. Well, Havel said he wanted everyone
                    to have their say-so in all of this. And if some of them were left of center,
                    some were left of left of center, and others... The main one, of course, was the
                    Civic Forum. And then they had the Catholic Democratic Party and the — some
                    social — there were 23, I couldn't name them all. And it was fascinating
                    listening to them on the television. They had the panels, the same sort of thing
                    that we have here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Free to speak.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well they would have all of them. I mean we have mostly Democratic debates
                    and Republican debates, but there they had all the parties. And then there would
                    be questions. And some of them would be very articulate and others were less so.
                    But they all had a chance to say their piece and then they'd argue among each
                    other. You know, one would say something... And that was fascinating to watch.
                    That wouldn't have been possible!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you said the farmers were voting Communist.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Most of the farmers voted Communist because most all their farms have been
                    collectivized. And they're very happy with that. They feel that they don't have
                    the responsibility of getting out whether rain or shine to take care of their
                    crops, feed their stock and worry about anything. This is all taken care of by
                    the State. And so many of them, perhaps not all of them, but in many cases they
                    were going to vote for Communists, they said.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well were they worried about who owned where they
                        lived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, that didn't bother them that much anyway. And the children had moved
                    away. In the old days, you know the custom was you stayed on the farm and the
                    oldest son or somebody would stay there. But that's all [gone now] or else, if
                    they did work on the farm, they only worked 9 to 5 or whatever the hours were,
                    and they didn't have to stay until it was dark, so they were quite satisfied
                    with that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well it's logical.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: It's going to be a long haul for many of them, and there are going to be
                    some disappointments along the way, too, I think because I'm not sure that many
                    of them know exactly what democracy is other than the freedom of speech and
                    freedom of press and religion and all that. They don't realize that they're
                    going to have to work for it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The work ethic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: That's something that the President himself stressed. That the morality of
                    the people — he wasn't thinking in terms of their spiritual morality — but of
                    the whole being of the human morality has gone so low that people don't care. I
                    mean their attitude was, “It's not mine. It doesn't matter.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “Nothing better comes by working.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: And of course just at the time I was there they were talking about raising
                    prices which they subsequently did on food and housing. Eventually they're going
                    to turn back some of this housing to the original owners, but that's going to be
                    a long process because it has to be proved, and, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Does this worry them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: In cases where people are living in those houses, they'll be evicted. And
                    where will they go? Because they have only those kind of box-type houses —
                    tenements, apartment buildings. And while they recognize the fact that if they
                    had it, they'd want it back, too, it might create some hardships for them. They
                    might have to be moved out to someplace where they don't want to live.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These people who left Czechoslovakia are indeed going
                        back.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: No, but there are many people who are still there whom the property was
                    taken from because everything was nationalized. They don't realize that they're
                    going to have to pay for it in such [increased] prices because very little will
                    be subsidized. They're going to have to pay in order to have a free economy.
                    They're going to have varied prices — that's something that they're not used to.
                    But perhaps there will be more for them to buy, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at least they had a taste of it between the wars, they
                        know. They have had a history of it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: The older people did, but the younger people haven't had, they haven't
                    lived under anything that was democratic. They might have read about it or heard
                    about it. They did have people who would visit the States or West Germany or
                    England and they'd come back with news of those countries. But they know nothing
                    but this constant obedience of the orders of the Commissar. It's going to take
                    some adjusting, mental, mostly mental, and physical, too, to a certain
                    extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do they have pensions? What will happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: They have pensions, but they're very little. Now my friend — he's the
                    pediatric surgeon. He has a very minimal salary now, something like... If I say
                    an exact figure I'd be wrong, but I can just give an approximate of 2000 crowns
                    a month. Now that isn't much. When I was there the exchange rate was 25 to 1.
                    That's going to change too, it's going to be lower. But even so he's been
                    supplementing his income by writing. He writes books, he's written many medical
                    journals and some of them have been translated into German. So people all
                    supplementing somehow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well that shows a spirit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well young people — young married people have all their salaries of course
                    which aren't high. But if they have children, they get a supplement for each
                    child. Now whether that's going to continue is another thing. This is what
                    they're all worrying... Of course, these are things that affect you
                    economically. But it's going to affect them economically if they're going to cut
                    down on that particular subsidy or if they're going to completely eliminate it.
                    I don't know. But of course if they have a free economy, people will work to
                    promote themselves. Right now they didn't care because they knew they couldn't
                    get up to the top.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It didn't make any difference.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>KIDD: No, whether they worked or not. So that's something that they have to
                    adjust their thinking to. Not just to stay in the same rut because you can't get
                    any higher. We can get it if we work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You get paid accordingly and you rise in your
                        profession.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: An honest day's pay for an honest day's work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do they feel about the East German situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well those I spoke to, not everyone, were a little bit apprehensive, let's
                    say, about the re-unification of Germany. Since they'd suffered so much under
                    previous Germans practically all their lives. And whether it's going to be... I
                    tried to reassure them that I didn't think that that would be something that
                    they'd have to worry about, certainly not in the near future. But I know...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They have both Germanies on their borders, they're right
                        there, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Well you see East Germans could come there very easily because the Eastern
                    Block countries could travel within their own countries very easily. You didn't
                    have to worry about visas or anything like that. The East Germans used to come
                    and buy up all the stores and that's what the Czechs didn't like because we go
                    there and it's all gone. They're still there. It's going to take a lot of work
                    and a sort of readjustment of their morality in the sense of working honestly,
                    not just...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mary, again, I keep asking you to repeat this, but tell a
                        little bit about the exhibit that was on [during your visit].</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>KIDD: It was called “Moy Dema” which is translated “My Home.” The street in
                    Prague that turns right to the powder tower, it's called Nebshibgobia. And this
                    street was partially — almost all of it — closed off the traffic. What they had
                    done at this point was to have banners or what did you call them before —
                    bunting depicting the various periods in the history of Czechoslovakia. They had
                    starting with the second World War. And above the street there was this huge
                    camouflage net that depicted the years during the War. Then right after that was
                    more bunting and this was representing the flags of the French, the British, the
                    Russians and the Americans which was the occupation in that short period between
                    '45 and '48. Then you went down along the street and these buntings would be
                    hanging down in flag-type size. Then you had a period in — gosh, I can't
                    remember now how many rows of it — it was just the Russian flag, red, red, red,
                    red, one right after the other, until the present time. And now they're starting
                    a new era with the Czech flag, just the Czech flag and nothing else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And I think the idea was just such a good one. You said
                        there were films...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: Yes. In each section that depicted, say the war years, and then the
                    occupation, the liberation really, by the Russians and so on. They had kiosks
                    that had the newspapers of that period all over these kiosks. You could read
                    what had happened and what was happening at that time. And this went on all the
                    way down the street under the Nazis, and after that when you had the — I would
                    say interim government really. That was under Masaryk and Benes and a few of
                    them and then that stopped. There was one interesting part. They had a series of
                    painted faces but they were cut-outs of various figures in the Communist Party
                    in Czechoslovakia. Kurdvald and Slansky and all the others going on. But one of
                    the funny things — again I don't know whether it was by accident or by intent —
                    one of the heads was knocked off. And I don't know whose head it was at this
                    point. (laughs) It wasn't anyone that I think I knew. That went on until you
                    came to the powder tower and that's when it ended.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What a wonderful idea.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>KIDD: It was very moving. Not only the older people were interested. You saw
                    young people... This was the thing that again... The youth — maybe it's because
                    I'm older now that I was so aware of it. But it was the youth who were
                    interested in this because perhaps they heard about it from their parents, but
                    they weren't even born at parts of it. It was the young people that were really
                    so anxious to know more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well you know back in the years when we were living there,
                        they were trying to brainwash the children and have them spy on their
                        parents and so forth. Yet the one thing that every young Czech wanted was a
                        bit of old American Army equipment. A button or an Army insignia. So you
                        realize that they hadn't ever really [gone] over...</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>KIDD: Well they've been told by their parents many of these things. And of course
                    many of the parents did turn to Communism purely for economic reasons. Others
                    because they really believed it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well that's what I meant about those two friends of
                        yours, too. Well Mary, this has been so interesting and I think this will be
                        a wonderful addition to the tape of your life there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHICAL DATA:</p>
                <p>Spouse: Coburn Kidd</p>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service: 1946Left Service:1969You became affiliated with Service:
                    1949Left Service:1951 (as employee)</p>
                <p>1969 (as spouse)</p>
                <p>Relationship to Foreign Service: Spouse of AEP, FS Offspring, Parent of FSO,
                    FSO</p>
                <p>Posts: 1949-1951Prague, Czechoslovakia 1952Vienna, Austria 1952-1956Washington,
                    DC 1957London, UK 1959-1960Tokyo, Japan 1961-1966Bonn, Germany 1966-1969Hamburg,
                    Germany</p>
                <p>Spouse's position: Political</p>
                <p>Place/date of birth: New York City, NY - October 4, 1920</p>
                <p>Maiden name: Mary Frances Harak</p>
                <p>Parents: John and Lucie Harak</p>
                <p>Date/place of Marriage: September 1, 1952; Lisle, Illinois</p>
                <p>Education:</p>
                <p>Parochial School, NY</p>
                <p>Sacred Heart Academy, Lisle, Illinois</p>
                <p>New York University Night School</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>Profession: Secretary, Translator, and Interpreter in Czech</p>
                <p>Volunteer and Paid Positions held: At Post: Embassy Woman's Club Meals on Wheels
                    - Bonn Volunteer at hospital - Bonn</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
