<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000985">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Stuart W. Rockwell </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR STUART W. ROCKWELL</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 5, 1988</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, what attracted you to the Foreign
                        Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I was at college and in school very much interested in foreign
                    languages. I majored in French and Spanish at Harvard College, and when I
                    graduated from college, it seemed to me that a good place to use foreign
                    languages and to acquire greater skill in them would be the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you been deliberately taking courses that would
                        prepare you for the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. I only took courses that would increase my knowledge of foreign
                    languages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this translate into getting into the Foreign
                        Service when the time came?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I have to confess that when I decided to go into the Foreign Service, I
                    had to go to a so-called “cram school,” as there were certain parts of the
                    Foreign Service examination, such as maritime law and the law in general, and to
                    a lesser extent, economics, that my college education had not covered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: This was in 1941 that I entered the Foreign Service. I took the exams
                    in 1940.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you see the handwriting on the wall, as far as where
                        the world was going at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I don't think I had any very profound thoughts at that time. I just
                    wondered what I was going to do with myself next.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You came into the Foreign Service, I would assume, before
                        Pearl Harbor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of training did you get to prepare you, once you
                        were in the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I had no training at all. I went directly to my first post and had
                    on-the-spot training.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Panama.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Panama.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a vice consul?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Vice consul in the passport and visa section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would a brand-new vice consul do at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Largely passport services for American citizens in the Canal Zone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume, particularly when the war started, there must
                        have been quite a few restrictions, and you must have had to be particularly
                        vigilant as far as who was an American citizen and that sort of thing,
                        weren't you, at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We didn't have to worry too much about that, because the Canal Zone
                    authorities vouched for their own people. We were dealing, obviously, with
                    mainland types, not American citizens of foreign origin. They were all hometown
                    U.S.A. people living in the Canal Zone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then after that assignment, you entered the military
                        service.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: After I did a stint in the consular section, I went into the political
                    section of the embassy. After my tour in Panama, I went into the military.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the political concerns of the United States in
                        Panama that you would deal with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: They were largely directed toward the nature of the Panamanian
                    government and its relations with the Axis powers, particularly under President
                    Arnulfo Arias, who was considered, with good reason, to be pro-Axis.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would we do about it? Were we able to do anything? We
                        were pretty much top dog at that time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We didn't do anything directly about it. Arias made the mistake of
                    leaving the country when he shouldn't have. He was not authorized. While he was
                    away, the National Assembly voted him out of office, in effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get involved in snooping around to find out what
                        the Axis influence was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We were involved in observing the Panamanian political scene. There
                    was, to my recollection, not a great amount of Axis influence in the country
                    itself. But what there was, was largely in the economic field. I mean, there
                    were trans-shipments through Panama to Germany that required close observation
                    on our part.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You moved from Panama, you went into the military, and
                        then you were in Ankara from 1946 to '48. Then you were on the
                        Palestine-Israel-Jordan desk.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We don't want to go over the same ground as elsewhere. Was
                        this fairly well covered in your interview in the Truman Library, do you
                        feel? Relations particularly with Israel at the time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, that was the main thrust of the Truman Library interview.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any thoughts on areas that they might not have
                        covered?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: This was some years ago. I must say I don't recall exactly. They were
                    interested in the background of our relationships with the Zionists, and then
                    with the State of Israel after it was established, as well as the maneuvering
                    within the Congress and within the State Department concerning the establishment
                    of the state of Israel.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this type of assignment come out of the blue, or had
                        you been ready? Because having both Panama and Turkey really didn't prepare
                        one for dealing with the Palestinian problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No, it was quite fortuitous, largely because the Department of State,
                    foreseeing that there would be trouble in Palestine when the Mandate ended in
                    1948, transferred all the married officers out of the Consulate General in
                    Jerusalem and replaced them with single people either from Washington or from
                    neighboring posts. I was detailed from Ankara to Jerusalem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On another project, I spoke to you several years ago about
                        your time in Palestine at this point, but I wonder if you could recount a
                        little. What were you doing? You were caught between two fires there,
                        weren't you, in the Consulate General in Jerusalem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. The Consulate General was located in what became the Israeli
                    sector. We also had access to the Jordanian side and would occasionally go to
                    Aman, also to report on the situation there. Basically, however, we were pinned
                    down during the fighting and were merely doing our best to report what was going
                    on. Of course, the Consul General had an important capacity as a member of the
                    three-man Peace Commission in Jerusalem, and as such, he met with his
                    counterparts in the French and Turkish embassies, and also dealt with the Jewish
                    authorities before the establishment of the state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to develop contacts at that point in both
                        Jordan and Israel that you were able to use later on in your later
                        career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Some of us were, especially the person who was detailed to cover the
                    Jordanian side of things. I did meet again, during the course of my career,
                    people whom I knew in Jerusalem, but I was never assigned again to Israel,
                    although I dealt with Israel in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to move briefly through your career so we can
                        concentrate on your more senior ranks. You were in Madrid from 1952 to '55.
                        What type of work were you doing at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I was chief of the Political Section in Madrid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our attitude at that point towards Franco?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Our attitude was favorably neutral, I would say. In other words, we did
                    not approve of him, but we had no quarrel with him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the chief of the political section, how would you
                        organize your office, as far as how would you assign officers, for
                        example.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We had them divided on Spanish foreign affairs and Spanish domestic
                    affairs and intelligence, dealing with Spain. At that time, Spain had a
                    protectorate in Morocco. Of course, the relations between Spain and the European
                    nations were strained. On the domestic side, there was more or less a stagnant
                    situation, because no meaningful political parties other than the official ones
                    were tolerated. So it was a rather static situation. The major thrust, I think,
                    of the Political Section was to give to Washington an idea of how the ordinary
                    Spaniards were living under the regime, how they felt toward it, and what the
                    regime's relationships with the European countries were. Obviously, Spain's
                    relations with us at that time were somewhat controversial since there were many
                    people in this country, particularly in the Congress, who felt strongly
                    unfavorable to the Franco regime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did that have much of an effect on the operations at the
                        embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The heat was pretty well absorbed in Washington at that
                        time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In moving on, you were in the War College in 1956, and
                        then you became the Director of N.E., which stood for Near East, from 1957
                        to 1960. Since the various bureaus keep changing their areas of
                        jurisdiction, in 1957, what did N.E. cover?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It covered all the Levantine Arab states, Near Eastern Arab states. By
                    that I do not mean Tunisia and Morocco and Algeria, but Egypt, Lebanon, Syria,
                    Iraq, Jordan, the Sudan, and also Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was this set up? You were the director, and then under
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: There was a deputy director. Then we had desk officers in charge of the
                    individual countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You reported to whom at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: To the Assistant Secretary for Near East and South Asian Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was that at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It was Bill Rountree, I guess, at that time. This is '57 to '60.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is '57 to '60, because I know you came back later on
                        and did pretty much the same thing. How did things work for you? You were
                        there at an interesting time, because you were there during the invasion or
                        the landings in Lebanon, and [Gamal Abdel] Nasser was a major player at the
                        time. As the director, how did you operate? What type of work did you
                        yourself do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I suppose most of it was the normal work of an office director, in the
                    sense that there is the daily flow of messages coming in that require an answer
                    or analysis. There are the meetings with other elements in the department on
                    joint positions; there are meetings with other agencies of the government on
                    problems that involve them; there's the constant need to prepare briefing papers
                    for the superior officers in the department, particularly if there's some event
                    coming up like the visit of a foreign statesman or a trip by the Secretary
                    overseas. One has to respond constantly to the Congress and their concern over
                    matters that require attention. Then there are the dealings with the local
                    embassies, the foreign embassies. I think the normal function of an office
                    director.</p>
                <p>In our case, we had a rather unusual situation in that Mr. Dulles was very much
                    interested personally in the Palestine issue, and so we were constantly on call
                    directly from him for meetings, often on weekends at his residence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In what form would his interest take? Did he want to look
                        for a solution, or did he just want to keep informed on what was
                        happening?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Oh, no, he wanted to be directly involved in the solution of problems
                    that occurred, particularly in the direction of policy, because he had very
                    strong ideas. He, as you know, tended to consider that these regional issues
                    were part and parcel of our relationship with the Soviet Union and with the
                    Communist Bloc as a whole. Therefore, what was done in the local context or
                    regional context, in his view, frequently either had repercussions in our
                    relations with the Russians, or were due to maneuvers by the Russians affecting
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From your vantage point, did you see the situation
                        differently, as really a locally generated situation which the Russians were
                        taking advantage of, or did you see it as one where the Soviet Union was
                        stirring things up?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think that we saw it much more as a manifestation of Arab
                    nationalism, particularly insofar as the activities of Nasser were concerned,
                    and in regard to Lebanon, as a result of the factional differences between the
                    confessions in that country, much more in that context than as either a result
                    or a consequence of Russian maneuvering.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have sort of a continuing dialogue with Secretary
                        Dulles to try to have him see this thing within a more local context, rather
                        than a broader one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think one would have to know Secretary Dulles to know that once he
                    got an idea and made up his mind, there was no point having a dialogue. He was
                    determined and he was dedicated and he was convinced, and he directed the policy
                    on the grounds of the primordial importance of relations with the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did he view Nasser?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: As an agent of the Russians, a mischief-maker, an agent of the
                    Russians. And he felt particularly bitter about him because he felt that Nasser
                    had betrayed him in connection with the Aswan Dam, that Nasser had been using us
                    against the Russians as a bargaining chip, and that especially when members of
                    Congress began to put heavy pressure on Secretary Dulles, he decided that Nasser
                    had misused us and that we should not go along any longer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had the Aswan Dam crisis occurred at the time you were on
                        the desk? Did you have any role in this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Not really. That was carried out at a pretty high level, and the World
                    Bank was involved, the British, the French, and the Treasury.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: For the record, I wonder if you could explain what it
                        was.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: The project was to create the Aswan Dam and how to get financing. The
                    Egyptians turned to us and the World Bank and anybody who might be inclined to
                    help them, including the Russians. Of course, it was the Russians who built it
                    in the end, after we had decided not to go along and had withdrawn our offer of
                    help. The Russians built the dam, and the whole thing, in my opinion, turned out
                    very badly from our point of view. It goes to show how important, at least at
                    that time, the individual reactions to the actions and activities of other
                    individuals could be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So we're really talking about a personality antipathy that
                        built up there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was anybody able to say, “But Mr. Secretary, if we turn
                        this down, the only other logical place to go is with the Soviets. If you're
                        anti-Soviet, you're leaving a wide-open hole for them to move into”? Or was
                        this foreseen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That was, of course, one of the points that was made, but the answer to
                    that often was, “Well, we're not sure the Soviets can do it. If they want to do
                    it and spend all that money, so be it. But we are not going to deal with
                    somebody who is as unreliable and as treacherous as Nasser.” Especially when the
                    Congress was up in arms about Nasser's attitude toward Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we feel about Nasser, not only there, but also as
                        a force within the Arab world?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: When Nasser came to power, we made, I think, quite a sincere effort to
                    cultivate him and to turn his energies into a useful direction, as far as we
                    were concerned. We tried to protect our friends against him, like the Jordanians
                    and the Iraqis. And that was the reason that we went along as far as we did on
                    the Aswan Dam project, because we thought it might help to bring Nasser more or
                    less in line with our own goals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In line with Nasser, there were two events at this time
                        that come to mind. One was the overthrow of the Iraqi monarch, which was
                        rather closely followed by our landing in Lebanon. Were you involved in the
                        preparations and the negotiations for the Lebanese landing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you see it at the time, and what were you doing on
                        this particular situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We were dealing, in effect, with the Lebanese, especially Charles Malik
                    and Camille Chamoun, the president and the foreign minister, both of whom were
                    Christians. We were trying to help them defend themselves and their country
                    against what we considered at that time to be the efforts of the Syrians and the
                    Egyptians to undermine the sovereignty of Lebanon on behalf of the Muslim
                    segment of the population. In accordance with the Eisenhower doctrine, we were
                    telling these people that we would help them if there was any organized effort
                    to undermine their sovereignty. So in effect, we gave them a pledge which they
                    held us to. One of the reasons that we agreed to go in there, which had a
                    salutary effect, that we should have gone in, I think, was because Mr. Dulles
                    was convinced that the Russians were goading the Egyptians and the Syrians to
                    undo the sovereignty of Lebanon as a Western ally.</p>
                <p>In retrospect, I think it's quite clear that the Russians were not doing that. It
                    was merely that the forces of Arab nationalism were operating against what many
                    of them considered to be a Christian monopoly of power in Lebanon, and a
                    tendency by the Christian leaders to subordinate Arab interests to those of the
                    Western powers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we find ourselves particularly attracted towards the
                        Christians in Lebanon because of like religion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: There was no doubt about it, in the long history of American
                    involvement on the Christian side, the American University in Beirut, the fact
                    that Malik himself was educated in the United States was a very persuasive
                    interlocutor. I think there was a great deal of sympathy for the Christians in
                    Lebanon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the situation in Iraq, when King Faisal was not
                        overthrown, but killed, at the same time by a military coup, did that have
                        any effect on how we viewed the Middle East?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: There were those who thought that having landed in Lebanon, we should
                    try to do something militarily to undo the coup in Iraq, but they were not
                    listened to. Actually, the Iraqi revolution, we knew nothing about, and we
                    didn't anticipate it. There again, I don't think the Russians had anything to do
                    with it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we see this as a part of a movement of unrest that was
                        going to sweep us out of the area?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. There was great concern that it was the beginning of destruction
                    of Western and American influence in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During this time I was a young vice consul in Dhahran in
                        Saudi Arabia, and we felt very nervous about the situation there, too,
                        because we noticed that thermos jugs had Nasser's picture on them. Nasser's
                        picture was everywhere in the marketplace, and there was a feeling that
                        anything might spark an overthrow of the Saudi monarchy and putting a
                        hostile group in. We felt that Arab nationalism was hostile to the United
                        States.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Were there any voices within the State Department that were saying, “Maybe we
                    shouldn't do this”?</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: There were a number of voices in N.E. which were saying that, but they
                    were obliterated by the overall domination and policy by Foster Dulles, who saw
                    it, as I said, very decidedly in the context of a super power confrontation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So looking at the operations of the State Department at
                        that time in a critical area—and you were down in the engine room of the
                        State Department—our policy was very definitely run by the Secretary of
                        State.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No doubt of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: With no real chance for whatever expertise or what have
                        you to maybe deviate somewhat in one direction or another.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I don't want to give you the impression that the place was full of
                    doubters, because I don't recall that people like Rountree or myself or anybody
                    else really had that much of a conviction that Dulles was wrong. I mean, he was
                    so eloquent and there was no doubt the Russians were stirring things up, it
                    suited them fine. It seemed a good idea that they should be stopped from doing
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking back on it, from a practical measure, the landing
                        in Lebanon did seem to work at the time. It froze things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, but it had nothing to do with the Russians. I mean, it deterred
                    the Egyptians and the Syrians, so it served its purpose, but I'm not sure what
                    would have happened if we hadn't landed, in the sense that I'm not sure that the
                    government there would have been overthrown by hostile forces. But in any event,
                    there was that very strong feeling that if we did not live up to our pledge to
                    Chamoun and Malik, that we would be considered to be a pretty weak influence in
                    the area. So I think, on the whole, it worked out pretty well, but I think we
                    were very lucky. Only one Marine was killed, I think, and that was in an auto
                    accident of some kind.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As compared to our efforts in the last few years, in which
                        we landed Marines and had almost 300 killed, plus the whole place fell
                        apart. As we're speaking now, it's still badly divided, with little prospect
                        that in the future it'll put itself together.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At that time, Europe certainly held our interest, because this was the main front
                    line against the Soviets. Did they tend to dominate the workings of the State
                    Department? From what you say, it looks like Dulles did give quite a bit of
                    attention to your operations.</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Well, no. As a matter of fact, of course, Dulles and Eisenhower worked
                    very strongly against the French and the British in the Suez Canal operation, so
                    I mean, it wasn't as if on that particular issue that the Europeans were able to
                    throw our policy off the tracks. It was considered very unfriendly by them.</p>
                <p>Also, in connection with the Aswan Dam issue, the Europeans went along more or
                    less, except for the Russians, of course, along with our views about that. So I
                    think that European influence had certainly no negative effect, and maybe some
                    positive effects on our policy in the area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about our dealings with Israel? This has always been a
                        very controversial subject, the feeling that the State Department
                        professionals are dominated by Arabists, whatever that means. I mean, in
                        other words, it's almost as though they are a group that are friends of the
                        Arabs and by nature, then, are opposed to the Israelis and to Jews. It must
                        have been a very difficult position to have been Director of N.E. Affairs,
                        with a Congress which is basically much more friendly towards Israel for
                        domestic reasons and maybe just personal feelings towards the area than
                        toward the Arab world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, that's true.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of pressures came on you? Were there
                        pressures?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Indeed there were. There are constant pressures—congressional letters,
                    “Why are you doing this? Why aren't you doing that?” Constant visits by Israeli
                    officials to press their point of view. People within the government who have
                    nothing to do with the State Department, involving themselves in matters such as
                    loans and the like to Israel, whether or not to grant a loan. Every facet of
                    policy making seemed to come into contact with someone who had a very strong
                    feeling about Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And from a practical point of view, the strong feeling was
                        support of Israel rather than opposed to Israel.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As the professional paid to look at the area and see the
                        balance, you see a large number of Arab states who are violently opposed to
                        Israel. Israel is basically a small country without great strategic
                        significance, as far as oil reserves or anything else. Did you find yourself
                        trying to be the voice, to explain that there is something else in the
                        Middle East besides Israel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. Of course, we used to do that. We used to go out on speaking
                    tours, to audiences, to explain what our policy was and why it was the way it
                    is, and what we thought. But after all, Israel is an independent state, it's a
                    friendly state—it was a friendly state. It has strong connections with many
                    American citizens who feel very strongly about it, and there's certainly no
                    place, in my view, in an office like the Office of Near East Affairs, for
                    somebody who's biased against one of the most important states in the area. Then
                    one has to remember, too, that the Arabs are their own worst enemies. They make
                    it very difficult to defend them by the things they did and continue to do.</p>
                <p>So I didn't come to that office with any Arab experience at all. I had no
                    particular predilection for the Arabs or for the Israelis, for that matter. I
                    just felt that one had to deal with both, and they had their point of view. If
                    one is to be effective, one had to understand those points of view, not seem to
                    be espousing one or the other.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have a problem with your various desk officers, to
                        have them see both what our policy was and, at the same time, to present
                        their cases without having them appear biased?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: These people who were desk officers, they were all good officers. They
                    were realistic, they understood the atmosphere with regard to Israel in this
                    country. There were none of them whom I would consider to be rabidly pro-Arab to
                    the point where their judgment was clouded or where their actions were biased.
                    They understood. They would have preferred other policies and other actions
                    because of their interest in the Arab world. They accurately foresaw that if
                    certain things were done, the reaction in the Arab world would be very negative.
                    But at no time did I feel that any of them were undermining our policy or
                    speaking against it in any inappropriate way, because they were realists, they
                    were professionals, and they knew that, in effect, no other policy was likely to
                    be established.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you feel that there was a problem within the bureau,
                        anything that was written that would be considered by an outsider to be
                        unfavorable to Israel, that would immediately end up in the hands of a
                        columnist or in the Israeli Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That was always a possibility. We felt that there were people in the
                    government—not necessarily in the State Department, but possibly also in the
                    State Department—who could not be relied on not to make these documents
                    available. I don't think that that constrained people to any great degree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There wasn't the feeling, then, “I'd better say the right
                        things or I may be tarred with an anti-Israel brush, and I'll never move
                        ahead in my career because of Congress”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. I don't think that people were that intimidated. Obviously, there
                    were those who were considered by the Congress or by Friends of Israel,
                    particularly American Jews who were interested in the problem, who were
                    considered to be less friendly than others to Israel. But I don't believe they
                    ever could make a good case that their recommendations were strongly biased or
                    prejudiced in any unreasonable way. It's just that they obviously tried to
                    produce a balanced perspective, and in so doing, they had to describe what they
                    considered to be the Arab interests as they saw them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any sort of back channel type operation going on
                        at the time? Were people saying, “I can't put this on paper, but let me tell
                        you what I think or what is going on here,” or this type of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I imagine there probably was, but at a very high level. I didn't have
                    any personal knowledge of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to move on to your time from 1960 to '65 in
                        Tehran. You went out there under the Eisenhower Administration. The
                        ambassador at that time was Edward T. Wailes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had he asked for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. I don't believe he had. I think that the person who assigned me out
                    there was Loy Henderson.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In these interviews, I keep running across references to
                        Loy Henderson running into people on the way to the men's room or walking
                        down the corridor or something, and saying, “Where are you going?” They'll
                        say, “I've been assigned to such and such.” He says, “Oh, you don't want to
                        go there.” Apparently, he kept a very close eye on assignments and was
                        always sort of moving out of the system. Did he ask you if you wanted to go
                        or get involved in that assignment at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: As I recall it, he merely told me that that's where he wanted me to go.
                    So it sounded like a good place to go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the situation in Iran? We're talking about the
                        period of 1960 to '65, when you went out there as deputy chief of
                        mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That was the period when the Shah started his so-called White
                    Revolution, when he had achieved victory over the oil companies to the point
                    that Iranian revenue from oil was greatly increasing, and when his ambitions for
                    modernizing his country were at their height, and when his own position within
                    the country as a result of the prosperity that was beginning to be felt
                    throughout, was at the highest. So although there were problems, he didn't
                    really permit any kind of full-fledged free political participation. The secret
                    police were always to be thought about if you did criticize the regime too
                    strongly.</p>
                <p>Nonetheless, it was a good time for most Iranians and certainly for educated
                    ones, because the country was booming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Moving to the operational side, each ambassador uses his
                        DCM in a different way. Was there any difference between the way Wailes and
                        then later, Julius Holmes, who took his place, did they use you in about the
                        same way? They were both career ambassadors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Julius Holmes was much more directly involved than Tom Wailes was, so
                    under Holmes, there was less substantive work for the DCM to do than there was
                    under Wailes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What do you mean when you say “substantive work?”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I mean that Julius Holmes was an interested formulator of policy and
                    somebody who desired to be directly involved in dealing with the Iranians at a
                    high level, whereas Tom Wailes was much less vigorous in that sense, and really
                    preferred to have things brought to him and form his own views and make his
                    comments on the basis of what he was given.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What would Holmes do with you, then, when he was your
                        ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: He would rely on the DCM principally for the administration of the
                    embassy. At that time, we had the other elements there, like the Armish MAAG and
                    the mission to the Gendarmerie and the economic aid mission. There were constant
                    meetings and Country Team meetings and that kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our interest in Iran at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It eventually became strongly political and strongly economic, as well,
                    because Iran became one of our best customers for many, many things. But we had,
                    of course, a long history of involvement with Iran, going back to the time when
                    the Shah came back from exile and to our role in the Azerbaijan crisis, when the
                    Russians wouldn't leave Azerbaijan after the war and tried to set up a regime
                    there. Iran seemed to be an important Middle Eastern country which was not
                    involved in the Palestine crisis, and which seemed to have interests which
                    paralleled ours, particularly as regards the Russians, under the monarchy, of
                    course. Then of course, there was the oil, which was of interest, too. So we had
                    major stakes in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could view this from both the Washington perspective
                        and out in the field. Was there a difference between the approach to the
                        area between the Eisenhower Administration and the Kennedy
                        Administration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, very decidedly. The Kennedy Administration was much more concerned
                    than the Eisenhower one about the political regime and the political situation
                    in Iran, in the sense that the Kennedy Administration thought that American
                    influence should be directed toward influencing the situation in Iran in the
                    direction of a more democratic administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Looking at it now from the perspective of at least 20
                        years-plus later, there have been arguments saying that the effort to bring
                        reform in essentially a very conservative country created resentments which
                        led to the eventual overthrow of the Shah. As far as the embassy was
                        concerned, was anybody saying, “Wait a minute. We better not be doing this.”
                        At least sponsoring democratic reforms?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Quite the contrary. If there was any objection within the embassy, it
                    came from people who felt we weren't doing enough. In effect, we really weren't
                    doing very much, especially when I was there, because nobody had any idea that
                    the Mullahs—in fact, I don't believe that the Mullahs had any influence or were
                    organized at all at that time. But in any event, nobody on the Iranian side and
                    nobody on the American side paid any attention to the Mullahs. Things were going
                    so well for the average Iranian, as long as he could overcome his aversion to
                    working with the regime, that there were no real centers of opposition to the
                    regime. In fact, the regime, during the time that I was there, really took over
                    of its most vocal critics who were lured back to the country from critical exile
                    by the new jobs that were created.</p>
                <p>So if anybody says that we did too much and that had much to do with what
                    eventually happened, I certainly don't agree with that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were we doing, just expressing our hope that things
                        would get better?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Especially under the Kennedys, the ambassador was instructed to talk to
                    the Shah about the need to create a bridge to the middle class and to relax the
                    controls that he was exercising on the political process. We also kept in touch
                    discreetly with the opposition, such as it existed at the time. Later on, after
                    I left, especially under Henry Kissinger, the orders were to stop interfering in
                    the Shah's business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is some bitterness about the fact that we
                        deliberately cut ourselves off from any opposition movement. Traditionally
                        our role is to talk to everybody, at least everybody who is halfway
                        legitimate.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That, of course, is the way it should be. The problem in Iran was that
                    the Shah was paranoid about anybody, especially American diplomats, talking to
                    the opposition. He certainly was able to find out rather quickly whether there
                    had been any such talk, and he left no doubt that he was not pleased, and if
                    this continued, that the people involved would be asked to leave the
                    country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at the time you were there, you could talk?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: You could up to a point, but if you talked to somebody like Ali Amini,
                    for example, who was one of the better of the politicians, from our point of
                    view, but whom the Shah did not like because he was jealous of him and thought
                    that he wasn't loyal, if you talked with him, it soon got back to the Shah, and
                    the Shah let it be known that he didn't wish this to continue, or else there
                    would be a request for departure on a non grata basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were there, was the Shah very much in control of
                        everything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was the Shah, not advisors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right. Nobody counted for anything but the Shah.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Shah was calling the shots. How did you find the
                        embassy staffed? Was it a good operating staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: In any group, some are better than others. We had some outstanding
                    people and we had some mediocre ones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Going back to the time you were there, did you find that
                        the American presence was overwhelming, as happened later on when we were
                        putting so much military equipment in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. It was not overwhelming when I was there, but it became so later, I
                    understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about our military involvement or military aid? Was
                        this a major program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, it was a large-scale program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it at about the level that you felt was correct for
                        the situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: As far as I could see, it was correct. We were constantly involved in
                    trying to curb the Shah's appetite for new equipment, but insofar as the
                    military presence was concerned and the kind of training that was done, it
                    seemed quite appropriate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any splits on how to deal with the Shah
                        regarding his desire for military equipment? Was the American military
                        trying to sell more to him and the State Department side was holding back,
                        or vice versa?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It wasn't the military so much as the civilian manufacturers of various
                    things like airplanes that were causing most of the trouble, because they would
                    whet the Shah's appetite in sending out people and giving him demonstrations and
                    whatnot. I think our military was thoughtful enough to realize that you couldn't
                    overload the circuit. They didn't feel as strongly as the State Department did,
                    though.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is an unclassified interview, but how did you find
                        the CIA there? Was it an effective instrument or was it too much in bed with
                        Savak? That's the secret police.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: The CIA was certainly closely involved with Savak. I didn't feel that
                    they were doing anything in their daily operations that was inappropriate. I
                    never was sure just what they were doing. In the sense that I know they're
                    supposed to tell the embassy everything, you never know for sure that they are.
                    Certainly when Yatsevitch was head of the CIA there, he had a relationship with
                    the Shah and the royal family that was extremely close, and I felt
                    inappropriately so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this translate as far as you were concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It translated into sort of back-channel messages and meetings with the
                    Shah without the presence of the ambassador, which I didn't think was right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the ambassador feel about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Wailes didn't seem to mind. Holmes did mind and put a stop to it as far
                    as we knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the information that was shared with you from
                        the CIA? Did you find CIA was giving you a different perspective than, say,
                        the political section? Or were they duplicating?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No, they seemed to be pretty much in tune as far as local developments
                    are concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you say, at the time, the local scene was not
                        unfavorable to what we wanted.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Then we move from 1965. You came back to Washington and you served in NEA as the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary in NEA, which stands for Near Eastern and South Asian
                    Affairs. What were your responsibilities?</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Greece, Turkey, Cyprus, and Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you moved away from the Palestinian side of
                        things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Greece and Turkey later were moved into European affairs.
                        How was the situation at the time? This is under the Johnson Administration
                        for part of this period, and then into the early Nixon period, too. What was
                        our interest in Greece, Turkey, and Cyprus at that time, '65 to '70?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Greece and Turkey were NATO members. We all know the strategic position
                    of Turkey and the Straits, the Greek connection with air bases. Also, the
                    Greek-American community is an influential one here. Turkey has one of the
                    largest, if not the largest, number of people under arms in NATO. Turkey had
                    taken part very honorably in the Korean War. I think that our interests were the
                    traditional ones in that strategic part of the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If I recall now, this is the time of the Cyprus problem.
                        Was that at a particular boil during this time? It goes up and down from
                        time to time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I'm sort of unclear about the exact timing. Of course, when I was there
                    in that position, the Greek Government tried to overthrow Makarios and to bring
                    about enosis between Cyprus and Greece.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Enosis is the word for “union.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. So that was a big crisis, and that resulted in the Turkish
                    invasion of Cyprus. So that was a boiling point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Turkish invasion came in '74, didn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I don't remember the exact date.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cyprus is always a problem. Did you have much of a
                        lobbying effort on the part, say, of the Greek-American lobby?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, there were a great many people who were opposed to the Greek
                    colonels, and there were people like Tom Pappas, who were very favorable to the
                    Greek colonels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tom Pappas was a Greek-American citizen who was head of
                        Esso Petroleum, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, he was a businessman and he was, as I recall it, very much in
                    favor of the colonels.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Also, he was very influential in Republican politics. I
                        know because as an aftermath of the Watergate business, I had to serve a
                        subpoena on him because he was on the Republican Finance Committee and was
                        part of the investigation. I had to subpoena him when he was in Athens, when
                        I was consul general there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>What was the attitude of the Johnson and then the Nixon Administration toward
                    Greece and Turkey, sort of a plague on both your houses? Did they try to leave
                    it to the professionals, or did they get very much involved?</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think they left it more to the professionals. There was a general
                    feeling that the Greeks and the Turks were constantly asking for too much money,
                    and that we should give them what was needed in order to achieve our interests
                    there, but that we'd been helping there for many, many years and that it was
                    time to taper off. I think there was not a tremendous amount of interest,
                    especially in Turkey, more in Greece than in Turkey.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And in Greece it was really more because it was an
                        unpopular regime.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. However, the Nixon Administration, especially under Henry
                    Kissinger, didn't feel very uncomfortable with the Greek regime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just for the record, there was an overthrow of a
                        democratic government in 1967 in Greece led by Colonel Papadopoulos, and
                        that regime lasted until 1974.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The National Security Council was run by Henry Kissinger during part of that time
                    when you were there, from '69 to '70. Did you feel the National Security Council
                    was very interested in the area, or was Vietnam absorbing most of their
                    efforts?</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: What period are you talking about?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in from 1965 to '70. You were the deputy
                        assistant secretary for NEA. Nixon came in in 1969. So you would have had
                        1969 and part of 1970 before you went to Rabat.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. I don't recall that the NSC got very much involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That really answers the question. There were other things
                        to do done.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We used to have to go over there and explain what we wanted to do.
                    Henry Kissinger would sit there and listen, but he didn't intervene. He didn't
                    seem to be particularly concerned about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was only, I think, that he got rather involved later in
                        the '75-'76 period.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You were appointed as ambassador to Rabat, Morocco, from 1970 and you served
                    there until 1974. How did that assignment come about?</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I believe it came about because somebody else was appointed that didn't
                    get through the Senate. So I was the State Department's candidate. The one who
                    was appointed was a political appointee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: He eventually got another post, but he didn't get this one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this because there was a feeling that Morocco was too
                        sensitive to turnover to a political appointee or was it just
                        personalities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I don't really know the answer, but my belief is that Senator Fulbright
                    considered that this man was not the appropriate person to send to Morocco,
                    possibly because I think he was of Jewish background. I'm not sure of that, but
                    anyway, I was the Department's candidate. When he failed the confirmation, I was
                    then put forward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before going out there, you already, of course, were
                        dealing with Near Eastern affairs. But did you have any instructions or any
                        stated objectives from the State Department when you went out to Morocco, or
                        was it just, “Go out there and do a good job”?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's more or less it. Our relations with Morocco were tranquil.
                    Obviously it was far removed from the Middle East, and it was just to keep
                    things ship-shape. There were no specific instructions except the usual ones of
                    promoting American business interests. We had a Voice of America relay station,
                    we had a naval communications unit. We were supposed to maintain those.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went out there in 1970. How did you see the situation
                        in Morocco at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It was another of these one-man countries like Iran, and there was
                    unrest because of that. There was a feeling, especially among the younger
                    people, that there should be greater democratic participation. But the main
                    problem turned out to be the corruption that was endemic there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The one-man rule, this was King Hassan. He had been King
                        for how long by that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: He succeeded his father in February of 1961. The country became
                    independent in '56. His father died. I guess he was on the throne certainly 9
                    years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the corruption could be laid at least to the fact that
                        the King didn't do something about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. In fact, members of his own family were involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we see corruption as being a problem, as far as the
                        United States was concerned?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was just something we reported on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It was something that we were concerned about, because it affected the
                    stability of the regime. In some cases it was American companies who were having
                    the bite put on them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that the United States, as a government, our
                        interest was in tranquil relations, our relay station, and our naval base
                        there. But what were our commercial interests there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Quite limited. Morocco was not a good market for U.S. products. It was
                    pretty much tied up with France. Except for a limited amount of tourist type
                    stuff like a hotel, U.S. commercial relations were really not terribly
                    important. Phosphates, perhaps. But we were a competitor in phosphates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you didn't find that there was a dominant American
                        commercial interest that guided you, or that you had to be watching this all
                        the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. The Moroccans didn't make it easy for Americans to engage in
                    commercial activities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find much of your time spent trying to help
                        American commercial firms do business there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, that was one of the roles of the embassy, and particularly
                    commercial firms that got into trouble because of the ambivalent attitude of the
                    Moroccans toward contracts. We had to help them try to resolve some of these
                    disputes they were having. Goodyear, for example.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you say “ambivalent attitude,” a contract was only
                        good as long as it served the purpose?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right. What was good one year wasn't necessarily good the next
                    year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In doing these interviews and my experience also as a
                        reporting officer, one of the hardest things to do is to report on
                        corruption, not because it's not there, but one always is a bit concerned
                        that if you over-report on corruption, this will begin to either be leaked
                        to the United States press, and then the next thing you know, you're going
                        to have to answer to a leak in the other country, or else that you may so
                        disgust the policy makers if you talk about corruption, that they may make
                        some decisions which are not really based on American interests, but ones of
                        abhorrence of corruption. Did you find this was a problem, how to report on
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. I think we reported regularly on the corruption factor, but since
                    the American commercial interest in Morocco was so limited, it wasn't a dominant
                    characteristic of our reporting or of our daily life in Morocco. It was just a
                    fact of life that if a foreign firm wanted to get something in the way of a
                    contract or permission to build something, they had to grease the way. Of
                    course, it's not only in Morocco that that happens; it's well known throughout
                    the Middle East and Far East, for that matter.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>It seems, as it turned out, that people who were really more concerned than
                    anybody were some of the Moroccans themselves, who felt that their country's
                    good name was being besmirched, and that the King was not doing enough about
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems meeting with what would amount
                        to the opposition in Morocco? You didn't feel the same constraints that you
                        felt when you were in Iran?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. The opposition was also not so well organized or as meaningful as
                    it was in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How would you describe, from your perspective, the role of
                        King Hassan?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It's a one-man rule, certainly, and I think that King Hassan turned out
                    to be extremely clever, a good maneuverer, a good survivor, in a sense, a
                    courageous person. I think it has to be said also that at least the time I was
                    there, most of the Moroccans were apolitical. They expected to have a monarch,
                    and all they really wanted was that the monarch do a good job. They didn't
                    conceive of Morocco without a King, except possibly for some of the younger
                    elements, the student people. So I would think that Hassan has been a pretty
                    good King for that country, a pretty good ruler. I don't happen to think that
                    his standards are the same as the normal Anglo-Saxon ones, but why should they
                    be? He's not an Anglo-Saxon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the United States play any role in giving help or
                        advice, or was whatever there was of this nature really French? Would you
                        say that France was the dominant foreign power, if there was such a thing as
                        a dominant power?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: The U.S. gave quite a lot of advice because we got involved with
                    military assistance and economic assistance in Morocco, and also relations with
                    the French were quite strained because of the expropriation of the French
                    colonial interests there and the seizure of the land that the French were
                    farming. So I would say that the French rather withdrew from direct
                    participation. They had their cooperants, their young men and women who went out
                    there to teach and that kind of thing, but that was principally in the interest
                    of maintaining the language. So insofar as meaningful programs were concerned in
                    the country, the French were not in a terribly important position when I was
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We were looked upon as being the main source to turn to
                        for certain types of assistance.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, I guess so, but the Moroccans always complained that we didn't
                    give them enough. Of course, it was a modest program compared to what we were
                    doing in Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any repercussions there of the Vietnam War or
                        opening to China or any of those things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: It seems to me the Moroccans sent some sort of a contingent to Vietnam,
                    medical people or something. Yes, they made a contribution. For a while, we
                    thought the Moroccans were going to vote with us on the two-China question. They
                    almost did, and then they backed down at the last moment. Having told us they
                    would vote yes, they voted to abstain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at a very famous birthday party.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is on July 14, 1971. I wonder if you could tell what
                        happened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: This was the King's annual celebration of his birthday, which took
                    place at his summer palace south of Rabat, between Rabat and Casablanca, at
                    Skhirat. It usually involved all the notables of the realm and all the chiefs of
                    foreign diplomatic missions. It was a stag party, and everybody was very
                    informally dressed in sports clothes, and there were opportunities for golf and
                    tennis and swimming and clay pigeon shooting, but mainly for a huge banquet at
                    mid-day in this summer palace. It was a very sportive affair, supposed to be,
                    until just as we were about to go in to sit down to lunch, we heard these sort
                    of popping sounds, and somebody said, “Oh, the King has arranged fireworks for
                    us this year.”</p>
                <p>And until people started to fall with blood pouring out of them, we realized that
                    the palace was being attacked, and the King's entourage, especially the military
                    members, rushed out to defend it and were cut down. The rest of us were trapped
                    inside or out on the golf course or wherever we might be. There must have been a
                    thousand guests there, at least.</p>
                <p>Eventually, the guard was overcome and the attackers forced us all out of the
                    palace and required us to lie down in front while they searched for the King,
                    who had hidden in the men's room of the palace, which they didn't know about,
                    with some of his key people. They never found him until the very end, but at
                    that time, the command of the rebels had figured out that the King had fled to
                    Rabat somehow, so they had gone to Rabat to try to catch him.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>When the subordinates finally uncovered him and realized that contrary to what
                    they had been told, that the King, instead of being endangered by devious
                    foreign types and disloyal Moroccans, was being endangered by themselves, they
                    reversed their attitude and declared their loyalty to him. The King dispatched
                    General Oufkir to Rabat to get control of the city, which was being attacked by
                    the rebel group. In fact, the Ministry of Information had been seized and the
                    radio was under rebel control. So the ringleaders were court-martialed instantly
                    and shot.</p>
                <p>It turned out to be an offshoot of this problem I mentioned earlier, that the
                    head of the military household of the King was a very personable officer who was
                    personally affronted by the degree of corruption and felt the King was not doing
                    enough about it, and felt that the King should make way for the Crown Prince. He
                    got the cooperation of Colonel Ababou, who was the head of the cadet academy at
                    Fez, and owing to the position of the head of the military household, it was
                    possible to infiltrate during the night 1,000 or 1,200 of these young men,
                    cadets, into the surroundings of the palace. They were the ones that attacked
                    the palace, who had been told apparently that the King was in danger, and that
                    it was their patriotic duty to liberate him.</p>
                <p>But obviously, what happened, apparently, was that Colonel Ababou decided that
                    this was a good opportunity to get rid of the King and establish a sort of
                    Libyan-style republic. The fact of the matter is that Colonel Ababou asked the
                    head of the military household where the King was, and the man knew where he
                    was, because I saw him lead the King into his hiding place, and he didn't let
                    on. So Colonel Ababou had him executed right then, right on the spot, as being a
                    traitor to the cause. So there were two people with different motives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What happened to you and the other diplomats?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We were lying on our faces outside the palace until the King was
                    uncovered by the cadets who were left in charge, and as soon as they laid down
                    their arms, everything returned to normal. It was very strange. I mean, there we
                    were with all our limousines parked down in the parking lot. Although the
                    Belgian ambassador had been shot dead and the Syrian was wounded, we all went
                    back to Rabat, and the countryside seemed perfectly normal. People were selling
                    fish by the roadside, there were swimmers at the beaches. It was hard to believe
                    that this bloody event, which must have cost the lives of about 130 people, had
                    occurred only two hours or so ago.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Makes one realize that diplomacy and getting close to
                        someone in power is not always the best place to be.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any role that the United States played in
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No, it had nothing to do with the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There was another attack on the King. This was on August
                        16, 1972, when he was coming back from Paris, when he was attacked by his
                        own air force which was escorting him. These planes, were they American
                        planes?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: They were American planes piloted by English-speaking Moroccans who had
                    been trained in the United States. They were based at Kenitra, which was where
                    the U.S. naval communications unit was. So all this was very suspicion-making.
                    But the fact remains that our people at that base had no idea what the Moroccan
                    pilots were up to. The hangar and the environs of where the planes were were
                    declared off limits to them. They didn't speak Arabic or French. So we didn't
                    have any idea that these pilots were plotting to do the King in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the King wonder about our role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Oh, instantly everybody said the U.S. must have known about it, and if
                    we didn't tell the King, that was therefore very unfriendly. Yes, I'm sure he
                    did, although it doesn't make much sense for us to try to kill the King of
                    Morocco. That type of a situation is ripe for that kind of interpretation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find yourself making special representation to the
                        King, to let him know?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he seem to accept this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: He seemed to accept it, but I don't think he did. I think that it was a
                    shadow over the rest of my career in Morocco.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's always the feeling that somehow, if anything
                        happens, I know this was true when I was in Greece and many other countries,
                        they always think, “Aha! The United States is behind this.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the more you protest, the less likely you are to be
                        believed.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right. But you had to admit that the circumstances are very
                    suspicious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you when this happened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I wasn't even in the country. I was on home leave, as I recall it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again I ask my unclassified question. How did you find the
                        work of the CIA in Morocco? Was it giving you good information? Did it seem
                        to be inobtrusive?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, it was all right. They seemed to be spending most of their time
                    dealing with out-of-country matters, like who the Algerians were sending in or
                    whether the Russians had any agents. There again, the situation in Morocco
                    itself was not one that was so dynamic that a lot of information was needed or
                    available.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It really wasn't a place where spies hung out and
                        exchanged information and that type of thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not being a front line state with Israel, our concerns
                        there must have been minor.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Of course, they had the usual good relations with the Moroccan security
                    service, and they sometimes produced some rather interesting information about
                    who the King was going to throw out of office or promote or do something like
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The CIA reporting, as far as you knew, did you share the
                        information they had of what went on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, I'm speaking to you now as a former
                        consular officer. You must have found yourself much more involved with
                        Americans who got into trouble because of the hashish and all, didn't you,
                        in Morocco? Wasn't there a real protection problem there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Well, no, because it was perfectly easy to get hashish in Morocco, and
                    the Moroccans were very relaxed about people who bought it. The problem usually
                    resulted from people who left Morocco and got picked up in Spain for carrying
                    this stuff. But we didn't have very many cases of people who were picked up in
                    Morocco. There were two or three that I can remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Morocco seems to have been on the tourist circuit,
                        particularly the young students.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Including, I think, at the time, my daughter went through
                        there. So you must have had a great flow in and out of young people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes, there were a number of them, but they didn't seem to get into an
                    extraordinary number of problems with the local authorities. They were
                    tolerated. They went to Marrakech and Tangier, sat around smoking pot, I
                    suppose. It was not a major problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We have a consulate in Tangier, one of our oldest. That
                        came under you. Did you find that a very useful post?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was more there than for historical purposes, did you
                        think?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. Tangier is a backwater, as far as Morocco is concerned. It used to
                    be important when it was an international zone, but nothing much happened up
                    there. Well, nothing much happened anywhere except Rabat, really. The commercial
                    capital is Casablanca.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do we have a post in Casablanca?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: A Consul General.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this a useful post for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Well, yes, insofar as there were American business interests that were
                    concentrated in Casablanca.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You then became Deputy Chief of Protocol from 1974 to
                        1978. How did you view this appointment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I viewed it with some misgivings, because I felt it was not a
                    substantive job and that I would have preferred to have another mission, but it
                    turned out to be a very interesting job, and certainly one had some fascinating
                    experiences. It was not a substantive job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why did you get this particular job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think the reason was that there had been a succession of political
                    appointees as Chief of Protocol, and I think the personnel people felt that it
                    would be useful to have a career deputy in that job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You served under two Chiefs of Protocol, Henry Catto and
                        Shirley Temple Black.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: And then Evan Dobelle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At least two of those, although political appointees,
                        Henry Catto came from El Salvador, and Shirley Temple Black came from Ghana.
                        At least they had at one point been ambassadors to those countries, so they
                        weren't complete novices in the field of diplomacy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: That's true. They weren't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your job involve?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Actually, it involved doing anything the Chiefs of Protocol didn't want
                    to do or didn't have time to do, assigned me to do, and that was usually to
                    share the burden of these foreign visits and all the things that went with it,
                    preparing the briefing papers, arranging the entertaining and the travel,
                    accompanying them to the White House. Also, we were involved, of course, in the
                    President's travel overseas.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there during a very interesting period. For one
                        thing, on travel, you were there during the end of the Nixon era, where at
                        the very end he was taking trips, in a way, it seemed to be to stay out of
                        the country more than anything else. Did you get involved in those
                        trips?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No. The Nixon White House excluded the protocol office from those
                    trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any particular reason for doing this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think it was just the zealousness of the advance people in the White
                    House at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you get along with the White House normally?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: On the whole, pretty well. I mean, certainly at the working level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you give me any examples of things you might have
                        gotten involved in of interest?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Of general interest, we were heavily involved in the Bicentennial
                    celebration, and particularly in the Tall Ships sail past in New York Harbor,
                    and all the chiefs of mission were invited aboard the aircraft carrier. I've
                    forgotten what the name of it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: USS Enterprise?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We had to shepherd them up there and get them aboard the carrier, get
                    them off and get them back to Washington, make sure that they were comfortably
                    treated.</p>
                <p>Various of the State dinners, particularly if there was an important visitor,
                    were of interest, such as when the Shah came, all the stops were pulled out. Or
                    the President of France.</p>
                <p>That kind of thing was more the highlights, but the daily routine in the office
                    dealt with the care and feeding of the diplomatic corps here, the foreign
                    diplomatic corps, the question of gifts to U.S. officials by foreign
                    representatives, the problem of entertaining people, the management of Blair
                    House, for example, the guest house. That kind of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it's a major administrative job. Let's take the two.
                        What was Henry Catto's method of operation?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: He's basically a very relaxed person.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A good Texan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. He had good relationships with the White House. Actually, all
                    those people that had that job seemed to me to be quite skillful. Shirley Black
                    was certainly a capable Chief of Protocol.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She has made somewhat of a contribution to protocol in
                        that she sometimes returns and gives briefings on protocol problems. She
                        took quite an interest in it. Coming from the film background, did this add
                        anything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Sure. People were interested in her, you know, Shirley Temple. She was
                    one of the things to see if you were a foreigner and you were invited to
                    Washington. You certainly wanted to meet Shirley Temple. But she was much more
                    than that. She was a competent person and she took a serious interest.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say, looking at old films, you look at that small
                        child, and you're really talking about somebody who is very bright. Right at
                        the beginning, she must have had a very high IQ in order to do that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No doubt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the competence, I guess, has continued. Were there any
                        great problems that you had to deal with when you were working in
                        protocol?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I don't think so, no. There were numerous administrative difficulties
                    and transportation problems, airplanes that didn't arrive and caterers who
                    didn't work the way they were supposed to, and people who refused to go where
                    they were supposed to go, such as during the signing of the Panama Accords. We
                    were responsible for seating all the foreign ministers and the heads of state.
                    The foreign ministers were supposed to be in a separate section from the heads
                    of state, and some of them refused to leave their head of state. One had to
                    practically push them out because there were just that many seats for heads of
                    state. That kind of thing, but it's not a great problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any problems, say, with a chief of state who
                        just left in a huff?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: No, not during the time I was there. One of our problems always was the
                    King of Morocco, who would cancel at the last moment when he was invited on a
                    state visit. He wouldn't leave once he got here, but it was very hard to get him
                    to arrive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did people sort of point to you and expect you to
                        straighten it out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Fortunately not, because he'd done this before. He did it while I was
                    there. He backed out at the last minute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just a character trait or was it for security
                        reasons?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: One never really knows the reasons. Obviously he thought it was not in
                    his interest to be seen with the Americans at this particular time, probably
                    because of something that was happening with the Palestine problem. Also,
                    there's always been the talk that his mother is very superstitious. She would
                    decide the stars weren't right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sounds familiar. We're both laughing because there have
                        been stories in the last few months that Nancy Reagan, the President's wife,
                        has her own astrologer to decide what things would be done because of the
                        stars. This is not something only for Moroccan protocol.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One of the things that's been done fairly recently in the field of protocol, of
                    policing diplomats, is to insist on rather strict reciprocal rights, mainly
                    because the feeling is that we've always been rather laissez faire about
                    diplomats in the United States, but our own diplomats are often put under rather
                    strict restraints in other countries. Were there any efforts made to try to
                    correct this while you were in protocol?</p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: We had in place the regulations for the Soviet diplomats, and nothing
                    much happened about that when I was there. They continued to be restricted, as
                    our people were in Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In these interviews, I've talked to several Chiefs of
                        Protocol, Henry Catto, Marion Smoak, and Alberado Valdez, asking them about
                        the role of the Chief of Protocol. Several of them have mentioned that they
                        felt the Chief of Protocol often was underused, you might say, from a
                        political or policy point of view, in that they do, because of the job, stay
                        with the visiting chiefs of state for a long time and are in a position to
                        both report on but also maybe to have a certain amount of contact with
                        chiefs of state that often an ambassador to that country never would have,
                        just because of propinquity in traveling, but that there's no effort made on
                        the part of the desk or the political section to say, “Look, if you're there
                        and you have a chance, here's what our policy is. Do whatever you can to
                        support it.” Do you feel that this is a missed opportunity?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Henry Catto felt very strongly about that, and he and I used to prepare
                    memoranda of our conversations with these people. I mean, after all, the Chief
                    of Protocol receives the briefing book. He knows what the policy is. It's up to
                    him. I don't see that the desk has to nudge him. If he's any good, he ought to
                    be able to keep his antennae alert and pick up whatever he can. It isn't as if
                    the circumstances are all that fortuitous. I mean, usually you're going from one
                    place to another in a limousine; you're not just sitting around drinking with
                    this person for hours on end. The opportunity isn't all that great. Also, a lot
                    of these people don't want to talk to somebody who is not on the substantive
                    side. They're not about to get involved in a delicate conversation with somebody
                    who they consider not to be really important enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We usually close these interviews by asking several
                        questions. Looking back on your career, what would you say was one of your
                        greatest satisfactions or accomplishments?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I consider that probably the greatest satisfaction I've had, it sounds
                    a little overweening, perhaps, is to represent my country in a favorable way to
                    foreigners, and to counteract in some way the impression that some people have
                    that Americans are not necessarily very expert in dealing with foreign affairs
                    and foreigners. I have felt that I was good at the representational side of
                    things. I've felt also that in connection with the Middle East, that I was able
                    to provide a balanced view and a balanced influence in an emotional issue at a
                    delicate time.</p>
                <p>Apart from that, I took great satisfaction in the Foreign Service as a career, as
                    a way of life. I found it extremely interesting and broadening. I think I had
                    good luck at both the people I served under and in the posts I had, even though
                    I almost lost my life on two occasions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Other than the King's birthday, what was the other
                        occasion?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: In Jerusalem.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there when the Consul General was shot.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in the alley with him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Yes. So I guess my feeling of satisfaction is a general one rather than
                    a specific one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about frustrations? Do you have any particular thing
                        that you wish had been done differently or you would have done something
                        differently, or you were involved in something that could have been done
                        differently?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think one of the frustrations of this kind of a career, especially in
                    the State Department, is the problem of dealing with a bureaucracy within the
                    Department and with other agencies. I found that one of the most frustrating
                    parts of being assigned to Washington, that it was so hard to get anything done
                    quickly unless one could get the Secretary to order it to be done
                    immediately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you're looking at this particular problem, you served
                        under the Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, Ford, and Carter
                        Administrations. Did any of these administrations have a little better
                        control over the bureaucracy, or the bureaucracy goes on, no matter who's at
                        the helm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: Well, the bureaucracy goes on, obviously, no matter who's the
                    President. It has to. Departments have to be run. I felt that the Republican
                    administration under Eisenhower and Dulles had more control of the bureaucracy.
                    I also felt, obviously, that Henry Kissinger had a major control of the
                    bureaucracy, and he was able to get things done merely because of the force of
                    his personality and the fact that he occupied two positions. He was at NSC, and
                    then he came over to the Department. I felt that the Johnson Administration had
                    no control to speak of, it was not notable for control of the bureaucracy.</p>
                <p>I remember going way back to Franklin Roosevelt, when there hardly was any
                    bureaucracy. Things were much simpler in those days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Speaking of those days as opposed to now, you had, as you
                        said, a very satisfying career in the Foreign Service. But from what you can
                        gather, how do you view the Foreign Service today? If someone were to ask
                        about recommendation to join the Foreign Service, to go into it, how do you
                        view that as a career today?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>ROCKWELL: I think one has to have a basic interest in foreign affairs, obviously,
                    and if that is the case, I think the Foreign Service is still a desirable
                    career, as long as you're not going to feel that you've failed in it if you
                    don't become an ambassador. I think the Service is having a difficult time in
                    its administration, and particular forces are combining to alter the way things
                    are done, the way promotions are made and all that. But when you come right down
                    to it, the essence of the Foreign Service is foreign service, and that still is
                    going on and is still an interesting thing to do, at least for part of one's
                    working life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mr. Ambassador, I've enjoyed this very much and I want to
                        thank you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ROCKWELL: You're welcome. I've enjoyed it also.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
