<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001411">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Ruth A. McLendon</title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs History
                    Project</p>
                <p>RUTH A. MCLENDON</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial Interview date: December 18, 1995</p>
                <p>Copyright 2006 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What's the date today?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The 18th.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Today is the 18th of December, 1995. This is an
                        interview with Ruth McClendon. That's M-C-L-E-N-D-O-N and its being done on
                        behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and I'm Charles Stuart
                        Kennedy. Well, sort of to start at the beginning, could you tell us when and
                        where were you born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was born in 1929 in Fort Worth, Texas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you tell me about your family and early childhood
                        please?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: My family, my parents on both sides were born on farms in Texas. My
                    grandparents on my father's side were pioneers in a way. They had homestead land
                    in west Texas and settled in Rockwall County, Stonewall County. I've forgotten
                    the name of the other county. My mother's family were from Comanche County. My
                    parents met in Fort Worth and lived there the rest of their lives. My brother
                    and I were born there and grew up in a very middle to lower middle class
                    neighborhood that had once been a small town clustered around a small Methodist
                    college. It was almost like growing up in a small town.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes and this of course was the period of the Depression
                        for part of this.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>McLENDON: It was primarily Depression years and money was tight. Our pleasures
                    were if you tried to think of your most typical small town childhood. You
                    virtually knew everyone as you grew up and the teachers, most of them, had known
                    my mother when she was still a teacher and if you didn't know people through
                    school and neighborhood you knew them in church. It was a very simple secure
                    existence. We spent all of our vacations visiting our grandparents and other
                    relatives on farms and had marvelous times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I'm sure. Where did you go to high school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I went to the public schools right in my neighborhood never more than
                    five blocks away from my school, three blocks from the high school. I went
                    through on an accelerated program because the school system changed, when I was
                    midway through and split my class and booted half of us up and kept half of them
                    back. So, I ended up graduating at 15.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good heavens.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: And went straight into college at TCU because my brother had started
                    there and this was 1945 and he thought he was going to be drafted and wanted to
                    have at least one semester together before he left. I joined him at TCU and
                    stayed on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were at TCU. That's Texas Christian?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Texas Christian University. It's a very small school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very small school in those days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: 1,500 students.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh boy. You were there from '45 to '50?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: '49.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '49. What were you taking?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I changed majors five times. I ended up with a major in political
                    science and English literature and modern history.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What moved you toward the liberal arts field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I had always been fascinated by literature and history and I still am
                    and also philosophy. I wish now that I had been curious, more curious about the
                    sciences and acquired a better education there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what about foreign affairs? I mean this is, the
                        United States was entering out into the world at that time. I'm a
                        contemporary of yours, I was born in 1928.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was a new thing for us then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By reading the newspapers we got a wonderful geographic
                        feel for the world because the war was being waged while we were kids and
                        well reported and then at this time the United States was emerging as the
                        major power in the world and how was this affecting your time as a
                        student?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was wrapped up in the war primarily when I was in high school because
                    just before I graduated, just as I graduated from TCU the war in Europe ended
                    and the handwriting was on the wall, but that, the war was like a dark cloud for
                    me. This feeling of dread that never escaped you. Who next might be killed and
                    how many and when will it ever end. So, it was I guess the most tremendous
                    relief I've ever known and it was finally over. But it did leave my generation,
                    our generation with a determination that it never happen again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did this, you're saying TCU, it's a Christian
                        university, a small one and in the middle of Texas. One would think
                        everything would be very insular, but the United States was all of a sudden
                        taking an expanded role in the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, TCU at that time was insular. Some of my professors were not. The
                    career counselors such as they were in those days had only two careers to
                    suggest for women, teaching and secretarial; clerical and I was determined to
                    avoid either. I went into political science. I preferred English Lit, but I saw
                    only teaching at the end of that, so I went into political science hoping that I
                    would become a lawyer. That held until the spring of my senior year. I'd already
                    been accepted at Vanderbilt Law School. I'd been turned down by Harvard with a
                    one-line reply to my letter of application. Harvard Law School does not admit
                    women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that nice?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>McLENDON: They did the following year. They started the following year. That
                    spring the head of the political science department, Dr. Spain, called me in.
                    He'd received notice of a special scholarship for women at the Fletcher School
                    of Law and Diplomacy and he very much wanted me to apply for it. The deadline
                    had passed, but he insisted that I go ahead and apply. Then I read a little bit
                    more about the school. I was fascinated and had nothing to lose so I applied.
                    Fletcher being a small and informal school accepted me and offered me a tuition
                    scholarship. Once I went to Fletcher I was pointed very much in the direction of
                    the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Absolutely. Well, describe Fletcher. You were there from
                        when, from '49 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: From 1949 to June of '51.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe Fletcher and what you got out of it at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: That's hard to describe because I got so much out of it. Fletcher was
                    in those days a small school. The number of new students that they accepted for
                    the master's program each year was limited to 50. The students who continued on
                    for a second period or a third or as some did five or six working on Ph.D.'s
                    brought the total number up to 100, but that's still quite low.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Of those Fletcher reserved about 10% of its places for women which was
                    unusual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It really was, yes. Had this been going on for some
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The Fletcher School was founded in '33.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But I mean reserving its part for women? Had this been a
                        policy for some time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, I think so. I think so. I know there were Fletcher women dating
                    back to the earlier years. But it's an international school. A fairly high
                    percentage of its students come from other countries and several countries use
                    Fletcher as one of the training schools for their Foreign Service. Thailand for
                    example, Pakistan. I'm not sure of others. In the year of '49 when I went there
                    Pakistan sent its first, the best of its first Foreign Service class to
                    Fletcher. At the last minute we received seven Pakistani Foreign Service
                    Officers as part of our class. For me it was a beautiful exposure. Coming from a
                    provincial school to a very provincial state and a very how would I say,
                    unsophisticated background, it was a whole new world out there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I'm sure it was. What was your impression of the
                        Pakistanis? I mean Pakistan had just become a state. British India had been
                        partitioned.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We were concerned because the Kashmir dispute had already arisen of
                    course and it had that bloody time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, a bloody separation. It was just awful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We had a couple of Indian students already at Fletcher and we were
                    concerned that they might be on unpleasant terms. In fact, the Indian student I
                    knew best rather adopted them and took them under his wing and helped them
                    adjust to our culture and they were good friends. The Pakistanis were like
                    anyone, some you liked and some you weren't so fond of. We tended to resent them
                    because most of us were on tight money and they had their salaries plus generous
                    allowances.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes that made a tremendous difference in those
                        days.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We pretended to resent their style of living, but that was beside the
                    point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any feel towards what America's role, I mean was
                        Fletcher preparing you or were you looking at America's role in the world of
                        1950, '51?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, very much so. Our studies were more classical, that is the Fletcher
                    curriculum was a conservative one and we studied diplomatic history, American
                    and European and the Far East as we called it in those days. You had to take
                    international law organization and economics, but we were always looking at,
                    taking the lessons of history and applying them to present times, taking
                    international law and thinking how it applied into current problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you specialize at Fletcher at all or was it a fairly
                        general education?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was general. You specialized in your first year for your master's
                    only to the degree of taking two out of your four courses in one subject because
                    you had to take one course in all three areas. It's a much broader curriculum
                    now, but they still tend to emphasize the need for general knowledge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, as a woman we're still talking about a difficult
                        time for women finding careers in the early '50s and all. How did you
                        analyze and what were you getting about whither women in foreign relations
                        at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, Fletcher had a speaker's program for luncheon guests and
                    speakers. Sometimes ambassadors, sometimes representatives of business friends
                    with international connections. We'd get an impression from them. The
                    ambassadors from other countries would look at the number of women students and
                    tactfully applaud the school and confess that their own Foreign Service had no
                    women officers. I remember a representative from Morgan Bank who was describing
                    the terms on which Morgan admitted its trainees. For the men graduates with
                    master's degree it would offer $60 a week which even in those days was pretty
                    small potatoes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, it was.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: But for women, he said frankly we're not interested in women, but if
                    one were exceptionally qualified we'd pay $40 a week which was less than a steno
                    person would get. We got the message and we thought about going into editing as
                    an editor or something. I remember going on a trip down to New York with a
                    friend who graduated from Wesleyan and we had lunch with a friend of hers who
                    was doing editing with one of the publishing houses and the field was very hard
                    to get into, it paid a pittance. It didn't particularly discriminate against
                    women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I graduated from Williams in 1950 and I got caught up in
                        the Korean War, but I remember visiting friends of mine from Smith who were
                        in New York and they were all, editing was what they did in those times.
                        This was some extremely bright women ended up going there and again living
                        six to an apartment or something like that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: In order to afford it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>McLENDON: When people, when women began to talk about how disgracefully the
                    Foreign Service had discriminated against women I tended to put it in
                    perspective and they did, no question about it. I tend to put it in perspective
                    and say, in comparison with almost anyone else they didn't. They were fairer and
                    tried harder to be fair than anyone else.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think the real one that the Foreign Service couldn't
                        quite swallow was the marriage thing. That if you were a woman and you got
                        married you had to get out. Other than that there were women coming in and
                        getting the same salary and all that. Not many.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, they weren't necessarily getting the same salary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No. They took a look at whether you were married or single. There
                    wasn't much discrimination in the salary level.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were faced with the sort of bleak prospect you
                        and thousands of other bright women coming in and the world was changing,
                        but it hadn't really changed yet, but it was sort of on the way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: In those days the world didn't realize it was going to change toward
                    women. They thought everything would, they'd taken women in during the war and
                    when things settled down they'd all go back home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: And rear the children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, okay, how did you approach this then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, with the same spirit that I applied at Fletcher. I decided I had
                    nothing to lose and I took the Foreign Service exam as soon as I was old
                    enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had to be 21.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: You had to be 21 in those days.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You started in school at 15.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I wasn't quite 21 when I, I was 20 when I went off to Fletcher. I
                    wasn't 21 until I finished the first year and I couldn't take the Foreign
                    Service exam until the following year. I tried to find a job in the meantime and
                    when I didn't I went back to Fletcher to continue working. I went ahead and
                    applied for the Foreign Service and I was still determined to stay with it at
                    least until I was turned down. I passed the written and in the spring of my
                    second year at Fletcher I went down to Washington for the orals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be '51?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: This would be '51 and one of my classmates at Fletcher, a good friend,
                    Bill Allen was scheduled for his orals on the same morning I was, so we took the
                    train down together and stayed with Fletcher friends down in Washington. Bill
                    passed his orals with distinction and I was deferred on mine. The chairman of
                    the orals board explained it, he said that quite frankly they thought that I
                    would not stay there. That I would be engaged within a year and would not stay
                    the course and because of the policy that women officers must resign if they
                    married, they didn't think they could risk the $5,000 it would cost to make me a
                    productive Foreign Service Officer. I could see the point, but they said I
                    passed the written with a high enough score that they didn't want to turn me
                    down altogether, so under the deferral I could take the orals again without
                    having to take the written anytime between 11 and 24 months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The basic assumption being if you didn't find a mate or
                        something like that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: If I didn't become engaged and was stubborn enough to continue then
                    they would consider me again.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you talk a little about the oral exam? I mean some of
                        the things that you remember about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, it was, for me some of the questions were if they went into
                    diplomatic history or international law or relations or something it was easy.
                    Then they would touch on my weaker areas of economics or geography. I know one
                    question was, they were very nice, they were sort of fun, but one question they
                    asked me on geography was the main branches of one of the rivers. I think we
                    started up the Mississippi and then the Ohio and so forth. They finally got up
                    far enough that I couldn't tell them the main tributaries and the member of the
                    orals board who had asked the question, gave the name of one river and another
                    member turned to him and said, “That river leads into the Chesapeake. It doesn't
                    go anywhere near the _____.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Probably the Susquehanna.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Which gave me the impression they weren't terribly serious about that
                    one. In those days the Department of Agriculture was usually represented and he
                    was the only grumpy member of the board. He asked me about the war with Mexico
                    and the acquisition of the territories and I explained the treaty terms and then
                    he said how do you justify this? It's pure conquest. I said, today we would not.
                    That's the way we look at it today, but in the 19th Century that was a perfectly
                    acceptable way of conducting foreign policy. He said, well, I disagree and I
                    think it was an immoral land grab or words to that affect. I said, I hope you
                    don't think that about Texas. I had pointed out that Texas did fight a war of
                    independence and won. I didn't mention that it was largely subsidized from the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, how did you feel because I mean today this would
                        have set off, I mean somebody said, well you'll probably get engaged and we
                        won't take you. The logic at that time made sense, but how did you deal with
                        this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was not a committed career woman. Like most women of my generation
                    I'd been brought up to think that marriage and children was natural, it was a
                    natural life to be desired. I simply wanted to follow my interests as to where
                    they took me and see where I came out. I intended to marry if I found the right
                    man, if I met the right man, I intended to marry in those years. I wasn't going
                    to marry just anyone. I had no intention of marrying just to marry. Just to
                    follow that lifestyle, so I thought it perfectly fair to say that. I couldn't
                    have said that I wouldn't. It didn't upset me as much as it would a young woman
                    today. You couldn't say that today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know. What I'm trying to do is to capture the time. We
                        accepted an awful lot of things that we wouldn't and probably today people
                        are accepting that in another next generation they wouldn't either so its
                        not as though its that a benighted a time, its just different generations
                        and different thoughts.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I know. That reminds me of one of my best friends at Fletcher was Paul
                    Walsh and Paul and his wife, Marie, were close friends all these years. Paul
                    rather hurt my feelings once at Fletcher when he said he was talking to two of
                    us, the women, and he said you shouldn't be here. I said why not. We're doing
                    just as good a job as you are and he said because you're taking the place of a
                    man. He said, you're going to leave and get married and not use your education
                    whereas a man would continue to use the education. Well, 20 or 30 years
                    afterwards, after that incident.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which you remembered.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: When we were having dinner with friends, I turned to Paul and reminded
                    him of it and said I want you to take back those words.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what did you do? Here you are and they say, well, in
                        the proviso that you stay from engagements and all, we'll look at you again.
                        What did you do, we're talking about 1951?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I just shrugged my shoulders. I was feeling discouraged at that point,
                    but not terribly because all my friends at Fletcher had reassured me that I
                    probably wouldn't make it the first time around. I remember that I was in the
                    corridors in the old Walker Johnson building where BEX had its interviews and
                    personnel branch had its offices. I was doing some other job hunting while I was
                    in Washington at the time and I ran into an ambassador who had been on my orals
                    board and he was very kind. He asked me what I was doing. He said, “You are
                    going to continue in the Foreign Service aren't you?” Because they had
                    recommended I enter Foreign Service staff to see whether I liked it or not. I
                    was exploring it. I said, “Well, do you think I should? Do you think I have a
                    chance?” He said, “Oh, yes, you just get a little experience and continue.” He
                    was very encouraging and that's the way it turned out. I entered Foreign Service
                    staff and they were very kind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you explain what the Foreign Service staff was?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>McLENDON: The Foreign Service staff basically was the clerical branch and they
                    made no allowances for education. You had to come in at the bottom and pass the
                    typing test if possible. If you didn't pass the typing test you were sure to be
                    assigned to communications. Fortunately I passed the typing test. In those days
                    it was very personalized and they hand-picked my assignment to be placed in a
                    position in which the office needed me for my trainability more than for my
                    clerical skills which were at a very low level. It happened to be as a clerk to
                    the one visa officer in Sao Paulo. I went through training at the same time as
                    two of my classmates went through the basic officers' course, my Fletcher
                    classmates. I did not realize, I was happy and I was excited about going
                    overseas and I was thrilled with having my first job, even though it was
                    clerical. I did not realize until just a couple of years ago when I pulled out
                    the letter, my letters that I had written home and my parents had kept all those
                    years and every other letter I wrote had some expression of bitterness and
                    resentment over where my Fletcher classmates were and what they were doing and
                    there I was cooling my heels because I was a woman. You know, all these years, I
                    had thought I didn't resent it that much because it faded with time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, faded with time. This is why I wanted to capture
                        this. How did they train you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was a combination of orientation to what the Foreign Service is and
                    then they sat us down with typewriters and we had to familiarize ourselves with
                    what was then called a Foreign Service Correspondent's Handbook in which you
                    practiced the various forms of letters and telegrams and diplomatic notes. Lord
                    help me if I ever had to type a diplomatic note.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, those things had to be letter perfect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Of course, no erasure. When I got down to Sao Paulo, we had an
                    agreement, my boss and I, if it had to be letter perfect, we would send it to
                    one of the other secretaries who were all good pals of mine and say pretty
                    please, would you do this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I also like to nail it down, you were in Sao Paulo from
                        when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was in Sao Paulo from July of 1951 to June of 1952.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: 1952, so a year approximately.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Approximately a year. No, maybe early August.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anyway, we're talking about essentially a year. What did
                        we have in Sao Paulo and sort of can you describe the consulate there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We had a consulate general. It was not nearly the size it is now, but a
                    small consulate general, rather heavily on the area of economic commercial side
                    and I assume it still should be except to the extent the consular work doesn't
                    devour the whole thing. The consular section such as it was consisted of one
                    officer who handled only citizenship and protective service citizens which was
                    not a full time job, but he didn't like visas and he was the senior, the chief
                    of the consular section. The visa officer was somewhat overworked, but only
                    because our procedures in those days were so backwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Can you describe a little of the life in Brazil and
                        in Sao Paulo at that time as you observed it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Sao Paulo at that time was the fastest growing city in the Western
                    Hemisphere. One thing I remember is of Sao Paulo is the sound. You could not
                    escape the sound of construction, of buildings being constructed, of new bridge
                    crossings and underground crossings and every form of transportation being
                    constructed. It was I guess about two million in the city. It was still a
                    livable size.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the social life there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The social life I fitted in with the other clerks and secretaries. We
                    were a small enough post to be sort of an informal family and we would get
                    together with officers and their families. Not long after I arrived, I teamed up
                    with two other women who were looking for quarters because we didn't have
                    furniture and furnished apartments were not to be had, so we started a system of
                    house sitting. We would house sit houses of families who had gone on home leave
                    for two, three or five months. That way we had a very comfortable furnished
                    house and we could be flexible. We had very little to pack up and if we needed
                    extra furniture we knew that we could borrow some from the consulate general and
                    haul it in the consular jeep. We were gypsies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the consular general when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Julian Greenup.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Julian Greenup.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Greenup.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: He was replaced by Clarence I cannot remember his last name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's all right.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: He was very kind to me, but I cannot remember the last name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find your Foreign Service experience was at
                        this place?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, I was fascinated with Brazil and still I didn't like it much. I
                    was, that was before I had learned to look a country with more understanding. I
                    reacted to Brazilians rudely and Brazilians as with some of the continental
                    cultures and I found it in Mexico. I had gone to live with a Mexican friend when
                    I was 16 to learn Spanish. If you were of the people one knows, they were polite
                    and otherwise no one else was entitled to politeness. The French were a little
                    like that and the Brazilians were and I reacted against that. I had dated a
                    student from Brazil my first year at Fletcher, had almost become engaged to him,
                    and that should have given me a kind of feeling for them, but it didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you say the Foreign Service family, how would you
                        describe it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: My social life consisted of the Foreign Service family and some
                    friends, a young single international group I had met through fellow boarders at
                    homes in Sao Paulo. I met a young American physicist there and he had introduced
                    me to friends of his. I had a cluster of friends who included Germans, one
                    Czech, one Dutch, one or two Brazilians and so forth. We read plays.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh yes, wonderful exercise. It's a little hard, I'm not
                        sure how it is today, but in those days the staff so many of the secretaries
                        would be coming essentially out of the same educated class, the same gene
                        pool as the officers that the interest.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Even those who didn't had the gumption and the interest to want to go
                    overseas. They were a good group.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a good group, but I think in many ways, in large
                        embassies things would sort of fall out because that's the problem of large
                        embassies, but in the smaller places it is very cohesive because it wasn't
                        them and us as far as the staff versus the officer corps then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, in those days it wasn't. We were a family. We liked and enjoyed
                    each other. They would all go on trips together, several of the women and with
                    one or two of my friends from the circus, my little play reading group. It was a
                    fun time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Later you got involved from time to time on the consular
                        side. What was the consular work like in Sao Paulo at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, my God. Consular work was just totally buried under layer after
                    layer of regulations that simply could not be all carried out and procedures
                    that were just totally out of date. We had to fingerprint every applicant for
                    every visa, non-immigrant visas as well. A businessman going for a brief trip to
                    the United States, a full set of fingerprints. Oh, just total absurdity. The
                    files we kept, just total absurdity. It was a system I fought from the day I
                    first encountered it until the day I retired.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did it sort of appall you at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. It appalled me at the time. It was so totally. Not to the degree
                    it did later because I was still green enough to think well, maybe for security
                    reasons we have to do these stupid things, but no, the system was appalling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Excuse me a minute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The system did not make allowances for human nature.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Or the sensitivities of foreigners, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Or the sensitivities of foreigners. I remember that only the
                    flexibility in the mind of the officer applying the law allowed us to survive. I
                    remember there was at that time and may still be a section in the immigration
                    law that prohibits the issuance of a visa to anyone who is entering the United
                    States primarily for the purpose of engaging in immoral behavior.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, in immoral sexual practices. I think that was
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I remember we were handling the application of one of the better known
                    of the Brazilian industrialists who was going to the States with his mistress. I
                    sort of raised my eyebrows and said, “How do you get around that?” He looked at
                    me, and of course he's going for business, and he said, “She is going for
                    shopping.” It says primarily.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When that came in a little bit later, I said, well, you've
                        got to figure out what are they going to be doing most of the time, unless
                        they real sort of sexual athletes, they're going to be doing a lot of other
                        things, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No one is doing it primarily.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean who would go to the United States to. But it was
                        embarrassing to have to administer this law. These things were thrown in by
                        congress on almost a whim or something. Were you feeling the hand of
                        McCarthyism or something like that while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Here you are a new girl on the block and all of a sudden
                        this manifestation of.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We were all painfully aware of McCarthy and when I really felt the hand
                    of McCarthy on the Foreign Service was when I came back and passed my orals and
                    was brought in by the Foreign Service class of 1953. I said the Foreign Service
                    class of 1953 because we were the last Foreign Service class for 18 months, the
                    only one that year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The next one was renumbered and called class one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Was it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was mine. I started in July of 1955.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>McLENDON: We were a small class. There were 20 of us. The Eisenhower
                    administration had taken over and John Foster Dulles had pledged to rid the
                    State Department of all those commies and at that same time they were determined
                    to cut it back substantially. We took a RIF of I think one-third that year,
                    one-fourth to one-third. They were trying to select out and they did select out
                    25% of the Foreign Service Officers. My class was caught up in that before we
                    had our commissions because no one was commissioned for 18 months and no one was
                    promoted for 18 months because the promotion lists, the commission lists, were
                    all held up in the senate until everyone got a new full field FBI security
                    clearance. The debate went on in the personnel division. We were in training
                    three months and throughout that three months they were debating within the
                    personnel division, there was a debate whether we would be considered career and
                    they would hang on to us or whether we were to be dropped at the end of our
                    training. So, every week we would call, we had two contacts in personnel and
                    we'd get one side from one and one side from the other. It was all right for me,
                    I was single and young, but there were married classmates. Some of them with
                    children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they tended to be older because of the veterans and
                        all this coming back in yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. So, it was a stressful time and at the end of it I was one of the
                    first to be cleared because as it turned out I had been investigated by the FBI
                    before my orals and that was accepted. A number of us were cleared and were able
                    to take overseas assignments and a number were held back and two of our class
                    were dropped, not permanently, but one they simply allowed him to be drafted
                    because he had served all but I think two months of the amount of time that
                    would have exempted him from being called up for the Korean War and the State
                    Department would not ask for his, they could easily have gotten him excused for
                    that, but they wouldn't and that allowed him to be called out. The other one
                    there was some vague report of a security issue that they didn't have time to
                    investigate and so they dropped him saying if they later had time to investigate
                    and if they cleared him he could come back and he did eventually. My attitude at
                    the end of the training was if I had another job and had the moral courage I'd
                    leave this outfit. It isn't worth it. It isn't worth working for. It doesn't
                    have any loyalty to us. Not any sense of loyalty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I came with that same feeling that John Foster Dulles and
                        his group would, the phrase was that Dean Acheson he would not turn his back
                        on Alger Hess. I had the feeling that John Foster Dulles would turn his back
                        on anybody.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I was in Washington at the time of the changeover in administration. I
                    attended both Dean Acheson's farewell meeting with the entire staff of the State
                    Department and Dulles' first. At Acheson's, his senior staff members had taken
                    up money and purchased for him the chair in which he sat as a cabinet member in
                    the cabinet meetings as a farewell gift. Of course with his wit and graceful
                    turn of phrase he smiled and said, “This has not been a chair of ease.” Then he
                    went on to explain his philosophy. He said, “I have taken it from my role to be
                    that of the political appointee who is responsible for the policy of this
                    department and who defends it and who takes the blame. The career service are
                    there for the long run. They are not responsible for these political fights and
                    it's my role to bear the brunt of that, not you. You're doing your best.” Of
                    course everyone was very much touched by that. The following week Dulles gave
                    his address to the staff and said things are different, things are going to
                    change around here. We are going to insist on positive loyalty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That phase positive loyalty stuck to him like a tar baby
                        for the rest of the time and many would never forgive him for that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I will never forgive him. I never forgave him I should say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the time you were new to this business, did that send a
                        chill up into your spine?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It did indeed. At the time I thought as a career officer I'll simply do
                    my best in the traditions of a non-political career service and try to survive.
                    I didn't realize that it was going to have a permanent effect on the culture of
                    the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, was there much in your group after this contrast?
                        What were you talking about between Acheson and Dulles? Do you recall how
                        people were talking about this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We admired Acheson. He'd been a great Secretary of State. He was a
                    creative Secretary of State. Dulles came across as a very negative man. Almost a
                    fanatic on the Cold War. I did meet him. This was at a time when all Foreign
                    Service was taken upstairs to meet the Secretary, but he was never comfortable
                    dealing with the underlings on his staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I want to go back just a bit. Before we leave Sao Paulo,
                        were there any protection and welfare cases that particularly stuck in your
                        mind or was there not much?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. You know the old protection and welfare cases. There'd been a
                    traveling circus in Brazil that was owned by an American couple or at least the
                    wife was an American citizen and the circus went bankrupt or ran short of funds
                    in Sao Paulo. They had to sell what they could of the menagerie and physical
                    assets to settle their debts and then there were some left over. Well, the
                    husband died and little was left and the assets gradually dwindled down. She had
                    to be put in a nursing home and the assets were down to one elephant. The
                    consular officer negotiated a rental arrangement; a lease arrangement with
                    another circus on that elephant and the rental was just enough to pay the
                    expenses in the nursing home. No one knew the age of the elephant. They knew he
                    wasn't a young elephant by any means and the question was would the elephant
                    live long enough so that the funds would be there for the widow or would the
                    widow die first and then what does one do with the elephant. While I was there
                    the widow died and we breathed a sigh of relief. We didn't have to come up with
                    some source of funds for this widow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went back and took the oral exam. Was this any
                        different or how did you find the oral?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, it was a breeze. I think they'd made up their minds ahead of time.
                    I had studied up on geography.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you know the sources of the Ohio by this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, I'd memorized. Mr. Bartlett was our professor of history at
                    Fletcher and he had made us memorize the terms of the treaties. He asked very
                    detailed questions and you would have to trace the northern boundaries or trace
                    the southern boundary as laid out by such and such treaty. So, we memorized that
                    sort of thing, but I'd also done a bit more studying on exports and imports and
                    that sort of thing. It was sort of a breeze.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there anything about the training at the time except
                        you had this whole McCarthy and this whole RIF and all that hanging over
                        your heads as far as were you in or were you out of the Foreign Service. How
                        did you find the training of your class?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Long and boring. I think not much that was of real interest. I remember
                    the consular training the fun part was Francis Baylor a seaman in shipping.
                    Remember sailor Baylor?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>McLENDON: The really fun part was that we had a week's excursion in New York to
                    visit the UN which of course I'd done while I was at Fletcher and to visit the
                    customs house which was fascinating and to go out with INS and greet an incoming
                    ship and see how they processed the incoming to visit Ellis Island and see how
                    they processed for Ellis Island, all that kind of stuff. Sailor Baylor was our
                    escort. All I remember of that week was just a lot of fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was great. I stayed at the seaman's institute. Men
                        could do that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Men could do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I mean there were lots of sailors staggering in at all
                        sorts of hours.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It wasn't considered suitable for women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. I felt a little out of place there. I'd been an
                        enlisted man for four years, but this was a pretty rough crowd, it was a
                        rough area.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Not a bad introduction for consular work I should say.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, we're back in business. Ruth, now, where did you go?
                        You got out and finally they determined they were going to keep you all or
                        most of you in this basic officer course and we're talking about '53 is
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes, we're talking about '53.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Whither?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I went to Manila. I was originally assigned to a slot in the political
                    section, which was biographic reporting. Thank God that was changed, but it
                    served me a bad turn later. I was supposed to go to that, but a consular
                    officer, an officer in the consular section had developed hearing problems and
                    could not handle the consular work and was moved into that position and they
                    moved me into the consular section which worked out very nicely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Manila from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: From July of 1953 to September, no early October of 1955.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you kind of give a feel for the Philippines in the '53
                        to '55 period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was seven or eight years after the war. Manila was not yet
                    completely rebuilt. Of the capital cities, Manila was second only to Warsaw in
                    the amount of devastation and bombing and attacks. It had not yet recovered. It
                    had received its full independence from the United States a year after the end
                    of the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1946.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was delayed. We had the commonwealth act in 1935. It was supposed to
                    receive independence in 1945 on our independence day, July 4th and we postponed
                    one year because the war was not yet over in Asia in 1945. They had become
                    independent with all of the devastation the war had wreaked in the Philippines
                    and without assistance from us to rebuild at first. They had a rocky start for
                    independence, but we did come in with the war plans act and we did a lot of
                    compensating. A lot of money was poured in which did help in rebuilding. At the
                    time this was before the Filipinos had become very nationalistic. They were
                    still largely pro-American. There were Philippine nationalists. They were
                    particularly journalists who loved to beat us over the head, but it was still a
                    country in which we had far too much influence, you couldn't avoid it. We had a
                    special economic relationship. We had negotiated an agreement which had
                    established preferences for Philippine products in American markets and the same
                    for American products and American investments in the Philippines. We had the
                    Philippines bases agreement which guaranteed our role in protecting the
                    Philippines as the price for the bases. We didn't pay a cash price. The
                    relationship was close, too close for a healthy development of the Philippines
                    and they were beginning to resent it. It's awfully hard to cut an umbilical cord
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe the embassy at the time and then we'll
                        get to your job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The embassy was in and still is I guess in the old high commissioner's
                    residence right on Manila Bay, a nice old, art deco, early '30s building. Very
                    pleasant and surrounded by Quonset huts because we had to expand it temporarily
                    and we had a whole cluster of Quonset huts off to one side that was staff
                    housing. We had some larger Quonset huts on the other side that housed USIA and
                    our snack bar. The consular section had the ground floor and one entire wing off
                    the ground floor plus a few offices on one side, plus a few offices in the other
                    wing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>McLENDON: My first ambassador there was Raymond Spruance, the former admiral and
                    everyone loves Ambassador Spruance. He was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the victor of Midway.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Midway. He was not only highly respected, but venerated I would say for
                    his role in Midway certainly by the ex-navy, but he was also a thoroughly
                    decent, nice human being. Just the nicest sort of person to work for. His wife
                    was like him. She was a delightful woman with a long experience of being a navy
                    wife and looking after the morale of the navy wives under her husband's command.
                    She was a superb ambassador's wife. They were a lovely couple. I didn't work
                    obviously with Ambassador Spruance on political matters, but my friends who did
                    respected him also for his common sense as well as grasp of important elements
                    in the relationship. The criticisms that I heard of him tended on the side that
                    he was ex-military, he was overly committed to the importance of those bases,
                    but who wasn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which really remained for the next 30 years, the same
                        thing. Can you describe the consular section? Was it one of our biggest at
                        that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was one of our largest. Manila was, I think, at that time our
                    largest embassy or one of the largest embassies. We had a large AID mission. We
                    had a large military assistance group as well as bases. We had a large consular
                    section. We had a heavy demand for visas and we had probably the largest number
                    of American citizens abroad at that time because of the long relationship and
                    because of the over 5,000 Philippine veterans who had been naturalized at the
                    very close of the war and were still citizens and with children.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, who was in charge of the consular section?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was there two years and we had five different consuls general.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Why?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The first one, the best one was selected out that year. He was
                    basically a political officer who was moved into the consular section and I'm
                    not sure why. He was selected out. It was because we selected out 25% and it
                    happened to be a bad time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, a bad time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>McLENDON: He was followed by an old-line consular officer and I don't remember
                    his name. I can see his face, but I don't remember his name who, let's just say
                    he was unimaginative. At one point Terry Sanders took over the consular section,
                    I don't know why. He was sort of interim. He was basically an economic officer
                    and I think very bright, but a bit temperamental and not at all interested in
                    consular work. Then we had Raleigh Gibson who was transferred down to us from
                    the political section. He was on his last six or eight months before retirement
                    and he retired from there. I think the first three I mentioned, we're talking
                    about only a few months and I don't know why. Then the last was Hayward Hill and
                    our name for him was Haywire Hill who was a very nice person, very tender
                    hearted and not inclined to pay much attention to consular regulations. The
                    heart ruled the head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, what were you doing there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was moved around a lot. I started off in the citizenship side and I
                    was working under Irv Ross who was an old line staff officer who had been in
                    Manila since the days of the high commissioner, had been interned there during
                    the war and had returned after the war and he was a complete character. The
                    complete opposite of the type anyone would identify with the Foreign Service as
                    being a Foreign Service Officer. I would say he looked like a retired merchant
                    marine or non-com in the navy, balding, very heavyset, tattooed I think, a real
                    character. When I was brought in and introduced to him as his new junior officer
                    he looked me up and down and said, oh. He wasn't a bit impressed. Irv and I got
                    along. When he learned that I had done some consular work on the clerical side
                    and I didn't mind, I didn't at all mind being sat with one of his senior
                    Philippine employees, we called them local employees, to be taught the
                    intricacies of nationality law as applied in the Philippines a former
                    possession.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where it was extremely complicated.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Where it had all kinds of complications, yes, because our Foreign
                    Service national employees were very high quality. They did a higher level of
                    work particularly on the nationality side than I'd ever seen anywhere else. They
                    could process the cases, handle the interviews, bring the case entirely to
                    decision point, write a draft decision and then bring it in to the officer for
                    the final interview and decision. I seldom had to make changes, occasionally a
                    minor grammatical or file change in the decision, but I almost never had to
                    question either their law or their evaluation of the individual in terms of
                    reliability.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any particular problem type citizenship
                        cases?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, yes. We had a very high level of fraud. I knew when we went through
                    consular training in the Philippines it had been mentioned as that. The
                    Philippines and Hong Kong were in competition of who could produce the greatest
                    number of fraudulent claims to citizenship. Hong Kong had by far the more
                    elaborate system set up. The Philippines' operation was much more amateur, but
                    it became more professional to the degree to which we professionalized our
                    handling of it. We had basically two types of fraudulent cases. Three. One, the
                    largest number involved Filipinos who claimed to have been born in Hawaii. There
                    had been from the late '20s or early '30s, I think, a program by the Hawaiian
                    sugar planters association importing labor from the Philippines. While most of
                    them did not remain in Hawaii permanently, they had children born to them there
                    and then returned to the Philippines. There were literally thousands of American
                    citizens by birth who had at one time been returned to the Philippines as
                    children with their families. After the war, when we made war reparations
                    available to American citizens in the Philippines, that put a high premium, a
                    high cash premium on American citizenship. So, immediately we had all kinds of
                    competing claims for citizenship. There were a lot of Filipinos who simply
                    obtained the birth certificates of those born in the Philippines. They might
                    have come from the same village in the Philippines as the parents and then filed
                    their own claim. The child who had been born in the United States might have
                    died and you've never known about the citizenship or what have you, but we had
                    this steady flow of applications with all kinds of fraudulent documentation and
                    no capability of investigating except we could send it back to the immigration
                    service in Honolulu. They could do a field investigation and interview those who
                    lived still, Filipinos who still lived in the same area in which this person was
                    allegedly born. And sometimes turn up information that clearly indicated that
                    this was not the one; or we could get attestations from the home village in the
                    Philippines from the priest and the mayor and the chief of police, but given the
                    system in the Philippines of village loyalty and everybody will do anything to
                    help somebody else, those were not worth the time it took to look at them, to
                    glance at them. So, that was one type.</p>
                <p>We had the case of the Philippine veterans who had been naturalized, never had
                    left the Philippines, never had been in the United States, but had been
                    naturalized in the Philippines at the close of the war or the close of their
                    service. Never had any intention of going to the United States to live because
                    they just considered the tie between the two countries would go on forever. They
                    married and had children and of course Philippine families tend to be large.
                    They would register a child a year with us and no questions asked and then
                    somewhere along the line we began to realize that not all of these children
                    belong to the same father. If they didn't happen to have a child born that year
                    they'd register the brother's child or cousin's child, anybody's child, you
                    know. We were acquiring American citizens at a much higher rate. Then the third
                    case was what we called the bamboo Americans and these tended to be veterans of
                    the Spanish American War who had settled in the Philippines or those who had
                    gone out with the U.S. military at whatever time back in the old days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The turn of the century.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>McLENDON: And had settled down and married and taken a Filipino wife and settled
                    in happily. A notable percentage of them tended to have multiple marriages. We'd
                    have first one family who would come in and be registered as his family. By this
                    time the original American was in most cases dead, not there for us to ask
                    questions, and we'd get one family registered and then another group would turn
                    up claiming to be also the family and then in some cases a third, but we'd have
                    competing families because of course under our nationality laws only the
                    legitimate wife and the Philippines did not legally recognize bigamist marriages
                    or polygamist marriages. We had fraud in that case because then we had all the
                    competing claims about well the other marriage never really took place. All of
                    this was complicated by the fact that with all of the devastation of the war
                    parish records and civil records had been destroyed and even where they perhaps
                    had not been destroyed it wasn't very hard to get a certificate from the local
                    priest saying that they had been. So, it was reconstruction on the basis of
                    affidavits of very little credibility. It was fun.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much attempt of the Filipinos to get to the
                        consular officers either through money, sex, gifts or what have you or
                        anything like that or was that a problem?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I did not hear of anything like that involving an officer. We did have
                    a strange incident in the visa section in which our receptionist who did the
                    initial counter interview, who was American staff personnel, found $500 in cash
                    on the floor, this packet of $500 in cash lying on the floor of the main
                    processing unit of the visa section. No one ever claimed it. No one ever
                    admitted having lost any money, possibly because it could have been a perfectly
                    legitimate case of which the applicant, it had slipped out of the pocket and
                    they had so little faith in recovering it they never thought to mention it.
                    While I was there and later after I left, several of our Filipino staff had to
                    be dismissed for fraud.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was many years later in Korea and it was endemic
                        there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: There was a lot of pressure on the visa side and perhaps on the
                    citizenship side. I was not aware of it on the citizenship and I don't remember,
                    I cannot think or remember hearing of any of our Filipino staff on the
                    citizenship side who was ever let go because of fraud. One was eventually let go
                    because of rudeness, but I can't think of anyone else. On the visa side I knew a
                    couple of them and I must say there were a couple of them when I worked in the
                    visa section that I watched very closely.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is tape two, side one with Ruth McLendon. You moved
                        over to the visa side what after about a year or so or?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I don't remember the timing of it, probably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What then.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: But then they transferred two officers from the political section down,
                    three actually. One was in the economic section and one from pol/mil or
                    something, political military, but they were transferred down at their own
                    request because they wanted to have a stint in consular work and learn that they
                    were on their perhaps third tour. All good friends and they became my very good
                    friends. We were buddies and I learned a great deal from them, but we were sort
                    of a, there was a great deal of camaraderie. We would switch around so that we
                    were all learning the different aspects of the work. I spent less time on the
                    visa side. I may have spent not more than six or eight months there I guess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you deal with, what were some of the problems in
                        the visa side that you were doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Again, it was fraud. There it was a very heavy pressure on
                    non-immigrant visa of those who in fact intended to remain in the United States
                    by whatever means. We had high pressure on non-immigrant visas almost year
                    round. It was high volume work. We also had a long waiting list on the immigrant
                    visa side, but with a quota of 100 a year as an Asian country in those days we
                    were not issuing many except to the non-quota category, the wives and
                    husbands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much fraud in the marriage business particularly
                        with sailors, soldiers, American soldiers, sailors who were married more for
                        money than?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: There may have been some of that, there undoubtedly was, but we were
                    not as much aware of it in those days as we had seen later. I don't recall ever
                    having to give the kind of in-depth interviews that one gives in those cases. In
                    most cases there was at least one child already.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Something was going on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Someone had been around. No, it wasn't that, I think that became a
                    fraud sideline a little bit further down the road.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you left there, I mean is there anything else we
                        should cover do you think?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>McLENDON: One thing, this is ego speaking, but I take credit for finally having
                    had a tantrum in simply insisting to the Department that we had to have a small
                    investigative unit of our own. It was absurd to attempt to handle the kind of
                    fraud cases we were handling without the capacity of asking questions vocally. I
                    blew my stack one day after I sat and took the affidavit of a man, an American
                    citizen, who admitted to having fraudulently identified five individuals as
                    persons born from his home village, born in the United States, and not one of
                    the five was. I thought that's egregious fraud. So, I put together some figures
                    and a description. I wrote it, in those days, to communicate with the passport
                    office, one wrote by dispatch, not by operations memorandum or other more
                    informal methods, but by dispatch. I wrote a dispatch and had it cleared. I
                    think I was the acting chief of the citizenship section at that time, so there
                    wasn't anyone to clear it with, but the consul general who very wisely suggested
                    that I clear it around the embassy, which I did. The first place I started was
                    with our security officer to get his advice and I incorporated his advice into
                    it and then I cleared it with the political section I think as high as the DCM
                    and the administrative section. It went out and when it hit the Philippine desk,
                    Dave Koffell, who was on the Philippine desk at that time with Bob Fuline and
                    Bob told me later that they carried it into his office, tips his finger and
                    said, who wrote that? What's responsible for that? I made a modest request. I
                    thought that we had to have a small investigative unit of our own consisting of
                    a minimum of one American officer and one or more Filipino investigators, or if
                    that were failing that, I forgot what my second request was. Or failing that,
                    that we at least be allowed to send an officer over to the Hong Kong fraud unit
                    for him to get some training and look into it there. The officers on the desk
                    interpreted that as the desire of our consul general to get a free trip to Hong
                    Kong. The passport office was really upset when I gave them the statistics on
                    the fraud. I've never seen it happen so fast until the Mexico thing. I think it
                    was three months we had our authorization. It was very fast.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This wouldn't have been Frances Knight, would she have
                        been there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, she carried an awful lot of weight.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes and when she got mad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When she got mad, she would go straight to both congress
                        and to J. Edgar Hoover. I suppose too the times were right, you know,
                        people; we were being super patriotic and all I suppose fraudulent American
                        citizenship didn't sit very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, just that degree of fraud in any operation didn't sit well. It
                    makes you look stupid.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But when you left there you must have gone with a certain
                        aura of she who gets things done.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I don't know. I felt that it was, I was just very, I thought, at least
                    I accomplished one thing. One thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Then you went to where, to Australia, was that
                        it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, unfortunately because I had been listed on the personnel records as
                    having been assigned to biographic reporting position in Manila, when the,
                    remember we're talking 1955 and the, what was his name? The Wriston Report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Wriston Program, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The Wriston Report had come out in '54 pointing out all the positions
                    in the Department of State that should be filled by Foreign Service. All of the
                    cross training that needed to be taking place and every available Foreign
                    Service Officer was being dragged back to Washington and put into positions in
                    the Department. All these people in the Department who had never intended to go
                    overseas were being forced overseas. I was dragged back and put into the
                    division of biographic reporting, the Division of Biographic Information.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was in INR, wasn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was in INR. It was the deadliest part of INR.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Diego Asencio was in there at that time, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose you just got these reports and essentially filed
                        them, is that it?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>McLENDON: That is what we were supposed to do. We were supposed to get these
                    reports and it was full biographic report filing, but more often it was a
                    mention of the person in a paragraph or a sentence or less in a longer report.
                    Then you were supposed to excise this little squib and card it and put it in the
                    card file, which was largely clerical. I was in the Western European branch and
                    we had, let's see, one, two, three, four, five, six officers and two clerks, one
                    of whom didn't work much. The old biographic hands were very much upset when I
                    kept pointing out that our proportions were reversed, we should have at least
                    five clerk typists to every officer or to every two officers because it was
                    primarily clerical work. Yes, we pulled out the information together and did
                    biographical work, but that was very low level writing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you up against sort of an entrenched little kingdom
                        or something there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, it was an entrenched little kingdom that very soon disappeared.
                    It was a little kingdom. It had been a cozy nest for a lot of people primarily
                    women, but there were men who were also comfortable there. Intelligent, well
                    educated, deeply interested in the countries they were working on and
                    knowledgeable about them who happened to love the detailed work of following
                    people. Then we had the Foreign Service Officers coming in and looking at this
                    with a completely different viewpoint and then we had the younger wave of
                    Foreign Service Officers coming in like Diego and a few others who not only had
                    a different way of looking at things, but weren't about to do that clerical work
                    and things began to change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you doing that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Three years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Three years?!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Three years. I finally got out. I would have liked an assignment to
                    political or economic work, but I was ready to take anything to get overseas
                    again. So, when they offered me Adelaide, because we were just reopening, I
                    jumped at it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, you were in Adelaide from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: January of 1959 to June of 1961. I was there two and a half years
                    because I had to be extended to get on the right assignment cycle.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Adelaide like and what was the importance
                        consular wise of Adelaide?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Adelaide had been one of our old posts, we had had a consulate there
                    for more than a hundred years and then we closed it in 1953. Now we were
                    reopening. Originally it had been there to protect seaman because we had whalers
                    in the area that would come through the southern seas and other shipping of all
                    kinds. Later on there was not very much justification. We kept fairly busy with
                    visas. We had a growing number of American citizens there as American firms
                    invested in Australia. We had a fairly active commercial program that was
                    largely carried on by our senior Australia staff. We did some minor political
                    reporting all of which the Department could have lived without. It was my first
                    chance to become involved in political reporting because John Ausland who was
                    principal officer had been in political work most of his life and was rather
                    blas� about it and practically willing to turn it over, most of it to me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I might say that John Ausland comes up in my radar all the
                        time because I'm on an Internet connection. He's continually commenting on
                        things. It's a diplomatic history connection on the electronic net and he's
                        continually making comments to people about they got it wrong, you know,
                        this is what happened. He's still doing his political reporting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I would think John would be pretty up on it. He tends to do his
                    background work pretty carefully. John was a very sensible, laid back sort of
                    type. We didn't really need to be there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there two of you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: There were two of us. It was fun, but I can't think of anything
                    essential in it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were the Australians there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They were overwhelmingly friendly. It wasn't a case of getting out and
                    making friends, it was a case of fighting off invitations from everyone, fending
                    off I should say because you couldn't spread yourself that thin. No, they were
                    great and very easy to make friends. You could make friends anywhere. It was a
                    little sticky. I was supposed to have the labor party for a beat and it meant
                    largely trade union members and they were just as nervous as cats with a woman
                    officer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. It made them uncomfortable. They weren't used to women in that
                    position.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they really were, my understanding is that the labor
                        party in Australia was almost a direct import from England, I mean a very
                        working class, very class conscious and all that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, very, yes. Australia as a country has a reputation for being not
                    class conscious and that is largely true. They are very democratic as a rule.
                    Adelaide at that time tended to be the exception because the south Australians
                    were the first to tell you that south Australia was not settled, never settled
                    by convicts. They were younger sons.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sort of remittance men and that type of thing.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They didn't put it that way. The implication was that they were never
                    of that class. It was a mixture because they were the younger Australians and
                    the intellectuals and they were delightful. It was, the top level of society in
                    Adelaide was like a step back into the 19th Century and in fact Mallory Ausland
                    and I were both compulsive readers and I discovered Trollop about that time and
                    we decided that that was probably the best guide to Adelaide society. We were
                    working our way through all of the Trollop novels and we thought that some of it
                    might possibly be important, but that's getting pretty far advanced here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Those were pretty racy crowds.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Pretty racy crowds. You're better off. Anyhow. When John and Mallory
                    left they gave me as a farewell present, they had found an old blotter with a
                    silver cover over it and they had it engraved Adelaide 1861.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it by this time you really were hooked on the
                        Foreign Service, weren't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, yes and I loved Australia. I traveled all over Australia and loved
                    it and went back later to visit my friends. The Aussies are great friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your family back in Texas think of this girl
                        running around to all these places and all that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, my parents were very supportive, my mother particularly. For my
                    parents it was a bit of a sacrifice because we had lost my brother the year
                    after he graduated from college. He drowned in an accident and I was the only
                    one left. They were still willing to free me and allow me to go off and follow
                    the kind of life I did and not produce grandchildren, not marry and produce
                    grandchildren as they had every right to hope I would and never criticized me
                    for it. I thought it was remarkable and something that I deeply appreciated, but
                    my father I know would have much preferred that I stayed at home and marry and
                    have children. My mother vicariously was right there with me, enjoying every bit
                    of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's great. Did you, I mean, let's take I mean at this
                        point we're talking about the Kennedy administration just coming in. Did you
                        see any change in the role of women in the Foreign Service, what you could
                        look forward to, how women were dealt with, not necessarily with Kennedy,
                        but in the time now that you'd been in.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Not that soon, no. In fact, not at all. I didn't. I went back from
                    Australia to go into Burmese language training because even though there were
                    things I hadn't liked about the Philippines and I hadn't liked the climate of
                    the Philippines, the longer I stayed away, the more homesick I got for it. I
                    also had realized that if I were going to have any sort of chance at a career in
                    political work, I needed a specialization in an area that was not terribly
                    popular. So, I applied for southeast area specialization and specifically Thai
                    or Burmese. There were of course always more applicants for Thai training and
                    they happened to have no volunteers that year for Burmese.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You took Burmese, what was it a year course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was the regular ten-month course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you describe Burmese as an American approaching this
                        language?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Burmese has a writing system, but it is not based on the Roman
                    alphabet. It is an alphabet which is derived from Bali, which is similar to
                    Sanskrit. It grammar actually is closer to Japanese than to any other language
                    which is odd, but the Burmese grammar is very simple. It is a tonal language. It
                    has four tones, not as difficult to a Westerner as for example Chinese with its
                    five or six tones, but it is composed of one-syllable units, consonant vowel,
                    consonant vowel and multiples. You string them together.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find it as far as your grasping?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I found it fascinating. I found it certainly for the first month or so
                    the hardest work I'd ever done. I was physically exhausted at the end of the day
                    from the concentration. We were six hours a day in class with two of us in class
                    and a tutor. He was a lovely man to go through that kind of training with
                    because he was very relaxed and gentle and he had lots of funny stories and he
                    didn't push us too hard, but he was free with explanations when we needed them.
                    So, we survived. The only thing was he smoked a smelly pipe and FSI was at that
                    time in the basement of Arlington Towers. You remember that network of
                    underground corridors and little cubicles? We were at the very back of that
                    network in a tiny cubicle and the ventilation was very poor when you got that
                    far back. He would puff on that pipe and it didn't bother me at all at first,
                    but that spring we would take a break and go outdoors and it took a physical act
                    of will for me to go back inside. I had to force myself to go back inside that
                    classroom.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were doing that I was taking Serbian for a year
                        with some very intense work. An underground garage is not the best place to
                        learn a language.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No. Anyhow, I loved Burmese. I loved the Southeast Asia studies. It
                    gave me a chance to do a lot of reading on Burma.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Getting ready to go out there, how did, I mean what was
                        American interests in Burma at that time. We're talking about, I mean you
                        went out in '62 I guess?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, when I started preparing to go they had a parliamentary regime
                    that wasn't working very well. They had a number of insurgencies on their hands.
                    They were a friendly country in which we had a number of economic aid projects
                    and a military assistance group operating and a lot of exchange USIA programs
                    operating. We had a full complement there. Then slightly more than midway
                    through my training the army officers had started the revolution and arrested
                    the cabinet and began the Burmese socialist revolution. They started down a
                    radical socialist path. An intensely nationalistic fear of foreigners.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Xenophobic.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>McLENDON: More xenophobic than anything else. I arrived in July of 1962 very
                    shortly after the student demonstrations. These had resulted in the army
                    suppression which had resulted in the deaths of over 100 students. I don't think
                    the full number was ever known and they arrested hundreds. So, there had been a
                    rather brutal crack down right before I got there. It was at the time I first
                    arrived. I think the Burmese people had been accustomed to British rule and then
                    of course they'd had Japanese domination during the war, but then a return to
                    the British rule and quickly independence. Then this attempt at parliamentary
                    rule. They had been accustomed to a moderate government all these years
                    basically and they had not yet become adjusted to this government. They did not
                    yet realize what they were up against and they were still being fairly free to
                    talk and be with foreigners and so forth. That changed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there at a very interesting time, but you were
                        there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was fascinating. I was there four and a half years. I was there from
                    July of '62 to December of '66.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you see Burma? I mean we've talked about the
                        political situation was just in the process of changing. It had changed,
                        but.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It had changed and they were just in the process of their revolution.
                    Let me describe first what happened to me and then I'll go into that if I
                    may.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay. Please.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I can speak with less authority on the earlier part, the first year I
                    was there than the later part because of one of the things, you know, another of
                    these little switches that the Foreign Service felt free to pull on women
                    officers in those days, more than men. I was a mid-career officer at this point
                    of what, two, three, four posts. I had finished Burmese training with the
                    highest score by one they had. I was supposed to go into the political section
                    as a Burmese language officer. The DCM decided to move a first tour officer from
                    the consular section who wanted to change out of consular work into the
                    political section and give me the consular job which was a job appropriate for a
                    first tour officer and the DCM did it. Although I protested, I didn't have much
                    to say about it. Fortunately, the officer who was moved up in my place, although
                    I resented it terribly, was in fact a fine officer. He turned out to be a fine
                    officer and I had nothing against him, but it wasn't right Fortunately during
                    that first year we were inspected. The inspectors supported me and the
                    recommendation was that I be moved into the political section at the first
                    opportunity. That eventually took place but for that first year I was not in a
                    position to follow the political situation except through the newspaper and so
                    forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, who was the ambassador and DCM at that time when you
                        first arrived?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, we had an ambassador who was a former missionary, a political
                    appointee, a Kennedy political appointee. John Edgerton, a former missionary. He
                    knew Burma. With a good supportive DCM he would have been a good ambassador, but
                    he had been too close. He also had been with the Ford Foundation and he was too
                    closely associated with the Ford Foundation for this revolutionary regime to
                    accept him. At that point, no ambassador could have been effective I think. His
                    DCM was not supportive and he was a weak man himself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was Alexander Schnee. He would undercut the ambassador with the
                    staff and it was an embassy divided within itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's sad because it's obviously a small place and it
                        doesn't take much to create a very unhappy feeling.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It doesn't take much to create unhappiness and it was not a happy
                    place. But fortunately, Edgerton was replaced by Hank Byroade and Hank Byroade
                    was exactly what we needed once we got him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the youngest general.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The youngest brigadier general since the Revolutionary War and had been
                    the ambassador to Egypt at the time that we backed out of the Aswan dam project.
                    If you've heard that story you know something of Byroade's personality. Byroade
                    could be a hard charger, but he was also one of the best judges of human nature
                    I've ever worked with and a very nice guy to work with. Anyhow, he came along
                    and we were in good hands. We weren't going to have that kind of problem
                    anymore. From the time Byroade arrived he was fretting. First, it took him a
                    while to get in and present his credentials. Then after he did, after that
                    formal meeting with the Head of State he couldn't get in to see him at all. He
                    was cooling his heels and fretting and he wanted to know why. There were those
                    within the embassy, and this was something that I'd struggled against with Rick
                    Schnee, there were those within the embassy that were convinced Burma for all
                    practical purposes was a communist country. It was going to go down the
                    communist line, it was a satellite of China and this was it. I think the first
                    report I remember writing when I wrote, when I joined the political section.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would be about '63?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: This was '63, the fall of '63. Was a visit by I think it was from
                    China.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Premier of China.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Foreign Minister at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Foreign Minister, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: All the publicity, all the headlines of the newspapers were about these
                    friendly relations and that was in the English language press in Burma. There
                    were still two English language dailies. I read also the Burmese press and
                    commentary. My task was supervising the translation pool and I would select
                    things for them to translate and there was a lot of comment in Burmese on the
                    other side and one of the most telling comments was here he comes again. They
                    told a story, a Burmese tale of a bully who made the point of brushing his teeth
                    in front of his, who wanted to be known as the sweetheart or a lover of a
                    certain village girl and she would have nothing to do with him. So, he made a
                    point of performing his morning brushing in front of her house so it appeared as
                    if he had stayed there. In effect the comparison was with the Chinese Minister.
                    He was coming down with all this fanfare to make it appear that Burma was a
                    satellite of China. I wrote a dispatch on that visit pointing out the contrast
                    and the chief of the political section and I were on track on that. We both
                    agreed that Burma was very carefully following its own path and was trying very,
                    very hard to stay out of both camps. Byroade understood that very well and
                    agreed with it, but he didn't understand, he couldn't see why they should be so
                    suspicious of us and I remember sitting down with them and saying they have good
                    reason. If you look at the surface. If you know enough to see surface
                    indications and don't know what was actually going on, they have good reason
                    because there were a number of things. There was a group of Buddhist monks while
                    I was up in Mandalay temporarily in charge of Mandalay before I went to the
                    political section had started the first public opposition to the regime and it
                    created quite a stir. We followed them very closely because remember this was
                    '63 and just over the way in Vietnam we had the monks burning themselves. We
                    were acutely sensitive. This was the same group of monks who had been active in
                    the agitation for Burmese independence. The first group of Buddhists monks to
                    become politicized and they had played a role in the Burmese movement for
                    independence, so there was also that angle to consider and consider how much
                    they might do. So, we were, as it turned out that was the same group of monks
                    that were anti-communists and our USIA had been providing I think equipment
                    primarily to help them in some of their anti-communist efforts. Equipment like
                    movie projectors and cameras and things like that. We're not talking about
                    subversive stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, but I mean, very, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We're talking propaganda stuff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Maybe a printing press, we may have loaned them or bought them a
                    printing press. I don't know that side of it. I was only aware of it because
                    some of it had been handled in Mandalay, not while I was there. All of this had
                    stopped before this time. We also had some aid projects that looked funny. We
                    had some Americans who were still wandering around the country and had been
                    there since the end of World War Two and may or may not have been brought in by
                    the CIA or recruited by the CIA as reporting. I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me stop here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: From my side I guess I could say, the monk who came out who started the
                    protest movement, asked to meet me in Mandalay. Met me at the residence of our
                    branch public affairs officer. He and his senior Burmese assistant were there
                    and his interpreter. He made a perfectly straightforward appeal for help against
                    the Burmese government, against the revolutionary government. Why are you
                    fighting communism everywhere in the world and not here? I just without any
                    policy instructions from my government, I just said, we are involved in Vietnam.
                    We have our hands full in Vietnam. We have very limited interests in Burma and
                    Burma is a long way from the United States and we are not going to get involved
                    here. We're just, that's just not in our interest at this point. I told Byroade.
                    I said, I assume the Burmese military intelligence knew about that meeting
                    because they must have been following him and they probably were following me.
                    The only thing is they probably don't know that I told him no. They probably
                    don't know what I told him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Of course he later came down; he didn't want to take that no for an
                    answer and later he came down to the embassy and was given an appointment with
                    the ambassador. I pointed out that he was seen coming in here and the Burmese
                    Government know that, but they don't know what you told him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your analysis, yours and him and obviously the
                        political section and ambassador's analysis of why this government coterie
                        took this very xenophobic line which is really quite different from around
                        there and it remains that way to today?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I think it was that their experience. The Burmese had an inferiority
                    complex in dealing with foreign powers. Their experience was that when they had
                    any dealings with foreigners they got taken over first by the British and then
                    the Japanese. They didn't want to be dominated by our culture. They didn't want
                    to be dominated by us politically and the alternative, it seemed to them, was
                    they would likely be dominated by China which they wanted if anything even less.
                    One statement that I heard quoted and I'm not sure who it was, it may have been
                    Harrison Salisbury.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was a writer for the New York Times.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: He was. He had come to Burma in 1965 or so, and had an extensive
                    interview with Burmese officials and then came back and briefed us on it. After
                    that briefing, I said for the first time I think I have heard the true version
                    of why Burma is doing this. It was either that interview with Salisbury or a
                    later one in which he was equally or almost equally frank with another visitor
                    whom he'd known a long time. The Burmese said, he pointed and looked at a map
                    and he just sort of seemed discouraged and he said, “I wish I had a pair of
                    atomic scissors and I could just cut this off from this continent and move it
                    someplace else.” He feared the pressure from China and yet to be drawn into our
                    train would provoke trouble too, he feared.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any affinity with India?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, the opposite. There was a strong racial prejudice against Indians
                    in Burma, racial and cultural. Because the Indians had been brought in as
                    laborers to build the railroads and to do all the work that the Burmese would
                    not do. Then they stayed and then had taken over and adapted very well and taken
                    over the economy and they were the merchants and the bankers and the civil
                    servants and so forth. The Burmese felt that between the Indians who had been
                    brought in by the British and the Chinese the overseas Chinese, who had come in
                    their own way, they felt that economically they had lost control of their
                    country that way. That was another motivation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Government working to get rid of the Indians and
                        Chinese?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They did get rid of the Indians by forcing those who were not third
                    generation Burmese to leave. There were these forced deportations of Indians,
                    all the while I was there. Well, first they were encouraging all of those who
                    would leave to leave and then they were forcing out the others, they were making
                    it impossible for them to stay. They were leaving; there were chartered boats.
                    The Indian embassy, the Indian government was running just a fleet of chartered
                    boats taking them home. Those who could afford it were flying out.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, we've got this increasing xenophobic country
                        that don't want to get involved with us.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They don't want to get involved with anybody.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a political officer and the whole idea of a
                        political officer is to mix and mingle and find out what the ruling people
                        are doing and you're representing this country which is becoming an anathema
                        to the ruling party. How did you operate during your four and a half years
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We weren't talking to the Burmese representatives of the Burmese
                    government at any significant level. What we were told didn't have much
                    significance. The Burmese who would talk to us had no influence in the
                    government. We were watching and reading. I was reading the Burmese newspapers.
                    We were talking to our Burmese friends. Some of my friends were retired. Some
                    were in nonpolitical jobs, technical jobs that were still needed. We were not
                    talking; they were not in on the political decisions. We were not talking about
                    political decisions. It just gave a feeling for how the Burmese react and how
                    they think and how likely it might be that these policies of the government
                    would succeed. I thought no way with the Burmese, no way. The most
                    individualistic people on earth, they'll never ever bring them to the first
                    step.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was their leader getting his socialist ideas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Of course we had CIA operating and they had sources that I didn't know,
                    but some of them were good. I had access to most of the agency people and in
                    fact they sometimes touched base with me before they went out on a report after
                    I'd been there a while. We knew a lot of what was going on, but not through your
                    normal diplomatic contacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the insurgents?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, Lordy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One always used to hear about the flag insurgencies, red
                        flag, white flag, black flag.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes, the red flag communists, the white flag communists, the
                    insurgents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The mountaineers?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>McLENDON: No, not mountaineers. Some insurgents were in the south and east
                    primarily over to the Thai border which is when that became such a sensitive
                    area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they weren't?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Not mountaineers. Some were largely Baptists, or Christian which is a
                    further division. There were about 14 or 15 different groups, most of them
                    small. The Kia were the big threat because they had at one time had moved within
                    30 miles of Rangoon and had Rangoon surrounded. There were just wide areas that
                    were either no man's land or largely held by the rebels. I remember we had a
                    very bright officer who joined the political section at that time who was just
                    convinced that the government was going to collapse in a couple of months
                    because. We'd go over the map. We were sitting with him and trying to explain
                    why we're not going to say in such strong terms that the government was really
                    in very serious straits from these rebels. He pointed out all the territory they
                    held and then I said, yes, but look at the productive areas of the country. Look
                    where the rice was produced and those are not held by the rebels. I said the
                    areas you are talking about are economically dependent; they are not income
                    producing areas. As long as they can hold that, this central strip, that's where
                    lies the revenue. He was furious. He just thought we were overcome by localitis
                    and couldn't see the real picture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was America, I mean at this time, I mean, did you
                        feel that as long as Burma didn't turn violently red or that the Department
                        of State, hence the American government was quite content to leave it as it
                        was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We were told in not so many words, we've got our hands full, we'd just
                    as soon forget about you. We know you don't feel appreciated and you think all
                    of your reporting is not appreciated and we know you think we don't give you any
                    of our time, but we don't worry or think about Burma.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, of course we are talking about a tremendous
                        commitment in Indochina.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: You're talking about an increasing commitment because the dividing line
                    in Vietnam was '63 with the fall of Diem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there until '67 is that right?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: '66. The end of '66.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: '66. Did you see Byroade getting anywhere?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes, I saw him beginning to get someplace. When Byroade finally got his
                    first appointment with the head of the Burmese Government, I spoke to Byroade. I
                    said, if you're going to overcome this, with ego I don't want to make it sound
                    as if I had to tell Byroade how to conduct his business. Byroade I will say
                    again was one of the shrewdest, the best ambassadors in terms of knowing his
                    people and how to get his message across. Knowing his people, I mean knowing the
                    government he was dealing with. I suggested to him that there were a lot of
                    things that needed explaining. He had better be prepared to explain everything
                    in terms that would be credible. He had to say that what made the Burmese feel
                    suspicious was in fact not directed against the revolutionary government.
                    Byroade spent weeks waiting for his appointment doing the most thorough
                    preparation I've ever seen. He demanded and I think got agreements from CIA that
                    they would brief him completely on everything they had ever done in Burma. That
                    was the promise in any case and he was briefed very thoroughly. So this meeting
                    made a start and then he was able to build on that and he began to make headway.
                    The leader was beginning to at least trust him personally. Then we had an
                    opportunity to invite the leader for a State Visit. Now this was not terribly
                    popular with Washington at the time, but we proposed that it would serve both
                    our interests to invite him for a State Visit to Washington because he was a
                    representative of a thoroughly independent and neutral nation which had gone out
                    of its way to make us feel unwelcome. By inviting him to Washington with full
                    honors we would show to all the independent neutral nations that we had nothing
                    against it. As long as it is genuine neutrality, we respect it and we'll work
                    with it. It would show that he didn't just visit communist countries, but was
                    respected and invited to visit the leader of the Western side. Somewhat to our
                    surprise, he was invited. We got him in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you there when he went?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it go?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>McLENDON: It went very well. Not without your usual glitches. You think
                    everything and everyone is agreed and then they start bringing in the protocol
                    people. They want to overturn everything you've set up. Well, that's what
                    happened. That was the only big problem. It went very well. The leader did not
                    want to wear a military uniform because he was aware that that would not be well
                    received, and he did not want to wear traditional Burmese dress. He was very
                    sensitive to the reaction that Westerners have to a man wearing a basically a
                    sarong and a funny looking hat on his head with a bow on the side. In Burma,
                    Burmese men wearing it look dignified and fine, but in a Western capital, no. He
                    also detested white tie and tails. So, he was making a state visit to Japan on
                    the same trip and they had managed to get agreement from Japan that he did not
                    have to wear white tie and tails to call on the emperor and that was a
                    first.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The Japanese had waived their protocol which is very, very unusual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Court driven, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: So, then after he was already en route to London with the wardrobe he
                    had packed, the White House protocol got in the act. They absolutely could not
                    have a White House state dinner that was not white tie. We said, forget it. We
                    pointed out, well, not in those terms, one doesn't talk so bluntly to the White
                    House. We pointed out that if the Japanese royal family could waive their
                    protocol, surely, surely the White House could find someway to do it. So, I
                    don't know where it was decided in the White House, but it was decided to call
                    it a family style dinner. Since we were all on such close terms, it was a family
                    style dinner and it was so popular that LBJ decided to make that the style. He
                    liked those family style dinners.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, I've heard one of the things at least about later on
                        that the way to make inroads with the ruling group of military officers
                        there was golf. When you were there was golf much of an entree or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I don't recall the details. It may have been at one time, it may have
                    been later, not during my time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, you left there the end of '66. Is that right?
                        Where was Burma with the United States at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I was sad that Burma made such a hash of its economic policies. It was
                    just incredibly bad. I felt very sorry for that, but I felt that we were on a
                    sound course. We were dealing with them in the only way they could accept. They
                    could not at that time accept aid. Aid at that time would have been thrown away
                    unless they were willing to do something sensible in terms of distribution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, well, I thought we'd end at this point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We were doing what they could accept and we were willing to do.
                    Everybody by this time had calmed down and realized that they were indeed
                    neutral and were really fiercely determined to stay that way. We had a limited
                    role and as long as we accepted that it was a very limited role, we could get
                    along just fine and we did. After I left it wasn't long before they were
                    beginning to accept aid again in a limited manner where they had more control
                    and then they began to cooperate on the drug effort.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were drugs a problem at the time you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We did not recognize them so much as a problem, but yes. The golden
                    triangle was in existence at that time and we were aware at that time that the
                    KMT, the ex-KMT.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: KMT?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The remnants of the Chinese troops that had over the border from China
                    into Thailand. They controlled the opium traffic from Burma through
                    Thailand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before we leave here and stop this interview, was there
                        anything else in Burma, any problems or episodes or anything that we should
                        cover?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, it depends on your interest. One thing that was fascinating in
                    Burma was watching the attempt by the revolutionary government to impose these
                    radical socialist policies from elsewhere, imported from elsewhere, on a largely
                    rural, Buddhist, peasant society with highly individualistic ways. Another was
                    comparing the theory of the communist socialist state and revolution with what
                    happened in actual practice and at times it would move you to tears and at times
                    it was just like watching a Marx Brothers comedy. It was hilarious.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, another year has passed and this is December 16th,
                        1996. So, why don't we talk about your time in Burma, some of the events
                        that you saw there and if there are any problems or specific things that you
                        were dealing with?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I arrived four months after the socialist revolution had overthrown the
                    former government. Immediately before my arrival there were student
                    demonstrations in which the army turned the guns on the students. We never knew
                    how many were killed, far more than the government ever admitted. The estimates
                    were backed up by eyewitnesses who saw bodies being unloaded at hospitals and
                    morgues. The number was well over 100 and some estimates over 200. It was a time
                    that the revolution was just beginning to organize itself. I don't think that
                    the revolutionary council came into power with any real framework or idea of
                    what they wanted to do. They wanted to take over the country with a strong hand.
                    They were I think fed up with politicians who could waffle and they had been
                    convinced by some theorists among them that a radical socialist path would fit
                    Burma and would enable them to develop the country more quickly. In fact they
                    had as it turned out no concept at all of how to run an economy or how to run a
                    government. They were simply very good at military intelligence and at ferreting
                    out their opposition and arresting them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was our feeling about the composition of the Burmese
                        army, particularly the officer corps at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The officer corps were not those who had served under British rule.
                    These were the officers who had led the opposition, the nationalist opposition
                    to the British. Those who had led the movement that eventually led to Burmese
                    independence with the British were through. The army had remained loyal through
                    the years of parliamentary rule, but they had become increasingly restless
                    because the policies were causing more and more of the ethnic minorities to
                    rebel against the central government.</p>
                <p>I think they set about writing their policy after they took over and eventually
                    came up with the Burmese way to socialism.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have any or was there any chance for us to have any
                        input at that time? Did the embassy play, what sort of a role was the
                        embassy playing during this period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>McLENDON: We and the other embassies were totally out in left field. They were
                    not speaking to us. They were having nothing to do with us. They made it clear
                    to any government employee that his career was in danger if he was friendly with
                    foreigners. That feeling gradually spread so I would say the majority of Burmese
                    were afraid of us. The Burmese were on the whole very friendly. They would have
                    liked to be friendly and if you could get outside of Rangoon, they were
                    friendly. Army officers had taken over the civilian posts of district
                    superintendents and that sort of thing or at least were controlling them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were there from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: From July of 1962 to December of 1966.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you were there about four years. What did you
                        do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, as one of my colleagues put it, we became expert criminologists.
                    We learned to interpret the newspapers very carefully, looking for very small
                    indications, reading the editorials. That's where my training came in handy
                    because I had spent ten months learning Burmese before I went out and I could
                    read the Burmese newspapers which were far more revealing than the English
                    language newspapers. It was very frustrating. Of course we had intelligence
                    sources and we sometimes had good intelligence through those sources. There were
                    still Burmese opposed to the government. There was basically a lot of popular
                    support for not just the U.S., but Western powers. We also knew that every such
                    contact was probably almost certainly known to the military intelligence and
                    that may have deepened their suspicions of us. For the first couple of years I
                    was there, the leader was really afraid that we were going to try to overthrow
                    him. I think he really thought that. A lot of our former contacts were among his
                    opposition and most of them ended up being arrested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, also, we had had a hand in some action that had
                        taken place. This was somewhat earlier, but there had been some rebellions
                        and the hand of the CIA was not completely hidden.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>McLENDON: If you look back at that time, if you look back at the sixties, that
                    was not so long after we had almost openly been involved in Guatemala. We were
                    much more an activist in political struggles within countries then than we are
                    now. These were the years of Vietnam. We had had close ties through our USIA
                    with the young monks association, and specifically with the group in Mandalay
                    more than in Rangoon. We had because the communists had made an attempt to
                    infiltrate the Buddhist monks or at least so we thought. I think we helped them
                    purchase a press, a printing press to put out their pamphlets and publicize
                    their viewpoint. I, of course, was not then nor have I ever been aware of what
                    our CIA might have been doing. When Henry Byroade came as ambassador, replacing
                    Edgerton in July or August of '63, I'd been sent to take over Mandalay while one
                    of the officers in charge was transferred. While I was in Mandalay some
                    dissidents began their open opposition to the regime. One of their leaders
                    started making speeches in Mandalay that were openly calling for resistance to
                    this in his view communist government. Through his contact with our information
                    office there, he sent word that he wanted to meet with me and we met at the home
                    of our branch PAO, Jim Bradley? Bradfield? I'm terrible with names, worse every
                    year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No problem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: But we met and this person made a direct appeal to the U.S. to
                    intervene and displace this allegedly communist government. I explained that we
                    had no intention, that we had our hands full in Vietnam and had absolutely no
                    intention of taking any action in Burma.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me stop here for just a minute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This is tape three, side one with Ruth McLendon. Yes?</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I even used my Burmese which was not fluent and it was very basic to
                    put it in so many words, our interests in Burma were very limited, that as long
                    as Burma remained independent and neutral then its government was of no direct
                    concern to us. We were sympathetic with the need for a government to follow its
                    own policies. He was polite, but he didn't take my word for it. I think a few
                    months later he came to Rangoon and asked for and received an appointment with
                    the ambassador where he was again turned down. I reported all this. By the time
                    I returned to Rangoon Byroade had arrived but had yet to meet the leader. I
                    think he may have, I think he had been allowed to present his credentials, but
                    there was no way he could get an appointment to sit down and try to talk with
                    him. He was very frustrated because Ambassador Byroade was one of the canniest
                    men I've ever known, canny in terms of human nature and in relating to people
                    and putting people at ease with him. He couldn't practice his skill because he
                    couldn't get his foot in the door. He was very informal with his staff and he
                    would wander around the embassy. At that time I think his wife had persuaded him
                    to give up smoking and he would wander around the second floor of the embassy
                    where our officers were trying to bum cigarettes from everybody around and all
                    of us had been warned not to help him out. He'd just come and flop down in the
                    chair by my desk and say, what can I do about this? You can't, until he is ready
                    to see you, you can't. He said, why is he afraid, what is he afraid of? I said,
                    you don't realize how it looks to him. Then I started listing all of the things
                    that had gone on before and some were going on. We had an ex-CIA stringer, an
                    American, who was a loose cannon still wandering around the country. We had of
                    course the monks; that was the worst. I pointed out all of the contacts that had
                    been made. Those who were in opposition to the military government or who had
                    become opponents who had immediately run to us asking for help. I said, you
                    know, the military intelligence knows very well they've been to see us, they
                    just don't know what we said. If you ever do get that appointment with the
                    leader you better be prepared to discuss our relationship, our activities, our
                    policy in Burma from the beginning. So, he did. He spent those intervening
                    months or weeks informing himself and he demanded that the Department lean
                    heavily on the CIA to brief him fully on everything they'd ever done in Burma so
                    that he was prepared to lay it all out on the table and discuss and answer any
                    questions. He eventually did get his appointment with the leader and he made a
                    reasonably good start and he had a further appointment and did discuss and
                    explain and because, then he was able to bring his real strengths into play.
                    They built a relationship of mutual trust so that in the last year I was in
                    Burma we were able to arrange a state visit for the leader. I don't know how we
                    were able to manage to do that, but we persuaded the White House to invite him.
                    Our point of view was that it would be the clearest possible indication that we
                    wished to be friends with the leader, the neutral, and that we would honor him
                    and respect him, too. It went very well.</p>
                <p>We had been on fairly close terms with Frank Trager who was a scholar, an
                    historian on Southeast Asia and particularly on Burma. The Tragers visited
                    Rangoon a couple of times while I was there and were always invited to the
                    government residence and had dinner with the leader. On the second visit Trager
                    I know came back and reported that the leader really trusted Byroade, and he was
                    practically the only foreigner he did trust.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did we feel as the leader took power and consolidate
                        his power during this time you were there up until 1966? What did we feel
                        the role of the communist Chinese was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We were split on that within the embassy. Military attach�s tended to
                    think that the Chinese were coming over the border any minute. We had one naval
                    attach� who had some sources who were very happy to take his money and tell him
                    anything he wanted to hear. He had some of the wildest reports from northern
                    Burma in the Mandalay area. Our CIA had better sources and their reporting was
                    much sounder. Before Byroade arrived, our charg� at the time tended to go with
                    the military attach� and I know there was some strange reporting coming out of
                    the embassy. While I was still up in Mandalay and when I came down on one visit
                    before I was transferred back I stopped in to talk things over with the
                    political counselor, Jim Martin. I said, some of these reports I've been
                    reading, that doesn't go with anything we're seeing. Jim gave a sigh of relief
                    and he said, “We have a problem here.” He said, “I'm glad you put it that way. I
                    don't feel that way at all. That's not my reading of the leader and where he
                    would head. It's not Burmese and it's not, it just seems out of character.” Our
                    charg� pretty well lost his reputation over this handling of the embassy during
                    that interim period and things settled down right after Byroade arrived. I think
                    we were able to get the reporting back on track. Again, that was where my
                    knowledge of Burmese came in handy. I got back to Rangoon and was able to read
                    the two official versions of the working peoples daily, the English and the
                    Burmese which were very different and the other Burmese language papers and I
                    could pick up on things. I also was able to supervise the translation pool and
                    select items that I thought important instead of leaving them entirely free to
                    select the items that they thought were of interest, I selected some that I was
                    particularly interested in. I think that was probably my greatest contribution
                    to the embassy in those years that I could help them get the flavor of these
                    very subtle, well, not very subtle, but was able to pick up on the editorial
                    comment that was viciously anti-American, but also the editorial comment and the
                    columns that were more subtly, but distinctly anti-Chinese. The headlines in all
                    of the articles in the English language press made it sound as if Burma was
                    right there in China's lap, but some of the other articles in the Burmese
                    language press were much less complimentary to the Chinese. So the report I
                    wrote was, I entitled it something like Warm on the Surface, Cool at the Depths
                    and tried to put it in balance. This was practically my first experience in
                    political reporting because I'd only done a little bit in Adelaide and that of
                    no importance at all. I will always remember that one because Jim came in when
                    I'd turned the draft in to him and he said, “I think that's the best report
                    that's been prepared in this section since I've been here.” We'd come out at the
                    same time. I'd been delayed in the consular section for a while.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>I tended to be sympathetic with what the leader was trying to do and this was
                    later confirmed by Harrison Salisbury that he was just driven with the desire to
                    keep his country isolated from what was happening in Vietnam and to keep it from
                    being taken over by China or become a tool of the Western powers. He was just
                    obsessed with this and the quote that Harrison Salisbury brought back to us
                    after his interview with him was that looking at a map of Asia and he said, “I
                    wish I had a pair of atomic scissors and I could cut us right out of there and
                    move us out in the ocean.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left there in 1966?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The end of '66.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I went back to the Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you doing in the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was assigned as direct, as chairman of the basic officers'
                    course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did that from '66 to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I started out as assistant chairman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. From when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I did that for a year. It wasn't a good assignment for me because I
                    needed desk experience if I were going to stay in political work. In fact, East
                    Asia personnel had agreed to it only on a deal that FSI could have me for a
                    year, but they had to release me to the Philippine desk after a year. There was
                    no desk, appropriate desk opening in EA at the time of my transfer that I was
                    due out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression, you're the first person who I've
                        talked to who sort of had their hands on the junior officers when they came
                        in at one point. What was your impression of the class or classes that you
                        dealt with in this '66 to sort of '67 period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>McLENDON: We had fine classes. We had the ex-Peace Corps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We had the first of the Peace Corps graduates. They were fine officers.
                    Not all of them survived the State Department, the Foreign Service system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess they were too used to being on their own?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They tended to be rebels. We had some and as anyone who has ever worked
                    with the junior, the younger officers, it's such a pleasure watching them as
                    they develop and rise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find, was this too early in the game for them to
                        be beginning about Vietnam or not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, no. We were running officer classes through at about six a year
                    then, six weeks and then we'd have a break of about three or four weeks and then
                    another. We had two classes. We always had evaluations at the end of the
                    classes. At the time I was working with Alex Davit who was the coordinator of
                    the junior officer training and my title was chairman. Alex was a great guy,
                    very upbeat. I was trying to warn them about some of the frustrations and some
                    of the problems and some of the problems that the Foreign Service needed to face
                    and get its act together in terms of management. I wasn't talking policy; I was
                    talking management and administration. I was upset at the second class. Alex had
                    pretty well left me almost to run it myself with Jim Martin because it was a
                    small class and he was phasing out and headed out for his next assignment. I was
                    really crushed at one comment at the end of it on the evaluation at the end of
                    it. One of the junior officers said it gave us the impression there was a great
                    deal wrong with the Foreign Service, but not much we can do about it. I thought
                    now there's a message for you. This was the end of the period of Crockett?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Crockett.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Crockett and then William Macomber took over. It was the end of
                    Crockett and Crockett had brought in all kinds of experimental things. This was
                    the days of letting it all hang out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sensitivity training.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Sensitivity training and that sort of thing. So, I went to one of those
                    offices in the Department and I said, “What suggestions do you have for our
                    training that will overcome this? Give them the feeling that this is their
                    Foreign Service. They have to do something about it and they're the future and
                    they're the ones who are going to need to be making some of these decisions.” He
                    said, “Well, let us organize something for you.” So, what they did for us was, I
                    have to admit in retrospect, not very impressive, but it was a lovely kind of
                    show and tell with a jazzed up video or slides and music and all kinds of
                    things. What made the difference with that class and this was the big class of
                    the year, the summer class when you take in the ones who just are ready to come
                    in from their graduate school or college; I was lucky enough to have Ed Adams.
                    Ed agreed to postpone his retirement to stay on with that class. Ed and I
                    divided the class and our whole approach was to turn them loose and encourage
                    them to get out there and do their own thing and come up with their own ideas.
                    All through that class we kept getting reports back of how blunt they were and
                    they asked all kinds of impolite questions. Not impolite, but hostile questions.
                    They were a joy to work with because as I said a lot of them were Peace Corps
                    graduates and they were not to be treated like children or couch potatoes. They
                    were a fine group and then a number of them were being assigned much against
                    their will to Vietnam because this was the year that the Secretary made the
                    decision, Secretary Rusk made the decision that we were going. We kept getting
                    reports back that Foreign Service Officers made the best district liaison
                    officers, much better than the military. They wanted all of the Foreign Service
                    Officers that they could get and they took some of the best and brightest of our
                    young officers and assigned them there much against their will. We fought that
                    as hard as we could because it was not the assignment they should have had. Some
                    of them had already served in Vietnam with the military. Some of them had Peace
                    Corps service out in the boondocks and they did not need another similar
                    assignment, but willy nilly they were snatched up and sent there. They were put
                    in the military training center, which was based in Arlington Towers for the
                    Vietnam program. That's when we really started to get complaints about them
                    because they decided all right, we're going to have to take on a great deal of
                    responsibility when we get to Vietnam. We'll just start right here. They did it
                    their own way. I went as an observer when they had their war games. This was a
                    Vietnam situation simulation game and our junior officers made havoc with it.
                    The military was livid because they played by the rules, but they played with a
                    far shrewder sense of what was actually likely to be going on in Vietnam. One of
                    them was playing, I remember very well, the role of headman. His role in this
                    simulation was headman of a village and he said if I were a headman in this
                    particular village in Vietnam with the Viet Cong leaning on me I'd sell out. So,
                    that's what he did. They were great. They made good reputations for themselves
                    in Vietnam, but the military never cared much for them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. It was a difficult crew. A little later I was in
                        Vietnam running the consular section in '69 to '70 and I was getting
                        feedback about them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Then you had my graduates.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. It was a little difficult because to be the heart of
                        the beast in the American Embassy. You had people, you had to almost sit on
                        them to keep them from protesting in front of the embassy. They were smart
                        people, I liked them and I always found that whole era was fun because you
                        also got more interesting work out of this crew, but you really couldn't
                        rely on absolute discipline.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, you couldn't except they were self-disciplined. You couldn't rely
                    on discipline which they disagreed with. That was a key division point between
                    the old Foreign Service and the new.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think most of us who went through that era as
                        supervisors kind of enjoyed the challenge if you were willing to play with a
                        challenge rather than to expect somebody to listen to your words of wisdom
                        and say yes sir or yes ma'am.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I never had any trouble with that, did you?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I thought it was great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I liked their brains. I liked their gumption. I liked their
                    creativity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think all of us found, I mean those who like that sort
                        of thing, it was great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I know some more conservative Foreign Service Officers couldn't stand
                    them. I had really hated going to FSI at the time that I did. Quite to my
                    surprise I discovered that I thoroughly enjoyed working with the junior
                    officers. I enjoyed them. I disliked what we were doing to them. I thought the
                    training course was as dull as anything could be, just deadly dull.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the problems I think is everybody wants to lecture
                        to that group and it means that they don't get the most inspiring lectures
                        either.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, that was another thing. I tried to point that out in staff
                    meetings. John Stutesman was I guess in charge of the school of professional
                    studies then and John encouraged new ideas up to a point. He would organize
                    things and he would go preferably to an offsite place for a week together of a
                    think tank. You would come up with all your ideas for doing things differently,
                    but you never got around to doing anything differently. You never got around to
                    the next step of putting this into motion. One of the last things I did in that
                    job was to present my ideas for reorganizing the training course, but nothing
                    was ever done.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you moved in '67, was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: In January of '67 I moved to the Philippine desk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Philippine desk. You were on the Philippine desk from
                        '67 until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Until I went to the War College in '69.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In this time what was the state of our relations with the
                        Philippines?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Incomplete effort to break the colonial ties. I had been in Manila.
                    That was my first post as an officer. We had at the time negotiated the Langley
                    Agreement, which would set up a preferential trade status for the Philippines.
                    No, I'm sorry, the Philippines had preferential trade status from the time of
                    independence. The Langley Agreement was supposed to begin to phase that out and
                    it continued special preferences for American investors, special positions for
                    American investors in the Philippines. When I had been on the Philippine desk we
                    were facing the renegotiation of Langley and we had renegotiated the bases
                    agreement, the military bases agreement, the other major source of problems for
                    us in '65 I guess it was and we were satisfied with the renegotiation. I'm not
                    sure. The Philippines thought they were satisfied until we came down to the
                    finer points of interpretation. The Philippines was then and so far as I know
                    still is, unsure of just how much they want to be independent of us. At the time
                    I was serving in Manila, I think any honest poll of the Philippine public would
                    have shown a majority preferred to remain with us or preferably become an
                    American state. Even those who were most nationalistic in their talk were
                    nervous about being on their own. They still had an inferiority complex. They
                    didn't think they could survive in Asia with communists in control of China
                    without us right there with our military. They didn't like to survive without a
                    lot of assistance from us in addition to the packet that they automatically got
                    with the bases. We were trying to roll back on that relationship and normalize
                    it to put an end to this special relationship. Our military were perfectly happy
                    with that special relationship as long as they needed their bases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then to put it in fairer terms, I mean this was at
                        the height of Vietnam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Oh, this was at the height of the Vietnam War.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Subic Bay and Clark Field were absolute key bases.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>McLENDON: And the State Department we recognized that. We said, once Vietnam is
                    over, then we can normalize, then we can talk about it and see whether we need
                    those bases and see what, but no, we weren't talking. We were trying to
                    encourage the Filipinos to think in terms of ending a special relationship. They
                    talked about it a lot, but they didn't want to. I was lucky enough at that time
                    to work with one of the smartest men I've ever known, Hoyt Price. Did you ever
                    know Hoyt?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. Hoyt Price?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Hoyt Price, an economist. He had his Ph.D. in economics, but above his
                    Foreign Service experience and his depth of knowledge in economics and his
                    understanding of human nature, he had the soundest common sense of any man I've
                    ever run across. When I talked with him I was curious about what we were going
                    to do about the Langley agreement, what our position would be. I talked with
                    Hoyt, what are we going to do to preserve these privileges, he said, “We're
                    perfectly prepared to let Langley lapse and not replace it with any agreement.
                    We are not prepared to give special preferences because the Philippines have to
                    learn to compete.” I said, “What about American investors?” He said, “Our
                    position is that if the Philippines wants investments they will know what to do
                    to make their country attractive to investors.” I said, “Is this going to mean a
                    lot of trouble?” He said, “If the Philippines wants investors, they will have to
                    create the conditions for them. If they don't, if they really don't want that
                    American investment, there isn't a treaty we could write with them that would be
                    worth the paper its written on.” I thought absolutely right. Absolutely
                    right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: We sat down several times with them to negotiate and when it came to
                    the final round, the negotiations collapsed because we wouldn't budge. Their
                    chief negotiator requested an emergency appointment, an immediate appointment
                    with the Secretary and of course was given it to appeal, make this desperate
                    appeal, don't let this these preferences go.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Anything happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, the opposition was firm that on the basis of, of course we were
                    paying heavily for the bases, we paid through the nose for the Philippines, what
                    did they call it? Civil action?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Civil action group.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Group.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In Vietnam.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. We wanted a shopping list. We wanted the numbers of how many
                    countries were actively supporting us in Vietnam and their price tag on that one
                    was just out of reason.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Quite a few Filipinos were working as third country
                        nationals in Vietnam. I mean they and the Koreans were the two big groups
                        that helped us maintain our forces there by working in the shops.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: That is still a major source of foreign exchange for the Philippines, a
                    major cash income for the Philippines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I mean not in Vietnam, but I'm thinking more of Saudi Arabia and places
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there senators or congressmen closely identified with
                        the Philippines who got to you all the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Well, it wasn't that they got to us all the time. The one who got to us
                    all the time was the deputy under secretary of the air force. He was called up
                    about every other day and was livid over something that had happened on the
                    bases. We had a couple of nasty incidents on the bases when I was there. The
                    first one involved a guard at Langley Point Naval Air Station who shot a
                    Filipino who was trying to steal a bicycle and because he was armed only with a
                    45 killed him and you can't do much else with a 45, can you if you hit? It was
                    one of those things. By the time we even had the embassy's cables reporting it,
                    the Pentagon had already been geared up into action and we had Senator Russell's
                    office calling and this senator's office and that congressman's office and they
                    were all hauling out the big guns. The embassy very much wanted to give the
                    Philippines jurisdiction over that case. Under the '65 bases agreement, the old
                    bases agreement had been a question of whether an incident had occurred on base
                    or off base and the '65 agreement was I think the one Japanese agreement. It was
                    a question of whether the military personnel were on duty or off duty, if they
                    were acting in performance of duties, then we had jurisdiction. In this case
                    there was the proviso if his action while on duty clearly exceeded the bounds of
                    his official duties. The argument that the embassy wanted to make was that his
                    shooting the young man as he did in the torso and killing him was excessive use
                    of force. Again, this is where Hoyt's common sense was our strength. When we
                    talked about it with him at first I was eager to go with the embassy to
                    demonstrate that we could give up jurisdiction. We trusted their judgment and
                    Hoyt just looked at me and said, “If you were in the Philippines without
                    diplomatic immunity, would you want to be tried in a Philippine court under
                    those circumstances?” I said, “No.” He said, “The Pentagon will never, never
                    agree to that.” He had a great deal of sympathy with it and when I thought about
                    it I did, too because the young man had a good record. He had served with honor
                    in Vietnam and I think he had been wounded. It was not a case of just a wild
                    drunk or anything of that kind. So, the end result was that we took it. Our
                    ambassador at the time was Governor Williams, Soapy Williams, an awfully nice
                    guy, and just the nicest guy in the world. When we indicated that it was not
                    going to be a clear cut, quick decision in favor of the embassy's point of view,
                    he insisted on coming back to fight his own battle. It just consisted of having,
                    talking to enough people and sitting in on enough meetings that he saw that
                    there was no way. We tried to use what leverage we could to say all right, we'll
                    agree that we have to claim jurisdiction, but you've got to clean up your act
                    and for heavens sake, arm those guards with something less lethal than a 45 and
                    give them clearer instructions and so forth.</p>
                <p>It was a fascinating look into our relations, the heart of our relations with the
                    Philippines and with the Pentagon. Just as I left the Philippine desk to go to
                    the War College, there was another shooting. Oh, I'm sorry, as a result of the
                    outcry over that case, the Philippines renounced the '65 agreement and we went
                    back to the original bases agreement, the on base, off base. Then the next case
                    that came up with a shooting that occurred on Clark Field or Subic, one of our
                    personnel had been out in the jungle area on base shooting, hunting for wild
                    pig. He shot a Filipino who was I guess bare from the waist up and to him he
                    thought he looked like a wild pig. It was altogether a much worse shooting than
                    the other one.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me just stop here.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: It was altogether a much worse case than the other one, but the
                    Filipinos accepted it our claim of jurisdiction because it was on base. They had
                    to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What type of government, who did the Filipinos have at
                        that time and what was our impression or your impression of it, who was the
                        chief of state and what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: This was during the earlier years of Marcos, Ferdinand Marcos.
                    Washington was very high on him because he supported us in Vietnam and he had a
                    beautiful wife and many of our leaders found her very charming. He frequently
                    sent her back to Washington. She came two or three times a year during the time
                    I was on the desk she was there. He didn't come at all. Our former consul
                    general in Manila, Lewis Carson, had retired in Manila and had known Marcos
                    quite well when he was a congressman and wrote for us an in-depth assessment of
                    the man that was quite the most revealing I've ever read of any foreign leader.
                    It was one of the first things that Hoyt gave me to read when I was reading in
                    on the desk and after I'd read it I wanted to sit down and talk to him about it.
                    I said, “I've read this.” He said, “What do you think of it?” I said, “It's a
                    great study, but why is everyone so high on Marcos?” He said, “What do you think
                    of him based on this?” I said, “I thought he's very bright and he's a very
                    shrewd politician, but I don't trust him. This is a man who could end democracy
                    in the Philippines. I don't see any merit to him.” I thought it was all there in
                    that study if you read it closely enough. Again, this was something Hoyt and I
                    agreed on, but we didn't go around trying to smear the chief of state of our
                    area of responsibility. We didn't have the facts. We only had these hunches and
                    then later, began to get the reports from American businessmen who had been
                    there with experience of 30 years in the Philippines. They were saying we're
                    accustomed to the Philippines and its ways and we're accustomed to paying the
                    cut, but this administration is really beyond bounds. We had all of these
                    warnings. That's why I couldn't understand once the Vietnam War was over why we
                    still continued to be so tied to the Marcos regime because by then they had done
                    away with elections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any, was there any change in our attitude
                        towards the Philippines, you were there during a major transition from the
                        Johnson administration to the Nixon administration.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get any feel for a difference?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Because we were involved in the war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: There couldn't be that much difference because as long as we were
                    dependent on those bases. We did what we could to make sure that Nixon was aware
                    of Marcos and of the problems with his regime and to beware of Imelda. Do you
                    remember that Nixon made that trip in July, I think it was July of '69 through
                    Asia and Manila was one of his stops.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, and he went to Guam and this was where he articulated
                        the Vietnamese doctrine I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. Well, of course the Philippines were not high on his list of
                    priorities at the time, but it was necessary for him to stop there because of
                    the relationship. We prepared the briefing papers and our guidelines from the
                    White House were to make them short and punchy and avoid diplomatic language. We
                    took them at their word and tried to do just that, but the sixth floor used a
                    red pencil on our efforts. They wouldn't let me describe Imelda Marcos, compare
                    her to Eva Peron or Madam Nhu.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you getting anything from your Filipino contacts, how
                        they regarded the Vietnam War and our involvement in it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: In the Philippines?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They were terrified of communists. They had fought and were still to a
                    degree fighting their own communist rebellion. In general they supported us in
                    Vietnam, but I think like all of the states that were close to us in Southeast
                    Asia they were becoming very nervous that we weren't doing better in Vietnam.
                    Perhaps not as early as '69. I think I'm reading too much in that from my
                    experiences later in Thailand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then you went to the War College in '70 to '71?
                        Which War College did you go to?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: The National War College.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The National War College.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was high Vietnam then, we were beginning to pull out.
                        What were you getting from our military at that time when you were working
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Almost all of them had had tours in Vietnam, at least one tour and some
                    of them multiple tours. All of them were extremely frustrated with a war that we
                    were not exerting the kind of force to win. All of them were humiliated,
                    chagrined and absolutely outraged at the fact that they had had to fight in a
                    war that was not supported by the public and they were cursed and hissed when
                    they came back to this country. They were supposed to be ashamed of wearing the
                    uniform that they'd always been proud of. All very human reactions. I sympathize
                    with them. I opposed the war in Vietnam. I just thought, I didn't know anything
                    about Vietnam, but if it had been in Burma, I know it would have never worked in
                    Burma. The Burmese might not have been so efficient fighting us, but they
                    wouldn't have done as much good to try and put the wrong kind of government in.
                    Anyhow, no, the dominant feeling of my class and it was from the whole year we
                    wanted to know how we got ourselves into this. What combination, what decisions
                    or combination of decisions put us there in the circumstances in which we were
                    and as each speaker came, with his presentation, the questions would zero in on
                    decision points and why this decision? With each speaker from the point that he
                    had handled, because we were, I won't say traumatized, except that I don't see
                    how anyone could have seen close up action in Vietnam and not have been somewhat
                    traumatized. We were almost obsessed by this and we got some very interesting
                    answers. No one gave us the whole picture, but a composite picture began to
                    emerge of Roger Hilsman on the decision to dump Diem. I've forgotten who it was
                    on the decision not to ask congress to declare war. Oh, Melvin Laird, maybe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Secretary of Defense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes. Secretary Rusk talked about his generation, the generation that
                    saw England go to war unprepared. Rusk had been a student in England at the
                    time, a Rhodes scholar at the time of the Oxford union debate, against a fight
                    for king and country and then saw them go into war unprepared after that. His
                    generation was traumatized by the unwillingness and inability to stand up to
                    aggression. He just didn't see the distinction between that and what was
                    happening in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You then, this would be 1970 you went where, or '71?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: In '70. In August of '69 I went into the War College and in June of '70
                    I went on out to Bangkok.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your position in Bangkok?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I was deputy to the political counselor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in Bangkok from when to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: '70 to '72.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Leonard Unger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Bangkok was one of our largest embassies at the time because it was
                    kind of our political base for the operations in Vietnam and Cambodia and Laos.
                    We had not one political section, but three on the State Department side of the
                    house and we're not talking about the third floor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The third floor being?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: CIA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The CIA.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Which was and of course, they were very large. We had a conventional
                    political section, that was the section I was in and we had a political military
                    section and then we had, what did they call it, public safety? Development in
                    safety? At that time we were deeply involved in helping the Thai government
                    develop its rural areas so that it would not easily become a Vietnam, not that
                    the two countries were similar in a way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I take it we were concerned about rural insurgency?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>McLENDON: Rural insurgency and strengthening village democracy and the economy
                    and all that and we had a lot of our aid that went in that direction. We had our
                    USIA deeply involved. They had a lot of their junior officers assigned in
                    provinces where their main function was not running a branch office, but helping
                    the local government with its public relations. They were inspected about that
                    time and that policy was changed shortly thereafter and they pulled out their
                    personnel from divisions of that type.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, when you look at this, in those countries we had huge
                        political sections and all this and when you think about it, what does it
                        translate into when it gets back to the people who use it. Sometimes one
                        almost has the feeling that we tend to throw people at a problem and money
                        at a problem rather than it's hard to decide what are our interests and
                        all.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I thought that our whole approach in Thailand was sadly skewed in that
                    direction - throwing too many people in and doing things that the Thai could
                    only do for themselves. The Thai aren't that bad for doing for themselves. The
                    government we were dealing with was corrupt at the top, but the king was a force
                    of strength as he is now. The Thai have for the most part been very capable of
                    looking after their own best interests in foreign affairs and they were doing it
                    then. I had the highest respect for their foreign minister and their staff.
                    There was one policy, one policy proposal of ours that I won't go into because I
                    doubt that it has been declassified that I thought was really suicidal, well,
                    not suicidal, but really about the worst thing that we could do. It was being
                    pushed very strongly from the White House and our ambassador had to try and
                    present it there and did. I know I worried about it until I finally read the
                    report of the meeting and saw the questions they asked and thought thank God
                    they know enough to protect themselves.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have many dealings with the Thai government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: No, I didn't. I didn't speak Thai, which wasn't necessary. Most of them
                    either spoke very good English or had their translators, interpreters with them.
                    I did not in Burma develop skills at representation and developing and using
                    contacts. I didn't pick up on it in Thailand and that was fine. Before I left
                    Thailand I made a decision to drop out of political work and return to consular
                    work where those skills could be less in demand and where I thought I did have
                    skills that I could put to good use. I liked political work from the research
                    and analysis point, but I just didn't take to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know how you feel. I stayed in consular work mainly
                        because the development and the work with representational skills, really is
                        social as a long term, but it's a very strong social component. If you feel
                        that that's not your thing, there are other things one can do.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>McLENDON: I had a good friend who was director general of information in the Thai
                    foreign ministry at the time and I wouldn't have even used him. When we were
                    together it was as if we were old friends and classmates and we relaxed and
                    enjoyed each other's company. He knew that I didn't pester him with questions
                    and he didn't pester me with requests.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What feeling, what were you getting from the Thai seeing
                        our effort in Vietnam, this was '70 to '72 really winding down, where was it
                        going? Were the Thai beginning to wonder about our commitment or what were
                        you getting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Yes, they were. I don't know how we handled that with Thailand after
                    the collapse of Vietnam as we pulled out of Vietnam with the collapse of
                    Vietnam, but someone must have handled it reasonably well because we remained
                    close. We remain close allies and there was a time I didn't think our
                    relationship would survive that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your feeling about the CIA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: They had some of the smartest people around and they had very good
                    sources. Our political counselor, Larry Pickering, was a Thai language officer
                    and this was his second or third, third tour I think in Thailand and he had
                    good, useful contacts. He did very good reporting. Most of our other officers
                    were talented. But they were largely wasted because Ambassador Unger was running
                    such a large operation and he felt he had to be informed in detail on such a
                    wide area including all of the neighboring countries that most of our political
                    section junior officers and most of the mid-career officers spent most of their
                    time doing briefing papers for the ambassador and seldom were given the time to
                    go out and develop information for reporting. I thought it a terrible waste.
                    It's just a function of the size of the operation when you're trying to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your impression of Ambassador Unger?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: Again, he was a Thai specialist, fluent in Thai, deeply knowledgeable.
                    He cared deeply about the country. I thought he was too willing to carry out bad
                    instructions from Washington without questioning them. We were so wrapped up in
                    Vietnam and I thought the embassy was out of touch with the feeling back home. I
                    thought they underestimated the strength of the opposition and the fact that we
                    were one way or another going to be forced out of that war and that we couldn't
                    play around as we had before. They were not as sensitive as I thought they could
                    be to how much we used to conceal from congress about what we were doing. This
                    was of course after some of our former allies in congress were opposing us very
                    strongly on Vietnam and questioning everything we did. I was out of step. I was
                    totally out of step at that embassy. That was another thing, another reason that
                    made it the hardest assignment I ever had and I thought the least, I thought I
                    was at my least effective.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, then I thought we might stop at this point. You left
                        there in 1972? I take it you asked for a shorter tour, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I managed to get my position abolished after an inspection. I
                    volunteered it, which did not raise my rating with my boss.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. Where did you go then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>McLENDON: I had to go home on emergency leave because my mother had a very severe
                    heart attack at that time. So, I left even before my travel orders had come in
                    or my assignment had been made. I had to stay at home helping my father with her
                    for three months and then by that time or not long after I got home actually
                    they had assigned me to Paris as chief of the American Services side of the
                    consular section.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Okay, we'll pick it up at that point.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
