<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001516">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Mrs. Joan H. Bartlett </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Program</p>
                <p>Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
                <p>JOAN H. BARTLETT</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Annabel Ebersole</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: May 11, 1990</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is Annabel Ebersole. Tape #1</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I wanted to ask you about your life growing up. Did you grow up in New
                    England?</p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes, I was born in Sudbury, Massachusetts and grew up there and I went
                    to schools near Boston. I went to college in Montreal. That was my first
                    overseas post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when did you meet your husband?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: We met just before I began college in 1955, through a mutual frienHe
                    was at Dartmouth, and we kept the romance going between Hanover, New Hampshire
                    and Montreal, which wasn't too far away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And after Dartmouth, (you said he's a lawyer) where did he
                        go to law school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: He went to Harvard. We got married the week after he graduated from
                    college. And then he went to law school for three years and he practiced law for
                    about two years before joining the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you working during the time he went to law
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I was having babies. I had part-time jobs. Tom was born just as he
                    began his first year of law school and then my second one was born just as he
                    was finishing his last year.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you in Washington before you had your first
                        post?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: We were there for six months, three months of which was language
                    training. So, six months in all and we were off to Paris for the first posting.
                    I was lucky.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your life like in Paris? Did you have help and
                        were you able to see a lot of the city and sites?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes. We had an au pair to help us out. We lived there in very nice
                    embassy housing. We traveled around Paris quite a bit, went out in the evenings
                    and had a wonderful time! And Sam was low enough in posting at the Embassy so we
                    weren't required to do too much in the way of entertaining and so forth. So we
                    kind of lived our own life, which was very nice. We had a wonderful Ambassador,
                    Charles Bohlen, and there was good morale. We were only there for a year and a
                    half and he was asked to go to The Hague. So we had sort of a split posting
                    between Paris and The Hague. So we just rolled over to Holland and began our
                    second posting. Put the kids in the car, the cats and dogs, and drove to
                    Holland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when was your third child born?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: She was born just before we came in the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had three children.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your experience like in Holland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I really recommend Holland as a nice place to raise children. There is
                    a lot of outdoor life there. The Embassy was small enough so that you knew
                    everybody. We knew a lot of people from other embassies too. The Dutch had a
                    tradition called Club de Jeudi, which was a club for diplomats. I think they met
                    one Thursday a month, so we got to know the people from the other Embassies and
                    that was fun and we made good Dutch friends who are steadfast still. They keep
                    writing and we visit back and forth.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the interaction like among the women, the other
                        wives at the embassy? Was your Ambassador's wife nice to work with in terms
                        of helping at functions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: Every time we came to a party, at which we would have a good time, she
                    always said, “Thank you so much for helping out.” I never felt that I had to
                    show up at a party or function anywhere during my Foreign Service days. I always
                    felt they could get along without me, so if something was wrong with the
                    children, I'd stay home. It was a nice group, a very nice group there at the
                    embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Hague strikes me as a lovely place from which to
                        travel to see other parts of Europe also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes, it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you go to Denmark?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: No, we didn't go to Denmark, in fact, we seemed to keep heading back to
                    France. When we were in Paris, we had rented a house south of Paris for a few
                    weeks one summer, and we did that again when we were in Holland. And we went
                    skiing in Austria and Germany and Switzerland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there an American school or did the children go to a
                        Dutch school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: There was an international school. Our oldest two went there. Our
                    youngest went to the local nursery school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did she wear a smock?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: No, I don't think it was a smock exactly. I went to visit the teacher
                    once and I thought my Dutch was quite good and I tried to use it whenever I
                    could. This lovely young teacher was saying to me “Mary is ...” I can't remember
                    the words now, and I said, “Oh, wonderful, wonderful. I'm so glad to hear that.”
                    But I went home and looked it up and what she said was, “Mary has been biting
                    and scratching.” I guess she was so frustrated because she couldn't make herself
                    understood that she was sort of attacking other children so I had to go back and
                    have another longer talk when I found out what that actually meant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Language can trip us up.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: That's what makes life interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you went to Cebu. So you had a drastic change in
                        pace, Cebu is in the Philippines. Did the children like Cebu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Oh, they loved it there. The Filipino's are so welcoming and
                    especially, I think, out of Manila. It's a small enough town, so it's easy to
                    get around. We had wonderful friends there. It almost seemed like one long party
                    when we were there. We would have luncheons, teas and dinners. We had lots of
                    household help. The nice thing I think there too was that a lot of events,
                    especially on weekends, the children were included. We'd have big beach parties
                    and we'd go to a little house with a couple of other people, a local Philippine
                    couple and the Peace Corps doctor and his wife. We all became quite good
                    friends. We built a house up in the mountains the three families together using
                    our old packing crates from Holland as the wood for the sides, and we had a
                    straw roof. We used to drive up there every other weekend or so to get some
                    cooler weather.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have lovely memories and pictures of that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: It was really special. It was called Busay, (the name of the town was
                    Busay). We later, when we came back to Washington, we bought a sailboat and we
                    named it Busay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in any volunteer work at either of these
                        posts, The Hague or Cebu?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: In Cebu I did some work at the Southern Islands hospital. There was a
                    marvelous man there named Dr. Solon who was working with malnutrition. He was
                    trying to set up a program to follow up on malnourished children after they left
                    the hospital because there was so much recidivism (they kept coming back). He
                    wanted people to go and follow up in their homes to help teach them nutrition
                    and health, and so I helped with that.</p>
                <p>I don't think I did any volunteer work in The Hague. One thing I did was I played
                    in an orchestra there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was it you studied violin?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I had taken lessons as a youngster, and I played in school orchestras.
                    I started taking lessons in Paris.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was it international? Was it a small group or an
                        orchestra?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: It was a small group.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So after Cebu, you came back to Washington for a period of
                        five years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And how old were the children by then? Were they all in
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes, they were. I think Mary, the youngest, was just going in the 1st
                    grade.She didn't know how to read, or her numbers or her alphabet. She had some
                    pretty fast pedaling and catching up to do. But she did! So by the 2nd or 3rd
                    grade, she was at the level of her classmates.</p>
                <p>Whereas Tom, who was going into 7th grade and Molly, who was starting 4th grade
                    did very well. There was a tiny little American school in Cebu that really
                    prepared them well.</p>
                <p>When we returned to Washington in 1970, we had some pretty rocky and difficult
                    years. We had been living the high life out on an island in the middle of the
                    Pacific fairly oblivious to what was going on in the world, in our country, and
                    in our family. This was the post sixties, Vietnam, pre-Watergate, busing era —
                    Washington was highly-charged. We were finding that all the fun and partying we
                    were used to abroad and were trying to continue at home had become a bit
                    sour.</p>
                <p>My husband joined AA [alcoholics anonymous] in 1975 and has been a loyal and
                    active member ever since. AA was a large part of our lives from then on and we
                    had three more overseas posts before he retired. But we kept it a secret from
                    everyone but other AA members. I was very proud of my husband: that he addressed
                    his problem, that he sought help and that he continued to “work the program”
                    (For those who don't know AA, this involves, among other things, readings every
                    day, meetings once or twice a week, helping others). Sam has done very well
                    himself and has helped many others in the past 20 years. Yet I felt we were
                    living a double life. (We were so good at covering it up, that to this day
                    people we've known overseas, when they come to visit, bring Sam wine or gin as a
                    houseguest present.) In retrospect, I think it was not a psychologically healthy
                    way for me to live. What he called “protecting his anonymity”, involved a
                    tangled web of deceit. And a lot of the lies and smoothing things over both
                    within the family and to the outside world was for me to do.</p>
                <p>Things are quite different now. There is so much openness about drug and alcohol
                    abuse. However, twenty or so years ago, drinking, even drunkenness, was far
                    better than admitting that one was an alcoholic.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>Ottawa was our first overseas posting after joining AA and it was a good one.
                    There were many meetings Sam could go to and it was an easy transition because
                    it did not involve a new language. We were very happy in Ottawa — we love winter
                    sports, camping and hiking, and Canada had all of those. And I had become very
                    involved in the community, playing in a chamber music group and an orchestra and
                    doing volunteer work at the museum. So it was a particularly hard post to leave
                    and I felt we were really going off into the unknown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you kept your house in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: No. That was one of the hardest things I had to do. Our orders read
                    “Ottawa to El Salvador, with six months language training in Washington.” But
                    only for my husband was language training. The rest of the family was supposed
                    to go to the home leave address. Well, all we had was a post office box in New
                    Hampshire as our home-leave address. Sam sent me down to Washington to try to
                    find a house. And at that time we had three kids and a couple of dogs and some
                    cats. And to try to rent a house, for six months with that menagerie at a price
                    we could afford was impossible. I'd go from one place in the State Department to
                    another, trying to get some help; trying to get someone to tell me what I was
                    supposed to do. I called up a friend and told her what was happening to me. She
                    told me about the newly-created FLO Office which proved to be a great source of
                    help and comfort! We went to Washington as a family in September of 1978 and Sam
                    went to El Salvador in February. Molly was in her senior year of high school
                    about to graduate, so I stayed in Washington with the two girls. Tom was in
                    college. We were all going to join Sam in El Salvador in June.</p>
                <p>But a week before we were to go, Sam called up and said there's been some really
                    bad stuff, a Swiss diplomat was kidnapped and things were getting kind of
                    touchy, and that we had better not comSo I came up here for the summer. He came
                    home in August and we put Mary into boarding school up here. They had a good
                    school in El Salvador, a good high school, one of the best in Central America,
                    but the country was in such a state of upheaval, we knew she might have to leave
                    at any point, so there was no point in starting her. She was going into 9th
                    grade and Molly started college in Canada that fall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was Sam's position at that point in the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: He was the Consul. It was a rough time there. I joined him there in
                    September. Everybody was coming for Christmas including Sam's parents and all
                    our children. Sam's mother was going to bring us a dog. We called her up at the
                    last minute because in November the Ambassador decided that the dependents would
                    have to leave in December. But our children came and we had a funny sort of
                    Christmas. Then on New Year's Day, I drove home with two of the children. Molly
                    went as far as Mexico City and took a plane back to Canada. Tom drove the whole
                    way back with me. It was wonderful. I loved seeing Mexico. When we left El
                    Salvador, we didn't have a guidebook or a map, so we had unexpected adventures
                    and surprises along the way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Had you taken any household possessions to El
                        Salvador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they stay behind with your husband?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes. I think I packed up a few things in case he had to get out fast,
                    he could. As it turns out, he did get out fast. I came out in January. He was
                    due to come out around October. He appeared at the door in August. There had
                    been a death threat on him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there many bombs going off? Did you have to look
                        under the car?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes. Oh, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess one becomes accustomed to it. Did you have a house
                        with security?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: We had a pretty good wall and a pretty good guard who used to fall
                    asleep in his chair every night. We also had a watchdog, which is said to be the
                    best thing to have. Sam always varied the route to work.It was sort of funny;
                    I'd ride with him to work at the embassy sometimes and we'd try to remember
                    whether we turned right or left yesterday. Always trying to figure out which
                    route to take. I worked at the embassy for a while on the emergency evacuation.
                    This was at the same time Iran had taken hostages. So, the embassy was very
                    aware and wanted to be prepared if that might happen. We mapped out the whole of
                    El Salvador and marked where American's lived and planned how we could get them
                    together in case everybody had to get out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the GSO handle the household concerns?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: We didn't get that far.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a very valuable thing to have done.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: One of the things we were trying to do was to go through this huge book
                    of what has to be done in an emergency at an embassy. I tried to convert it to
                    one sheet of paper.</p>
                <p>When we were there, the embassy was attacked and the archbishop was shot. But, in
                    spite of all these terrible things, there were nice things to remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were surrounded and attacked, did the Marines
                        fight them off or did friendly El Salvadorians chase away the rebels?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: It was the El Salvadorians who protected the embassy. They were backed
                    up by the Marines. There was no shooting, but they were surrounded at the
                    embassy. I was not at the embassy at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It takes one several months to stop looking under cars
                        here, doesn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Very much so. And not to jump when you hear a car backfiring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And to feel comfortable in a house without a wall around
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Our house was in a suburban neighborhood and there was a wall in the
                    front. People would build their walls higher and higher. I remember taking walks
                    in San Salvador, which I wasn't supposed to do, but I'd go out and look at
                    people's gardens and pretty soon I couldn't see anybody's gardens because of the
                    walls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were there for only four months?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Just four months.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you came home to Plymouth?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: No because at that time this house was rented out. So I came to Boston
                    and rented an apartment. The department that deals with emergency evacuations
                    was so wonderful! They kept calling up, to see if everything was all right and
                    to see if I was getting my checks on time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, good!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: We've never been so rich! I got allowances such as separate maintenance
                    and I was working as well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of job did you have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I was a secretary to an Education Consultant. It's an organization,
                    which everyone in the State Department should know about. They help find the
                    right school for your child. They do a whole battery of testing. There's another
                    one like it in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So that brings us up to 1980-1981.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Sam took a sabbatical year just so we could pull all the family
                    together. We did stay in this house that year after he came back from El
                    Salvador. He always wanted to be a lobsterman or fisherman, but he was offered a
                    job at Raytheon covering their Latin American distributorship. They made office
                    equipment at that time. He went all over Latin America. He loved it! Then we
                    went to Washington and he worked on Capitol Hill as State Department Liaison on
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So where did you live then?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: We lived in a little house in Hollin Hills in Alexandria. Then we moved
                    to Ireland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He was the Consul General in Northern Ireland?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You must have met some really interesting people!</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes, we did. The consul's house was the only place the Catholics and
                    Protestants were comfortable socializing. The fourth of July party was one of
                    the big events of Northern Ireland. We had 300 people at the house.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The children got two trips per year at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes. It was two a year, round trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Christmas and the summer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Our son, Tom, was too old. He was a schoolteacher at the time and did
                    an exchange teaching assignment in Bristol, England.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which country would you like to go back to for a
                        vacation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: France. We'd like to go back to El Salvador and see our friends there,
                    but I think it's always your first post you want to go back to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Have you felt the changes for wives since the 72
                        Directive? How did it change things for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: It didn't really hit me. I wasn't too serious about being “the
                    diplomat's wife” anyway. I did my own thing. Sam told me in the beginning not to
                    worry about it. He said it wouldn't make any difference to his career. Overall,
                    I think it's a shame they changed because we weren't able to work overseas, and
                    it was something you did as your job. Each person has a different nature, and I
                    wouldn't have been a career person anyway. It's good that they are working out
                    things for the wives who do want to work. It was a part of my identity during
                    that time. The first time I did “representational entertaining” was in Belfast.
                    I did a lot! I liked it. I felt it was a job, although a non-paying one. I got
                    quite efficient; doing all the menus and books. In Northern Ireland, most women
                    I knew did the same thing I did. They lived in big houses and castles and there
                    weren't a lot of servants so they did their own work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do your own children feel about representation? Do you
                        think they enjoyed their experience?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: I think they did. And they are all three very broad-minded. I did feel
                    guilty because our lifestyle was so disrupting to their lives. But around the
                    time of our son's graduation, we had a talk about how well he had done in spite
                    of his rotten life. He didn't think it was rotten. I don't think they suffered
                    too much. What they gained is something deep down in their souls. Unfortunately
                    they never learned to speak a language.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were never at the right age for the post you were
                        stationed at, were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: That's right. Molly went to a bilingual school in Paris for
                    kindergarten. Later she attended a bilingual high school in Ottawa. She started
                    the school year with maybe one word of French and by the end of the year, she
                    was spouting it out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Maracycle?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: This was thought up by an organization that tries to get more
                    understanding between northern and southern Ireland. We started out at 7:00 in
                    the morning in Belfast and cycled to Dublin, which is about one hundred
                    miles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they have lemonade stands?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: They had lots of refreshment places set up in every little town. The
                    mayor would come out and cheer people on. People sat in their houses and
                    clapped. It was a great day. I almost gave up a little beyond the half way mark.
                    Someone came along behind me and said, “Come on, lassie, you can do it, keep
                    going!” That cheered me on so I kept on going. Everybody whooped it up that
                    night in Dublin. There were bands and dances, and other things like that. The
                    next day, we went back again. I went by car. My husband went both ways. It was
                    about 3 days before the fourth of July. I kept thinking about standing up at the
                    reception!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you had just had someone graduate?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: Yes. Mary had just graduated from college. That was a spring we will
                    always remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From 1970 to 1975, did you see much of other State
                        Department wives when you lived in Washington?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>BARTLETT: Not really. We tried to see people we already knew. No, I didn't see
                    many wives, and I didn't have much to do with the State Department while I was
                    there either. I was more involved in life in Alexandria, where we lived.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Sam pleased with his career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I think so. We look back on it as having been a lot of fun. There were
                    frustrations: the red tape or bureaucratic details that have to be worked out. I
                    suppose he would have liked to have been an Ambassador. But you had to take a
                    lot of Washington assignments so that you would be known. We were very lucky in
                    our postings. I think Sam found them absolutely fascinating from the working
                    point of view, and, from the living point of view, I thought they were
                    interesting too. Even that time when I returned back here to the States, and he
                    remained in El Salvador, that separation may have been good. Maybe every 25
                    years, it's good to live apart from one another for a while. You can regather
                    your own self. I think he was ready to retire when he did.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess business had less red tape. The business mentality
                        is different from what we find at the State Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I think it's good when people see it from both sides. Otherwise you
                    have that “pie in the sky” mentality, where you think it's so much better in the
                    private sector, but when you get in it, you find it has it's own problems. I
                    think the thing he misses most, and I do too, are the people in the Foreign
                    Service. The bright, funny, witty, clever people we knew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And when you all become like one another's family when you
                        don't have the cousins and uncles, make you become a lot closer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BARTLETT: I think also, the experience of moving brings a family close.</p>
                <p>***</p>
                <p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA</p>
                <p>Spouse: Samuel</p>
                <p>Spouse's Position: Political, Consular</p>
                <p>Spouse Entered Service:1965Left Service: 1986You Entered Service:SameLeft
                    Service:</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Status:Spouse of Retiree</p>
                <p>Posts:</p>
                <p>1965-66Paris, France</p>
                <p>1966-68The Hague, Netherlands</p>
                <p>1968-70Cebu, The Philippines</p>
                <p>1970-75Washington, DC</p>
                <p>1975-78Ottawa, Canada</p>
                <p>1978-80San Salvador, El Salvador</p>
                <p>1980-81(Boston, Massachusetts)</p>
                <p>1981-83Washington, DC</p>
                <p>1983-86Belfast, Ireland</p>
                <p>Place/Date of birth: Waltham, Massachusetts; February 15, 1938</p>
                <p>Maiden Name:Joan M. Harding</p>
                <p>Parents:Theodore and Elizabeth Harding, carnation growers</p>
                <p>Schools (Prep, University): Dana Hall, McGill University</p>
                <p>Profession: Tour Guide, Ocean Spray Cranberry Association</p>
                <p>Date/Place of Marriage: June 21, 1957; Sudbury, Massachusetts</p>
                <p>Children:</p>
                <p>Thomas, b. 1958</p>
                <p>Molly, b. 1961</p>
                <p>Mary, b. 1964</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Positions held (Please specify Volunteer or Paid):A. At Post: Too scattered to
                    list</p>
                <p>B. In Washington, DC:</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
