<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001537">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="interview">Interview with Mrs. Leila F. Dane </title>
<title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
<name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Washington, D.C., 2010</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for education and scholarship.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or greater.</p>
</editorialDecl>


</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2010-03-16"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
<body>
<div>
<p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History Program</p>
<p>Foreign Service Spouse Series</p>
<p>LEILA (LEE) DANE</p>
<p>Interviewed by: Mary Louise Weiss</p>
<p>Interview date: June 9, 1987</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  This is Mary Louise Weiss, on June 9, 1987.  I am interviewing Lee Dane at her home in McLean, Virginia for the Foreign Service Family Oral History Project.</hi>
</p>
<p>Lee, I know you have lived most of your growing up life abroad, and I wonder what you were doing as a clinical psychologist.  You received just a year ago your doctorate in clinical psychology.</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  I don't have a doctorate in political psychology, but I have a specialty.  What I'm doing right now is my dissertation, and the times of the late 1980s doesn't really have to do with why I got my PhD in clinical psychology.  But let me answer the question, then we can backtrack.</p>
<p>You were the person who told me that Penne [Mrs. L. Bruce Laingen, FSO] was looking for someone to study the Iran hostage situation in terms of the families, and I was able to get the Iran hostage wives to agree that I approach the study from a strictly academic point of view so that it could become my dissertation, my doctoral dissertation.  And that led me into the study of victims of traumatic situationconcentration camps, prisoner of war camps, and that led me into all kinds of abuse fieldphysical, sexual, psychological.  I had to study all of that literature in order to be comfortable writing my dissertation, and so once it got published and I had my PhD, I was all of a sudden a terrorism expert when people needed terrorism experts.  But my desire to be a member of the helping profession dates way back.</p>
<p>I guess every child, every female child wants to be a nurse if they have a certain sense of maternal instinct, and it's strong in me.  When in my teens, I can remember wanting to be a psychiatrist.  I went through a period of wanting to be an actress, wanting to be a journalist, and my parents had all kinds of objections to everything I wanted to be, even a psychiatrist.  However, when we moved abroad, it didn't matter what I wanted to be; I had to be a linguist, and I studied languages.  But I never forgot that I wanted to be a psychiatrist.</p>
<pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
<p>And so when I came back to the States in the mid sixties, I first worked hard at studying statistics.  I can remember that I had inquired around and discovered that at my age to go through an entire doctoral program I would have to get straight A's all along the way.  As a middle aged woman you were not accepted into programs easily in those days.  So I was nervous about statisticI hadn't studied math since I left the United States in my mid teens, and I tried a few statistics courses to see whether I would be able to pull A's on them.  And then I got into my studying as soon as we got back (from India).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you manage to do that?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE: Not right away.  I got a C in my first basic statistics course.  It was tough.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you came back to Washington in the middle Sixties with this in your mind, having lived abroad most of your life, most of your growing up life, but not as a Foreign Service child.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  There was a period when my father. . .  When I first went abroad, my father was a political appointee.  He had been sent to Europe by the military, based out of Heidelberg, to administer the military rearmament of Europe.  However, they decided part way through his tour abroad to switch it from a military position to a diplomatic position.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What year was that, approximately?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  1952.  When he went from military to diplomatic he was moved to Paris, and we came directly to Paris once school was over that year.  I had just finished my sophomore year of high school, and we went straight to Alliance Francaise to learn how to speak French.  We were five children, and my mother had five servants and couldn't speak French, and had many diplomatic duties, and in those days it was “too too.”  They had the white gloves and had to fold the right corner of the calling card according to whether or not your delivered it yourself or your chauffeur delivered it for you.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You were a teenager at this point, and you were very much aware of what she was going through.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Very much.  Yes, I can remember.  The butler would come to me with his inebriated face, smiling, and saying, “Your mother just told me to eat the children and go to bed.”  And I realized that he just needed to laugh about it to someone.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You became an interpreter eventually, didn't you?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, I did.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: Is it in the family [language facility]?  Did she come to enjoy that kind of life herself?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  She was very stimulated by it, very stimulated.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q: You were in your teens.  And then you went to Hamburg?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  My parents went back to the States where my father was working with Standard Oil of New Jersey as soon as this military rearmament project was over.  I finished boarding school in Switzerland and came back to the States just as they were taking assignment in Hamburg.  They asked me to come with them, to postpone college for a year and go to interpreters' school in Hamburg, which I did.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you interested in doing that, or were you doing it for them?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No.  Theirs was more a telling than an asking.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But you found it useful later on; you used it to advantage.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  I think probably with my teenage mentality at work I probably decided to go because I had a French boyfriend I was very interested in, and he was doing his military service.  He would be free to visit with me in Europe, but never would get enough free time until after military service to come to the United States.  So I decided being in Europe I had more of a chance of seeing him.  We got married when I was twenty....</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Where were you married?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  In Staten Island, New York, and left immediately for Europe.  Our first assignment was Brussels.  He was with Singer Sewing Machine Company then.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  His first assignment?  You were together?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  And I met up with Bill [William A. Buell, Jr., FSO] and Jeanne Buell there, whom I had lived together with in Hamburg.  From there we went to Paris where my first son was born, and from there to Dakar, Senegal, where my second son was born.</p>
<p>I can remember being exposed to the term “Fair Ladies.”  Jeanne Buell gave me a lot of Foreign Service wisdom in those early days.  That was the year of the World's Fair in Brussels, 1968.  She used to refer to the “Fair Ladies” who would come over on preparation of the Fair.  She was talking of their superficial interests and how she was not particularly interested in spending her time with the women.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  American women?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did your husband's company have an exhibit at the Fair?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you were a real “Fair Lady.”  Then you went to Dakar?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  The African office was based in Dakar.  There I was a member of the American Women's Club.  We used to knit booties and bonnets for the sweltering Africans.  (laughter)  It was rather irrelevant, but it was fun.  It got us together; kept us out of trouble.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Who requested knitted booties?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I don't know that anybody requested them.  I think that was what we decided to do.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was that your first touch with American women's clubs?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  On a regular basis, yes.  In Hamburg and Brussels I had gone to a meeting now and then.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But you were now a wife.  You were international; you were an American wife of a French national.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
<p>DANE:  Right.  I was an American woman, and this was the American Women's Club.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did they do other things for the Africans?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  My memory doesn't go beyond that.  In Casablanca, where I moved after Dakar, they were very active.  They had a well developed program with local hospitals.  I used to give shots at a clinic that white Fathers gave in the heart of town Wednesday mornings.  They used to make diapers out of the wheat bags for the local hospital.  They did a whole lot of stuff for the local hospital.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That you felt were worthwhile.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  Much more relevant.  Especially the clinic assistance was worthwhile.  It was really making a difference.  I was exposed to very shocking things for an American to be exposed to, I guess. ... I can remember a woman (a) syphilitic woman, coming in to get (treatment).  She had a baby in swaddling clothes who was also to get a shot.  They took off the things the baby was wrapped in, and the nurse nun discovered that the baby was covered with measles.  She got furious that so many people would be exposed to measles.  She yelled and screamed at this mother ... who was so cowed, so cowed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did she cut the swaddling off?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I won't forget that experience.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You had another son born in Casablanca?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Patrick was born in Dakar.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you in Casablanca when President Kennedy was shot?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes I was.  I do (recall) very vividly.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What was the effect of it on the community there?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
<p>DANE:  Shock, horror.  Everyone was just immediately subdued.  I was at a cocktail party when the news came through, and the party broke up right away.  There was a memorial service for him in the cathedral in town which was well attended by the local dignitaries, and the entire international community.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was in India.  There was a tremendous response.  And then you came back to Washington.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's righI decided to go for divorce from my French husband, and I brought my two children back to Washington.  (I) went to secretarial school and trained to get a job as an interpreter, but they wanted to send me as a traveling interpreter.  The stable interpreting jobs with the State Department were for long term people.  You couldn't come in as a stable interpreter; you had to be a traveling interpreter first.  And my children were too young; they were four and six at the time.  So I ended up with a good job as researcher translator with Porter International Management consulting firm.  But it took a while for me to get there, and once I was comfortably stabilized, community members started making sure that Eb [Ernest B. Dane, III, FSO] and I got to know each other.  He was about the same age, also divorced with children about the same age, and he had also lived in Africa.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you meet him through your work?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No, through community members; the Jackson School Action Committee.  He says the only action it ever took was to get us married.  They tried to maintain a higher ratio of whites in the Georgetown public schools.  It was about 90% blacks from other communities that were either bussed in or driven in by their parents.  We left for Madras in (September 1969).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He was a Foreign Service Officer?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  He was a political officer whose specialty was Africa.  The Department in its infinite wisdom sent him to Madras, South India, where he eventually switched to Consular Officer because there was really no need for a political officer there.  There was a crying need for a consular officer that they did not have.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You both had all your children with you in Madras?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  Then I gave birth to Ann in Madras, so we had five children at that point.  The reason we were sent to Madras was because there were a lot of large homes and we were a large family.  The correspondence from the Admin. officer. . .</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  In Madras you were active in American women's activities.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  We also had a very active program of community involvement.  It was a wonderful group of very committed women, very bright women who related very well to the local South Indians.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was it community work?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Community work, hospital work, fund raising.  I did editorial work, wrote the updated “Welcome to Madras,” and I also acted as a lay therapist.  That was a fascinating period, the late sixties.  The Beatles had had an incredible impact on our Western culture.  They went to India and found a guru and explained to the Western world through their songs and their interviews how beneficial it was to have a guru.  All kinds of borderline types were flocking to India in search of the ideal guru, and finding nonexistent spies under their bed, and all kinds of things like that.</p>
<p>There were a lot of people in need of therapy, and I immediately became a lay therapist. I worked under the tutorial of Desai Dhairyam, who was a New York University (graduate).  He had worked eight years in New York before he came back (to India), and he opened a private institution for the insane in a little village south of Madras.  In Madras proper he had Madras Mental Nursing Home where Americans in India who had severe emotional disabilities would be taken.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So there were American patients as well as Indians?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  Madras was the center of the Orient for lobotomy at that time.  Lobotomy is very rarely practiced these days.  However, it was practiced in Madras, so there were a number of people who had developed physically beyond need of hospital who were in the mental nursing home who were recovering from lobotomies.  They were from various parts of the Orient.  Then there were Indians, and there were Americans, Canadians, West Europeans.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you work with the Westerners or the Americans?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I worked strictly with the English speaking Westerners, Americans and Canadians.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How did that come about?  Were you sought after, or did you hear about it through your women's club work?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
<p>DANE:  I was deeply touched by a suicide which was very obviously lack of perceptivity, lack of continuity, and improper, or let's say inadequate policy in the consulate.  At that time Eb was still political officer.  He was acting as consular officer every other day, and the administrative officer was acting as consular officer every day that Eb was not.  A fifteen year old kid came in with the most incredible sob story I have ever heard.  His family in California had kind of fallen apart and left him with his grandparents who became alienated, and he sped off around the world to find his mother who had married a Singaporean and was living in Singapore.  By the time he got to Madras he was suicidal and he had something like 60 cents in his pocket and no psychic energy, no energy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How did he come to Madras?  Had he been in Singapore?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No.  He was on his way to Singapore.  He only had a teeny weeny little bit to go.  He asked to borrow money so he could be repatriated back to the States.  Eb was consular officer that day, and told him that he could be repatriated back to the States, but only after he had made every effort to get himself back under his own steam.  He had therefore to go to American shipping companies and American airline companies in Madras, and be turned down by them before he could be repatriated back, for him to come back when he had done that, and they would set up the paper work.  He came back the next day and got the administrative officer, who gave him the run around, and he went and spent his 60 cents on lye and committed suicide in the hotel that he was staying in, which was a flea bag hotel.</p>
<p>I knew that the American Women's Club would have so happily loaned that young man money, would have made some way available for him to earn the money.  They would have made sure that he had gotten that last lap to Singapore.  It was a very touching story.  It triggered a lot in me.</p>
<p>When I went to the State Department on my return, I started talking about how I wanted the consular officers trained in counseling techniques, and how I wanted a mental health committee started up within the State Department, to kind of take an overview of what was happening, and listen to the stories (and) tell how people can connect.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Had they not had any of that sensitivity training?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  None.  They were trained in the defensive gestures ... what to say if this occurred, and what to say if that occurred.  They were not trained in listening skills at all.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Would your husband Eb, as consular officer, have any more training to help people who came into the consular office than the administrative officers?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I suppose they had been briefly exposed to consular officer training because every young Foreign Service officer has to do a consular officer stint, but in those days consular officers were not trained to do that.  Officers were perhaps slightly more trained because of negotiation training.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Do you know whether that has changed to your satisfaction?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes it has.  I understand that they now do offer micro counselor in the consular training.  It took a long time, almost ten years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was that when you said you had suggested a mental health committee in the (State) Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  (Yes).  That's when I first knew you.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was it just coincidental that that was the year the State Department, as with all other (U.S. Government) agencies, was requested by the White House to set up a drug abuse prevention program?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, if you were talking 1972.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was when it was, yes.  Your being there with a special interest in consular officers having more training, and having an interest in seeing that the State Department have a mental health committee, was at the right time.  Dr. Johnson had just been brought in as the first psychiatrist to the Medical Division.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  I wrote him a letter and sought to have an interview with him, and he was out of town.  I was interviewed instead by a consulting psychiatrist, a local man, whose name I forget, thank heavenone of these men who came in maybe one day a week and had been doing so for maybe five years.  I would say, “Well, have you tried this?”  And he said, “Well, I did mention it.”  And I said, “Well did you push for it?”  And he said, “What do you think I am, a masochist or something?”  Of that type of psychiatric care for our community.....</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  The Foreign Service community?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  Coming in once a week, seeing a patient now and then barely gives you a chance to see the pathologies common to the Foreign Service community.  It certainly doesn't give you the opportunity to look at the issues.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was he the only consulting psychiatrist?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No, there were others and they did evidently meet now and then with members of the Medical Division to discuss their work.  It was at that time that he would make a judgment about improvements that could be made.  But there was never any follow up; there was never any program to see whether anything did evolve from his suggestions.  And he was not committed enough to do it, nor were the others.  I don't want to say with whom else.  So it was definitely high time to push for mental health services within the Medical Division.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you meet Dr. Johnson soon after this?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  (Yes.)  He heard about my effort when he got back from his trip to the Orient.  He did call me in and did start these meetings of the concerned wives, and that's where I met you.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was (the program) at that time called the Youth Development Team, or was that separated out a little bit later?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Gosh.  Well, I'm trying to sort out when Charlotte Recknagel asked me to become Mental Health Liaison for the Association.  My first notes talk about 1974, but if I look at them, I don't see that we had any specific name for that group.  Do you remember when Pat Haynes took over from Frank Johnson?  That must have been in '76.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was abroad (in 1976).  Dr. Frank Johnson started the Mental Health Advisory Committee and he wanted representatives from the Foreign Service community and interagency representatives.  It met regularly, I think once a week.  He wanted a representative from the Association of American Foreign Service Women.  At that time I was on the board, and Naomi Mathews, the president, asked me if I would be interested in being on his committee.  That was how I came to join (the committee).</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
<p>DANE:  He had a pretty well developed peer counseling program for the youth.  I can remember I kept saying that drug use, drug abuse is a symptom not a cause, and we can't go sticking our heads in the sand about causes.  We've got to deal with the issues.  When Dr. Johnson told me that he was being retired in 1976, I became incensed, and I wrote a letter to the editor of The Washington Post.  (It) made such an impact that Dr. George Coehlo, at NIMH (National Institutes of Mental Health), talked about Lee Dane single handedly starting the mental health services at the State Department.  My cousin down on Capitol Hill invited me to lunch.  I'd never even been noticed by him before.  I hadn't realized that it would make an impact like that.  The State Department shook their finger at me and Charlotte Recknageno, it was Mary Buell who was president of AAFSW theI read it to her over the phone and got her phone approval of it (laughter).  Nobody knew what it was going to do.  Psychiatrists went into the budget from that point on.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He (Dr. Johnson) had set up a budget to include psychiatrists in Med here (in the State Department) as well as at (Regional Medical Offices) posts.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  However, there were turf battles.  Medical Division was getting moneys appropriated down to them, and within Medical Division, mental health services had to fight for its share and it just was not making it because it didn't have any people pushing it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Dr. Johnson had to become very bureaucratic to fight those battles, and it was difficult for a couple of months.  We've come along way.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  We certainly have.  There's a lot more to do, though, in terms of the turf battle issue.  When I see the issues affecting Foreign Service families today, it's quite clear that the effects of traumatic stress can be dealt with in out patient care.  They do not need to be hospitalized for that.  Psychiatrists aren't necessarily trained up to notice what is the effect of traumatic stress and what is another kind of pathology with the same symptoms.  And they have a tendency to call it another kind of pathology and hospitalize, which is the worst thing you can do for a person who is simply reacting to traumatic experiences.  And I hope in the fall when I get the institute (Institute for Victims of TerrorisIVT) operational, I'll be able to work with Jean German (director of FSI/OBC).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What institute?  The Foreign Service Institute?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No, the Institute for Victims of Terrorism.  You do know about it, I hope.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, I've heard about it.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
<p>DANE:  Let's talk about the institute later.  We're losing our chronology here.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Well, it doesn't necessarily have to be chronological.  I wondered if you would cover more about the Mental Health Committee which was so active and (elicited) so much enthusiasm (from) onlookers who come in, who were on leave, because it was open to anyone.  I used to invite wives whom I knew were interested.  Many of these women were coming back (from abroad) and getting training in social work.  You chaired that committee at one time.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Towards the end I did.  When you were there, the committee was lacking in power (and was) basically a support system for Frank (Johnson) and a lovely place for us to share our emotions about State Department passivity on the whole mental health issue.  It was a good forum for us to develop the empowerment necessary to become real activists on the issue, and for us to define the specific issues and what could possibly be done about them.  When Johnson was so called retired, he was replaced by a psychiatrist who had been told about us and had been told to keep us at arm's distance, and immediately we were told if we had problems we could go see him about them.  And we fought hard to continue the meetings but the wind was taken out of our sails immediately.  Of course the effect of that was that we demanded power, and we eventually got it.  The course of events was a very significant factor in all that because we were getting into the hostage taking and the Pakistan evacuation (1978).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was in the late Seventies.  To go back a little bit on the Mental Health Committee, I recall before I went abroad in 1974 and was on the committee, interest was falling, presence was diminishing by representatives of the Medical Division.  Very few were showing up, whereas earlier when many of them would be at those meetings (there was a great deal of exchange regarding programs.  Then) gradually maybe one (came) from Med at all.  It was really falling off sharply.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well, the Medical Division wasn't really very committed to it.  (However), the social workers organized themselves independently, and I'm glad about that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Oh, yes.  I thought that was a wonderful trend.  I don't know how active they are now.  But at that timthis was before '7in Dr. Johnson's program (it was) scheduled for the Medical Division (that) at each regional post abroad there would be a slot for a social worker, where there was a regional medical officer.  These would be coming out of the organized group of social workers, Foreign Service women.  (The Association of American Foreign Service Clinical Social Workers).  I don't know how many ever did go out.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  None.</p>
<pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I thought one had gone to Thailand.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  There were various communities that have community health services, but those are independent of the State Department.  (They got kick off money through the State Department.)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  The organized community action programs.  There was a big one in Bangkok, (for treatment of) drug abuse, and a few others.  One in (Cairo) Egypt started later.  I don't know how much of that kind of work they have there (drug abuse treatment programs).  It certainly includes community services and cultural programs.  But Dr. Johnson left in '76?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, early '76.  By that time we were pushing hard for a family liaison office, and it had developed into a concept.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Do you have any idea (who) started (it)?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Back in the mental health action committee, in your days.  Johnson himself was the one who was responsible for that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  One of the interesting things I saw developing in that mental health advisory committee when I came in to represent the (FS) women's association, was the change from (a) focus on drug abuse in relation to the youth.  We had the Youth Development Team.  I took a trip with him to several posts in the Far East and the Middle East, and my duty, I felt, was to search out the role of the women in the American communities to see whether there was response to their demands for employment, but also to find out how much they were interested in drug abuse amongst the youth, the students.  I discovered that many of the mothers, especially among Asian born wives, mothers, were themselves on drugs.  It was part of their culture but not necessarily, because there was a lot of alcohol abuse.  I began pushing to change the focus from just on the youth, vis-a-vis drug abuse, to families.  Parents also were some of the abusers, so it did develop into programs that involved families.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I never got very involved in that original outreach program.  I remember learning about it, but I wasn't involved myself.  When I did the teenage weekend re entry retreats ...</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was the first ever (of its kind in the Foreign Service).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  I did three in '74, '75, '76.</p>
<pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At your home in Great Falls?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  (Yes.)  I think we had our first year some counselor who had outreach to the orient program.  I can't remember his name.  The weekend retreat brought together some kids from various parts of the world and of relatively different ages.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were these American Foreign Service kids who were on leave or had just returned to the States?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  High school age, contemplating high school in the United States for the first time and were not used to school in the United States.  That program was very successful.  I would like to have continued that but it was an extreme drain on my energy and my pocketbook and it wasn't very well supported.  I tried to get it to be taken over by the Department or FSI or AAFSW, and finally AAFSW has taken it over now.  But it had to be.  It was dormant for a couple of years before it got going again.  It's a very worthwhile program.  Teenagers are the most vulnerable age group in the Foreign Service community and they really do need attention on that issue.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At that time were there any youth or teen programs at the Foreign Service Institute?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They did start somewhere later.  (Around The World In A Lifetime, AWAL, was formed in 1983.)</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It started when I started going away to school.  They did have a Landon (School) Teenage Foreign Service Day in the Spring.  It was a luncheon picnic and baseball game, things like that.  I think they had something in the Fall, too.  That was AAFSW activities.  However, I did want to talk to you about the panel that the Association did.  I moderated for the [panel], in the Spring of 1978.  At that time we had the Family Liaison Office (FLO) and community liaison officers (CLO's) in place in not many communities and offices, but ...</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was just the beginning.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
<p>DANE:  This more or less spelled out how we de fuse the LCU's, the Life Change Units.  My whole approach to mental health in the Foreign Service has been one of stress and stress management, and Life Change Units is a concept of Richard Rahe and Holmes and Masudtheir way of measuring one's stress level.  I was very very pleased with this program because it was the first display of an integrated approach to mental health in the Foreign Service where you have the preventive programs offered by AAFSW and FLO and FSI/OBC, Overseas Briefing Center, and we still had the Foreign Service Educational Counseling Center there.  I was a member of their board at that point.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Clarke Slade was (the director).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No, Bernice Muncey was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Yes, he had come into the Department, but he started it.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Then you had the assessment and referral branch through the Mental Health Services and of course the counseling center for alcohol counseling.  It was a pretty comprehensive approach; it was finally developed.  I felt I could close the chapter on activism for mental health within the Foreign Service at that point.  Many different programs have taken place since then.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What was the title of this (program)?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  “Mental Health and Foreign Service Living:  Issues and Answer.”</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That had, I believe, the largest audience of any program.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Oh yes, that was incredible!</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Mrs. (Rosalynn) Carter (wife of Jimmy Carter) had been invited and she sat there in the front row.  That's her thing (mental health).  I'm sure that wasn't the only reason people came.  It was a very good panel.  Dr. Coelho, whom you mentioned earlier, gave a . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  And Dr. Peter Bourne from the White House (Special Assistant to the President) and Dr. Stephen Hersh, (Assistant Director for Children and Youth, NIMH).  And Mary Louise Weiss.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And the first FLO director Janet Lloyd.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  And Joan Wilson, Bernice Muncey, Betty Ann Weinstein who was chairing the Foreign Service Community Mental Health Committee at that point.  The following year, the “Child of Many Nations” symposium was sponsored by the Association of American Foreign Service Women.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was to celebrate the International Year of the Child.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  And you participated in that.  That's the one Dr. Coelho was in; he was not in this one.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Dr. (Sidney) Werkman, too.  Yes, that was very successful.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  The Foreign Service Institute has done a lot of programs since then that are very specific and appeal well and are current.  I like them a lot.  I'm really glad to see them.  That was the first time I really started feeling positive about the programs.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They have these on a regular basis.  This (one) was in (December) 1979.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It was the first one that I felt was really relevant.  They talk about pro active behavior and community skills and management development and that kind of thing.  I had spent two weeks working on a revision of the community skills workshop way back just before Dr. Johnson was so called retired.  I can remember that I didn't touch a penny for it.  He was retired and it was therefore not given the chance to fly, and I can remember my frustration over that.  It was a good exercise.  (laughter)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  In the late Seventies there were several evacuations from our embassies in the Middle East.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I can remember specifically the Pakistan evacuation.  I worked on the Hotline up on the 8th floor.  The Operations Center is this great big room with a huge table and chairs all around it and telephones at each chair and a whole wall full of televisions, each one turned to a different channel.  Half of the table was devoted to Hotline for the Iran hostage situation and the other half was for the Pakistan evacuation situation.  That year (1979) was a very impressive appeal for crisis management.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Who were some of the other people working on that Hotline?  They were all Foreign Service women, (weren't they)?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  On the Hotline they were all volunteers.  The women for the Iran hostage situation (and), I believe, the Iran Working Group, were all volunteers.  There were a number of Foreign Service officers who were in the background back in the communications section of the Operations Center who did communicate with us in certain matters, but we were basically on our own. . . .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were the Hotline volunteers given any guidelines for handling evacuee family anxieties and questions?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  There was no formal presentation of guidelines. You had to grab somebody you thought might know something more than you did and bug them for any advice, and advice that you were getting was basically micro counseling skills advice.  You mainly do your listening, and be soothing about the emotions they are going through, and validate the emotions, and say you'll do the best you can kind of stuff.  There was a lot of dissension.  Mental Health Services was saying that it shouldn't be volunteers doing that.  Some of the Hotline programs in the DC area were already open and running, and run by volunteers.  I knew this full well and I spent a lot of time in the library of George Washington University justifying in print the fact that one could use volunteers, and taking this justification down to Mental Health Services and pushing for the right to use volunteers.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did they accept that?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Never officially.  No.  They just stopped pontificating.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was writing a report for the AAFSW on the evacuations at that time (from Iran and other Middle Eastern embassies) and looking into this hotline program.  Some of us were thinking that training in listening skills would be very useful to be sponsored at the briefing center (Overseas Briefing Center, FSI) for women going to posts so that when such an occasion would come up, they would be able to help (with more skill).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I think training in listening skills is excellent training for anybody, anytime.  It attunes you to a different awareness level.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That Hotline went on for quite a period of time as more evacuees were coming out of other (places).</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  However, my own involvement didn't go beyond Pakistan.  I was already into my PhD training at that point and a lot of pressure was being put on me to detach from my personal involvement at the State Department so that I could develop a more professional approach to what I was doing.  I went from being a volunteer on the Hotline (for families of evacuees) to being an assistant therapist to (Dr.) Isaiah Zimmerman in his group decompression with the Pakistan evacuees and their families.  From that point on I made a concerted effort to minimize my advocacy roles and allow myself to be more professional in any Foreign Service role I had.</p>
<p>Working with Dr. Zimmerman was a very good experience for me, and I would have liked to do a lot more than that.  Unfortunately the State Department Mental Health services is over focused on the use of psychiatrists.  There's no real interest in using psychologists who are really trained behaviorally a lot better than psychiatrists are.  In crisis management kind of things they're really better than psychiatrists.  I think they would recognize that themselves if they were asked to.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It was shortsighted, too.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well, it's like a Republican administration and a Democratic administration; when you're in, you take advantage of it.  It's the psychiatrists who hold the positions.  They just don't seem to want to share any of it with the psychologists.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You worked with Dr. Zimmerman?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  We did group therapy for the Pakistan evacuees.  It's a very situationally specific type of therapy.  Of course it was all volunteer; they all came if they wanted tNobody forced them to come.  It was made pretty clear to them that they would have fewer problems dealing with the aftermath of the evacuation if they allowed themselves to decompress, which is basically talk about what happened to them, and how they felt about it then as they were talking about it.</p>
<p>It's a kind of an interpretation exercise that validates the emotions and gives a reality base to the experience which is detached enough because one is looking at it from hindsight.  And so it balances the experience out, and it takes the anxiety provoking element away from the memory.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were these only wives you were dealing with in the group, or were there any children?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Entire familiehusbands, wives and childreonly those that wanted to come.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How long did you meet with them?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It was two evenings.  We offered to meet further than that; however, there were too few families interested in it, so it was decided that that would be the end of it.  I would say it was five hours, six hours in all.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You and Dr. Zimmerman.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  I had worked together with some of the wives before that in preparation to this to make it happen.  My entire commitment was something like fifteen hours.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you meet in the Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  The prep meetings were in the Department.  The actual group therapy programs were in FSI (Foreign Service Institute).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were those families, the women, (while the men might have been working), meeting by themselves as a group, a support group?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  They probably were.  As we wind up the last session (of this interview) together, I will talk to you about how the Pakistan evacuee situation was reflective of a period in my life where I was being encouraged by my professors to demonstrate my professional development, and minimize if not drop entirely my advocacy roles with the Foreign Service.  And so you saw me go from the Hotline workers, to the assistant, to the leader of the group therapy for group decompression, to detraumatization.</p>
<p>I feel that the Foreign Service is my community.  I feel more cathected [emotionally attached] to the Foreign Service community than I do to my place of origins, Staten Island, New York, or any specific place I have ever lived.  I identify more with the people than I do with a place, although I haven't lived with all of the people of the Foreign Service by a long shot.  They represent the kind of people that I have lived with, and therefore I cathected to them. And it's in that community that I see myself as the change maker.  That is the basis of my original advocacy work and my efforts to become a professional.  I still follow those lines where I want to work with my community.</p>
<pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
<p>I felt when I first started that the professionals back in the early Seventies didn't really understand the Foreign Service mentality very well, and I've discussed that with those who were willing to discuss it with me.  I have not discussed it a lot.  I have not tried to bring it up myself, but a lot of professionals respond negatively to Foreign Service people, especially wives who are seen as still wearing white gloves and still suppressing all of our emotions, and being genteel and congenial and appropriate, and not really showing much vitality towards dealing with the issues that need to be dealt with.</p>
<p>We have somewhat of a Pollyanna image, I guess.  I don't think that's true at all.  I think that Foreign Service living is a very tough lifestyle with all kinds of transitions that we must go through to survive.  The politicizing in the Foreign Service isn't any worse than it is in any other field, but the transitions that we as single individuals, as relationships of husband and wife, are far more stressful than most lifestyles are in the United States today.  Even among the geographically mobile lifestyles in the United States, transitions are fewer, less stressful.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And they are not within a new culture.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well, you get some international business people who are within a new culture, but ...</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I thought you meant transfers within the United Statemilitary going from post to post within the United States.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, that's true.  Those do exist, but they also exist on an international scale.  The transitions aren't as frequent or as severe as the transitions for Foreign Service families are.  And there are more support systems built in; there is no doubt about it.  And so perhaps we have developed this image of the white gloves and the suppressed expressions because of our need to contain.  I don't know.  I just think that most people don't understand us, and don't try to understand us.  I have never worn white gloves.  I can remember when I was arriving in Madras five and a half months pregnant wearing mini shifts and startling the diplomatic community.  But I'm just as much Foreign Service as the white gloves people are.</p>
<p>It's within this community that I do wish to act out my role as agent d'change.  I see the world in great need of the mediators.  When I kind of populate my imagination with people acting out what's going on in the world, I see the warmongers and the mediators, and all the others, and I see diplomats as the mediators.  There are many other kinds of mediators at work in the world today, but diplomats very definitely are mediators.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And trained to be.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes, very definitely trained to.  I was one of the few wives to take a negotiations course at FSI.  I wonder if anyone else has taken it since I took it.  I felt that it was high time that we more or less formalized the Foreign Service wife's need to be able to handle negotiations, so I took a negotiations course.</p>
<p>There is formal and informal training in negotiations.  Most of the wives have the informal training in negotiations.  They are playing mediating roles right, left and center as Foreign Service wives.  And I promote the role of mediation, and we need more and more of it.</p>
<p>My study of terrorism has made it quite clear that many of the experts are talking about how we are entering into a neo medieval society now where subnational conflict is just about everywhere in more or less muted form, and the threat of overt subnational conflict exists even where there is no expression on the overt level.  Those are always opportunities for the mediators.  I think that the role of the diplomat is not going to go away, and that it's a very needed role.</p>
<p>I see that it's very very difficult for the diplomat to negotiate in today's world.  And it's perhaps okay.  It was difficult in the nineteenth century, but people knew it was difficult then when travel was so hard and mail was so long in coming, and people knew the Foreign Service lifestyle was difficult then.  Now people think of it as jazzy, classy, jet setty, and they don't think of the difficulties, the stress of real life everyday living that it connotes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  There are more VIP committees now that are traveling to many posts relating to some crisis or current event, sidestepping, in a way, the role of the diplomat at the post.  People going out from the White House, the Defense Department, pushing aside the role of the diplomat at the post.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  And not listening to what the diplomat has to say.  Well, you talked to me earlier about coping with the husband's frustrations in the Foreign Service, and how that would inculcate in itself that particular topic that you just mentioned, is a big element in coping.  I don't know how many times I have heard wives talk of husbands coming home and complaining about their roles being usurped by the guys from Washington.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And their cables not being paid attention to.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  A lot of our contemporaries elected to leave the Foreign Service before they even would have had a chance to become a senior Foreign Service officer because they realized that it's very hard to do what the State Department rewards.  You can make significant contributions, but it doesn't necessarily mean that you are rewarded, and so it is legitimate to want to be rewarded.</p>
<pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I think it's necessary to continue the incentive, to keep the desire to remain loyal and productive in any career.  I think the incentive of decent pay scales, especially at the mid and lower levels, is lacking now and causing a number of officers and others at that level to leave the Service, or be very discouraged about remaining in the Service, whereas at the very top level there are bonuses. . . at the level where the salaries are pretty decent anyway.The pay rate compared to outside is very low at the lower levels especially.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  We had a good friend, John Graham, who was one of the Foreign Service officers to leave as a mid level officer because of lack of reward.  He started an outfit called The Giraffe Project, which is basically a project rewarding people for sticking their neck out, rewarding people for doing something that they wouldn't necessarily be rewarded for, something that was in the good of the human race.  It's a very loose concept of promoting mankind, and it gives the opportunity to radio news stations all over the United States to have a little upbeat news to give in the morning or the evening or whenever.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  We need more of that.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, we sure do.  We need to tell them.  We hear all about the thefts, hotels that burn to the ground, and abortion clinics that get bombed, and the automobile accidents, and God knows what else.  So it's nice to have a little bit of positive news the way John provided for us with his Giraffe Project.</p>
<p>I can remember when Eb was assigned to Haiti he stuck his neck out and was not rewarded for doing so, which is something he predicted, but was disappointed anyway.  So I sent off a proposal for him to be nominated as a giraffe by John Graham's Giraffe Project.  And so he was, and we have a certificate to demonstrate that he was rewarded in that way anyway.  What he did was just find a way to reduce the horrible waiting lines in Haiti (for visas).  When he took over as Con Gen (Consul General) there in 1981, people would stand accumulating a line about 8 p.m. in the hopes of getting through the Consulate section the next working day.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I remember when David was assigned there, his first post, he talked about going to work at six in the morning with the lines around the block already.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  We're talking about old people, young people, sick people, well people; whatever their condition was, they had to be in line.  Some of them paid someone to be in line for them so they could get a good night's sleep, if they had the money for it.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  This was right after the boat people (came to Florida)?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  It was during the boat people.  As a matter of fact, the boat people situation was reflective of the lines.  As Eb's new system went into effect the boat people situation was reduced.  There was a direct causal relationship there according to people who spoke to him and expressed their gratitude to him for having established that system.  He said that so many people who decided to go the route of the boat people would have waited in line or would have waited their turn if it had been a possible thing for them to do.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  They felt they would get through the line to the end (with his new system).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  A lot of local people expressed gratitude to him and gave him plaques.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He came up with an idea. . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It was just a simple appointment schedule, like today if you phone in, you will get an appointment, your name will be put on the list to be taken care of two or three weeks down the line.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It sounds like a very practical idea, businesslike.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  A very simple logistical thing.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But it was turned down (by the embassy).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well, yes.  He put it into effect because he was Con Gen, but everybody pooh poohed it and said that he shouldn't be doing that; he should be following normal procedures and everything.</p>
<p>I went to the French Embassy the other day to get a visa at the end of this week with my daughter.  They are having the same line problem that is really quite amusing.  Having lived through Haiti I knew just what to do.  You call the French Embassy and you find out when is the least time consuming time to come.  I played it the way they told me to.  They still have a lot of kinks to work out of their system.</p>
<pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
<p>I don't know whether they are willing to or not, but as I came out of the system with my visa, I asked to talk with a press counselor about doing some networking for the Institute of Victims of Terrorism, and the junior consular officer who took me over to the regular embassy, smiled very sophistically when I told him there were ways to reduce the line.</p>
<p>He said, “What, you want to reduce the linwhat for?”  And I said, “Well, you know it is very hot and people get emotional over things like this.”  And he said, “Oh really?  Tell me about it.”  And I said, “Well, you know it's hard on the aging, and it's hard on the infirm.”  And he said, “So what do you think it's like in France to come to the United States?”  So I told him about what Eb did in Haiti, and he listened quietly.  I don't know whether they are going to do that in Washington at the French Embassy.  He didn't make any comments.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You made your pitch.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That was funny to hear that sadistic line of his, getting back at the Americans for making others wait in line.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did Eb or anyone else in the Haiti Embassy try to make a change at FSI in the training to suggest this new form of getting visas?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I'm not aware of that.  I didn't live in Haiti.  We just visited frequently for long vacations.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You and your daughter?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  Ann was a competitive gymnast at the time, and I was writing my dissertation, and we were living in our home in Great Falls, Virginia.  We came down to help him move in in the summer of '81, and we visited two or three times a year for as much as Ann could get off from her gymnastics.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How old was Ann at that time?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It's '87 now and she's seventeen, so she was eleven to thirteen.  She had aspirations; whatever she was telling the rest of the world, she was hoping to be on the Olympic team.  And she was talented enough.  Her knees were presenting a problem.  She had Osgood Schlatter syndrome, and that was getting in the way of her learning the very risky double back flip where you need a lot of knee action.  She was making progress. . . she was winning a lot.  She was identified as a hopeful by her coaches, and so she had every reason for wanting to stay in the States.</p>
<pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  So you kept a home here and visited Eb at the post, Haiti, which was fortunately not that far away.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's right.  It was very close.  I enjoyed it a lot.  I enjoyed going down there;  I enjoyed the Haitian people a lokind of like a Caribbean vacation now and then.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  We visited our son at the time he was working with Eb.  It was his first Foreign Service assignment.  We enjoyed our visits, too.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Haiti isn't doing so well right now.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  At the same time your daughter Ann was competing in gymnastics and at school.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I had finished my course work and passed my comprehensives, which was about the most anxiety producing things I've ever done in my life.  I had all kinds of stress related physiological problems.  (And) I was into my dissertation proposal writing, and the subject was so complex that I had to submit three forms of a proposal before it got accepted.  That's where our university really cracked down hard.  In most places you do your dissertation and then you have an oral defense of your dissertation, which is very anxiety producing, whereas with our university they give you a lot of trouble over the proposal.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  What was that university?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Florida Institute of Technology.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And your dissertation topic?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  It was Coping with Long Term Stress, as viewed through the Iran hostage taking with families.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It also applies to the Foreign Service in general.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, right.  I interviewed fourteen of the Iran hostage wives.  At the time of the hostage taking there were twenty four hostages who were married.  You were the one who was instrumental in having me do my study on this, as a matter of fact.</p>
<pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I introduced you to Penne Laingen.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  She wanted someone to study it, and the State Department wasn't about to study it, at that point anyway, or at any future point heretofore.  So I told her as long as I could make it an academic piece I would be happy to study it.  The only trouble was that making it an academic piece meant fitting the criteria of my advisors, which was for a very focused approach, and this was a subject that just basically had not been studied before.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did it make it very formalized for the hostage families you were interviewing, more formal than it would have been otherwise?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, but that was good; that was very good.  There's a certain sense of security in that kind of formality.  I was using a structured interview approach and a coping scale which measured their everyday coping abilities, and the changes in their everyday coping abilities as a result of the hostage taking.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Were you meeting with them only here in Washington, or were you visiting others throughout the country?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I traveled throughout the country.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Did you meet in groups or did you see them individually?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Individually.  I met with them for two to four hours individually, and during that time they were given the opportunity to speak at length on the various questions I asked, and anything else they wanted to say, too.  I didn't tape.  I felt that their responses would be less spontaneous if I taped.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  (Was it) after or during the time when MED (Medical Services) was also meeting with the hostage families?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  This was after that.  I interviewed them in '83 and the meetings you're talking about took place in '81.  There are some people who still would like the meetings to occur.  Most people aren't thinking about it, but there are a few who would still get together.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It did start a network.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  Of course they had FLAG (Family Liaison Action Group) before I interviewed them.  That was their real network.  That was one of the fascinating things that my study spoke of a lot.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  FLAG was an acronym for?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Family Liaison Action Group.  It was conceived of by Penne Laingen and carried forth by Louisa Kennedy and Katherine Keough.  There was an interesting dynamism there.  I don't know why I feel compelled to tell you about it, but one of the principles of social psychology that I've learned full well over the years is the principle of an emergent leader.  When there is a new concept and individuals are responding to this new concept, natural leadership abilities take over the dynamics, and the emergent leader is the one who captures the leadership.  It's not necessarily the person who was supposed to be the leader, or who conceives of himself as the leader.  And once the concept dissolves that leadership goes away too.  So it was with FLAG.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Does FLAG still exist?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  No, it's gone dormant.  (We) tried to awaken it, as a matter of fact, to take over its corporate seal and its tax identities for our Institute of Victims of Terrorism.  (It) was Moorhead Kennedy's idea, and he's a member of the board of the institute, and he suggested that.  We couldn't find Katherine Keough who was the last known president of FLAG, and the Covington and Burling lawyer who did the pro bono work of establishing it is out of the country.  Everybody else is retired.  We did a lot of work trying to reactivate it, got some junior lawyers to look through all the tax books, and it's not incorporated anywhere anymore, so it must have gone dormant by virtue of no taxes being paid, no forms sent in for several years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was wondering if the present families of the hostages in Lebanon have formed a group, or are active in this same way at all.  Are you working with them?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes, they are forming a group right now as a matter of fact.  David Colette, who is the son of a Britisher, curiously enough, is out in Los Angeles, and he has an attorney by the name of Marilyn Barrett who is drawing up the papers for a group out there.  Their goals are very similar to our institute goals, not quite so comprehensive.  They want a unified public relations approach.  They want to be able to raise funds to cover the cost of counseling for hostage returnees and hostage family members, and they want to develop an information package to be sending to those families.</p>
<p>
<pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Are they getting any therapy now, the kind of counseling any of these families that you know. . . .?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  That's a hard question to answer, Mary Louise.  A psychologist is in a position where ethically speaking (he) is not supposed to be administering therapy without its being a formalized thing.  So therefore the relationship has to turn into a friendship relationship and be seen as a therapeutic friendship.  I know of one psychologist who is actually on the board of this group that is forming out in Los Angeles who has a therapeutic friendship with a few of the hostage family members and one of the returned hostages.  I don't know of any counseling that's going on with them.  I see the need.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Does that group have a formal name?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Not that I know of.  It's just beginning to be.  They have a lot of personality dynamics to work out.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Your Institute for Victims of Terrorism is based here in Washington, here in McLean (Virginia)?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well right now it's in our various home offices.  We are three psychologists and a director of funding and public relations.  We don't have IRS (Internal Revenue) statue yet, and so we can't appeal to major foundations for grants.  So we're working out of our individual offices, and this is the place where meetings take place and mail gets sent to.  It's been a very exciting thing to bring together.  Let me review that a little bit for you.</p>
<p>After my dissertation I had to get on to the final aspects of my qualifications for PhD which is internship, and that took me away from the city.  The Veterans' Administration Hospital changed their laws in such a way that I couldn't do my internship there, and when I came back to Washington I was immediately approached by two psychologists and political psychologists who are interested in terrorism and victimization et cetera.  They approached me about putting together a hostage conference [The Hostages:  Family, Media &amp; Government.  Washington, DC, 4 March 1987], and I was thrilled to do that.  So we did that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That was this year in March?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  March 4.  That was so successful that many people in government encouraged us to continue doing the same thing and to open an institute.  As my friend Don Kennedy says, it's an idea whose time has come, because people fell into place right away to be supportive of the institute.  It was a very emotional thing for me because professionally speaking I still feel very much the neophyte.  I like to think of myself as a student of humanity instead of an expert on terrorism.</p>
<p>I went through these feelings of inadequacy and empowerment as I was getting energy to put the institute together.  I knew it wouldn't happen unless I took it on as a 120% activity for several months.  It got me over the hurdle.  I don't feel like a neophyte anymore, but in the beginning I kept saying somebody with more experience with these kinds of things should be doing that.  Then I would talk back to people and I would realize that I have the experience that's necessary to put this kind of thing together.  So that's where the empowerment came in, and it was a very curious emotional development.  I'll never forget it.</p>
<p>(So anyway) we incorporated just last week, and I'm already getting all kinds of requests to participate in conferences, and I'm getting telephone calls from reporters, that kind of thing.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  It's really rolling then.  At the right time.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Right.  We're very much looking forward to the World Federation for Mental Health Fall conference in Cairo where we will do a major workshop.  We didn't expect it to happen this way at all, but we knew of the conference and wanted to go, and offered to do a small paper presentation or something.  Somehow the Secretary General of the World Federation of Mental Health saw it as tying in with the policy issues.  He wanted to address the peace effort in some way, and Sol Linowitz very much wanted him to address the peace effort in some way.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Is that why it was designated for Cairo?  Does that have a significance?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I think perhaps that's why Sol Linowitz wanted it to address the peace effort.  The President elect of the World Federation of Mental Health is Egyptian this year, Dr. Gamal Abou El Azayem.  It's a mouthful and I'm learning how to say it.  He will be presiding, and the major theme is mental health as opposed to pathology.</p>
<p>This is a radical departure for psychiatrists.  The World Federation for Mental Health is a non governmental organization, and it's an organization that gives various professionals in the mental health world an opportunity to dialogue without representing their governments.  Sol Linowitz saw iI assume this; I don't really know in construction, it's sort of an assumptiothat he saw it as an opportunity to enter into conflict resolution areas or somehow address peace making issues.</p>
<pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
<p>He had already been in negotiations with the secretary general who is Eugene Brody here at the University of Maryland's Department of Psychiatry about how this could happen.  The word had gotten out that the fundamentalist reactionaries in Cairo had already stifled a social scientists' conference because they were going to be addressing various issues involved in peace making that the fundamentalists didn't want to have addressed.  And so it was basically shelved, and Brody started thinking of a 1988 conference that would deal more directly with peace making than the annual conference would.</p>
<p>We presented this idea of talking about the human side of terrorism, and that basically addresses emergency mental health issues and emergency medical servicecrisis management.  Jean German's outfit (Overseas Briefing Center at the Foreign Service Institute) has been dealing with it with these tapes [”Crisis Work; Crisis Worker”, Managing Children in Crisis”, by Marilyn Holmes, Sheila Platt and Mette Beecroft for DS, M/FLO and FSI/OBC, 1986].</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Is Sol Linowitz on the board of this World Federation of Mental Health?  How did he get into the planning?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  You know, I wish I knew.  I really don't know.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  He's a great negotiator.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes he is.  I'd like to meet him some day.  If you know how to arrange that, make it happen.  I'd like that.  I know he's a fellow member of the World Future Society.  I don't know that he's a member of the World Federation for Mental Health.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Will he be at the conference in Cairo?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I don't know.  Rosalynn Carter will.  She will be presenting, and so will President Mubarak, the Egyptian president.  So it sounds like it will be an exciting conference.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Do you know what your paper will be that you will be presenting?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Didn't I share that with you?  Didn't I give you a copy of my letter?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I was going to ask if your Foreign Service focus will be coming in constantly as you work on the broader aspects of mental health, victims of terrorism?</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
<p>DANE:  Oh yes, very definitely.I wouldn't say only Foreign Service; I would say very specifically the Association of American Foreign Service Women.  I can't speak more highly of any association I have ever belonged to than I can of that association in the way they have addressed mental health issues over the years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  That's wonderful to hear.  We've done so much start(ing) with the Forum Report.  The Forum Committee is continuing to address basic issues affecting Foreign Service (people).</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Would you like a copy?  I can give you a couple.  (Her letter to President Elect Gamal Abou El Azayem)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I'd like to know whether after you go to the conference you will have had time to find out how the community program there, the community services program of Cairo, is doing.  That was very prominent in Betty Atherton's time.  She was the ambassador's wife.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I had lunch with Betty Atherton at a cross cultural conference related to therapy a couple of weeks ago, and we discussed that.  I don't know what kind of time I'm going to have for exploring those aspects of the community.  I will make inquiries, but I doubt if I'll be able to do more than that.  We're hoping to do a lot of networking at this conference.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Will there be a representative from that community group and/or embassy or women's association there in Cairo?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I hope so.  I don't know what to say.  I was down at the (State) Department last week, and I left a copy of the same letter I gave you for Tom Valk, who is currently head of Mental Health Services down in the State Department.  He is due to leave in July for Cairo.  Someone else will be taking over his position.  He will be there, yes.  I wanted to discuss with him those kinds of ideas, however he never got back to me.  I wasn't able to see him.  I just left the letter there.  I assume that he's very busy making plans for his departure.  It was considered of too low priority to get back to me on it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  No doubt you will catch up with him in Cairo.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
<p>DANE:  One final point that I would like to address in my review of what Foreign Service life has been like, some kind of an assessment of women's liberation and how it has played itself out in the context of the Foreign Service.  When I talk about the difficult transitions that Foreign Service family members have to go through, I think very specifically of that one in my own personal experience.</p>
<p>Coming back to the States was like a shot of adrenaline in terms of the issues that were at the core of our national attention.  I can remember in the mid sixties civil rights, and then when I came back from India, women's liberation.  I had brought Harriet, a nanny, with me back from India because I knew that I wanted to go to school, and I had to make straight A's the whole way.  I am a family woman, and I knew I couldn't do it without Harriet.  I really don't know how people can do it who don't have a Harriet.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You need to have had a post in India or a similar place . . .</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  To get in touch, to get a motivation.  (telephone bell)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Harriet was with you, was she not, until Ann was out of school and into her teenage independent years?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Harriet left shortly after Eb went to Haiti in '81.  Ann was eleven at the time.  I had finished my comprehensives by that time.  I had gotten all the A's I needed and there was nothing left but the dissertation.  (laughter)  But in terms of what I saw around me in the strugglthe money cruncForeign Service salaries just don't go very far.  It's important for a wife to be able to bring in money.  College education is so important and so expensive.  There are cheaper ways than the Ivy League schools, but even finding comfortable ways is expensive.</p>
<p>There are not too many careers that fit in with the Foreign Service lifestyle.  I've always thought you can be an artist, and you can be a writer, and you can go anywhere with your husband.  You can put those things down and do the entertaining you have to do, and take care of the senators' wives or whatever, and pick them back up again when you get free time.  But you can't hope to make a living being an artist or a writer; you're too far removed from your centers of commerce.  (For) an artist or a writer you've got to be in pretty close touch with what's going with those fields here in the United States to know how to sell what you produce.  As I say, money is the big crunch.  I feel for the women.</p>
<pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
<p>I can remember just as I was about to do the teenage re entry retreat programs, I met with a young woman whose name I've forgotten who had gone into real estate, and she was contemplating not going abroad with her husband anymore because she was getting into a field that could bring money and that could put the kids through college.  With her husband's mid level officer's salary it was impossible to think of a decent college foI think they had three kids.  And then I ran into her some six months later.  She was smiling like a cat who swallowed a canary.</p>
<p>There was a large apartment building and the man who bought it was going to have it turned into condominiums.  He enjoyed her so much that he made her promise to be the one who did the sale of each condominium.  She was anticipating bringing in a salary that year of over $300,000.  What it did to the family relations was incredible.  All of a sudden her husband's salary, which was what they'd been living on from the beginning of time, was a mere drop in the bucket.  Stories like thahow can you expect her to want to go abroad again?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Was he due to be reassigned abroad in the near future?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  I don't remember any of the details.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  Real estate could provide her these things.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  This was commercial real estate, and when you get a good one, you get a good one, and she just happened to get a good one.  But it's been tough for women.  If you choose a career you have to be career minded, and if you don't choose a career, if you think in terms of getting a job at this or a job at that, you're not anywhere near competitive because your resume looks too scattered, and you've got gaps here and there.  People want to know what did you do during that time.  You have no legitimacy if you don't go for an entire career.  So it makes for hard choices.</p>
<p>You factor in (that) you either have to be the old fashioned type who is willing to go everywhere and bear babies and live off a single income, or you have to decide to go for the career, stay in the United States and not have children, almost, because it's very hard to manage the Foreign Service lifestyle and children and career.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  And have it be compatible with the husband's attitude toward (her work) and how it would affect his career.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
<p>DANE:  Right.  It's very stressful.  I remember meeting on a plane one day when I was traveling somewherI sat next to an Indian professor who was teaching at a university in Washington, DHe was married to an Indian professor who was teaching at the University of Washington in Washington State.  They had been married over ten years; they were both very grateful to be in the United States, and very grateful to have excellent jobs that they upheld.  They got together for weekends maybe every two three months somewhere in the United States where they could manage to both be at the same time.  They said, “Well, this is what it is for us now “. . . .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  But they adapted and it was working for them.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Yes.  They both had very positive feelings about it.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  I remember in India meeting more than once several spouses, either husband or wife, who were alone on the occasion when we met them.  When I inquired about the wife or husband:  “Oh, she's teaching in Calcutta,” or “Oh, he works in Madras.”  I got used to the idea that many of these senior professional couples had been at this for a number of years and were accepting it, and it was working for them.</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  You have to remember that they have arranged marriages.  They don't fall in love or infatuation or anything.</p>
<p>The Foreign Service lifestyle has been good for me in view of the fact that I have virtually insatiable curiosity about human nature.  People never cease to fascinate me, and I have loved living in different places and getting to know people, and noticing how they are influenced by culture, how they are influenced by climate, how different aspects of them can be developed simply by relating to them from different perspectives.  It tends to feed my optimism about human nature, and I've enjoyed that aspect of the Foreign Service lifestyle very, very much.  I'm addicted to traveling and I will continue to travel as much as I can (manage in) my future.</p>
<p>I also want to express my appreciation of Foreign Service women.  I have known Foreign Service women more than I have known the Foreign Service men.  I guess it's not surprising that I would want to talk about how I appreciate the women.  I've met some truly beautiful characters.  I've met a lot of excellent role models, shared a lot of deep meaningful conversations, and I think they are creating a viable future for the diplomatic lifestyle, and I like to see that.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  You contributed a great deal already, and I'm sure we'll be hearing more about your work as time goes on.</hi>
</p>
<pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
<p>DANE:  Okay.  We'll keep in touch.</p>
<p>***</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  This is Mary Louise Weiss at the home of Lee Dane in McLean, Virginia, on December 3, 1987, continuing the interview on Tape No. IV, Side A.</hi>
</p>
<p>From your experiences with the American women's clubs in Europe, Africa and India, and doing lay therapy in Madras, you returned to Washington and became a mental health activist in the State Department.  On behalf of whom exactly were you directing your advocacwhich Foreign Service groups or persons?</p>
<p>DANE:  I was interested in the entire Foreign Service community without really singling out.  The whole time that I was the AAFSW Mental Health Liaison on the Foreign Service Community Mental Health Committee, I focused a good deal on the adolescents because the transitions that we go through is what makes our lifestyle so stressful, and adolescence is such a transition experience.  They are the high risk group.  I gave the weekend retreats for re entering Foreign Service adolescents, and I mainly did a lot of advocacy work for them.</p>
<p>Then we were in a period of a lot of crisis with the Pakistan evacuees and the Iran hostage families.  I focused on them because their crisis situation was such that they were truly deserving of the kind of attention that I was able to give them.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  How has your role changed in recent years since you were so active in the State Department?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Well, I feel more professional now, as I said earlier.  I'm not a neophyte anymore, and I'm able to take what I have learned to do in the context of working for the community and translate it to a broader base.  My community now is not AAFSW; it's WFMH, the World Federation for Mental Health.</p>
<p>There's a lot of transition and a lot of crisis in many parts of the world that are just as deserving of attention as the Foreign Service community and the transitions they are going through.  And we as a result of our Cairo conference have developed the opportunity to put together pilot programs along the lines of what is offered through community mental health programs and the National Organization of Victim Assistance here in the United States, and implement this in various countries who are willing to take part in the pilot project.</p>
<pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
<p>It will basically be mental health professionals in the Middle Eastern countries who will be pushing this in the next year and a half so that they will be able to come back to the next meeting of the World Federation for Mental Health in 1989 and give a report on the effects of this kind of program.  I feel very gratified that this is going to happen.  My relationship with Eugene Brody, who is the Secretary General of the World Federation of Mental Health, allowed this to occur, but I also feel that my history with AAFSW has allowed me to take a major part in this program.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italics">Q:  With the severe cuts in the State Department budget now, do you think that the Department can manage to effectively continue its role in supporting Foreign Service families in these areas of concern?</hi>
</p>
<p>DANE:  Not without continued sustained voices from AAFSW.  This group is beautifully placed to play out their role as “friendly watchdog.”  They are removed from the hierarchy, from the reward schedules of salaries, and their capacity to have psychological impact is therefore one of membership concern.  It is not a “Us Against Them;” it is “This is For us All” type of attitude that they can talk from.</p>
<p>If AAFSW continues as they have been in the fifteen to twenty years that I have noticed their activism in mental health concerns, I'm sure that they will continue to pay attention at the State Department.</p>
<p>***</p>
<p>BIOGRAPHIC DATA</p>
<p>Spouse:  Ernest B. Dane III</p>
<p>Spouse Entered Service:1960Left Service:  1983You Entered Service:1968Left Service:  Same</p>
<p>Status:  Spouse of FSO, Retired</p>
<p>Foreign Countries lived in:
1952 53Paris, France
1954 57Hamburg, Germany (child of non-career Minister for military rearmament)
1957-65Brussels, Belgium; Paris, France; Dakar, Senegal; Casablanca, Morocco (as spouse of French national)</p>
<p>Posts:
1965 69Washington, DC (married EBDane in 1968)
1969 71Madras, India
1972 81Washington, DC
1981 83Port au Prince, Haiti</p>
<pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
<p>Spouse's Position:  Consul General</p>
<p>Place/Date of birth:  December 13, 1936, New York City</p>
<p>Maiden Name:  Leila Amante Finlay</p>
<p>Parents (Name, Profession):</p>
<p>Luke William Finlay, corporate lawyer, Exxon (Standard Oil, NJ), Brig. Gen., (Retired);</p>
<p>Annie SueTucker Finlay, housewife</p>
<p>Schools (Prep, University):</p>
<p>La Ch�telaine, Switzerland</p>
<p>Hamburger Freundsprachen Schule, Germany,</p>
<p>Connecticut College for Women</p>
<p>American University, BA</p>
<p>Catholic University, MA</p>
<p>Florida Institute of Technology, PhD</p>
<p>Profession:  Clinical, political psychology</p>
<p>Date/Place of Marriage:</p>
<p>June 15, 1957, New York City, to Francis P. Bohin</p>
<p>November 16, 1968, Washington, DC, to Ernest B. Dane, III</p>
<p>Children:</p>
<p>Scott, born in Paris, France</p>
<p>Patrick, born in Dakar, Senegal</p>
<p>Ann, born in Madras, India</p>
<p>Volunteer and Paid Positions held:
      <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
A. At post: Paris, France: prof. free-lance interpreter, translator, teacher of English and French; Casablanca, Morocco: prof. free-lance inter�preter, translator, teacher of English and French; corresponding secretary American Women's Club;
Madras, India: Editor Welcome to Madras and other AWC publications; lay therapist at Madras Mental Nursing Home</p>
<p>B. In Washington, DC: (Paid) Secretary to sales director APECO; Administrative Assistant to Walker Eisenberg, Wine Importer; re�searcher, translator Porter International Management Consulting Firm; (Volunteer) AAFSW Mental Health Liaison to Department of State; Member of Board of Foreign Service Educational and Counseling Center; Co-Chairman Foreign Service Community Mental Health Comm.; Coordinator, Moderator to Conference of Mental Health &amp; Foreign Service Living: Issues &amp; Answers; coordinator Foreign Service Teenagers' Week�end Re-entry Retreats; Pakistan Evacuees Hotline to Families; Group Decompression for Pakistan evacuees; hundreds of hours of super�vised counseling</p>
<p>End of Interview</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>