<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000130">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Eugene M. Braderman </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>DR. EUGENE M. BRADERMAN</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Horace G. Torbert </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: April 30, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dr. Braderman we're very glad to have you here. I'd like
                        to ask you, if you would, just to start in and tell us how you got into the
                        international economic field, starting whenever you want to with your
                        education, or your first jobs, or even your prenatal influence if you want
                        to. And then we'll go ahead and you can chronologically tell me what went
                        on. But at any time you wish to skip ahead or skip back, it's perfectly all
                        right. How did you first get started in your career?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Well, I'm a Philadelphian by birth and was educated in the
                    Philadelphia public schools and went to college at Temple University in
                    Philadelphia.</p>
                <p>At Temple University I decided, through a variety of circumstances, to major in
                    the social sciences. Most of my work was in history and political science, with
                    a minor in economics.</p>
                <p>In my senior year, a number of my professors suggested that I continue with
                    graduate work. This was the Depression period and jobs weren't easy to come by.
                    So, the prospect of continuing my education was both a desirable one and one
                    that seemed to fit into the general economic picture.</p>
                <p>I applied for fellowships at a couple of universities and was awarded one by the
                    University of Illinois. At the University of Illinois, I was in the History
                    Department. My major was history, my minor was international organizations.</p>
                <p>Part of the reason for selecting that was the presence there of a professor by
                    the name of Clarence Berdahl who was a very well known authority on the League
                    of Nations, in which I had had an interest as an undergraduate.</p>
                <p>I was also very much interested in the problems of Latin America. One of the
                    professors—William S. Robertson—encouraged me to major in Latin American Affairs
                    as part of my work in the History Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I was at the University of Illinois on a university fellowship the first year,
                    and the urging of Professor Robertson was important because he was chairman of
                    the committee that determined who was to get fellowships for succeeding years. I
                    was impressed with him as a scholar, and he was satisfied with the work I was
                    doing as a student. So, we meshed pretty well, and I decided to major in Latin
                    American History.</p>
                <p>I did a study for my masters degree on the Chaco Dispute, a dispute between
                    Bolivia and Paraguay, and also one on the Leticia Dispute, a dispute between
                    Columbia, Peru, and Ecuador.</p>
                <p>And then for my doctoral dissertation, I did a study of political parties and
                    politics in Mexico during the Mexican Revolution, actually starting in about
                    1890 and running it to what was then the present time, which was 1938, when I
                    submitted my thesis and then got my degree.</p>
                <p>So, as you can see, I was deeply involved in international affairs. Curiously
                    enough, political affairs, not economic affairs, were the major part of my
                    undergraduate and graduate education.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had, I suppose, some economic courses.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: I did. The way in which I got into economics as a part of my career is
                    one of those curious things that occurs.</p>
                <p>I received my Ph.D. in 1938. University positions were not generally available. I
                    was recalled by Temple University to teach in a summer session, which I did. It
                    gave me some spending money. I did some research for a period of six months and
                    published a couple of articles, one on my thesis and another one or two on
                    papers I had done while I was in graduate school.</p>
                <p>During that period I was in Washington working on another Latin American project,
                    when it suddenly occurred to me that I was really not pursuing any ultimate
                    career objective. It was nice to have papers published, but it wasn't earning me
                    anything substantial, and my resources were dwindling.</p>
                <p>So I decided to look around. Among the people I talked to was Luther Evans, who
                    was then head of the Historical Records Survey, one of several federal projects
                    under the Works Progress Administration. He decided to hire me.</p>
                <p>He suggested that I go back to Pennsylvania (they had projects in virtually every
                    state of the Union) and become familiar with what was being done. He said the
                    paperwork would take about a month, he'd be in touch with me, and then I could
                    come to Washington.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>In Philadelphia, I ran into some internal politics I was not aware of between the
                    State Director and Washington headquarters. At any rate, the State Director was
                    looking for someone on what they called the non-relief payroll who could do some
                    editing and writing for them, and thought if I was good enough for the
                    Administrator in Washington, I was good enough for the State of
                    Pennsylvania.</p>
                <p>So, he said it would be useful to him, and it would certainly be desirable for me
                    to go to work immediately, instead of waiting without pay for a month. And I
                    did.</p>
                <p>At the end of that period, Washington came through with its job offer, but the
                    State Director offered me the position of State Editor for the state. There were
                    discussions between Luther Evans, the State Director and myself, and we decided
                    I'd stay in Pennsylvania. I did, and a few months later I became State Director
                    and ran the whole project until 1941.</p>
                <p>I still haven't answered the question about how I became a professional
                    economist, because in this job we were involved primarily in local, county, and
                    state archival work. We published a number of volumes as a matter of fact.</p>
                <p>But I knew this was not my career. Certainly, it was not anything that followed
                    from my graduate work.</p>
                <p>I took a number of Civil Service examinations, which were still in vogue at that
                    time, one of which was the junior economist examination.</p>
                <p>I qualified for that, both because of my undergraduate work and because I took
                    post-doctoral work at the University of Pennsylvania in economics. That gave me
                    enough credits to qualify me. Curiously enough, I was soon offered a position as
                    a junior economist with the Department of Labor. I left the Historical Records
                    Survey with somewhat mixed emotions, but it was really only a temporary job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By that time, of course, we were getting into the war
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: You're right. As a matter of fact, in 1940 I saw the winds of war
                    coming upon us, and I volunteered for a commission in the US Naval Reserve.</p>
                <p>In those days, they took an awful lot of time on their investigations, and it
                    took considerable time. Everything came out fine, except that I was turned down
                    for “inability to meet Naval physical requirements,” (my eyes). So, I did not go
                    into the Navy.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>I decided I wanted to do some work related to the war and applied for a position
                    at the Board of Economic Warfare. Among other things, they were looking for
                    people who had had either experience on the ground or knowledge of Latin
                    America. While I hadn't had extensive experience on the ground, I had spent time
                    in Mexico in connection with work on my doctoral dissertation. I also had spent
                    two years of intensive study of Latin American Affairs. I was employed in the
                    Mexican Division of the Board of Economic Warfare in 1942.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that went on pretty much through the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: I worked on Mexico for about a year, and then I was assigned as desk
                    officer for Peru, Chile, and Bolivia.</p>
                <p>I had an interesting assignment. I was one of a committee of three, named by Dean
                    Acheson, who was then—Assistant Secretary for Economic Affairs in the Department
                    of State, to decide what export licenses we would approve for goods going to
                    Bolivia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was basically a question of licensing exports rather
                        than preclusive buying?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Yes. Those activities were part of the charter of the Board of
                    Economic Warfare and then the Foreign Economic Administration, but I was
                    involved primarily in the export side.</p>
                <p>The Mexican assignment was primarily analytical, supplying basic information on
                    the kinds of goods we could get as substitutes for things that were cut off from
                    the Far East and elsewhere: for example—sisal from Mexico versus the copra we
                    were getting from the Philippines and other parts of Southeast Asia, and so
                    on.</p>
                <p>So, I was very much involved in economics. There was no commercial activity of
                    note because it was a wartime situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did this involve some field work? Did you go to
                        Mexico?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Yes, I did go to Mexico on a couple of assignments. I also went to
                    Venezuela on another assignment.</p>
                <p>And I got involved in peripheral things, because in 1943 I became Assistant to
                    the Director of the Latin American Division. He threw all sorts of odd jobs in
                    my lap, one of the most interesting of which had nothing to do with the normal
                    responsibilities of the Board of Economic Warfare or the Foreign Economic
                    Administration.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>The Foreign Economic Administration was essentially a combination of the Lend
                    Lease Administration and the Board of Economic Warfare. I might just say a word
                    about this unusual assignment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, by all means. Say more than a word.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It's an unwritten chapter in the history books.</p>
                <p>In 1942, when Rommel was advancing across North Africa, and the British were
                    retreating, they wanted to set up shop in Tehran.</p>
                <p>The Persians, at that time, were willing, except that they were then hosting all
                    sorts of other immigrants, not the least of whom were Poles who had suddenly
                    been released when the Soviet Union and the Western Powers became allies in
                    1941.</p>
                <p>These were Poles who had left eastern Poland as the Russians took their half,
                    while the Germans invaded western Poland and took their half. Most of the
                    millions who fled or were driven into the Soviet Union perished, but some
                    hundreds of thousands survived the ordeal.</p>
                <p>Then when Sikorsky set up his government-in-exile in London, these people became
                    citizens without a land. Some went into military service, but they were ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were not, however, most of them, part of the Polish
                        Army in the first place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, they had been civilians. Most of the people who did not join the
                    Polish regiments in the Allied armies were women and children and older men. And
                    they had been shipped, temporarily, to Tehran.</p>
                <p>They were also beginning, at this time, to talk about some kind of an
                    international organization that might take care of refugees. It was the
                    beginning of the thinking that led to the United Nations Relief and
                    Rehabilitation Administration.</p>
                <p>As a result of the need of the British for living space in Tehran, the Poles were
                    moved from Tehran to Karachi, several thousands of them. They were just
                    vegetating in and around Karachi.</p>
                <p>It was at this time, in 1943 as I recall, that General Sikorsky came and talked
                    to President Roosevelt about doing something for these people.</p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>The President said he would help financially, but he couldn't bring them into the
                    United States, because he had all sorts of immigration problems on his hands. He
                    suggested to Sikorsky that he might talk to President Avila Camacho of
                    Mexico.</p>
                <p>Sikorsky went to Mexico, talked to Avila Camacho, who said he would take up to
                    two or three thousand of these refugees, with three provisos: (1) they couldn't
                    engage in any activity that would compete with the Mexicans; (2) financial
                    support would have to be found elsewhere; and (3) they had to go back to Poland
                    at the end of the war.</p>
                <p>So, Sikorsky came back and saw Roosevelt and told him what the conditions were.
                    Roosevelt told Sikorsky that he would have to worry about where they go at the
                    end of the war; but that he (Roosevelt) was willing to arrange transport to
                    Mexico and provide the financing.</p>
                <p>For want of a better place to put the assignment (since the United Nations Relief
                    and Rehabilitation Administration was not yet organized), responsibility was
                    given to the Foreign Economic Administration. Since the camp was to be in
                    Mexico, it was put in the Latin American Division—one of those accidents of
                    fate.</p>
                <p>As the function didn't relate to exports, imports, and the usual things we were
                    we doing, the head of the division said to me, as his assistant, “Gene, you take
                    care of it. It will only be a temporary assignment because it will go over to
                    the U.N.”</p>
                <p>Well, when the charter of the U.N. Relief and Rehabilitation Administration was
                    drawn, they were permitted to operate everywhere except in the Western
                    Hemisphere. So, I retained this assignment until the end of the war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was your full time, your only job, or no, just that
                        you're doing it with your left hand?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, that's right. It was one of many assignments. My principal job in
                    this instance was to see that funds were available (we got funds through the
                    usual funding process), and also to see that the camp—when it was
                    established—was properly managed.</p>
                <p>I latched onto a chap by the name of McLaughlin, who had been head of the Relief
                    Administration in the State of California. He went down and was our supervisor
                    at the camp.</p>
                <p>The problems were fascinating. I could talk for an hour on that, but I'm not
                    going to.</p>
                <p>The end result of all of the activity was that, for political reasons, the Polish
                    Government wanted the refugees to return to Poland. They did not want these
                    people to go to the United States.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>I read all the intercepts and letters that they were writing, and knew that
                    almost all of them had some relative or connection in the United States and
                    wanted to come here. I also worked with then—Archbishop O'Boyle and the Catholic
                    Relief Services who were willing to sponsor those who didn't have connections.
                    So, in the end, after the war, they did come mostly to the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Meanwhile, did you provide work for them, or were they
                        just in internment camps and on the dole?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: We had just a few acres of land. Most of these people were farmers,
                    but it was not possible to farm. So they developed, essentially, an arts and
                    crafts program and a holding operation. It was not a very joyful experience for
                    them. I visited the camp in Mexico. It was located near Le�n, about 250 miles
                    northwest of Mexico City.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd never heard of this operation before, so I think it's
                        very valuable to have.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It was suggested that I write a book or an article, but I just never
                    got around to doing it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, we're getting it. So, the net result of this was
                        that we got several thousand additional Polish immigrants at the end of the
                        war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Meanwhile, I was working on various assignments in assisting the
                    Director in running the Latin American Division of the Foreign Economic
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was running the Foreign Economic Administration? Who
                        was the head man at that time? Wasn't General Maxwell ... No, he was
                        ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, that may have been earlier. Henry Wallace was head when we were
                    the Board of Economic Warfare. President Roosevelt appointed Leo T. Crowley to
                    head the Foreign Economic Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This lasted essentially through the war?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Lasted through the war. At the end of the war, there was a question of
                    what to do with the functions that were being performed by the war agencies in
                    general, and the Foreign Economy Administration in particular.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>Many of the functions had no peacetime purpose. Their usefulness had, hopefully,
                    served us well. But there were a number of functions that were to be continued.
                    And these were divided among several permanent agencies, the largest segments of
                    which went to the State and Commerce Departments.</p>
                <p>My natural inclination at the time (if you recall my educational experience, you
                    will see why) was to be in the political end of things. I initially opted to go
                    to the State Department.</p>
                <p>My boss, whose name was George Bell, was given the job of Associate Director of a
                    newly created Office of International Trade in the Commerce Department. This was
                    to be the international economic arm of the Commerce Department. He was given
                    the number two job, and he urged me to come with him and I finally decided to do
                    that.</p>
                <p>So that was the reason I went to the Commerce Department instead of the State
                    Department. In both cases, at State and Commerce, most of the FEA functions and
                    personnel were essentially liquidated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your initial specific function there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: George Bell (since I was still an assistant to him, my functions
                    derived from his functions) was an Associate Director of the Office of
                    International Trade. Henry Wallace was Secretary of Commerce. The Department of
                    Commerce had a grand design on the handling of most international economic and
                    commercial functions.</p>
                <p>This was the beginning of one of many disputes among the departments as to who
                    would do what. I got into the middle of many of these because my boss ...</p>
                <p>I've got to go back one step. In 1946 (another story), there was a new Foreign
                    Service Act. The Foreign Service Act established a Board of the Foreign Service.
                    My boss was named the Commerce Department representative on the Board of the
                    Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>The Board of the Foreign Service, like so many boards, decided to set up a
                    subsidiary body, which was called the Staff Board, to do its day-to-day work. I
                    was named Commerce Department representative on the Staff Board.</p>
                <p>It became our duty, under the direction, primarily, of Tyler Thompson, who was
                    chief of the Planning Division in the Department of State, to develop the rules
                    and regulations that would implement the Foreign Service Act of 1946. And for
                    many months I spent about 50 percent of my time working on Foreign
                    Service-related activities.</p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>During the course of that activity, the Director General decided it would be a
                    good thing to have somebody go overseas to explain the Foreign Service Act to
                    our missions. He thought, initially, Western Europe might be the best place to
                    start.</p>
                <p>Our new Secretary of Commerce, Averell Harriman, was one of those that believed
                    the United States had to do some things to help Europe recover. The Marshall
                    Plan was just gestating, but hadn't developed yet.</p>
                <p>One of the things that was done was to make a conscious decision on the part of
                    the United States, with the State and Commerce Departments playing leading
                    roles, to change the focus of our Foreign Service commercial activities from one
                    of promoting exports to that of encouraging imports.</p>
                <p>A colleague and I were named as a team of two to go to Western Europe to tell
                    Western European governments that the United States was prepared to do this. The
                    Director General of the Foreign Service, Christian Ravndal, decided this would
                    be a good opportunity to use the two of us for the function he had in mind,
                    which was to explain the Foreign Service Act to our missions overseas.</p>
                <p>So, in the fall of 1947, Emil Schnellbacher and I went to Europe. We visited 13
                    Western European countries in three months, with these two functions in
                    mind.</p>
                <p>Ambassadors arranged meetings initially for us with all of the staff, and then
                    smaller sessions followed.</p>
                <p>We developed and perfected what came to be the structure of missions for many
                    years thereafter—the division of an Embassy into the various sections: a
                    political section; an economic section, which later became an economic and
                    commercial section; a consular section; an administrative section; and a
                    cultural section. At that time the cultural function was in the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Organizational questions were of greater interest to the politically-appointed
                    ambassadors than to the careerists because the latter knew their way around.
                    But, we went through the gamut of questions and issues raised by the new Foreign
                    Service Act.</p>
                <p>We also had meetings with foreign government and business people about the new US
                    initiative encouraging imports. It was a revolutionary change in Government
                    policy and it got a tremendous positive response wherever we went, including
                    wide press coverage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time had the Marshall Plan been passed?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No. This was '47. General Marshall made his speech in June of '48 as I
                    recall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, you were very deeply involved in the
                        Foreign Service long before you were directly involved in the State
                        Department. I think that's great. Now you stayed on this for...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: I stayed on it until 1950. I suppose part of the initiative for the
                    next change was McCarthyism.</p>
                <p>The head of the Far Eastern Division in the Commerce Department was one of those
                    who was accused of various things, so far as I recall, never proven. At any
                    rate, he was induced to leave. Somebody had to be named to take over that
                    division temporarily, and I was asked to do that. I became Acting Director of
                    the Far Eastern Division.</p>
                <p>So, I moved from being a “Latin American expert” and a generalist on exports and
                    imports and trade to a new arena.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And in a new part of the world.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: A new part of the world about which I knew virtually nothing. That was
                    part of the reason for this assignment as far as the senior officers were
                    concerned: I had not “lost China.” I barely knew where it was.</p>
                <p>That temporary assignment blossomed in a great many ways. I spent the next ten
                    years as head of the Far Eastern Division. That was, for me, a challenging
                    experience and a fascinating one because I resolved to learn more about the
                    economic and commercial situation in the Far East than anybody else in the
                    United States. That was my objective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And probably wasn't all that hard in those days. It was
                        hard work, but there weren't that many authorities.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: One of the things that ensued was that I provided continuity since
                    Foreign Service officers moved from assignment to assignment. For example, the
                    US was a member of the Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East (ECAFE),
                    one of the United Nations regional organizations.</p>
                <p>There were annual meetings of the commission itself, and many meetings in
                    between. The State Department designations to all US delegations changed fairly
                    rapidly because of changing assignments in the State Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>As a result, even though I was in the Commerce Department, I provided “the
                    memory” for the US delegation for a long time. I think I went to something like
                    24 meetings of the Commission and various committees of the Economic Commission
                    for Asia and the Far East, over a 10-year period—probably more than anybody in
                    the history of the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a lot of meetings!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That's a lot of meetings. Through that process and other assignments
                    requiring travel in Asia, I obviously was in the field a great deal. I would be
                    away sometimes as much as two or three months at a stretch.</p>
                <p>I naturally got to know our missions very, very well. I knew virtually everybody
                    who served anywhere in South Asia and the Far East. Many of the friendships that
                    were developed then, I'm happy to say, I have to this day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now do you want to hit some of the high spots during
                        that long period, the things that you feel were the most significant
                        accomplishments or most interesting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Most of the work that was performed during the '50s by a regional
                    division, any regional division, of which mine was one in the Commerce
                    Department, was that of servicing American business, keeping in touch with both
                    our Domestic Field Service in the United States and the Foreign Service,
                    particularly the officers who worked on economic and commercial matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there also a function of sort of tutelage of the
                        Japanese, we'll say, or any of the other eastern powers in getting started
                        because they were such poor, downtrodden ...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: There was. One of the things the Commerce Department did, as part of
                    its function, was to send trade missions abroad. In the early 1950s, those trade
                    missions were oriented to promoting imports. That changed, obviously, at a later
                    time.</p>
                <p>I headed two of those missions, one to Japan, in 1956 and another to the
                    Philippines in 1960. On the mission to Japan, we had an economic officer from
                    the embassy by the name of Owen Zurhellen, a Japanese local employee, and five
                    American businessmen. I was the only one from Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were five American businessmen?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Five American businessmen. They were prominent in different fields:
                    one was a banker, one was a retailer, one was in transportation, one was in
                    marketing.</p>
                <p>The whole idea was to help discuss with the Japanese the nature of the US market
                    and what they needed to do to penetrate the market (lessons which they learned
                    all too well).</p>
                <p>We spent eight weeks in Japan. We visited all of the four major islands, some 18
                    different cities and towns. We got to know a great deal about the Japanese,
                    though, despite 19 visits to Japan, I still feel I don't know the Japanese very
                    well. Absorbing Japanese culture is very difficult, despite, some of the
                    superficial things one learns. It was a fascinating experience for all of
                    us.</p>
                <p>We were not the only mission that went to Japan, but you could say that these
                    missions were very successful in view of what the Japanese have
                    accomplished.</p>
                <p>There were other aspects to the operation. One related to our export controls. I
                    recall an experience in 1952, when the Japanese were to regain their
                    independence. We were concerned about whether or not they would maintain the
                    newly-imposed controls on trade with Communist China. It was decided that there
                    ought to be a mission to determine the extent to which we could trust the
                    Japanese to carry out that kind of responsibility when they were once more
                    completely independent. As a result a team of State and Commerce Department
                    officers was sent to Japan. I was a member of that team. We spent a month
                    visiting various Japanese government departments and business enterprises to try
                    to determine their attitude towards a continuation of controls.</p>
                <p>It was curious, as a generality, but we found a great distrust among the Japanese
                    for the Soviets. But the feeling regarding the Chinese was: they're people we
                    can handle. This stemmed in part from their experiences during the '30s, and in
                    part from their longer historical perspective. That has persisted as a Japanese
                    political viewpoint to the present day.</p>
                <p>At any rate, they did agree to become members of COCOM, as it's called, the
                    international committee governing export controls to the Soviet bloc, and
                    CHINCOM, which was the Chinese equivalent. That was another assignment during
                    that period.</p>
                <p>There were a wide variety of assignments during that period. I did a lot of
                    speaking before business groups throughout the United States. We had advisory
                    committees in various parts of the country and I would participate in those
                    sessions, always with a Far Eastern perspective.</p>
                <p>I recall another significant assignment. I was named a member of the US
                    delegation, in 1954, to renegotiate an agreement made between the United States
                    and the Philippines at the end of World War II in connection with their
                    independence.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>We insisted, in 1946, that the United States be given certain special economic
                    rights in the Philippines. In return, we gave the Philippines certain special
                    economic benefits in trade with the United States. They were part of this
                    agreement. That agreement was to be renegotiated in 1954.</p>
                <p>Senator Laurel was appointed by then-President Magsaysay to head the Philippine
                    delegation. An American publisher in New Hampshire, by the name of Langley, was
                    appointed head of the US delegation. I was a member of the US delegation.</p>
                <p>We negotiated back and forth for a long time. It essentially became a political
                    decision not an economic decision. It was decided to renew the agreement for 20
                    years, and both the benefits to the United States and to the Philippines were
                    continued.</p>
                <p>The continuation of these benefits was undesirable in the sense that the
                    Philippines didn't have to extend itself in the way another struggling, young,
                    developing country might have to in order to become economically
                    self-sufficient, because it was able to rely on protected markets for sugar, for
                    copra, and so on. It also gave American investors certain special privileges in
                    terms of investment in the Philippines. This agreement ran until 1974.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any particular relations with Korea at that
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Well, that reminds me of another experience, which related to Korea
                    and other countries.</p>
                <p>In 1953, when Eisenhower became President, he appointed Harold Stassen head of
                    the aid agency.</p>
                <p>Harold Stassen decided that he wanted to make that a very vibrant agency and also
                    had the notion that an aid plan in Asia, similar to a Marshall Plan in Europe,
                    might be the kind of thing that was needed to have the developing countries of
                    Asia get a jump start on development.</p>
                <p>He submitted his proposals to the Advisory Committee on International Financial
                    Problems, which was chaired by the Secretary of the Treasury at the time. While
                    there was some question about his regional initiative, it was approved. The
                    Administration went to Congress and got an appropriation of some 200 million
                    dollars, which it could use if desirable in pursuit of this objective.</p>
                <p>A team was to go to Asia to sound out the Asian countries on their reaction to
                    this. Stassen was hoping to get as members of his mission political appointees
                    at very senior levels.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>The Department of State decided that the Ambassador in each of the countries we
                    visited would be its representative. The Treasury and Commerce Departments,
                    however, appointed careerists, heads of their Far Eastern divisions—much to Mr.
                    Stassen's dismay, at least in the beginning.</p>
                <p>We did become fast friends, I may say, and I developed tremendous respect for his
                    ability. Since the Ambassadors were resident in the country, they did not travel
                    with us, and so there were only five of us on an Air Force plane (Stassen, a
                    Special Assistant and the Commerce and Treasury representatives). We had fairly
                    luxurious accommodations for those days before jets; we did have sleeping
                    accommodations, and so on.</p>
                <p>We spent three weeks abroad and visited virtually all the countries in Asia. In
                    connection with that mission, Governor Stassen also discussed other issues with
                    the heads of government.</p>
                <p>Our procedure was for Governor Stassen to be briefed en route to a particular
                    country. Of course, there were briefing books and all the usual preparatory
                    material, but he relied heavily on the briefings, primarily from the Treasury
                    representative and myself. But, he alone would do the talking at the meetings
                    with foreign government leaders.</p>
                <p>So, you mentioned Korea and that was what reminded me of it, when we had our
                    meetings with President Syngman Rhee.</p>
                <p>One of the key issues at the time was the exchange rate between the United States
                    and Korea, because the Koreans were really robbing us in connection with the aid
                    program. Our aid representative, Tyler Wood, had been unable to get them to
                    agree to anything. So, it was up to the mission.</p>
                <p>Stassen stuck to his guns. It was very curious; Syngman Rhee wouldn't give an
                    inch. But about 30 seconds before we were due to leave, and our plane was to
                    take off as we had a very rigid schedule, one of the military aides motioned
                    that it was time to go. Stassen and the rest of us stood up. And Syngman Rhee
                    then said, “I agree.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's negotiating right down to the wire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Right down to the wire. That was a very interesting thing to see. I
                    might say, that at a recess we had during that morning, several people,
                    particularly in the mission there, had urged us to give in, that Syngman Rhee
                    would never change, we'd end in stalemate, and that we shouldn't leave on that
                    note. But we stuck to our guns, and it worked.</p>
                <p>We also met with Prime Minister Nehru in India and other heads of Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was Nehru as a negotiator? Did he do some of the
                        negotiation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: In 1953, he had not become quite as anti-American as he later became.
                    Since we were there offering something, he was very interested. We had a couple
                    of sessions and luncheon, and so on. It was all very amicable.</p>
                <p>I was there, in India, two years later at an ECAFE meeting, and the Indians at
                    that time were very bitter, mostly because of our ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That we wouldn't give them completely free rein with our
                        aid, wasn't that it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, it was mostly because of what they regarded as our initial tilt
                    toward Pakistan. That became a very difficult thing.</p>
                <p>On another trip to India, I remember talking to George Allen, when he was
                    Ambassador, the morning he had to go in and see Prime Minister Nehru to tell him
                    that we were going to give military assistance to Pakistan. He told me at the
                    time that that was an assignment he wished he never had.</p>
                <p>And, of course, it turned out that way. He got quite a calling down from Nehru.
                    Our relations soured after that and destroyed itself in various ways.</p>
                <p>The Stassen mission did not really result in anything. While the Indians agreed,
                    to take the initiative and the Minister of Finance did issue a call for a
                    regional meeting to try to come up with a plan they never did so. The idea was
                    to get the initiative to come from the countries themselves, as they had in
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>But the situations in Asia and Europe were so different. Europe had educated and
                    trained people, the infrastructure, everything else; Asia had none of those
                    things. So, those who had counseled against this while it was being initially
                    discussed, who were overridden, were really right about the outcome.</p>
                <p>This was another of those assignments, of which there were dozens, that didn't
                    relate specifically to the day-to-day work of advising American business on the
                    economic situation in Asia, but which added spice to my life in that
                    position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, was this the period during which you started
                        negotiating various kinds of agreements, or was that later on?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That came later. Actually, I stayed in this position until 1958.</p>
                <p>When the Senior Seminar was formed in that year, the Commerce Department was
                    among the non-State agencies that were invited to send a representative, and I
                    was named as the Commerce-designee for the first Senior Seminar. So I spent the
                    year, '58-59, over at FSI in Arlington. It was one of the most fascinating years
                    I've ever spent in my life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the chair of it that year?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Willard Barber was the director. Actually, I had known Willard for
                    many years. He and I had been on a couple of missions to the Caribbean as part
                    of the US delegations way back during the war, so we were friends right from the
                    start.</p>
                <p>The most interesting thing to me about that year, of course, was my introduction
                    (in many cases it was introduction) to the military aspects of our security
                    policy: visits to SAC headquarters; to Army and Naval bases, a few of which I'd
                    seen in perfunctory fashion during my career, but never in terms of their
                    missions and how they would operate. All proved to me to be very, very
                    useful.</p>
                <p>My little overseas assignment with two colleagues in North Africa was also a very
                    interesting experience. We spent one month in Tunisia, Libya, and Morocco. I
                    gained some perspective of the Arab and Middle Eastern and North African
                    viewpoints.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By this time, you'd covered all the continents, which is
                        more than most of us who spent our entire time in the Foreign Service were
                        able to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: At the end of that assignment, I came back to the Commerce Department,
                    and there was a very real question of what I should do. The State Department was
                    much better organized with respect to onward assignments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, they keep moving people, yes, obviously.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: The Commerce Department people didn't move, particularly during the
                    '50s. There was not a lot of movement at senior positions because there was no
                    place to go.</p>
                <p>But I was given a number of special assignments. I was sort of biding time. My
                    job as Director of the Far Eastern Division was there for me to take, but the
                    Director of the Office of International Trade asked me to take on various
                    special assignments and I agreed.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>One of the most interesting was an assignment that related to general aid
                    functions. I don't remember the legislation under which it was carried out, but
                    what is now the Office of Management and Budget (then the Bureau of the Budget)
                    was assigned responsibility for carrying out the task, along with
                    representatives of State, Commerce, and Aid.</p>
                <p>I remember being assigned to the White House for three months, and we talked to
                    people in a variety of agencies. This was one of those studies that we
                    completed, but I don't think it was ever implemented in any fashion. I don't
                    regard that as any great achievement, although it was a very interesting
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>Then the administration changed—John Kennedy became President. Luther Hodges was
                    named Secretary of Commerce, and he brought in, as an Assistant Secretary for
                    International Affairs, a professor by the name of Jack Behrman.</p>
                <p>Jack was an academic who had done a lot of writing, but he also had a great
                    interest in how our foreign economic policy was to be carried out.</p>
                <p>Since it was a new administration, you'd expect a lot of political appointments,
                    and there were a great many, but Behrman decided he was going to look among the
                    careerists for his senior positions.</p>
                <p>One of any number of reorganizations that had taken place over the course of many
                    years took place then. A new structure was created with two principal bureaus:
                    one dealing with export promotion functions and the other dealing with policy
                    functions.</p>
                <p>I was named head of what was called the Office of International Programs, which
                    was part of the Bureau of Economic Programs (which I later came to head, all
                    within a very short space of time).</p>
                <p>This was the bureau that was responsible for the Commerce Department's interests
                    in foreign economic policy. It was the first time since shortly after World War
                    II that the policy and promotional aspects were separated.</p>
                <p>It was in this connection that I became involved, very heavily, in the work of
                    developing a new Trade Act. There was a bill on the Hill. The so-called Dillon
                    Round (named for Douglas Dillon) had just been completed, and we were going to
                    be heading into the Kennedy round of trade negotiations. The legislative
                    authority for the Kennedy round was on the Hill.</p>
                <p>It was decided, for political reasons primarily, to give the job as head of the
                    US team dealing with the Congress to the Secretary of Commerce and not the
                    Secretary of State. So, Luther Hodges became that person.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>He had a small group, primarily State and Commerce people, advising him. I was
                    part of that group. For a time we would meet every day. There were also a whole
                    host of inter-agency committees, obviously, that were working on the
                    legislation.</p>
                <p>I spent a good deal of time during that period working on the development of the
                    legislation, which was approved by the Congress in 1962.</p>
                <p>At the end of 1962, the Secretary and Assistant Secretary came to the view that
                    the business of separating out the policy and promotional aspects of our
                    international work in the Commerce Department was not fully productive, and
                    decided to combine the bureaus. And I was named Director of what became the
                    Bureau of International Commerce.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a major job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: We had over a thousand people in the bureau. We had a budget of over
                    25 million dollars—1962 dollars—as I recall. In today's terms that would be
                    hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
                <p>We were running a world-wide program. We still were relying on the Foreign
                    Service as our international arm to do our work abroad. Economic officers were
                    doing the policy reporting, which was utilized by all government agencies,
                    including Commerce. The economic and commercial officers, mostly, were doing the
                    trade promotional work, which was virtually an exclusive responsibility of
                    Commerce's, except for the agricultural function which belonged to
                    Agriculture.</p>
                <p>During this period, there were a number of attempts to wean the Commercial
                    Service away from the Foreign Service. Because of my position, I became involved
                    in this process. At one time, as a matter of fact, in the early '60s, with the
                    support of Senator Magnuson who then headed the Senate Commerce Committee, the
                    Senate approved legislation to establish a separate Commercial Service. Many of
                    us had mixed feelings about the virtues of that.</p>
                <p>While I contributed to the effort, because I was then in the Commerce Department,
                    I believed then, perhaps because of my very early work with the Foreign Service
                    and my continuing contact with the Foreign Service throughout all of my career,
                    that the most effective work we could do would be through a unified Foreign
                    Service.</p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>I suppose I was always committed to the notion that a unified Foreign Service was
                    best. We almost got it once. I remember a visit to the Secretary of the Treasury
                    in the late '40s to try to get their handful of Treasury Attach�s in the Foreign
                    Service. If that had been successful, all the agencies at that time would have
                    been in the Foreign Service, because Cultural Affairs was still in, and
                    Agriculture was still in, as a result of the 1939 agreement that brought in
                    Commerce and Agriculture. But that didn't work.</p>
                <p>And then in 1955, as I recall, the Secretary of Agriculture went to the
                    President, and by suggesting that it was no different to have Agricultural
                    Attach�s report to Agriculture and be responsible to them than to have military
                    Attach�s report to the military, Eisenhower agreed, and Agriculture left the
                    unified Foreign Service. But Commerce never quite did until much, much
                    later.</p>
                <p>Reverting back to what I was saying, we utilized the Foreign Service for our
                    overseas activities. We developed many new initiatives that were part of an
                    export promotion program that President Kennedy inaugurated and Secretary Hodges
                    carried out.</p>
                <p>This export promotion program resulted from our recognition of the fact that
                    overseas markets were becoming more and more important to the United States.</p>
                <p>There was for the first time in 1963 a “White House Conference on Export
                    Expansion,” in which the President and five or six Cabinet officers
                    participated, and which I helped to develop and carry through.</p>
                <p>We developed programs for enlarging our export expansion activities overseas,
                    which had by now become export-oriented, not import-oriented.</p>
                <p>We established trade centers abroad—the first one was in London—and there were
                    eventually trade centers in any number of cities around the world.</p>
                <p>We also developed a program of trade fair participation for commercial reasons.
                    We had had a program of trade fairs abroad, which we operated in my Bureau for
                    USIA. They did the general planning and selected the places, but my Bureau put
                    these fairs on.</p>
                <p>Well, during this export promotion period we developed the commercial trade fair
                    programs. Thus we ran two fair programs during this period. There were also
                    advisory committees that were established with businessmen to try to encourage
                    them to export as well as to develop closer relations between business and
                    government. There always seemed to be antipathy between government and business
                    in the United States, even in carrying through what was apparently a mutually
                    beneficial endeavor.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>I found this period, which runs from 1962 to 1965, in which we were promoting the
                    exports of the United States in ways we had never done before, a very
                    fascinating period.</p>
                <p>And unlike my activities in prior years, I now devoted most of my time (though I
                    had the other responsibilities as well) to the promotional aspects. So, for me,
                    this was a new aspect of the work for which I was responsible, and I found it
                    all very, very stimulating.</p>
                <p>We did increase our exports. As a matter of fact, I remember testifying before
                    Mr. Rooney, Chairman of the House Appropriations Subcommittee on our budget on
                    one occasion. He asked me whether the seven and a half billion dollar surplus we
                    were running that year was the result of the activities of the Bureau of
                    International Commerce.</p>
                <p>And I said, with a smile, “Of course it is.”</p>
                <p>He took it graciously. That was something he didn't always do, but he did that
                    time.</p>
                <p>Considering that we're running a trade deficit these days of over 100 billion
                    dollars, that was quite something.</p>
                <p>Well, of course, we really didn't do it alone. American business, superior
                    products, international marketing and a lot of other things did it. But it was
                    very good to be part of that effort.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think nothing of that sort is ever accomplished by
                        any one effort or one group of people, but you could be a positive element
                        or a brake. Well, now, how long did this last?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: This assignment was a continuing one. As part of our export promotion
                    program, we started to enlarge on the kinds of contacts we would have with
                    Foreign Service officers. Just as there were chief of missions meetings (and had
                    been for many years), we decided we'd have regional meetings with economic and
                    commercial officers.</p>
                <p>Because of my belief in a unified Foreign Service, I was pushing a consolidation
                    of economic and commercial work, which then were sort of separated. In most of
                    the missions they weren't, as a practical matter, but on paper they seemed to
                    be.</p>
                <p>We would have meetings of both economic and commercial officers. I traveled the
                    world in those years, between '62 and '65, at regional meetings where the
                    principal participants from Washington were State and Commerce officers, with
                    Commerce taking the lead on these. From time to time there would be other agency
                    representatives, depending on what kind of agenda was developed in each part of
                    the world.</p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>I mention this not only because it was an activity that took a considerable
                    amount of my time, but also because it relates to the Foreign Service and to the
                    integration of our activities abroad in trying to get more Foreign Service
                    involvement in commercial activities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It wasn't always easy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No. One of the problems always was that Ambassadors did not
                    necessarily regard themselves as being the principal commercial officer of an
                    embassy. Frankly, they never were really encouraged to do so. Secretaries of
                    State were not so inclined and never pushed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And, unfortunately, the Economic Bureau of State, in my
                        feeling over the time, was sort of an independent fiefdom that followed its
                        own..., had its own relations around the government and with Congress and so
                        on and so forth, and was not really an integral part of the State
                        Department.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Right. What you're saying leads in to the next aspect of my career and
                    my being brought into the Department of State.</p>
                <p>During the course of these activities, I got to know, among others, the Director
                    General of the Foreign Service, the Under Secretary of State for Management, as
                    well as substantive officers with whom I had been dealing. I was involved
                    because of my Bureau's use of the Foreign Service to carry out our programs
                    abroad.</p>
                <p>In 1965 there was a reorganization of the Department of State's Economic Bureau.
                    They decided to create a Bureau of Economic and Business Affairs. Anthony M.
                    Solomon was named Assistant Secretary. He had been, for a short time, Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary in the Bureau of Inter-American Affairs.</p>
                <p>He decided, along with Under Secretary Crockett, that there ought to be a major
                    State Department initiative in developing closer relations with American
                    business, and that the Foreign Service should take a more active role in the
                    promotion of American trade and investment.</p>
                <p>I was approached to come over and serve as one of several Deputy Assistant
                    Secretaries to head up that function, among others.</p>
                <p>So, in the early fall of 1965, I came to the Department of State as Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary with a longish title of Deputy Assistant Secretary for
                    Commercial Affairs and Business Activities, which was supposed to describe my
                    function.</p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>I was given that as a basic responsibility; “that” being the development of
                    programs which would relate the State Department and Foreign Service more
                    closely to American business objectives as they converge with US policy
                    objectives—in this case the promotion of US trade and investment interests
                    abroad.</p>
                <p>Also included in my area of responsibility was the Department's interest in
                    antitrust, which brought me into contact with the Assistant Attorney General for
                    Antitrust and international activities in that field.</p>
                <p>Another was intellectual property, which gave me the State Department's
                    responsibility for patent, trademark, and copyright affairs. It was in
                    connection with one of our hearings that I first met Mr. Tully Torbert, as a
                    matter of fact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was trying to remember when we first met. I thought it
                        was longer ago than that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It may very well have been earlier than that, but I remember going up
                    on the Hill together.</p>
                <p>So, there were diverse responsibilities. The new thing the department didn't
                    have, in depth, were programs for encouraging American business to look more
                    favorably on the department and encouraging our own officers to respond better
                    to the needs of American business overseas.</p>
                <p>Some programs we enlarged, and many new programs we initiated. One that we
                    enlarged was a program that then existed in the Department of State. It was
                    embodied in what was called the Advisory Committee on International Business
                    Problems, then headed by Clarence Randall, who had served several presidents and
                    had also been head of Inland Steel Company.</p>
                <p>I was sort of the Executive Director, and we decided to enlarge the committee. We
                    included chief executive officers of some 12 major companies, and brought a
                    variety of problems to them two or three times a year.</p>
                <p>The general pattern was to have substantive discussions morning and afternoon and
                    a luncheon with the Secretary. That was about the way it went.</p>
                <p>Tony Solomon was very good about his own participation, and sat in on all of
                    these meetings. Businessmen were good about attending, though their advice was
                    difficult to come by very often. The Secretary, unfortunately, was preoccupied
                    with Vietnam, and most of his talks at lunch related to Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm afraid he didn't think of much else at that time. He
                        thought of it about 90 hours a week.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That was true.</p>
                <p>In any event, the Advisory Committee was one activity that had already existed
                    that we enlarged upon. I also established a much larger annual series of
                    meetings with chief executive officers around the country. We had an all-day
                    session, somewhat akin to the way Foreign Service Day is now run. Our invitation
                    list included something like 500 chief executive officers.</p>
                <p>It was interesting to note that in the first year, responses were slow in coming
                    in. I later discovered through friends, that one CEO would call another one to
                    find out whether he was going or not. Was this something that he should be seen
                    at or not, because it was new for the Department of State to be asking large
                    groups of businessmen to come in this way.</p>
                <p>We had a very successful first meeting, and this continued year after year.
                    Businessmen were given a feel, from people at Assistant Secretary level and up,
                    on what was happening abroad and how, in a general way, their interests would be
                    affected.</p>
                <p>Our objective, of course, was to bring them into the process, to show an interest
                    in them. I think this helped a great deal in many ways. More businessmen would
                    come and ask for advice on the political end. They would still go, obviously, to
                    the Commerce Department for commercial information. But they would come to the
                    Department of State for views on broad political and economic issues at that
                    time, and so on.</p>
                <p>There were very good contacts that way, but our principal aim (and the one that
                    did pay off) was that more of these people, who had avoided embassies when they
                    were overseas, would go in and see our people abroad.</p>
                <p>Now in order to induce Ambassadors to do more, we had to do something about that
                    and developed the idea of sending a letter from the Secretary to Ambassadors
                    telling them that export promotion was one of their important responsibilities
                    (a letter which you have received at various times, and others). It was the kind
                    of thing that, in some cases, may have been acted upon; in most cases, it went
                    from the In to the Out basket because, obviously, it was a one-shot
                    proposition.</p>
                <p>I remember, as an example of a lack of interest at senior levels one occasion,
                    when I was going to a meeting of the inter-agency Committee on Export Expansion,
                    it was chaired by the Secretary of Commerce, and the Secretary of State was a
                    member. I was to go along as an advisor. I think William Rogers was our
                    Secretary at the time. The Secretary called in the morning and said he couldn't
                    make it, but Mr. Irwin, the Under Secretary, would represent the Department.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>So, I met Mr. Irwin, and as we were driving over to the meeting he said, “Well,
                    how are things going in this field? What are the issues that are coming up?”</p>
                <p>I gave him a briefing, and somehow or other he said, “Are you happy with the
                    things we're doing in State?”</p>
                <p>And I said, “No, not at all.”</p>
                <p>He asked, “Why is that?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, there's no real interest in international commercial affairs on
                    the part of senior officers, either in the Department or overseas.”</p>
                <p>He asked, “Why is that?”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, it's very simple: first, you're going to this meeting; the
                    Secretary isn't going to this meeting.”</p>
                <p>He took that all right, I must say.</p>
                <p>I added, “That's fine, you're the Under Secretary. But you just came back from a
                    series of meetings in Central America.” (I had known he had been on a mission to
                    four Central American countries.) I asked, “Tell me, how much of your time did
                    you devote to a discussion of commercial matters?”</p>
                <p>He looked at me sheepishly and said, “None.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Every Ambassador knows that. They're going to work on matters you
                    discuss. Until you change, they're not going to change.”</p>
                <p>I was really very bold.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think Irwin was a guy you could do this with.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That's right. I wouldn't have done it with Rogers. I know that from
                    other discussions we've had. Although on other things, particularly
                    jurisdictional issues in this area, Secretary Rogers was very active and very
                    positive. This is an aside to this particular subject, but is related.</p>
                <p>Secretary of Commerce Stans made several attempts to take the commercial officers
                    out of the State Department during this period.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>I must have written 150 memos on why a unified Foreign Service made more sense
                    than breaking it apart.</p>
                <p>I was the Secretary's and Assistant Secretary's principal advisor on this
                    subject. I remember, first with Mr. Solomon, and then our next Assistant
                    Secretary who was Phil Trezise, and we would meet with Rogers, the staff, and
                    others on this issue time and again. Mr. Stans did not gain his objective.</p>
                <p>However, it was a very difficult business to get the State Department to change
                    its point of view on commercial matters. There were a variety of reasons for it.
                    Many people in the department looked down on anything that was not “policy.”
                    Trade was something to be shoved aside. While there were a few Foreign Service
                    officers who were delighted to have commercial assignments or economic
                    assignments with a strong commercial component, many were not.</p>
                <p>It was also true, particularly during the earlier period, that the way to the top
                    was through the political cone. If you will look, during that period, at the
                    percentage of promotions of political officers versus economic and commercial
                    officers (let alone consular officers, who were in even worse shape, and
                    administrative officers), those who worked the political cone did best.</p>
                <p>Also, our entrance examinations at the time were not primed to bring in
                    top-flight economic and commercial people. So there were a whole host of things
                    which militated against this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Once they did bring them in, the officers wanted to shift
                        over, as, frankly, I did. Not that I was a great economic guy, but my
                        background was business.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Anybody who wanted to get to the top pursued the political ladder. As
                    a matter of fact there weren't any, commercial officers, except for some of
                    those people who came to State in 1939 when the Commerce and Agricultural
                    Services were consolidated with State. Except for a few of those, at least in
                    the time frame we're talking about, none of the commercial people became
                    Ambassadors. They just plain didn't.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think this is an extremely valid criticism, and I
                        have never heard it so well put. You were the expert on it.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It was my job to flush it out and see what I could do about it. I must
                    say that I got great support from Tony Solomon, support that if there were ever
                    any crucial issue he would go to bat. He didn't spend much time on it
                    personally, because he was interested in the policy side of economic affairs,
                    too. But he gave me free rein and gave me support when I needed it. Bill
                    Crockett was marvelous. There was nothing he wouldn't do. He'd hold meetings, he
                    would do anything vis a vis other agencies that made sense.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact we convinced the then-Assistant Secretary of Commerce (who
                    had been my boss and became Secretary of Commerce), Sandy Trowbridge, that
                    combining the economic and commercial functions was the best line. This was
                    before Stans and the incidents I referred to earlier.</p>
                <p>In this period, Crockett and I, meeting with people like Trowbridge and others,
                    were able to make them feel that a combined economic and commercial function
                    within the Foreign Service was the best road to take. I'm not sure we were
                    correct. Later, of course, the Commerce Department got its own service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some of the officers went over there.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Not all, because in smaller missions, economic officers still promote
                    commercial functions. So, it's a divided function. I don't think that's good. I
                    still am a believer in a unified Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>We did many other things to try to encourage commercial activities. The State
                    Department took over and promoted the regional conferences. We held two or three
                    a year. This was meant to encourage greater interest on the part of State,
                    through Commerce, of course, was always an integral part of these meetings.</p>
                <p>We tried to do everything we could to encourage the notion that economic and
                    commercial work was a whole; it involved policy and promotion; it was of
                    importance to the United States; and it was something that every Foreign Service
                    officer ought to find worthwhile.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dr. Braderman, when we left off on the previous tape, you
                        were discussing the problems that you had because so few people in the State
                        Department were really concerned with commercial affairs. I'd like you to
                        continue on that and give one or two more examples if you will, and then get
                        on to the negotiating phase of your function.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Very good. I'd be happy to do so.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>Well, in some ways this assignment within the State Department to try to induce,
                    seduce, or develop a greater interest in and affinity for commercial work
                    overseas was frustrating.</p>
                <p>As I indicated earlier, many of the department officers were not interested; some
                    felt it degrading. At the same time, there were dozens and dozens of officers
                    who did splendid jobs, both within the department and especially overseas in the
                    pursuit of these functions.</p>
                <p>There were really two dimensions to the activity. One was what actually was being
                    done, principally in our missions abroad, in furtherance of US business
                    interests which were consonant with US interests. And the other was the
                    administrative and bureaucratic business (that happens mostly in Washington)
                    with respect to who would be responsible for this and that function.</p>
                <p>Being in Washington I had an involvement with both problems, but a particularly
                    heavy one in the administrative infighting on this subject.</p>
                <p>While it was our intention to maintain and further the concept of a unified
                    Foreign Service (but, within that, provide other agencies with the services they
                    needed abroad), there were a great many things that occurred which made that
                    impossible.</p>
                <p>Some of the demands of other agencies were excessive. I think the department was
                    right in rejecting them. But on other occasions, there were requests that were
                    made that made good sense.</p>
                <p>Let me give you an example of one of those I regarded as excessive. In order to
                    give greater importance to the commercial function, the Department of Commerce,
                    at one point, suggested that there be regional Ambassadors for Commercial
                    Affairs. One might be stationed in Paris and cover three or four countries.
                    Another would be stationed in Rio and cover several surrounding countries, and
                    so on.</p>
                <p>To my mind, that made no sense at all. But it was a serious proposal put forward
                    by the Commerce people and supported by their Secretary (of Commerce). We had to
                    refuse to go along with that proposal.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, they pointed to the inadequate number of commercial staff
                    abroad. It was true not only in the commercial area, but we were concerned at
                    the moment with that particular function.</p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>They proposed joint actions with CMB and Congress to try to increase the number
                    of people doing commercial work abroad. This was after Mr. Crockett had gone, I
                    may say. I think his attitude would have been different. But the department
                    administrative people at the time and the Secretary, in looking at their
                    priorities, didn't see why they should push for more commercial officers, which
                    they regarded as conflicting with the effort to increase officer support in
                    other areas. And, therefore, they didn't support the commerce proposals.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, at one juncture, Commerce was able to persuade the Office of
                    Management and Budget to grant, within the Department of State's budget, because
                    that's where the commercial officers were placed, an increased allotment for
                    commercial officers.</p>
                <p>As I noted earlier this effort was, in fact, fought by many elements within the
                    Department of State as competing with their own interests and one that they
                    didn't want to support. Some of the bureaus refused, or at least delayed,
                    allocating commercial jobs even after appropriations were approved.</p>
                <p>So there were problems of this kind on the administrative side, which deterred
                    the effort, even though individual officers abroad were doing great jobs in
                    sponsoring substantive export promotion activities, which were enhancing the
                    foreign trade of the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's a very useful part of history to get down,
                        and certainly an apt statement, I think, of the situation. Well, do you want
                        to go on a bit to the negotiating aspects of this job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: All right. I'd like to talk about two assignments I had during the
                    course of my service as Deputy Assistant Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>One dealt with the Philippines. I have referred to the Philippines before, in
                    terms of my participation in the 1954 Laurel-Langley negotiations. (I didn't
                    mention I was on a trade mission to the Philippines in 1960.)</p>
                <p>In September of 1966, President Johnson and President Marcos of the Philippines
                    met. As is customary after such meetings, there was a joint communique.</p>
                <p>One element of that joint communique was an agreement that each President would
                    appoint a team to discuss concepts underlying a new agreement to replace the
                    Laurel-Langley Agreement of 1954. (That agreement, you see, was to run for 20
                    years—until 1974.)</p>
                <p>While this was only 1966 President Marcos believed it would be desirable to start
                    very early and get a new agreement in place before the old agreement
                    expired.</p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>As a consequence of this statement in the joint communique, in June 1967, teams
                    were named.</p>
                <p>On the recommendation of the Department of State, the President named me as
                    Chairman of the US team.</p>
                <p>The President of the Philippines named Cesar Virata, who at that time was Under
                    Secretary of Commerce and Industry and chairman of the Board of Investments in
                    the Philippines, to head the Philippine team.</p>
                <p>The US team was composed of a desk officer, and someone from the legal office, of
                    the Department of State and several people from other agencies.</p>
                <p>The first meeting of the teams occurred in November of 1967 in the
                    Philippines.</p>
                <p>Anybody who knows anything about the Philippines knows there's a very peculiar
                    ambivalence among Filipinos about Philippine-American relations. It's, in some
                    senses, distant. In other cases, it's family. It stems from a variety of
                    experiences during the course of American involvement in the Philippines.</p>
                <p>Though many Filipinos speak English (you hear English everywhere), that's often
                    regarded as just a veneer. Knowledge of Spanish and Spanish culture run deep,
                    and underlying both, of course, are the indigenous languages like Tagalog and
                    indigenous culture.</p>
                <p>Filipinos have their kids in school (at college level) in the United States; they
                    have their money invested in the United States; they come to the United States
                    for visits and vacations; and they regard us, in this sense, as family. Yet when
                    it comes to particular business ventures and enterprises, then things are quite
                    different.</p>
                <p>I had any number of opportunities, particularly on that trade mission in the
                    Philippines when we spent some six weeks all over the country, to get many
                    different indications of how the same person, within the space of ten minutes,
                    would evoke both emotions with respect to the United States and those who
                    represented the United States: this warm, family feeling and this
                    antagonism.</p>
                <p>And I think this reflects our relationships in everything from bases agreement to
                    the commercial relations which we were talking about.</p>
                <p>Well, back to the meetings, themselves. There were two principal areas for
                    discussion between us. They were the areas that were embodied in the original
                    1946 agreement, which had been extended to 1954, and which were due to expire in
                    1974.</p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>One area was the special trade concessions given to particular Philippine
                    products, which gave them preferential markets in the United States. I've
                    mentioned them before: sugar, copra, lumber, and so on.</p>
                <p>The other was the investment area, which was of less interest to the Filipinos
                    because they had less capital to invest abroad, and of more interest to the
                    United States, which had significant investment interests in the
                    Philippines.</p>
                <p>What the Filipinos wanted to do was trade-off one against the other and continue
                    the agreement. Our view, the US view, was that the agreement (which was
                    renegotiated as the Laurel-Langley Agreement in 1954) should really have had an
                    end date, not a date for renegotiation, because this kind of relationship
                    between two independent countries was not based on sound principles. That one
                    country, in this case the United States, was inherently ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Paternalistic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Yes, it created a paternalistic position. (Thank you.) It really made
                    us the father and the Philippines the child—one of those things I noted earlier
                    that the Philippines resented very much.</p>
                <p>At the same time, when we discussed the agreement, they wanted to continue it.
                    This is the ambivalence of which I'm speaking.</p>
                <p>Throughout these discussions, which we held in Baguio in the Philippines (a very
                    lovely city), I tried to explain the virtues of ending these special
                    relationships—both special relationships. On the investment side, it was not
                    that we weren't interested in continued US investment in the Philippines. We
                    were, but we felt it should be based on Philippine acceptance of investment, as
                    investment is accepted in the United States, because it's good not only for the
                    investor, but good for the receiving country as well.</p>
                <p>And that's the principle on which we believed our investments should be received
                    in the Philippines, for which you needed no international agreement.</p>
                <p>We, therefore, did not want to perpetuate the principle in an agreement as
                    something special, because when things got ticklish or difficult it would always
                    be pointed to, and the charges of paternalism would come to the fore.</p>
                <p>And we felt that the special trade concessions were not desirable because, again,
                    it continued a paternalistic relationship.</p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>The Filipinos understood the implications of the continuation of these special
                    arrangements. But strong economic interests in the Philippines wanted these
                    privileges continued.</p>
                <p>So, it was the intention of the Philippines to get an agreement from us that
                    would continue the trade privileges, and they were willing to give us special
                    concessions in the investment field.</p>
                <p>We had a stalemate as a result of these discussions. We adjourned for further
                    consultations—the panels (as they called them), teams (as we called them) would
                    report to our respective governments and give additional consideration to the
                    issues.</p>
                <p>Well, that was done, in a sense. We had a second meeting of both teams in October
                    of 1968. Those meetings were held in Washington, but they were more of the
                    same.</p>
                <p>The Filipinos tried, in Washington, to do what they had done in 1954: put the
                    issues aside and make an appeal on political grounds.</p>
                <p>Carlos Romulo used all of his persuasive powers. He was then Secretary of Foreign
                    Affairs. He came and he talked to our Secretary who wavered a little, I must
                    say, just as the people had wavered earlier.</p>
                <p>He went up to the Hill (he knew more people on the Hill than some of us did) and
                    tried to use his influence there.</p>
                <p>Some pressures were put on us (some properly and some improperly), but we stuck
                    to our guns. Essentially, both departments that were heavily involved, State and
                    Commerce, supported the views of the members of our team.</p>
                <p>As a result, the Filipinos went back to the Philippines wiser in the knowledge
                    that we were going to insist on these discussions sticking to the economic and
                    commercial realm, and not being decided on political grounds alone.</p>
                <p>But it was clear that having these meetings was not going to get us anywhere. We,
                    as I've indicated, did not see any virtue in a new treaty. The Filipinos only
                    wanted a treaty if it was going to continue the special trade privileges.</p>
                <p>And so, through desultory cable traffic back and forth, the teams continued,
                    through our Ambassadors, to “negotiate,” discuss, or call it what you will, and
                    the treaty eventually died a natural death, which was what we wanted.</p>
                <p>I thought that would be an interesting example of a negotiation that, from our
                    standpoint, succeeded by failing to produce an agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great. Now, you had another one?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Yes, I was going to give you one that ended in a treaty, one of which
                    I feel very proud. As a matter of fact, I consider it perhaps the greatest
                    achievement of my career.</p>
                <p>It was in an esoteric area (at least for me), the field of patents, which, as I
                    indicated when I discussed my coming to State, was one of the group of functions
                    that was in my bailiwick.</p>
                <p>Shortly after taking over as Deputy Assistant Secretary, one of the members of my
                    staff, Harvey Winter by name, informed me of an international patent meeting in
                    the Department on the following day. Harvey was the one person who worked on
                    patent, trademark, and copyright issues (the chief of that division was
                    primarily interested in our antitrust work). That was the total, in-depth
                    competence of the department in international patent matters, I might say.</p>
                <p>Harvey Winter is still in the Department of State, and he's still handling these
                    matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was he an attorney?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: He was not an attorney. It would have been useful if he had been an
                    attorney; it would have been useful if I had been, as well, for this particular
                    function, because many of our dealings were with patent attorneys.</p>
                <p>Well, he told me that the following day we were having a celebration called
                    International Patent Day, which was part of a festivity that had been arranged
                    by the Patent Office to celebrate the 175th anniversary of the US patent
                    system.</p>
                <p>It had turned into an international meeting and people were here from all over
                    the world. In the name of the Department of State, he, as the principal person
                    involved, had agreed to participate in the day's activities. So, I got involved
                    and got to meet a good many people who were concerned with patent affairs.</p>
                <p>Even though I'd been in the Department of Commerce (and the Patent Office is in
                    the Department of Commerce), that department is so compartmentalized, as are
                    most departments of the US government, that one bureau not only is not involved
                    in, but knows very little about what another bureau does.</p>
                <p>I think, when I was Director of the Bureau of International Commerce, I had one
                    person somewhere down the line who worked with the Patent Office on
                    international patent matters, but I was not personally involved. So, I came with
                    great knowledge and great experience to this particular assignment.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>At any rate, as so often is the case, Harvey Winter prepared speeches for the
                    Assistant Secretary and for me, and we duly gave them.</p>
                <p>But the important thing is that at one of the parties during the course of the
                    three-day session, I began to hear about some of the problems in the
                    international patent field.</p>
                <p>One was that if you filed an application for a patent in one country, and you got
                    it eventually, it was good only in that country. If you were an inventor and you
                    filed in the United States, you got a patent in the United States.</p>
                <p>Somebody in Germany, say, could steal that knowledge and information, because you
                    had no patent or patent rights in Germany.</p>
                <p>That means that a person who wanted coverage everywhere had to file everywhere,
                    or he had to file everywhere that somebody might have had a similar idea or
                    wanted to utilize his idea, if he was going to get patent protection.</p>
                <p>I asked some of the experts, including the head of the International Bureau for
                    the protection of Industrial Property (he was the head of the International
                    Secretariat for the Paris union which covered industrial property), why this had
                    been allowed to develop all these years.</p>
                <p>And he told me they had made a few attempts during the course of the history of
                    international patent matters, but had never been able to get agreement. There
                    were always those who pushed nationalistic views to the extent of not wanting to
                    give up any of the nation's sovereignty by accepting an instrument issued by
                    another country.</p>
                <p>And I asked, “Well, aren't there ways around that?”</p>
                <p>He said, “We've never been able to come up with anything satisfactory.”</p>
                <p>Well, that meeting came and went. I then remember on one occasion having lunch
                    with Harvey Winter, when I raised this issue with him. He gave me the same
                    explanation, because he knew the history.</p>
                <p>And I said, “There must be some way we can satisfy that particular impediment,
                    which would be an impediment in the United States as well as in other countries,
                    and still come up with some method by which we could reduce the duplication of
                    effort both for applicants and national patent offices.”</p>
                <p>So, we played around with ideas, and then decided that the next time we saw
                    somebody from the International Secretariat we would talk it over with that
                    person.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What International Secretariat?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: The International Secretariat was the Bureau for the Protection of
                    Industrial Property (BIRPI—as it was generally called) at that time. It has now
                    blossomed into a new organization, which I helped to create, called the World
                    Intellectual Property Organization, which covers patents, trademarks, and
                    copyrights as well. But at that time, it was just concerned ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a function of the United Nations, however.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, it was an independent organization with the usual affiliation that
                    other semi-independent organizations have. But it was not a United Nations
                    entity like the World Health Organization or World Meteorological
                    Organization.</p>
                <p>We talked to the Deputy Director on one of his trips to the United States. He was
                    interested, I think in part, if I may be honest, for bureaucratic reasons,
                    because anything done in this area would enhance and enlarge the scope of the
                    work of the organization. But he also had a sincere substantive interest. He
                    said some member country would have to introduce a resolution of some kind to
                    get it before the body.</p>
                <p>The appropriate body for that purpose was the Executive Committee of the Paris
                    Union, which would be meeting next in Geneva in September 1966.</p>
                <p>Well, with that in hand, I then had lunch with Edward Brenner, the Commissioner
                    of Patents, a very knowledgeable fellow who had been a patent attorney for a
                    major firm and had come into government during the Kennedy Administration as
                    Commissioner of Patents.</p>
                <p>We talked about it, and he said it sounded like a good idea to him.</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, you're the US representative at the Executive Committee of BIRPI,
                    if we draft a resolution; would you introduce it?”</p>
                <p>He said, “I'll be glad to.”</p>
                <p>So, we drafted a resolution, he introduced it, and it was unanimously adopted by
                    the Executive Committee of BIRPI in 1966.</p>
                <p>Now here we are, we're starting with an idea. That's all, just a plain idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And by this time it was something generated from the
                        bottom up, but the Commissioner of Patents was the guy who had the policy
                        authority to decide what...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Well, he was interested in joining with us in having the problem
                    studied. I was fascinated by the prospect of developing a new international
                    cooperative effort. The reason I refer to this is that it is so rare in a
                    Foreign Service officer's career that one can start with an idea and bring it to
                    fruition as a treaty.</p>
                <p>To accomplish this, it was important to stay in the same job. Part of the reason
                    I didn't go into the field earlier was because of this. I wanted to see it
                    through. That was a personal desire, and my bosses went along with it. So, I was
                    able to stay with this project for the period of time that it took to do it.</p>
                <p>Well, we now had moved from an idea in our mind's eye to an idea on paper as an
                    international resolution to study it.</p>
                <p>The Secretariat was great. In a matter of a couple of months it came up with a
                    very rough draft of what might be an agreement. Its tentative title was “Patent
                    Cooperative Treaty”—a name that stuck.</p>
                <p>The way they got over the issue of national sovereignty was by eliminating what
                    would have been a very useful thing, but would have been a stumbling block, and
                    that was whether or not a patent issued by one country would be valid in other
                    countries.</p>
                <p>In other words, they finessed that particular question. Nowhere in their draft
                    was that result anything we would attempt to achieve. Rather, the core of the
                    proposal was that if you applied in one country, that filing would be valid in
                    other member countries. One could then continue the process and get a patent
                    that would be acknowledged as a patent in other countries without separate
                    filings in other countries. This was the general notion.</p>
                <p>Beginning then, in 1966, first through these discussions that we had, and then
                    through a series of international meetings, which began with six countries. It
                    was decided (mostly after discussions between the Secretariat and ourselves)
                    that too many people at the beginning would be unproductive. And, also, we
                    wanted the participation initially of those countries that had the greatest
                    stake in this, and they would be the countries that had the most patent
                    applications.</p>
                <p>So, six of the countries having the most patent applications were the countries
                    that started to have a series of meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you remember which they were?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Well, yes, I think so: United Kingdom, Federal Republic of Germany,
                    the United States, France, Japan, and the Soviet Union. A representative of the
                    International Patent Institute also participated.</p>
                <p>The six countries met together a number of times between January and April 1967.
                    We enlarged upon and modified this very rough draft.</p>
                <p>Then, I think it was in October of 1967, we had our first sizable meeting of 23
                    countries. This was the first time that the other countries became involved.
                    Various intergovernmental and non-governmental organizations also participated
                    in the so-called “Committee of Experts.”</p>
                <p>Then, again, we continued a series of working sessions, working committees of
                    various kinds to review this draft and try to perfect it. This process at the
                    international level went on for the rest of '67, '68, and '69. Additional
                    countries became part of the process in 1968. I think at the end of '69 or the
                    beginning of 1970, we had a “final” draft.</p>
                <p>While these international negotiations were going on, there were many differences
                    of opinion, but there was a general desire to move ahead, a general willingness
                    to give up those national prerogatives, which were necessary in order to achieve
                    a common purpose, while at the same time maintaining national sovereignty on the
                    basic issue of a country's right to issue a patent. At the same time there were
                    also other discussions going on in practically every other major country, but
                    particularly in the United States, which were much more divisive than the
                    international negotiations.</p>
                <p>There are components, I think, of any international treaty that obviously involve
                    other groups, whether it's the environment and you're dealing with the Wildlife
                    Federation, for example and business and everybody else. In this area, we were
                    dealing with the Patent Bar as well as the American business community with
                    international operations.</p>
                <p>There was that part of the Patent Bar composed of independent patent attorneys.
                    They were people who made their money from handling patent cases. A great deal
                    of money was made by filing patent applications. They were not interested in a
                    procedure that would make one patent application good in ten countries. They
                    fought this tooth and nail from the beginning to the end.</p>
                <p>There was that part of the Patent Bar composed of in-house patent attorneys at
                    major international firms. They were generally in favor, because superseding
                    their peculiar patent interests were the interests of their companies. If they
                    could find money-saving procedures, they were obviously interested in it.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>Because of my other contacts with chief executive officers, as a result of other
                    programs that I referred to earlier, in terms of trying to strengthen ties
                    between business and the department, I got to know many CEOs.</p>
                <p>There were a number of recalcitrant patent attorneys that I was able to induce to
                    change their minds by talking to their CEOs and explaining that the companies'
                    interests happened to be the US interest at the time. And they gave walking
                    papers or marching orders to their patent attorneys. But most of the in-house
                    patent attorneys and industrial firms supported it.</p>
                <p>I, obviously, had to argue the case in the patent forum. I made more speeches at
                    state and local patent and bar associations in this short period of time, than I
                    had ever thought possible.</p>
                <p>While I was not an attorney, and it would have been useful to be one, I found
                    matching wits with my soon-to-become attorney friends and colleagues, as well as
                    antagonists, very interesting.</p>
                <p>One of the most gratifying was a debate, which was deliberately set up as a
                    debate, at the American Bar Association annual meeting in Philadelphia where I
                    was pitted against one of their stars.</p>
                <p>Following our debate, the patent section voted to support the international
                    initiative we were undertaking.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By that time, you were a patent attorney.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It required study and hard work, but it was a lot of fun. One has to
                    become a student of all of these things, just as any of us does, whatever the
                    assignment.</p>
                <p>The most difficult part of this negotiation was the domestic negotiation. Then
                    there were the issues of getting people on the Hill convinced that these were
                    things we ought to do.</p>
                <p>We needed support in a variety of ways—for appropriations for some of the
                    initiatives early on, and then later when we decided to have the diplomatic
                    conference to negotiate the final treaty in Washington.</p>
                <p>I must say that the then-chairmen of both the House Judiciary Committee,
                    Representative Kastenmeier, and Senator Burdick on the Senate side were very
                    supportive. Both are still in their respective jobs, I think, on the Senate and
                    House sides. They were on delegations of some of the major meetings we had as
                    this process developed.</p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>We went through the process of getting support, domestically, from most of the
                    groups Patent Bar.</p>
                <p>I did a number of things during the course of this project, on the advice of
                    various people, to try to induce some of the die-hard people to come aboard. I
                    even put one or two of our antagonists on an advisory committee that the
                    department had on international patent matters to advise us through this whole
                    process.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, that was a very good technique for keeping all elements of the
                    patent community informed on what we were doing on the international side, as
                    well as keeping ourselves informed on what the strengths and weaknesses of our
                    position were going to be. And there were things we learned and positions we
                    adopted that were modified by suggestions that were made. It was really a
                    working advisory committee, a very good one, and a number of members of that
                    advisory committee served on US delegations at some of our meetings.</p>
                <p>Well, we had a final draft developed, as I say, early in 1970, and we set a
                    meeting for May and June of 1970 in Washington. It was called the “Washington
                    Diplomatic Conference on the Patent Cooperation Treaty.”</p>
                <p>That meeting was convened on May 25, 1970. There were 55 member countries of the
                    Paris Union officially represented. In addition, there were 23 other countries
                    that came as observers. There were 11 inter-governmented organizations present,
                    and there were 11 international non-governmental organizations represented—with
                    a total of some 300 participants.</p>
                <p>We met continuously until June 19 and worked over this draft treaty line by line,
                    sentence by sentence. There were areas where there was easy agreement, and there
                    were some very difficult issues. One of them that was difficult wasn't settled
                    until the final plenary session.</p>
                <p>I served as president of the conference. We were using our facilities at the
                    Department of State, so we met in plenary session in the Loy Henderson Room.</p>
                <p>I remember deviating from the line-by-line approval process that we'd been going
                    through, to take up a whole article, because it was the only way I thought we
                    could get approval. I asked for an up-or-down vote on that article. It kind of
                    confused some of the opponents who approved of 90 percent of the article, but
                    not the other 10%—but they had no chance to vote on that portion.</p>
                <p>At any rate, it was approved unanimously. The treaty was signed by 20 countries
                    initially; others followed. It was ratified by the Senate for the United States
                    in 1973. There was implementing legislation that was required (I was no longer
                    involved), but that was approved in 1975, and the treaty went into force.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>That is why I say I went from an idea, which I started to identify over lunch, to
                    an international treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A great many of us are jealous of you—I am already—to have
                        accomplished something like that. That's absolutely great.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It was fascinating to do that.</p>
                <p>Now, once that treaty was done, I felt kind of relieved. I had felt guilty,
                    really, staying in the department. I enjoyed my assignment as Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary, and I had a wide variety of responsibilities, as you can see from a
                    few of the things I've identified. But I really wanted to get out into the
                    field. I felt that I should have a long time ago. I hadn't many years to go
                    because we were still operating under the rule of retirement at age 60.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were you by this time, a reserve officer, or regular
                        FSO, or what?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That's an interesting side light, as a matter of fact. When I was
                    asked to come to the Department of State and I was offered the job as Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary, I said, “That's all well and good, but ...”</p>
                <p>I was, incidentally, not only Director of the Bureau of International Commerce,
                    but I was also a Deputy Assistant Secretary of Commerce, so the title wasn't all
                    that significant to me.</p>
                <p>I said that if I ever went to the Department of State I wanted to be an FSO. I
                    didn't believe any officer should be in the Department of State, other than the
                    required civil servants and the political appointees we had, unless you were an
                    FSO. Well, you can appoint somebody Secretary of State, but you can't appoint
                    him an FSO.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have to go before a board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: You have to go before a board. What I wanted was an understanding that
                    I could take the exam. This was one of two or three things that I asked about.
                    One of the things that was a sine qua non was my being given an opportunity to
                    become an FSO if I could.</p>
                <p>So, Assistant Secretary Solomon talked to Crockett, and Crockett said it was fine
                    with him. So I came on with that understanding, and, therefore, I was appointed
                    an FSR-1. (I was actually a GS 18 at Commerce which was a little better.)</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A little higher, probably. I took a cut to come into the
                        Foreign Service, too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: I was an FSR One. Actually, the same kind of attitude that governs
                    anything that's new or different governed there. The people down the line in the
                    appointments process didn't want to have anyone come in at the top.</p>
                <p>A number of months passed. I would see Crockett regularly because of his personal
                    support of those activities I was undertaking on the department's behalf. He
                    would ask me how things were going, and generally I would say, “Just fine.”</p>
                <p>But once, after about three or four months, I said, “It's a little disconcerting.
                    Nobody's called me from the Board of Examiners about an examination.</p>
                <p>He said, “I'll see to that.”</p>
                <p>The next day I got a call from the Board of Examiners, and the Executive Director
                    said, “We've been trying to put a proper panel together. After all, you are a
                    very senior officer, and we have to have a couple of Ambassadors, so it's not
                    just run of the mill.”</p>
                <p>I said, “I understand.”</p>
                <p>“At any rate, we'll be very prompt,” he added.</p>
                <p>And in a few weeks, they did get a panel together.</p>
                <p>I met with the panel, which was chaired by Ambassador Howard Cottam. The panel
                    was determined to, I'm sure, be fair, as a panel is supposed to, but also to
                    probe deeply as to why this individual, who had so much to do with the Foreign
                    Service and Foreign Service people all his life, was just now getting around to
                    taking an examination for the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>Actually, there's something I didn't mention, but is relevant to that particular
                    point. After I got my Ph.D. and was doing that research I referred to very early
                    on, and didn't have a job, one of the professors at Temple University (as a
                    matter of fact the head of the department who had given me the summer assignment
                    and who later hired me, although I didn't accept the position) said he knew
                    someone by the name of Joe Green in the State Department, and if I were
                    interested he'd be glad to write him and arrange for an interview. And I said,
                    “That would be fine, I'd like that.”</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>So, when I went to Washington later, I had a session with Mr. Green, who was just
                    a name to me then, but someone I got to know much better later when I sat on the
                    Staff Board of the Board of the Foreign Service. I was also an alternate on the
                    Board of Examiners—I didn't mention that. But he interviewed me, and he took me
                    in to see the then-Assistant Secretary, I think his name was Shaw.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Howland Shaw.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: G. Howland Shaw. In those days, any applicant for a position would see
                    senior people in a way that doesn't happen today. I did have a session with Mr.
                    Shaw, and he indicated two things: one, that at that time, which was 1938, they
                    were not hiring, and I don't believe there was an examination given at the
                    time.</p>
                <p>But he also proposed something I have never forgotten. He urged me to go home and
                    reflect on it. He said, “You know, you have a marvelous educational background
                    for a Foreign Service assignment.” (Since at that time it had practically all
                    been in history and political science, with a little bit of economics.) He said,
                    “But there's something else one needs in the Foreign Service and that's a call,
                    similar to that you might feel if you were going to become a minister.” He
                    wanted me to go home and see if I got the call. And in that sense, I didn't.
                    But, that's an aside, I suppose.</p>
                <p>In any event, there was no examination except for the other Civil Service
                    examinations that I mentioned, one of which I took and it resulted in that
                    economics job in the Labor Department.</p>
                <p>But back to the Board of Examiners and the panel that was talking with me. I knew
                    them all, which was helpful, but that also meant that they knew of things they
                    could ask in some greater depth than might have been possible had they not.</p>
                <p>They asked me all kinds of questions. I thought every question was very
                    appropriate. Some were very penetrating and some were lighter in tone. It was a
                    grueling experience.</p>
                <p>I can well understand how someone who is junior taking the orals, a much younger
                    person without the experience I'd had, could be frightened and put
                    off-balance.</p>
                <p>At any rate, we had the session, and I was informed shortly thereafter that they
                    had approved my appointment. Then it went through the usual processes, but was
                    held up in the Senate.</p>
                <p>There were two names on the list: mine, and the other was Michael Blumenthal, who
                    had been a reserve officer and a Deputy Assistant Secretary, having come from
                    private industry.</p>
                <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                <p>Our two names went up, but the chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
                    was having some kind of a battle with the department and held up all
                    appointments, including ambassadorial appointments, and our two nominations were
                    among them. So it was several months ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this still J. William, or was it Church by this
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: It was J. William Fulbright.</p>
                <p>But it was approved, and in 1966 I became a Foreign Service Officer Class One, a
                    Secretary in the Diplomatic Service, and so forth. That, obviously, didn't
                    change the nature of the work I was doing or anything of the sort. It just
                    changed ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It gave you a certain kind of job insurance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: That's right, and met one of the criteria I had set for happiness in
                    the job. That was satisfying.</p>
                <p>We were also talking about where I was headed after the completion of my role in
                    the Patent Cooperation Treaty. Actually, they are not causally related, but it
                    did make it easier for me to break away.</p>
                <p>It would have been almost impossible for the department in the latter stages to
                    find someone who could fill in in the same way that I could at that stage of the
                    negotiating process. Harvey Winter had the technical knowledge, but he didn't
                    have the general contacts and clout, although a very able officer.</p>
                <p>The usual wheels started to turn and various positions were looked at. I was told
                    that there were no decent ambassadorial assignments available. Having lost my
                    principal sponsors, who might have been interested in pushing a significant
                    Ambassadorial assignment, I knew that that was probably not in the cards,
                    certainly not in any country I'd care to serve in. So, the personnel people
                    looked for number two slots at embassies or Consul General posts. I preferred to
                    be my own boss.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's a tremendous advantage.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: So, I was offered either Milan or Amsterdam, and I picked
                    Amsterdam.</p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>It was still thought, at that time, that it would be useful for the Consul
                    General, the chief of the post, in addition to at least one other officer, to
                    know Dutch.</p>
                <p>So I enrolled in a Dutch course with my wife. We were the class, as a matter of
                    fact. It was very good. We had two different instructors. There wasn't enough
                    time to do the full 24 weeks, which is regarded as the minimum for the
                    achievement of a 3.3 level. We took 11 or 12 weeks, and I think we both got a 2
                    level out of that. Dutch is a difficult language. I knew some Spanish and
                    ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Dutch is closer to German.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: In getting my doctorate, I had passed the written examination in
                    German, but that was a case of memorizing words and then promptly forgetting
                    them—unfortunately, but that was the case.</p>
                <p>While I thought Dutch was very difficult, we did learn a good deal. And I must
                    say here, in reference to the Foreign Service's language requirements, that I
                    think knowing the language is a very important ingredient, even in a country
                    like Holland where most all the people you meet at senior level speak English.
                    They speak four languages, of which English is usually their number two.</p>
                <p>We traveled the country; we saw more of Holland than most Dutch do. When you get
                    to the small towns and you speak the language, they invite you into things that
                    you'd never get into otherwise. That was one thing. Also, they appreciate the
                    fact that an American has learned their language, because so few of us do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Especially one that's limited to a one-country
                        language.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Only 14 million people around the world speak the language.</p>
                <p>But, also, I had promised myself I was not going to be a prisoner of staff in
                    reading the newspapers. And I was able to read the Dutch newspapers, because
                    there's no substitute. While there is the European edition of the Herald Tribune
                    and so on, it does not cover Dutch events. The only way to keep up with the news
                    in the Netherlands is either through listening to Dutch radio or reading the
                    Dutch newspapers. I had some difficulty listening to the news, I could get some
                    of it, but I had no difficulty reading the Dutch newspapers.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>I continued my Dutch studies in the Netherlands. I had lessons three times a week
                    with a Dutch teacher and became more proficient. Wherever I went it was useful,
                    and it makes more friends for the United States, which is part of our purpose.
                    So that was a very useful, as well as a wholesome, thing.</p>
                <p>The post, itself, for me at this stage of the game, was small potatoes in terms
                    of administration. We had a staff of fewer than 40. I had been running staffs
                    for 30 years that were larger than that.</p>
                <p>It was a new experience in that it was not part of a headquarters staff. It was a
                    new experience in that it was semi-independent, in the sense that the Ambassador
                    always rules the roost overseas. But, even though distances are small, the 35
                    miles between The Hague and Amsterdam was enough of a distance so that there was
                    no interference.</p>
                <p>I served under two political Ambassadors, Middendorf and Gould. Both
                    relationships were excellent—we got along very well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you in charge of all the commercial activities in the
                        country?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, no I was not, and I understood very well why it had to be so. As a
                    matter of fact, I had had close relationships over the years with both the
                    Economic Counselor and the Commercial Attach�. I won't mention their names, but
                    I was partly responsible for keeping the Economic Counselor in the service when
                    he had some difficulties early in his career, and the Commercial Attach� had
                    worked for me on two occasions in the Commerce Department.</p>
                <p>But they both said, you know, this is our job and it's countrywide, and while we
                    know that you know this and that, do you mind if we run economic and commercial
                    activities here. And there was no question in my mind that they were right.</p>
                <p>I had a Commercial officer on my staff, and he's the one who kept those contacts.
                    I regarded my job to be running the Consulate-general and running it well,
                    hopefully.</p>
                <p>There are 11 provinces in the Netherlands and my Consular District included
                    seven. So I was responsible for our relationships with seven Commissarisen, who
                    were the equivalent of state governors, as well as with city and other local
                    officials.</p>
                <p>That was another essential difference in my experience, not working in a
                    headquarters as I had all my life, but working with local authorities. The
                    people I knew best were Commissaris, the Mayor and the Chief of Police and
                    people of that sort, not the Minister of Economic Affairs or his staff.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>Now, there were a couple of highlights (or lowlights) in this experience.</p>
                <p>My wife was a great help. This was a period of change in the status of wives in
                    the Foreign Service, when they were asserting their independence and so on. My
                    wife was not under the heel of an Ambassador's wife. In any event, though
                    independently minded, she stepped in and did the things that a traditional
                    Foreign Service wife should do, in terms of local and community activities and
                    all of those things, and she enjoyed them.</p>
                <p>She had done a lot of volunteer work in things like the League of Women Voters
                    and so on, earlier. It appealed to her and she did them well, and also the usual
                    amount of entertaining that one has to do.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, we were able to do more than usual. This is an aside that
                    might be useful to somebody who listens to this.</p>
                <p>Like every chief at a post, you have a very limited amount of representation
                    expenses. Not being independently wealthy and having been careerists, we were
                    limited in what we could do with our own resources. So, we devised a variety of
                    techniques for entertaining more modestly.</p>
                <p>Her Dutch helped her. We learned of somebody who was just starting out in the
                    catering business. He had a restaurant and was very much interested in the
                    diplomatic end. He was Dutch and knew only Dutch, and he didn't know where to go
                    or who to go to. There was a local resident, that I happened to meet, who
                    introduced him to us.</p>
                <p>My wife was able to establish a relationship with him, initially, purely on the
                    basis of the fact that she could converse with him in Dutch.</p>
                <p>She made an arrangement, which continued throughout our stay, in which he charged
                    us something like 50 percent of what he would charge any other customer for
                    running these affairs. What he got out of it, of course, were the contacts he
                    made by doing a good job for us.</p>
                <p>To mention one or two other things: when I had been in Washington as Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary, one of my contacts was with the Motion Picture
                    Association.</p>
                <p>The Vice President for International Affairs was a former Assistant Secretary of
                    State, named Griffith Johnson. I had known Griff before, in other ways, but we
                    had official relationships because of problems for the US motion picture
                    industry abroad, particularly in repatriating earnings in US dollars.</p>
                <p>As a result of our relationship, I used to receive invitations to come to the
                    Motion Picture Association's preview showings of new films.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>I always found that people who were invited to those, came. Even very prominent
                    people, who would not go to the best of cocktail parties, would come to his
                    private showings.</p>
                <p>During a party that was given just before I departed for Amsterdam, and at which
                    he was present, my wife went to him and said, “Griff, you know it would be a
                    great idea if we could do some of this in Amsterdam. Is there any way we could
                    do it?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, there are a number of representatives of American picture
                    companies. I'll tell you what I'll do, I'll write to our regional representative
                    in Paris and ask him to get in touch with you. You tell him what you want and
                    see if something can be worked out.”</p>
                <p>Soon after I got to Amsterdam, I got a call from Paris. The chap introduced
                    himself and said that one of the company representatives in Amsterdam who
                    handled the Netherlands for the association had asked him to call me, which he
                    did.</p>
                <p>We had a meeting, and I told him what I was interested in doing, which was to
                    have some movie house offer to give me their private screening room, and then
                    let me show current movies.</p>
                <p>Well, out of this initial conversation, I developed relationships with three of
                    the people who had private screening rooms, and about once every month or two, I
                    would put on a private screening.</p>
                <p>What worked in Washington, worked there. Whether they were important local
                    officials, or American businessmen, or whoever—I mean, to be able to walk into a
                    private screening room and sit down ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And see a new film.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Correct. This movie-entertainment socializing was a great success. The
                    Dutch drink a lot of sherry. I learned that at my first party when I was trying
                    to figure out what drinks to serve. So, my wife and I would bring sherry and
                    cookies and a few other things. We'd have a little party beforehand, then have
                    the movie, and then sip something afterwards.</p>
                <p>It turned into a very nice social evening for some 15 to 25 couples, depending on
                    which theater we used. And that supplemented other official-social events. The
                    movie people donated their screening rooms, and all I'd have to do was pay for
                    the screen operators. So, for something like $50 an evening, I'd entertain an
                    average of 20 couples. It was really a great thing.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>I also found that companies, on some occasions when they were having regional
                    meetings abroad, or things of that sort, would want to arrange parties with
                    local officials. I was often able to add a guest list to another guest list to
                    get them in on it. You know, I did the usual things one has to do with those you
                    regard as important, but there were peripheral contacts that I could toss into
                    those parties. It worked out very well.</p>
                <p>So, I did an awful lot of party-giving that I wouldn't have been able to do
                    otherwise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Great, you learned the ropes awfully fast. Since you
                        started in the Foreign Service in 1947, you had some experience for it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: As I said, we decided to tour the country. We used our weekends thus,
                    since the Dutch, like so many Europeans pretty much keep official engagements to
                    weekday evenings. We found ourselves very busy Monday through Friday, but
                    weekends not so much.</p>
                <p>Later in our tour, as we developed a number of Dutch friends, we'd be invited to
                    everything from picnics to hunting parties, which might include a weekend. But
                    in the earlier period, our weekends were free.</p>
                <p>We had decided to pick a different area each weekend, and either drive or take a
                    train, go out and wander around and see the country. This was very useful in
                    many ways.</p>
                <p>One related to the attitude of a couple of the major newspapers toward the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>I've got to go back and remind you that this period was 1971-1974, when we were
                    at the tail end of the height of some of the feeling on Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Anyone over 35, who knew our participation in World War II, the Marshall Plan,
                    and so on, loved the United States. Our relationships with the older generation
                    were great.</p>
                <p>But anybody under 35, roughly speaking, hated the United States with a passion.
                    Since the Dutch have a propensity for involving themselves in other people's
                    affairs, particularly the youngsters, they decided we were “the enemy” at that
                    time. (Later it was the Greek Colonels, and so on.)</p>
                <p>They always have somebody they want especially to love or hate and in that period
                    it was the United States, and the antagonism to our role in Vietnam. They really
                    took off on us.</p>
                <p>Now The Hague was fairly quiet, because it is a quiet city, so the Ambassador was
                    not unduly harassed. He got some attention, but not much.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>But Amsterdam, that was the place. I was not only Mr. Nixon, I was the
                    personification of everything these young people hated about the United States.
                    There would be demonstrations almost daily.</p>
                <p>In the beginning, many of them were small. I would go out and discuss Vietnam
                    with these youngsters (it would usually turn into argument), and I would do it
                    in their language. I had been in Vietnam, they had not, so it gave me an
                    advantage. And I would argue the case.</p>
                <p>But when the groups got to be very large, you just couldn't do that. Once or
                    twice I invited them into the consulate general for discussions, but that didn't
                    work very well.</p>
                <p>The demonstrations escalated. We had two, more or less serious, events. One was
                    an occupation of the Consulate General.</p>
                <p>This was a period when these kinds of things were just beginning to happen around
                    the world. The Department of State was definitely not geared up to handle, not
                    even to understand, this kind of thing.</p>
                <p>I think the only international event of consequence in this regard had been the
                    Pan Am plane incident in Jordan, where they'd been blown up. But nobody expected
                    anything in a nice country like the Netherlands.</p>
                <p>I would report from time to time, either as part of an embassy report or my own,
                    on some of these demonstrations. But when they got to be a daily event, they
                    appeared routine and our reports were ignored. The people back home were not
                    interested in reading that kind of stuff, anyhow.</p>
                <p>But on one occasion one morning, we were occupied. Shall I go into it?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Sure, by all means.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: I don't know whether we were the first establishment that was
                    occupied, but we were one of the early ones at any rate.</p>
                <p>What essentially happened is that when we opened our doors about 8:30, the
                    demonstrators planned it so that they could rush in behind the officer who
                    opened the door.</p>
                <p>I should point out that the previous evening the administrative officer at the
                    Embassy called to say that someone at a tavern was overheard to say an American
                    establishment was going to be taken over at some unspecified time.</p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>Curiously enough, I had gotten word that something might be happening to an
                    American installation, somewhere in the Netherlands, sometime in the next two
                    weeks. I had heard that the night before.</p>
                <p>It could have been a military base. We had two consulates general and the
                    embassy—it could have been one of them. It could have been a business
                    establishment, one didn't' know. Nevertheless, I took it seriously.</p>
                <p>I called the Chief of Police and alerted them to it, and he said he would put
                    some cars on watch around the Consulate General.</p>
                <p>I learned later that he did (they assigned a Volkswagen, which they were using to
                    roam around the city in those days), but that officer had gone off duty at eight
                    o'clock.</p>
                <p>So, at 8:30, our door was rushed. I was just getting ready to leave the house,
                    which was a half-mile from the consulate general, to come to the office.</p>
                <p>We generally opened at 8:30; though we didn't open for business to the general
                    public until 9:00. And opening for business was important because we were one of
                    the largest visa-issuing posts in the world. I think in my last full year, 1973,
                    we issued 42,000 visas—it was a lot of visas.</p>
                <p>I got a call from my Commercial officer saying that he had barricaded himself in
                    his room. We had been occupied. There were two local employees in the building
                    that he knew of, and that was about it.</p>
                <p>He had taken one peek in the hall before he pushed a desk or something up against
                    the wall. They hadn't disturbed him, but he didn't know when he could get to the
                    phone again.</p>
                <p>I called The Hague, spoke to the Ambassador, and I asked for instructions.</p>
                <p>He asked, “What are you going to do?”</p>
                <p>I said, “As soon as I get off the phone with you I'm going to call the Chief of
                    Police, and get up to the Consulate-general, and we'll get these people
                    out.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, that's fine with me. Go to it.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Patted you firmly on the back and...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Those were Middendorf's instructions to me.</p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>I called the Chief of Police, and we met at a corner near the consulate
                    general.</p>
                <p>These people had taken over the building. They had banners up from the top floor
                    saying: “We won't get out until the US gets out of Vietnam,” or something to
                    that effect. They had horns and they were blaring forth and what not.</p>
                <p>We discussed ways of getting into the building. There were some little
                    foul-ups—they didn't bring any ladders that would get to the second floor and so
                    on, but within a half-hour they had the necessary equipment, and they started to
                    do that.</p>
                <p>And then I remembered that one of our back doors had a broken latch (it was a
                    metal sliding door). The building was very easy to get out of; it was very hard
                    to get into once you bolted everything up. In addition to bolting all the doors
                    and windows they had put file cabinets up against all the doors. But the back
                    door was a weak spot, so we were able to get that open.</p>
                <p>And then they told me, under Dutch law you had to give the people who were
                    occupying the building a chance to get out. So, I asked for the leader.</p>
                <p>They said, “We're all leaders.”</p>
                <p>So I shouted that they'd accomplished their purpose, they'd taken over the
                    building, now wouldn't it be a nice thing if they got out peacefully, or
                    something to that effect.</p>
                <p>They refused.</p>
                <p>I was discursive that day and I made three separate appeals, asking them to get
                    out.</p>
                <p>Later, when the matter went to court, I learned that if I hadn't done it three
                    times, it wouldn't have been legal.</p>
                <p>After the third time they still wouldn't get out, so we had the police break
                    through this already partial opening. They took them all into custody and
                    arrested them. We went back in the building and it was ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They hadn't destroyed files or anything?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: No, in that we were fortunate. They used files only as barricades,
                    used desks only as barricades. They didn't try to get into any classified
                    material, which we only had in limited amount, and almost all in one secure
                    place in the consulate general. So, there was no security problem from that
                    standpoint.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>They were interested in making a point. They had planned to stay 24 hours, I
                    learned later. Instead of that, they were in there an hour and a half.</p>
                <p>I was on the board of the American Schools. I had offered to have a Board
                    luncheon that day in the consulate general, which is not set up to serve lunch,
                    but we were going to do it.</p>
                <p>By God, at 12:30, we had lunch. Everybody on the staff pitched in, got every desk
                    back, files straightened up, everything all ready. And we were back in business
                    by noon. That show of team spirit and loyalty was really great.</p>
                <p>But, at any rate, that was a very unpleasant experience.</p>
                <p>Another, that was also unpleasant and more fraught with potential danger, was
                    this incident. We contracted with a firm to have our establishment cleaned
                    regularly. What they would do was generally clean waste baskets, tidy up
                    bathrooms, and so on, every day, but do the heavier cleaning once a week.</p>
                <p>The consulate, on the ground floor, had a big, waiting room area where people
                    interested in visas, passports, and services of various kinds would come in and
                    then be serviced by our employees. That waiting room still had some of the old
                    overstuffed furniture that was a relic of by-gone years.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, the consulate general had been used by the German commander of
                    Amsterdam as his headquarters during the war, and the residence was used as his
                    residence. There were some things, including security stuff, in the basement
                    that were still a remnant of the German occupation.</p>
                <p>But the point was that this was a big, open room in which people sought services.
                    We generally closed at five o'clock for outside visitors, and then our staff
                    used the next half hour or so to get things organized and files away. The
                    American staff, most of them, would stay as long as whatever they were doing
                    required.</p>
                <p>About 4:30 one afternoon, I got a call from one of my local employees, who
                    handled visas, saying that he thought we had a bomb, could I come downstairs. I
                    was on the second floor US (first floor European.) I came down to the ground
                    floor, and I said, “Hans, what is it?”</p>
                <p>He said, “There was a big package (something that would resemble a Safeway or
                    Giant grocery package here in the United States), which I found behind that
                    sofa.” And he said, “I picked it up and I took it out and threw it in the
                    bushes.”</p>
                <p>And I said, “You thought it was a bomb, you say?”</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>“Yes.”</p>
                <p>“Well, you should never have picked it up.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Well, I didn't think about anything. At any rate, it's sitting there in
                    the bushes.”</p>
                <p>I gingerly went over and listened, and I thought I heard something ticking away.
                    So I called the police. They said they would send somebody right over. Well, it
                    took them almost ten minutes to get anyone. A squad car came by, an officer
                    looked at it, and he said, “There's a bomb in that.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, what are you going to do about it?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Look, we don't know if it's a big one, a little one, or what it can do,
                    or anything of the sort. We need an expert.”</p>
                <p>I asked, “Do you have an expert?”</p>
                <p>He said, “We have one man on the force who specializes in this.”</p>
                <p>(This takes on, somewhat, the characteristics of a not-so-funny comedy, but
                    anyhow ...)</p>
                <p>So I said, “Well, get him, quickly!”</p>
                <p>They didn't have any walkie talkies, so they said they'd send one of the squad
                    cars out to find him. Well, it took 20 minutes for them to find this fellow, who
                    came riding up on a bicycle.</p>
                <p>He took one look at the bag in the bushes and said, “That's a bomb.” He said, “I
                    wonder if it's a percussion bomb because if it is I don't want to touch it.”</p>
                <p>I said, “It's not a percussion bomb. It was inside, it was carried out here.”</p>
                <p>He said, “Oh, okay.” And he turned to me and asked, “Does anyone around here have
                    a pair of pliers?” (This is in the year 1973, a big-city's expert on bombs.)</p>
                <p>So we went to one of our cars and got a pair of pliers. And he defused the bomb.
                    Then he took it apart, and I have shots of all the parts and everything
                    else.</p>
                <p>He said, “In five minutes that would have gone off.”</p>
                <p>I asked, “And what would have happened in five minutes?”</p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>He said, “If it was in the building where it was placed, it would have blown the
                    building to pieces and everyone would have been killed.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Boy! That's something for your memory book.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: What do you do at that stage? By this time there were crowds around,
                    newspaper people, including a couple of stringers for the US media. I made a
                    quick decision. (And remember we didn't have much experience in that sort of
                    thing at that time.) I decided that one of the things that whoever had put it
                    there wanted to do, aside from killing some of us, was to get publicity. So, I
                    offered no interviews. As matter of fact, we closed the consulate general and I
                    quickly left. And I was unavailable that evening.</p>
                <p>The next day, I got several calls. I said things had worked out all right and so
                    on and so forth. As a result there was very little publicity about it.</p>
                <p>The mayor, of course, called me, and he was very hopeful that I wouldn't try to
                    make a big thing out of it.</p>
                <p>The mayor and I had become good personal friends, although politically we were at
                    odds. He was a Socialist, and I am not. He was 100 percent against our
                    participation in Vietnam. We used to have tremendous arguments on this score.
                    And by 1973, a lot of Americans were very much against our ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Even before that. I mean when you have two boys in college
                        in the '60s...</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Yes. Well, he thought I might, or somebody might make me, use this
                    against the city in some way. And I told him that I was going to keep it quiet,
                    and he was very much relieved. And we did.</p>
                <p>But, you sit there and you wonder: Is this person going to try tomorrow? The next
                    day? Where? How?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have any indication of who did it? They
                        wouldn't have claimed credit until it blew.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: Nobody indicated anything, and nothing on that score ever occurred
                    again. Our house was broken into, but I don't think it was related to that. At
                    any rate, it gave me pause.</p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>One of the things we began to do was to change the physical nature of the
                    consulate general. We got funds to put up barriers and bullet-proof windows. We
                    employed a security guard.</p>
                <p>As we began to move into the latter part of 1973 and early 1974, with much of the
                    activity continuing, I found that instead of spending my time making friends for
                    the United States, as well as handling the routine tasks that one has to, I was
                    spending an awful lot of time on security.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm afraid that's the history of a lot of the Foreign
                        Service in the last ten years or 15 years.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: And it went against the grain. I always felt that when a foreigner
                    came to the US Embassy or the Consulate-general, his first vision of the United
                    States should be that we are a free and open society. That's what he should see.
                    But when he had to come and find barriers and so on ...</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And yet, still, a solution to the problem is of immense
                        importance. Well, we're practically at the end of this tape. Do you have any
                        final thought?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>BRADERMAN: My final thought is that of all my experiences and so on in my varied
                    life, I've had a relationship with the Foreign Service all these years. One of
                    the reasons I feel such a deep interest in DACOR is because it's an organization
                    of Foreign Service people.</p>
                <p>I think the Department of State does a better job than most agencies in keeping
                    contact with those who served in one way or another—Foreign Service Day and
                    other things being examples. I think it was a mistake to have revoked passes.
                    That was a good indication that people were still part of the heart of the
                    Department. And I don't think security would have suffered very much. But I feel
                    a close affinity with the Department and with those who serve and have served
                    there, not only because there is this shared experience but because there is a
                    continuing intense concern with world affairs.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
