<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000979">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Idar D. Rimestad </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>DEPUTY UNDER SECRETARY IDAR D. RIMESTAD</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Thomas Stern </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: June 22, 1990</p>
                <p>Copyright 1998 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like to start by asking about your personal
                        background.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I was born and raised in North Dakota. I went to the University of
                    North Dakota and got a Bachelor of Philosophy degree in 1940. In 1941, I went to
                    Washington and obtained a job with the National Youth Administration. After six
                    weeks of training, I was assigned to personnel work. I had looked at the various
                    activities in the NYA and was not an engineer, not a teacher; there were a lot
                    of positions for which I was not qualified, but I was attracted to the
                    management-personnel field.</p>
                <p>After some further training, I ended up in the salary-wage division. I worked
                    there until December, 1942 at which time I transferred to the Office of the
                    Quartermasters' Office, in the salary-wage program. I stayed there until the
                    latter part of 1944 as a civilian employee. Then I transferred to the Manhattan
                    District, which was the organization that preceded the Atomic Energy Commission.
                    I was still in a salary-wage division, but with a much broader scope. It was a
                    small office which got into other management activities dealing with wages.A
                    salary-wage analyst would analyze an organizational unit—what it did, how it
                    fitted into the whole organizational structure. Then he would interview the
                    people in that unit and then would write job descriptions. Sometimes the
                    descriptions matched the capabilities of the employees, sometimes they didn't.
                    After we would finish a survey, we had a full picture of what the unit should be
                    doing and what its salary structure should be. This is the government's method
                    of setting salaries for its civil service. There was not usually very much
                    difference among government organizations on how salary-wage analyses were
                    conducted. There were people who went out to analyze specific problem jobs. I
                    spent most of time in that business looking at and working on total units.
                    Sometimes, it was a pleasant job—you could raise salaries; sometimes, it was
                    very unpleasant because the individual didn't measure up and management would
                    then transfer some of his duties to others. That was the very unpleasant part of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you enjoy the work? It was considerably different from
                        your academic training.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I enjoyed the work very much. Every day was a new day. You could go to
                    work in the morning and never know what you would encounter when you got into
                    the organizations. It was amazing in that people, to a considerable extent,
                    found their own level. If they were very productive and very good, you found
                    that they took over the more responsible jobs. Then there was the other side.
                    The person who doesn't quite measure up has duties taken away and put into a
                    position in which he will not produce too much, but also will not cause any
                    problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is an interesting comment because the public's view
                        of civil servants is that they are in a job which they do over and over
                        again and seldomly rise to the occasion. Your experience apparently was
                        different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. The fact of the matter is that people are different. Some are
                    better than others. There are those that are not going to sit there doing the
                    same thing day after day. They are going to reach for more duties; they are
                    going to reach for promotions. Others find their level wherever that might be
                    and sit there for the rest of their lives. Those who reach for additional duties
                    are rewarded by an upward reclassification of their positions or a vacancy at a
                    higher level arises and they move into it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's return to your career. In 1944, you started with the
                        Manhattan Division.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Right. I was there until mid-1946. It was still at that time part of
                    the U.S. military under General Groves. Then I got a telegram from G-1, which
                    was the U.S. Army in Europe asking whether I would like to come over there for a
                    year or two to help establish the salary-wage program for U.S. Army in Europe.
                    At that time, every division and every army had its own system and it was a
                    mess. Some uniformity had to be established for indigenous employees. There were
                    few American civilian employees in Europe at this time. It was mostly military
                    and indigenous personnel.</p>
                <p>When I left in November, 1946 I went on a one or two year assignment, after which
                    I could return although about this time the Manhattan District was being
                    converted to the Atomic Energy Commission—that happened towards the end of 1946
                    or early 1947. By that time, I was in Europe—Frankfurt for a while and then
                    Heidelberg, enjoying my work. it was a completely new operation. The first year
                    flew by rather quickly and I was asked to make decision on whether I wished to
                    return to the US to exercise my re-employment rights or would I prefer to stay
                    in Europe. At that point, I didn't want to leave.</p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>At about this time—late 1948—there were discussion about establishing the High
                    Commissioner's Office and they were recruiting. I along with several others was
                    asked to come to Frankfurt to be interviewed for jobs. I was being considered
                    for a position in salary-wage administration with the possibility of becoming
                    the assistant director of personnel if things worked out. One of the division
                    directors would be selected to be the deputy to the Chief of Personnel. Glenn
                    Wolfe was responsible for the management side of the High Commissioner. Dave
                    Wilkin interviewed me, but I also talked to Glenn Wolfe. I was offered the
                    wage-salary position and accepted it and stayed there for approximately three
                    years. Then I became the assistant chief of the Personnel office.</p>
                <p>We were going through a very hefty reduction of personnel at that time. we were
                    turning activities back to the Germans and therefore reducing our own personnel.
                    I was the assistant chief for about six months and then I was promoted to
                    Director of Personnel for the High Commission. In late 1951, we—my family and
                    myself—had moved to the Bad Godesberg office and housing complex which had been
                    built under Glenn Wolfe's direction. Bad Godesberg was close to Bonn, which had
                    become West Germany's new temporary capital. The living in Bad Godesberg was
                    very nice. We had our own grocery store, swimming pool, gymnasium, school. It
                    was a totally self contained unit. One didn't have to go near the German economy
                    if one didn't want to. But the situation was rapidly changing by the mid-1950s.
                    In 1947-48, the German economy was in terrible shape. The whole system was in
                    bad shape. The Office of the High Commissioner did what the Army had done; it
                    set up self-contained units that didn't have to rely on the local economy. by
                    the time I left in 1954, the economy had improved to the point that a lot of
                    one's material needs could be acquired from local stores. I don't know if and
                    when the Bad Godesberg commissary was closed, but it certainly wasn't necessary
                    after 1955-56.</p>
                <p>If the commissary stayed open after that or worse, if it is still open, it is a
                    little sad because it encouraged Americans never to go to the German economy.
                    They could have been in Bad Godesberg for two years and never leave the American
                    compound, which is sad. I can understand it happening in Moscow or China or in a
                    lot of places where some support is necessary. But in Western Europe it
                    certainly wasn't necessary after the mid 1950s.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>I returned to Washington in the Spring of 1954. When I joined the High
                    Commission, I was appointed as a Staff-2 Officer. Subsequently a group of three
                    State Department officials came to Germany looking for people in the High
                    Commissioner's Office who wished to make the Foreign Service their career. I had
                    that interview—the only member of the team that I can remember was Huston Lay, a
                    lawyer. I was approved for transfer to a permanent Foreign Service appointment.
                    I had by this time already decided that I would enjoy a career in the Foreign
                    Service. I didn't see myself as remaining in personnel work, but wanted to get
                    into some over-all management position eventually. I had enjoyed my assignment
                    in Germany immensely. I had found it a real challenge. It had involved relating
                    to high ranking civilians and generals. As in everything else, you don't win all
                    the battles, but you had to win a fair share. When you made decisions, better
                    than half had better be right. You can't operate very long if you don't. While
                    in Germany, one of the people I got to know well was John J. McCloy. People had
                    a tendency to go to him to complain. So I would trot up to his office and
                    explain the situation to him. He never reversed me once in approximately the
                    dozen cases that were raised with him. I was of course very careful on some of
                    these because they were lawyers, economists. etc. out of the U.S. who had joined
                    his staff. Frankly, a lot didn't measure up and were transferred to positions
                    which were somewhat lower than the original appointments or contracts called
                    for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did McCloy get involved in management to any considerable
                        extent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I am sure he talked often with Glenn Wolfe. He was a hands-on manager.
                    I got to know him later on again in another job. He was always hands-on and
                    didn't brook any nonsense. If you tended to be too loquacious or if you
                    wandered, he got you back on track in a hurry. He was a very effective
                    administrator, but he also let you do your work. He didn't bother you unless
                    something came up that invariably involved a friend or someone who was in
                    Germany whom he felt he had to massage a little bit or to take the time to
                    convince him that he had looked into it. The large problems were over-all
                    management and housing with which I was not involved. I was strictly
                    personnel.</p>
                <p>In 1956, I was assigned to the Washington Regional Personnel Division in the
                    Department of State. This was a unit that placed Foreign Service officers in
                    positions in Washington which had been designated as positions to be filled by
                    Foreign Service employees. Bob Ryan was one of the top men in the personnel
                    office at that time. My job was to talk to the various bureaus in the State
                    Department to see what their upcoming needs might be and to inform them that I
                    had a Foreign Service officer who might fit that vacancy. Sometimes you had to
                    go to two or three Bureaus before the officer was placed.</p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>I was in that unit for six-eight months and then was put in charge, under an
                    officer by the name of Sydney Laffon. He was a very nice fellow, a typical
                    Foreign Service officer. He was smart; he knew the system. The Wriston program
                    was in full bloom at this time. He knew changes were coming and he wanted to
                    accommodate to them. I had been there for a year perhaps when I applied for an
                    FSO appointment under the Wriston program. I was interviewed and accepted as an
                    FSO-3, which corresponded to my grade of FSS-1; they wouldn't promote in the
                    transfer, but they would bring you in laterally.</p>
                <p>I stayed in that position until November, 1957. Those were interesting times
                    because we were bringing people to Washington, as recommended by the Wriston
                    Commission. Many didn't really wanted to come, but they had been overseas for
                    four, five, six years and the policy had become that if they had been overseas
                    for that long, it was time to assign them to Washington for a tour of duty. I
                    generally sympathized with that policy. I am not sure that I agreed with the
                    strict enforcement of bringing officers to Washington every four years because
                    situations differed. I did agree that they shouldn't stay in India, for example,
                    or Guatemala six or eight years. That was wrong. When these officers returned to
                    the U.S., it was a foreign country for them. One has to guard against that
                    syndrome. However, if you are in London or Paris, that is a different situation.
                    For those assigned to Third World countries, it was important that they return
                    to see what was going on in the real world.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us a little about the personnel system in the late
                        1950s. It has been alleged that it was very much “club” oriented; that is
                        geographically oriented with each Regional Bureau taking care of its own
                        officers. Is that the way it was?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, but it is probably never going to change. People in the European
                    Bureau get to know each other. They will know the junior officers as they rise
                    through the ranks. There is a tendency on everyone's part to be with people they
                    know and whom they know to be capable. Sometimes, the “old buddy” system brings
                    people that are not so capable, but that one would find any place. The system at
                    that time worked pretty well if you had a Personnel Office in Washington that
                    was strong enough to oppose successfully the Assistant Secretaries. Many of the
                    Assistant Secretaries were hard-nosed. They wouldn't accept nonsense from
                    anybody. There was one EUR Assistant Secretary who was particularly difficult.
                    But his Executive Director, Herman Pollack, was easy to work with. I liked him.
                    If he felt you were doing your job, he would support you. Fred Irving followed
                    Pollack and he was another good man. Again, if you did your job, he would back
                    you. If he had differences with you, he would discuss them with you. These men
                    had great influence; very rarely did the Assistant Secretary over-ride them or
                    take issue with them on personnel cases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But as a system, you were satisfied then how the personnel
                        assignment process worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, because the people making the assignments, in every instance, were
                    people who were part of the system, who were in Personnel for a four or six year
                    tour of duty and then went on. They were not professionals in the sense that
                    they came to Personnel and were going to spend their lives in that office,
                    assigning people here and there. It doesn't take a mental giant to figure out
                    that if EUR needed a political officer to work with a foreign President's staff
                    or Foreign Ministry, you had to have an officer who had some knowledge of that
                    country's political situation and who spoke the language of the country. He also
                    had be a personable fellow and out-going. That is the kind of officer you
                    needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a professional personnel man, did you have any qualms
                        with Foreign Service officers working in the Personnel Office?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No. I felt that one of the greatest assets at that time was the
                    assignment to Personnel of people of different experiences and background so
                    that they could see that Personnel didn't have six heads. When they returned to
                    their areas of specializations, they then trusted the system and brought that
                    trust to their colleagues. It was a great plus. It may be still true today, but
                    back then, there was great trepidation when people had to do business with the
                    Personnel Office because they didn't trust it. But if they knew someone in the
                    Office or had worked in it, they were much more comfortable. This had a way of
                    getting back to the top people in the Department. That is where it really
                    helped. If the lower rank officers and staff are happy, then this obviously
                    colors the leadership's view. Until officers got to senior positions, such as
                    chief political or economic officer or DCM, we had very few problems. It worked
                    well. When they reached the senior levels, that small group at the top, then you
                    had a different situation. The Ambassador had strong feelings about whom he
                    wanted; the Assistant Secretary had strong feeling about whom he wanted. At any
                    one time, we had a half dozen officers who could do a given job. Whom do you
                    select?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you assigned to the domestic side of Personnel all
                        during this period or did you move into foreign assignments as well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: My job throughout the period was placing Foreign Service officers into
                    Washington positions. I had nothing to do with Civil Service or with overseas
                    assignments. Every month I would get a list of people who would be available for
                    assignment in the next three months and then I would try to place them.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>When you got to the senior positions, that was difficult at times. There were
                    officers who had not worked out very well. We had a medical complement—that was
                    an over-complement, to which “hard-to-place” officers were assigned as a holding
                    operation. I am sure that it is still part of today's system. What would one do
                    with an officer who just hadn't worked out and every one knew it and no one
                    wanted him? Yet, he had efficiency reports that were pretty good. So we would
                    bring him back on that over-complement list. That was always a problem. We used
                    to have as many as 50 or 60 people on that list. The pressure from senior levels
                    was always to get rid of that complement to save money. But I think it is a
                    necessary part of any system that requires relatively frequent re-assignments.
                    There may be an officer coming from India, for example, who had been there for
                    four years who ran into some problem—be it medical or professional—that makes
                    him difficult to place. What is the system going to do with him? He has to be
                    put in some place so that he can get paid while his problem is being resolved.
                    You can't fire him; there is no basis for doing that. The written record does
                    not provide a basis for doing that at that time. The complement was also used
                    for good officers who because of accident of timing could not be assigned to
                    permanent positions, but whom we knew would eventually be so assigned. There
                    were lots of those; as a matter of fact, I think most of the officers on the
                    over-complement list fell into that category. Only approximately 10% of the
                    complement was impossible; the rest wasn't. Most of the assignment problems
                    arose because the vacancies did not match the skills of the officers who were
                    available. I had a number of good friends who were very competent, but for whom
                    we didn't have an appropriate vacancy. But we knew that we would have some. So
                    we would put one on the complement and when the vacancy arose, we had an officer
                    immediately available. We often put officers in that situation in the offices to
                    which they would be eventually assigned, but they would continue to be charged
                    to Personnel's budget until the actual transfer to a permanent position
                    occurred.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your next assignment was to Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In 1957, I knew that my tour of duty in the Department was coming to an
                    end and I had to think about what my next assignment would be. I talked to Syd
                    Laffon. He said he would look into overseas possibilities. He said that there
                    were two jobs that he knew would be opening in late 1957: one, was
                    administrative counselor in Madrid and the other was administrative officer in
                    Moscow. There were some other people in the room during this discussion.
                    Everybody jumped and said that I should take Madrid—beautiful housing, a nice
                    club, etc. Every single person in the room said the same thing. They thought I
                    would be a fool not to take Madrid. It would be a delightful place to spend four
                    years. I thought to myself that I heard this so much—an officer goes to a post
                    because of family considerations, for reasons having nothing to do with the job.
                    Then he's stuck; he sits for four years doing little in a very nice set-up. So I
                    asked for a few days to consider the choice. I talked to my wife; she thought
                    Madrid would be great. There was a school there. If we went to Moscow, we would
                    have to send our two girls to West Germany—it had the nearest American school—a
                    school run by the U.S. military. One of my daughters was to be a junior in high
                    school and the other would just start eighth grade.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>I thought about the various issues and finally decided on Moscow. It was a post
                    where things were happening. If I were to make the Foreign Service my career,
                    then that would be the place to go. So I surprised everybody. Fred Irving called
                    me and asked: “Are you sure that this is what you want? You prefer Moscow over
                    Madrid?”. I said: “Yes”. This was the Fall of 1957. It was one of the career
                    turning points for me because I got to Moscow and everything broke loose. First
                    there was a big American exposition during which the Nixon-Khrushchev “kitchen”
                    debate took place—I was just a couple of feet away from Nixon during that
                    dialogue. Then the U-2 plane, piloted by Gary Powers, went down—I was one of the
                    half-dozen officials who got the first view of the plane.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me take you back to late 1957 when you were first
                        assigned to Moscow as administrative officer. Until then, your experience
                        had been entirely in the field of personnel. Your Moscow position had a much
                        broader range of responsibilities? How was the transition?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was very easy because as a salary-wage man, I had become familiar
                    with all the administrative jobs. I had spent lots of time in procurement, lots
                    in finance—reviewing what people were doing. It wasn't going into something that
                    was completely new. As a salary-wage analyst, I had gotten into every one of
                    those administrative activities. And I knew them pretty well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you felt comfortable with other areas of administration
                        besides personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I would not have been comfortable getting into economics or
                    political work or public affairs; that I wouldn't have messed with.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the ambassador in Moscow in 1957?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Llewellyn Thompson—a great guy. I didn't know him at all when the
                    assignment was made. Thompson called Fred Irving, whom he knew well. He asked
                    Fred whether he should take me. Fred said: “Yes. Absolutely. Take him”. I
                    arrived in Moscow not knowing anybody, the Ambassador, the DCM, anybody, not a
                    single soul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that feel?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was difficult because Fred Irving sent me with some instructions.
                    For example, the Political Section and most of the Economic Section were using
                    Embassy vehicles as if they were their personal cars. Fred wanted that stopped.
                    He was concerned that one of the people would get involved in an accident and
                    that then the Department would have to explain what an officer was doing on a
                    Sunday afternoon on an outing with his family in a government car. These weren't
                    trips in the city; they were going out into the country-side. Fred wanted that
                    practice stopped. So I went to the Ambassador and explained to him that the
                    Embassy had a problem with its senior officers using government cars on weekends
                    for personal use and that I had been instructed to stop the practice. If anyone
                    needed a car, he or she should get either the Ambassador's or my approval, so
                    that we could document the reasons for the use of the car. That new directive
                    did not go over very well because the use of government vehicles for personal
                    purposes had been the practice for many years. We only had five or six sedans
                    and every Friday night, officers would take the cars and use them over the
                    weekend. But that stopped.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were the living conditions in Moscow in the late
                        1950s?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: We had two sets of living quarters for the American staff. We had
                    apartments in the Embassy itself—that is where I lived—and then we had an
                    apartment building near the University. I wouldn't say that living conditions
                    were tough. The most difficult aspect of living in Moscow came from the
                    isolation—we had no Russian friends; all contacts were with other Embassies. The
                    diet was fairly restricted. There were two or three restaurants one could go to.
                    We got a half a dozen tickets to the Bolshoi every week, which would be given to
                    whom ever asked for them. The first year of my tour was alright. It was
                    interesting. The second year was not so interesting. When I got into the third
                    year, I didn't like it at all. It was dull; you couldn't do anything. You could
                    walk the streets, but there was no social life except within your own group. I
                    was very friendly with the Germans, the British, Italians, French and the
                    Scandinavians. We had good relations with the Turkish Embassy and the Japanese
                    Embassy. That was about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How often did you get out of Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Every six months. I got out easily because there was the Ambassador's
                    plane that came in every six months. I would take it to Germany to buy goods for
                    the Embassy and the Commissary. I would fly back to Moscow the following week.
                    The plane would also carry about a dozen staff members. There were a lot of
                    people who didn't want to avail themselves of this opportunity because the plane
                    flew into Berlin and then they were on their own. They didn't want to go there.
                    Tickets to Copenhagen and Stockholm were very cheap. So there was no problem in
                    leaving Moscow. People would save up their leave so that they could take an
                    extensive vacation in Italy or France or some other country.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the limited social life was wearing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. As I said, not for the first year. Everyone enjoyed the first
                    year; it was fun and interesting. Most people didn't stay for more than two
                    years. I stayed more because Eisenhower was scheduled to come to Moscow. That
                    didn't happen, but I was requested to remain at post during the planning period.
                    I didn't leave Moscow until August 1960, although I was eligible to leave the
                    previous November. The Eisenhower visit was canceled because of the U-2
                    incident.</p>
                <p>We had one or two private Americans in Moscow at that time and they found it a
                    hardship. Most of the Foreign Service personnel had been in places like
                    Nicaragua or Indonesia or other Third World countries. They didn't find Moscow
                    too bad in terms of living conditions. They thought they were pretty good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What is the role of administration in an Embassy like
                        Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Total and complete logistical support, including groceries. We worked
                    with the Russians (BUROBIN was the name of the organization we worked with) in
                    handling problems that our personnel got involved in or getting more trips to
                    Leningrad and matters of that kind—the social aspects, not the official ones. My
                    office was the contact with the Russians on everything, except for political or
                    economic work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Russians provided the local personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. All good KGB people. That was well known—no question about it. We
                    were always finding wire-taps on telephones. Some of the Russians were maids.
                    I'll never forget the naval attach� who was fiddling around with his telephone
                    one day. He unscrewed it and out popped a small gadget. It was a listening
                    device which had been placed between the two beds. He said: “ Wait until my wife
                    finds out. She is always after me to come over to her bed to visit her. She will
                    be very unhappy!”. We found a lot of that type of thing. I remember that when
                    Ambassador Thompson wanted to discuss some sensitive issue, he would hand me a
                    piece of paper and we would exchange written notes instead of conversation. He
                    used to say that there was just no way of knowing how the Russians might have
                    bugged his office. It was about at this time that we got a secure room, but your
                    inclination is to blurt out one sentence assuming that this wouldn't make any
                    difference.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>But the whole building was bugged—every room. They bugged the rooms by placing
                    devices behind the radiators. The bugging system was a single system so that
                    moving one radiator didn't make any difference. You would have to shut the whole
                    water system down. They had been there for several years before I got there.
                    They were there during the two and half years I was there and they were there
                    after that. If someone would have moved his refrigerator, he would have spotted
                    the bug.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The local employees had access to the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, up to the fifth floor. On the sixth floor, there were the DCM's
                    and the military attach�'s residences. The seventh and eighth floors were
                    offices. So the locals did not have access to those floors unless they were
                    escorted by a Marine Guard. My office was on the first floor to which the locals
                    had access.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was the American staff while you were in Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It had its ups and downs. In general, I thought they were very good. On
                    the administrative side, with probably one exception, I would have hired them
                    all. They were very good. They were a gung-ho group. I didn't realize until I
                    was leaving that one of my officers was an alcoholic. I never knew it. I always
                    wondered why he was never available on weekends. You could never reach him. That
                    is when he would load up. The rest of the week he didn't touch alcohol. He was
                    the only one who could have been a problem. As a matter of fact, after his
                    return to the U.S., he got into some kind of trouble and was let go. I am sure
                    that the Department screened potential assignees very carefully before sending
                    them to Moscow. One had to be pretty well adjusted to be assigned to Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the stress of confinement and limited social
                        activities affect personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, particularly the wives. They would be contentious; they would find
                    problems where there weren't any or complain about perceived problems that
                    couldn't be solved. There were problems that went with being in Moscow; if a
                    wife couldn't accommodate to them, I would call in the officer and asked him to
                    get matters under control because there wasn't anything we could do. Moscow was
                    Moscow and couldn't be changed. Some would be unhappy with us for not having
                    fresh vegetables or meat or something along those lines. I would ask the officer
                    whether he wanted to stand in line at the meat market. He or his wife could
                    stand in line for hours, but would probably get some meat. There was no way the
                    Embassy could provide the meat. The complaints were about little stuff. It
                    didn't affect efficiency or subject people to KGB enticements. There were a
                    number of individuals, as history has told us, who apparently did play around,
                    but it was not obvious to us at the time. The KGB was a problem for single
                    people.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had a Marine detachment during your tour?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. They were no problem while I was there. The problems with the
                    Marines came later after my tour. We did have one Army fellow who was
                    socializing too much; so the Army transferred him out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who was the DCM when you arrived in Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Richard (Dick) Davis. Just before my departure from Moscow, Davis was
                    replaced—he had been the DCM for two of the years I was there. Neither of the
                    DCMs was involved in the management and administration of the Embassy. They
                    generally left me totally and completely alone. Dick would listen to his wife
                    and come back with some tales about alleged problems. For example, we needed a
                    garage for our automobiles. We had a big vacant lot beside the Embassy. I had
                    decided to take one-half and build a garage on it so we could get all our cars
                    under cover. We had eleven vehicles and only three could be inside. The ladies
                    opposed the idea because the vacant area was being used by their children as a
                    playground. I had watched this for sometime; there was a lot of mud when it
                    rained. It wasn't really a playground in any sense of the word. But Mrs. Davis
                    got all the ladies together and they all agreed that no garage should be built
                    and that the playground should remain as it was. I went to the Ambassador and
                    told him that we desperately needed the garage. I pointed out that half of the
                    lot—75 feet by 100 feet—would still be available for play. That is a big lot to
                    play on. He asked: “For heaven's sake, who is creating this problem?”. So I told
                    him that Dick Davis's wife was leading the opposition. He said: “Forget it. I'll
                    take care of it”. I never heard another word about it. That was the only time
                    that I went to the Ambassador with an administrative problem. We had all sorts
                    of problems on who could get on his airplane—we had twelve spaces and sixteen
                    wanted to go—and that sort of thing. But we managed to decide that at my level.
                    The Ambassador made a studied effort not to get involved in my work unless he
                    had to—like the playground matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the Embassy staff a congenial group?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I think there was a good team effort. You had the political and
                    economic officers—that was a clubby group in that they didn't mix much with
                    anybody else. Then you had the administrative, consular and military personnel—
                    a group that socialized together a lot. At Christmas time or Thanksgiving, the
                    whole Embassy got together. There was no animosity between any of the groups,
                    except that the communication people, the military sergeants, the consular and
                    administrative people—who were all more or less at the same level—tended to want
                    to be together. The political and economic officers, of whom there were only
                    six, more or less stuck together. But these divisions didn't create any
                    tensions.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned car usage as a major problem at the
                        beginning of your tenure. What other administrative problems did you
                        encounter when you were in Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Housing. That was a perpetual problem. There was always a shortage. Our
                    Embassy was growing. Even if Washington assigned one additional person, we had a
                    problem. We were always pushing the Russians to give us more housing. We
                    couldn't do anything with the main building itself. That was completely filled.
                    The Russians had set aside some housing units for the foreign diplomatic
                    community. All were looking for more space. The others would complain that we
                    were getting more than our fair share. It was a constant battle with the
                    Russians to let us have another apartment or two. That was true throughout my
                    tour. The Russians were building at the time; they also broke relations with
                    Israel and other countries. The units occupied by the diplomats from those
                    countries would be immediately reassigned to other foreign missions. But there
                    was a continuous great demand by all, although probably more from us because we
                    had by far the largest Embassy in Moscow.</p>
                <p>We didn't have temporary quarters. We wouldn't permit any new arrivals unless we
                    had permanent quarters for them, unless it was for a very short period and then
                    they would stay in a hotel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about financial resources? Any problems with that
                        issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: We got extra-special treatment from Washington. When we desperately
                    needed money for something, we would get it. Our needs were small compared to
                    London, Paris or Rome. We would ask for $18,000 when Paris would be asking for
                    $1,800,000. We never had any problems with money. We knew what our budget was
                    and what our expenditures would be. We weren't going to get any more housing,
                    cars or anything else. The Russians put the limits on. So money was never a real
                    problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about visitors?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: We had lots of visitors. Until the U-2 incident, we had a tremendous
                    flow of visitors. I had opened up a small restaurant in one of the bays of the
                    old garage. Most of the officers objected to it because it would affect their
                    cost of living allowance if it were found that we had a restaurant which would
                    provide breakfast or lunch at lower rates than otherwise would be available.
                    They went to the Ambassador, asking that the restaurant not be opened. The
                    Ambassador found it hard to understand their position. He knew that the facility
                    would be welcomed by a lot of the staff, particularly the single people, who had
                    to go back to their apartments every day to make their sandwiches. So we opened
                    the restaurant and it was a great addition to the Embassy. It is still there.
                    But it was a problem when the visitors heard about it because they could get
                    bacon and eggs there. They came over to the Embassy for breakfast. We couldn't
                    refuse them since most had seen or would see the Ambassador. It would have been
                    impossible to deny them access to the restaurant. The restaurant operated with
                    non-appropriated funds totally and completely. The US government supplied the
                    building and the utilities. The fixtures had been gotten from the American
                    exhibition when that was closed. We made a lot of money from the Commissary
                    sales—cigarettes and liquor. That supported the operations of the restaurant. If
                    in some months we would run short in the restaurant, we would use the Commissary
                    surpluses to support it. The restaurant was for Americans only.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How much time did the Embassy devote to visitors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In the summer—June, July and August—it would devote considerable time.
                    If an Embassy officer was in town, he would have to see any visitor who wanted
                    to see him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Who were these visitors? Businessmen? Congressmen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I am going to say something I have never said before and my comment
                    applies not only to Moscow, but to many foreign service posts. Americans travel
                    to the post, come to the Embassy, sign in—usually want to go to the Economic
                    Section—, ask a couple of questions, get the answers and their business is done.
                    Now the businessman has his trip paid because it becomes tax-deductible
                    expenditure as a business expense. I saw more of that in Paris than in Moscow.
                    Many would sign in, do something that was reasonably official and were never
                    seen again by the Embassy.</p>
                <p>We had a number of Congressional visitors. That was when I first met John Rooney,
                    whom I found to be a very nice fellow—contrary to his reputation. He liked to
                    tweak the State Department on such things as too many cars, too many
                    secretaries, plush furniture and those sorts of things. But he always gave us
                    the money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Rooney had an unusual agenda when he visited Embassies.
                        What did he do in Moscow?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In Moscow, he wanted to see the building. I took him through the
                    building. He wanted to go to a typical Russian restaurant. We took him and he
                    thought the food was terrible. He was in Moscow for three nights—two days. He
                    saw the Ambassador and got a briefing, although he didn't really care for
                    briefings. He just didn't care for them. He had an assistant with him by the
                    name of Jay Howe who took notes and wrote up the trip reports. When we asked
                    whether we could write any of them, he said: “No. Jay will write whatever needs
                    to be written”. He did spend a lot of time in the building and Jay took notes on
                    what a terrible place it was. He went to the garage. We had paved the parking
                    area outside the garage and marked it for badminton and basketball courts. He
                    looked at that and said: “Is this what you got several hundred thousands dollars
                    for?”. I said that it was for the garage building; this was a parking lot. I
                    added: “Mr. Congressman, the markings that you see on the paved area are the
                    latest markings in parking lots”. He laughed and told Jay not to note this
                    innovation.</p>
                <p>We also had the Foreign Relations Committee and Agriculture Committee people
                    visiting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were these official visitors hard to support?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No, because they invariably had contacts already made with the Russians
                    whom they would see. In any case, most of them wanted to leave Moscow as soon as
                    possible and see Leningrad and Kiev. We had enough transportation to support
                    them; if we didn't we would rent cars. We only had four sedans available and
                    needed one or two for the Embassy all the time. We would send cars to meet the
                    official visitors at the airport and bring them back. If they wanted to do some
                    sight-seeing, then we would have to rent cars.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were the hotels adequate for the visitors?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: They hated them. But they were the best available. The Ukrania, which
                    was close to the Embassy, was a nice hotel, but it was not a Hilton. Before we
                    close this chapter of my career, I should say that it was a fascinating
                    experience—absolutely fascinating, mainly because we were dealing with another
                    culture—totally and completely different. You had to remind yourself of that all
                    the time. Just because we do something one way, doesn't make it right. In their
                    viewpoint, their way was correct.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Moscow in 1960.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Correct. While I was there, we had an inspection. We received a very
                    nice inspection report. When I left Moscow, I returned to Washington with a
                    considerable amount of home leave to my credit. State did not have an immediate
                    assignment for me, but there were a number of openings for which I would be
                    considered. These were to be discussed with me while I was on home leave. I had
                    been in North Dakota for two weeks when I got a frantic call asking me to return
                    to Washington immediately. I was told that there was an assignment for me in
                    Washington. I asked what happened to the overseas opportunities. I was told:
                    “Forget them. You are coming back to Washington”. The Chief Inspector, who had
                    been in Moscow, and who was a very good friend of John Kennedy's, had just been
                    assigned to set up a new Disarmament Agency. The Republicans had been getting a
                    lot of heat that they hadn't established such an Agency. So I was called back to
                    draw-up an organization chart, together with five or six other people, put some
                    boxes on the chart, so that the Republicans could announce that they had
                    established a Disarmament Agency. It took me about two weeks; most of the chart
                    is still valid today, even though it is now thirty years old.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were present at the birth of ACDA?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I was the third man on board. The first was the Chief inspector I
                    mentioned earlier; then there was another Inspector and a secretary. Then I came
                    on board. We put the organization chart together, some functional statements. I
                    certainly didn't know what it was all about and nobody else did either. But the
                    Agency had be established for political reasons. In a very short time, the
                    election campaign started in earnest and the press releases flowed saying that
                    the Disarmament Agency was in business. No one liked the name. Someone came up
                    with the idea that after the election, the name would have to be changed. When
                    Kennedy won the election, he appointed John J. McCloy to be the head of the new
                    Agency, which was very nice since I had known him from the High Commission
                    days.</p>
                <p>Then the job became one of hiring people. It was hire, hire and then hire some
                    more. We had a military affairs office, which was easy to staff because the
                    military had lots of people. We put the organization together and went to Bill
                    Crockett in State. Bill was very helpful in seeing that we got the staff
                    necessary to run the place. I reciprocated by being very generous in turning
                    administrative funds to him for State's support, since State was always in need
                    of money and we had more than we could use.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was ACDA's legislative authority at this time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was being worked on at that time—early 1961. Two things were being
                    worked on: legislative authority and on the SALT Treaty. When I started, the
                    Agency was an integral part of State. They had been in business for ten days.
                    They had a little office with three desks in it, with a big sign on the door
                    saying “Disarmament Agency”. That is all it was. It was strictly a political
                    deal; the Administration just had to get it going. By election time, we had a
                    viable organization; it didn't help the Republicans to get elected, but there
                    was a viable organization. It did blunt some of the criticism because there was
                    a sign over a door showing that some work was being done and there were people
                    working on disarmament.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were there, this Agency evolved; it got its own
                        legislative authority and the staff increased.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: That is right. We had our own appropriation. My main task as Executive
                    Director of the new Agency was to see that we got enough money, office space and
                    personnel—all the things that needed to be done to get an organization going. We
                    also had to insure that we got the right people. The political officers were
                    easy—we got those from State. The military personnel were easy—we got those from
                    Defense. But then there was an economic group and a technical group which were
                    involved in disarmament and arms control, which consisted mainly of University
                    people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Executive Office started as a one-man office. How much
                        did it grow while you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In total, the Disarmament Agency went from four people when I joined it
                    to about 150 in a period of four years. Our main problem was the tremendous
                    turnover. The other problem was that the various Directors of the Agency wanted
                    larger staffs. They just wanted more people. The Division chiefs would say that
                    they couldn't use more people. When you got into such matters as the SALT
                    Treaty, much of the nuts and bolts work was done by the Agency, but the more
                    difficult technical questions were contracted out. People would be brought in
                    temporarily to work on a specific project. John McCloy' successor was William
                    Foster. He was after me all the time to increase the staff. He felt that the
                    Agency was not getting enough people. The Division chiefs kept telling me that
                    they had all the people they needed or could use. We had an authorization for
                    200 positions, but while I was there, we never filled them all. Foster felt that
                    within the government, unless you had size, you would have very little
                    impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: On the administrative side, did you depend primarily on
                        State for support?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No. We had our own personnel office, which hired technical and other
                    personnel. We did our own contracting, particularly for studies, although
                    supplies and such things came from State. I understood that our contracting
                    people would check with their counterparts in State to make sure that they were
                    on the right track. We would also depend on State for the political people that
                    we needed. Sometimes, we asked State for some economists. The large military
                    staff came from DoD. We had our own small public affairs office—some from USIA.
                    We were housed in the old State building, of which we used about one-third. AID
                    will never forgive me for my weekend raid. You have to be quick on your feet in
                    our business. I had heard that there would be space available in the old part of
                    State. It was going to be divided between AID and us. I learned this on a
                    Saturday and immediately went to Mr. Foster. I told him that on Monday, the
                    space would be divided up. He said: Never mind Monday. Get a hold of our people
                    because we are going to move in today”. And so we did. We moved in and took the
                    space we wanted. Foster got the old office of the Secretary. We went in a and
                    worked very hard that weekend. So on Monday, AID was confronted with a fait a
                    compli, unless they wanted to move us out. That is how the Agency got prime
                    space in the building.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had your own budget. What was your relationship with
                        State and the Bureau of the Budget on financial matters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: We led a charmed life, while Kennedy was in power. He was very firm in
                    his support for ACDA. The problem was that we would show our requirements which
                    seemed always much higher than our current staffing. Where we had ten people, we
                    would ask for twenty. BoB would want to know why we had to double that staff. I
                    would turn the question over to the various division chiefs, who would visibly
                    sweat. But they would explain the requested increase. BoB knew that the
                    President supported the Agency and therefore didn't give us a hard time. Under
                    normal circumstances, we would have had a very difficult time. We would also
                    reimburse the other government departments for the people they assigned to us.
                    We never reimbursed the military. We did not reimburse other agencies such as
                    Atomic Energy for people that were temporarily assigned to us, but we did pay
                    State because we thought that we used that Department for so many
                    things—procurement, etc. I would get together with Crockett and we would agree
                    on a round figure. My assignment to ACDA was a major responsibility. I dealt
                    with top people in the White House and other parts of the government. When we
                    needed personnel or services, I was the person who had to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left ACDA in 1964 and you were then assigned to Paris
                        as Counselor for Administration. How did that assignment come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I knew that I would have to move sometime in 1964. So I went to Bill
                    Crockett around Christmas 1963 and asked him to keep me in mind for any overseas
                    vacancies that might come open. He told me that Paris would be open in the
                    Spring or Summer. He asked me if I would like that. I told him: “Yes, if I could
                    get it. I would like that”. I don't know what happened in the system, but I got
                    a letter from Personnel saying that I been assigned to Paris. I went to see the
                    Assistant Secretary for EUR with whom I had dealt before—we all knew each other.
                    I was a known commodity. The fact that the Deputy Under Secretary—Crockett—had
                    recommended me for the job carried the day because there were a lot of people
                    interested in the job—most of them could have done it. There are a lot of people
                    in the Foreign Service who can fill any position adequately; you have to be in
                    the right place at the right time. I was neither better nor worse than many
                    others; others might have done the job just as well. But I was certainly
                    qualified, having put together the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency. That had
                    been the big leagues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Paris was a different experience from anything you had
                        done before. How did you find the administrative side of the Embassy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Big and bloated. Paris was going through a very difficult time when I
                    arrived in 1964. Paris had been a huge post. When I got there, there were five
                    Ambassadors and their staffs. We had the Ambassador to France, the Ambassador to
                    OECD, the Ambassador to NATO, the Ambassador to UNESCO and then there was a
                    small economic group which dealt with the Ministry of Finance with about a dozen
                    people which was also headed by an Ambassador. We had to support all of them.
                    These Ambassadors didn't talk to each other; each had his own niche and was
                    separate. They might have talked to Ambassador Bohlen if they had a political
                    problem, but essentially they were little principalities to themselves. Each had
                    its own building a long ways from the Embassy. I visited each of them every
                    week; I went to their staff meetings every week. I would return from these
                    meetings and report to Bohlen if we had any problems—most of them involved
                    space. He didn't really want to know much about them. We got along fine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did either Bohlen or Bob McBride, his DCM, interfere with
                        your responsibilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No. McBride would want me to come up to see him periodically to brief
                    him on what was going on and what my problems were so that he could be prepared
                    if the Ambassador raised any questions. When the issue arose, he had been
                    briefed for a month or two and knew the background. He was very good. We would
                    have lunch often. I would go to his house for dinner and sometimes I would have
                    breakfast with him. I kept him fully apprized. We were going through a shrinking
                    process; we were trying to reduce staff; we were having space problems. We were
                    redoing the Talleyrand building; we were doing a lot of things that were
                    upsetting staff. We had to move them around or cut down on staff. Bob McBride
                    just wanted to know so that if Bohlen raised an issue, he would be prepared to
                    respond immediately instead of having to call me. He would call me after the
                    meeting to make sure that he had told Bohlen the full story. He had a good
                    memory and was almost always right in his responses to the Ambassador. But
                    neither the Ambassador nor the DCM interfered with the administrative support I
                    was providing either to them or the other four Ambassadors. Through my
                    experiences in the salary-wage area, the Moscow Embassy and ACDA, I had become
                    familiar with the administrative problems. They are usually the same wherever
                    you are. Only the location varies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is an interesting observation. Did you find a pattern
                        of recurring problems that you confronted both in Moscow and in Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. Space, for example. In Moscow it was both living and office space.
                    In Paris it was office space. We provided living space in Paris for about
                    two-thirds of the Embassy staff. The other one-third went out on their own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about the policy of government-provided
                        housing in a post like Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In Paris, we made a big mistake when we sold the Rhone Hotel. Cecil
                    Lyon sold it because he didn't want the Embassy involved in housekeeping. It was
                    a facility with seventy-eighty small apartments. We sold it for a good price,
                    but then had to pay three times as much to lease other space. In a Paris which
                    has such a high proportion of communication and secretarial personnel—lower wage
                    employees—, it is not practicable to ask them to find and pay for their own
                    housing. The government has to get the housing for them. It makes for a more
                    orderly way to transfer people to a post like Paris. Senior officers usually
                    have sufficient allowances to pay for their quarters, but in Paris they were all
                    in government housing. I agreed with that policy. Middle rank officers—FSO-3 and
                    above—had adequate allowances to find their own housing. But there are two kinds
                    of officers—the ones who abhor any kind of government housing—that is about
                    one-third; the other two-thirds prefer government-provided housing. The trouble
                    with the latter is that you cannot always meet the preference of each officer
                    and his wife. In a government owned or leased apartment house, all apartments
                    are roughly of the same size, so that an FSO-2 and a FSS-6 get roughly the same
                    apartments. There isn't anything you can do about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As a general policy, for those officers who had adequate
                        allowances, you supported private leases.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I would support it in Paris, Rome, London—the bigger posts, but not in
                    the smaller posts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any tensions among the various US agencies in
                        Paris because of the housing situation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes; it was always a struggle. They would all ask whether they were
                    getting their fair share. Out in Neuilly, we had some two-bedroom places and
                    some three-bedroom places. Everyone was assigned to that complex. If it was just
                    a couple without children, we would not assign them to a three bedroom apartment
                    regardless of rank. We needed the three bedrooms for families. Private housing
                    was available; that is true in most European capitals. You just have to look for
                    it. If you rent your own place, you are more apt to be satisfied with it than if
                    it is government-provided. I saw people renting apartments on the left bank,
                    which, if the government had provided, they would have had a fit. But having
                    rented the apartment themselves, they found it unique and interesting—right off
                    St. Germain where all the “action” in Paris took place. The government would
                    have trouble putting these people into such apartments because they would have
                    objected. But having found the place themselves, they were happy.</p>
                <p>Some of these problems are of course related to the allowances. For an FSO-3 or
                    above, the allowances are such that he or she can afford to rent his or her own
                    place. There is much to be said for letting people do as much of their own
                    renting as possible. All the complaining nonsense stops. If something goes wrong
                    with the water heater, it is their problem; they can complain to the landlord.
                    The officer understands that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How many U.S. Government Americans were there in Paris
                        when you got there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: There were 2,450 Americans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there much interaction among them, either
                        professionally or socially?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: The five groups I mentioned before were entities unto themselves.
                    Sometime, the NATO political officers would seek the assistance of the Embassy.
                    But essentially they were all independent. There were very few social
                    interactions. Practically none. I would get invited to all the parties, but I
                    think I was unique in the Embassy. The Ambassador and the DCM got courtesy
                    invitations, but they never went. The Ambassador would send courtesy invitations
                    to the other four Ambassadors, but they would never come. I was in fact the
                    linkage among the five groups.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were any efforts from the other four units to pull away
                        from the Embassy' support?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No. Not while I was there. No one ever mentioned the thought to me. The
                    main reason was that they all had good office space. All were in nice offices.
                    The only thing they might have done on their own would have been the logistic
                    support and that was no problem. We had enough space and personnel services to
                    satisfy them. They all had their own cars. Each Ambassador had his own car; NATO
                    probably had a half dozen cars; OECD probably had two and UNESCO had one. The
                    Embassy serviced them, but each unit garaged its own cars. The Embassy provided
                    personnel, procurement, general services. Each of these four units had one
                    American executive officer; they had no other administrative staff. They would
                    come to the Embassy to get whatever they needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you draw some conclusions from your experiences in
                        Paris concerning the general management of overseas establishments?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I felt that Paris and all big Embassies were too big, too many
                    people. We did too much business from these Embassies. We should be more like
                    the Europeans. If there was a problem, some one from the Department in the
                    capital city should be sent. With communications and transportation having made
                    such giant strides, an official can be at an overseas post the next day to work
                    on a problem. We used to be kidded a lot by the Germans and the British and the
                    Scandinavians—they would ask what we did with all of these hundreds of people.
                    Why didn't they stay in Washington? When you needed them you could bring them
                    over. I think there is a lot to be said for that. In Paris, 22% of the people in
                    the Embassy were State personnel. The other 78% belonged to other U.S.
                    Government agencies. Every US agency pushes to get into foreign affairs and to
                    put its people overseas. The Paris representatives of many of these agencies
                    didn't have enough to keep them occupied. They could take care of a problem when
                    it arose. But so could have their representatives if they had flown from
                    Washington. Such a system would not have required the officer and his family to
                    be in Paris with all the costs involved. We should rethink the size of these
                    Embassies and their functions because of the vast improvements in communications
                    and transportation facilities today.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While we are on that issue, have you reached any
                        conclusions about State Department's ability to support domestic agencies,
                        like Treasury, Agriculture, Commerce and USTR, for example? Could a better
                        staffed Foreign Service do a lot of the work for which the domestic agencies
                        send their own people overseas?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Of course it could. But all these agencies have vested interests. They
                    will go to their death before they surrender their overseas representation. When
                    I was in Washington, we had a big fight with the Social Security Administration.
                    It wanted to put three officers in Athens to pass out checks. Then they would
                    also spot check to make sure that the deliveries were accurate. I told them they
                    didn't need to do that. We had people who were perfectly able to do that. SSA
                    wouldn't buy and it got BoB to agree with it. I don't know how they got BoB to
                    agree, but they got their three officers to Athens to distribute social security
                    checks. If you are going to do that in Athens, why not in Poland where there are
                    many retirees? There were a lot in Italy, too. Their answer was: “We'll get to
                    those countries”. Every major Department in Washington has people overseas.
                    Commerce, Labor, AEC, all of them, have a foreign affairs staff which they have
                    built up over the course of the last twenty-five years. It is absolutely
                    unnecessary. Perhaps back in the sailing ship days, there may have had some
                    justification. But today you can get anywhere overnight, particularly in Europe;
                    with the fax machines and other communication improvements, there just isn't any
                    reason for the proliferation. But I don't know how one gets ahold of it because
                    you have to tackle every major government agency in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You attribute the changed circumstances particularly to
                        improvements in communications and transportation. Let me ask you about the
                        Foreign Service itself. I gather you believe that the Foreign Service could
                        perform a lot of these functions, like the passing out of social security
                        checks. Why do you think that the Foreign Service is not used more by
                        government agencies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I don't think that it stems from any opposition to the Foreign Service
                    as such. It is more a question of each agency building up its own little entity.
                    I have never heard any criticism, except from Commerce. Commerce never did like
                    State being so heavily involved in commercial work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long were you in Paris?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I arrived in June, 1964 and left in January, 1967 when I was appointed
                    Deputy Under Secretary for Administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I didn't know anybody in the White House until I was asked by Bill
                    Crockett to go to New Zealand to advance President Johnson's visit to that
                    country. In late 1966, the President went on a long journey throughout Southeast
                    Asia. Some posts like Wellington needed help when it came to major events such
                    as Presidential visits and Crockett asked me to be the control officer. I got
                    Bill's call about three weeks before the President was scheduled to arrive in
                    Wellington. So I hurried to New Zealand.</p>
                <p>There were about 400 people expected to accompany the President. Two-thirds of
                    those were either communicators or from the media. Where would we house such a
                    large contingent in a small city like Wellington? The racing season was on at
                    that time and the most we could find was twenty-two rooms in a hotel. That was
                    the maximum. I was sitting in the Ambassador's office looking out on the waters
                    and I saw a ferryboat. The Ambassador said that it traveled to and from the
                    South Island on an overnight voyage. I asked whether it had sleeping room? He
                    said: “Yes. You can sleep two-hundred and fifty people on it”. The light came
                    on. I asked him whether we could get hold of the ferry operator to do some
                    business. Fortunately, the company was just bringing in a boat which needed
                    rehabilitation, which would then be sent to Hong Kong to ferry passengers and
                    cars there. So we made a deal with the ferry boat owner. We rented the boat,
                    although for longer than we wanted because their union contract required it. The
                    operator put sheets on the beds and fixed it all up. So when the President's
                    entourage arrived, there were sleeping quarters for everybody. The guests were a
                    little surprised when they found they had to sleep on a ferryboat, but they did.
                    Marvin Watson, who was President Johnson's chief honcho for these trips, called
                    me and told me that he thought the ferry rental was brilliant. He said that back
                    in Washington, people didn't think we could pull off something like this and
                    that all hell would have broken loose when the President arrived in Wellington.
                    He had heard that everybody was to go to an Army barracks. Watson said: “You
                    know what would have happened if the media had to be put in Army barracks!”. The
                    visit went well and it had its interesting moments. I got a call one night—about
                    midnight. It was from Bill Crockett, asking me if had the wreath for the next
                    day's ceremonies. I said: “Yes. I asked my supply officer to get it”. Bill
                    asked: “Have you seen it? Please go see it and then call me back”. So I went to
                    the supply officer and got him out of bed. He said: “I don't have it. It will be
                    delivered at eight o'clock in the morning”. I told him I wanted to see it now.
                    He answered that I should tell the Presidential party that that couldn't be
                    done. I told him to get out of bed and get that wreath right then and there
                    because it had to be at the site at 7:30 in the morning. So the wreath-maker was
                    awakened and he made the wreath and delivered it that night. That was my first
                    lesson in Presidential visits: never take anybody's word for anything—verify it
                    yourself.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>The party left for Canberra. I got a call from there asking me whether I would
                    join the Presidential party for the rest of the trip, working as a liaison
                    between the top White House staff and the State Department supply and
                    procurement people. That is how I became acquainted with the White House. If
                    Marvin Watson wanted something, he would call me. If Moyers wanted something, he
                    would call me. They were really never too demanding. It was mostly little stuff.
                    But at least they had a name they could call. So we became acquainted. But how
                    and when the decision was made that Bill Crockett would vacate the Deputy Under
                    Secretary position and who would replace him, I never knew nor found out. I
                    presume that Crockett made a recommendation to Watson. I doubt whether he just
                    gave one name; it was probably a short list of three or four. By that time, I
                    knew Marvin Watson and he knew me. But to this day, I don't know the process
                    that led to my selection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about the Secretary and the Under Secretary? Did you
                        know them at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I was just a name to both of them. After my return to Paris after the
                    Presidential trip—on Christmas Eve—I got a call from the White House. I don't
                    remember whether it was from President Johnson or Marvin Watson. It may have
                    been Johnson, although he usually would not make this kind of a call. Whoever it
                    was said that the President wanted to see me the next day. I pointed out that
                    the next day was Christmas. So the meeting was postponed until the day after. I
                    flew back, reported to the State Department and then went over to the White
                    House—that was probably two days after Christmas. I saw the President in the
                    Oval Office. He asked me what my political affiliation was. I told him that I
                    was apolitical. He said: “Fine”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The appointment was then actually a Presidential
                        appointment as the “book” says it should be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I didn't see the Secretary or the Under Secretary until days
                    later. I think the Secretary was a little miffed. I told him that I took my
                    orders from the President. He had told me to return to Washington. I did and I
                    went to see him as instructed. After seeing the President I stayed in Washington
                    for a couple of weeks with nothing happening. I finally went to Bill Crockett
                    and told him that I might as well return to Paris. I felt it was silly to stay
                    in Washington and keep out of sight. There was a lot of speculation about who
                    was going to be the new Deputy Under Secretary. It was well known that Crockett
                    was leaving. So Bill called Marvin Watson who told him he would check the
                    question out. Later that day, Bill and I were having lunch in the Executive
                    Dining Room when on the ticker tape appeared a White House announcement that I
                    had been nominated for the job. That is how I learned that I had been
                    appointed—from a yellow ticker tape sheet. Nobody had said anything to me. That
                    is the way a lot of Johnson's actions were taken. He made the decisions and told
                    others later. I don't know why he felt so strongly about the Deputy Under
                    Secretary position, except that was obviously a job that he, and no one else,
                    wanted to control.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I assume that in part it had to do with overseas trips
                        during which he relied heavily on Bill Crockett and the Department's
                        administrative staff.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: That was certainly part of it. The other aspect had to do with
                    ambassadorial appointments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me pursue your relationship with the President a
                        little more. Did you escort him on other overseas trips?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I went with him to Adenauer's funeral. I still have some pictures
                    of you and me out at the airport when the President arrived. One could probably
                    write a book on every one of the President's trips because he was unpredictable
                    and arbitrary about his demands. For example, on the question of selecting
                    housing. In Bonn, as you will recall, he chose the DCM's house. Did that create
                    a fuss! But not with Johnson and Watson; they had no problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I believe that this was a particularly difficult trip
                        because the President had no schedule except for the funeral. He had a lot
                        of free time on his hands.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: That's right. He was interested in art works and everything else. I
                    remember that a lot of artwork was brought to the residence for him to view. I
                    never saw it, but apparently there was a lot of stuff there. I know that he took
                    a lot back with him. That was my experience with is art interests. I went with
                    the President to Punta Del Este and I went with him on a visit to all the
                    countries of Central America. We also went to Saigon and Danang. We went around
                    the world on that trip and stopped in Rome. Johnson didn't want to see the
                    President of Italy—that was a mess. These trips were heady because you had no
                    forewarning about what he wanted to do. He was absolutely mercurial.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But the President treated you well?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I had an excellent relationship with him. Only once did he call me to
                    chew me out—it was in the middle of the night. I had made a terrible mistake. I
                    had been told by some of my staff that there was a vacancy coming up as
                    Administrator of the Bureau of Consular Affairs. The staff wanted Barbara Watson
                    appointed. She was an Afro-American. They pointed out that this appointment
                    would be a real plus for the Department. So I issued a press release, never
                    realizing that that job was a Presidential appointment. No one had told me and I
                    wasn't smart enough to ask the right questions. My staff later said that I
                    hadn't asked whether that job was a Presidential appointment. I told them: “Come
                    on now! A presidential appointment and I issue a press release! Does that sound
                    reasonable?'. Anyway, the President called me about one o'clock in the morning.
                    He had stayed up and had read it. He said: “Don't ever do that again! If it is a
                    Presidential appointment, I announce it! How in the world am I going to get a
                    black woman out of that job. I have other candidates for that job. Now there is
                    nothing I can do about that. Don't ever do that again!”. That was that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So your main White House contact was Marvin Watson?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, and then later on, Jim Jones. I had other calls from the
                    President. Always on personnel. The Department had a system in which five senior
                    officers would sit together to pick a panel of candidates for various
                    Ambassadorial appointments, which then would be sent to the White House for
                    Presidential selection. The Under Secretary, the Deputy Under Secretary for
                    Political Affairs, myself, the Assistant Secretary for the region concerned and
                    one other would agree on a panel of names. I would put the papers together and
                    send them to the White House. One late evening I got a call from the President.
                    He said that he knew the Department was going to send him a list of names for a
                    certain ambassadorial position. He told me to delete one of the names and add
                    another name that he gave me, in lieu. He added that it was not necessary to
                    tell anybody about the shift. He repeated: “You understand that? It is not
                    necessary to tell anybody about this”. So I called my staff man in and told him
                    to come in at five o'clock the next morning together with his secretary to type
                    the necessary papers. He told me: “You can't do that”. I said: “ What do you
                    mean I can't do it. The President has instructed me to do it! You want me to
                    tell the President he can't have that name on the list. It is after all a
                    Presidential appointment”. So we did that; we forwarded the panel of names
                    including the President's man. About three days later, he named his candidate.
                    All hell broke loose. I got a call from the Secretary who was livid—he was
                    furious. Alex Johnson was livid; everybody was furious because they thought I
                    had pulled a fast one. The Secretary said that he would not tolerate having a
                    staff that was not trustworthy. So I told the Secretary that before the
                    discussion got completely out of hand and things would be said that we would
                    regret later, I should tell him that three nights earlier I had received a call
                    from the President instructing me precisely on what to do, including not
                    discussing it with anybody. I pointed out that since I had then told the
                    Secretary, that I was in hot water with the President if he discussed this
                    matter outside his office. He asked me: “Did the President say that?”. I
                    answered: “Yes”. The Secretary said that he didn't know the President's choice.
                    Then he said: “Thank you very much” and his face was tomato red. That was the
                    last I heard of that saga.</p>
                <p>The President would often call to ask whether a specific person's name was on the
                    list being sent to him. His questions were always about personnel. But he never
                    asked that we place someone in the Department. Sometimes the White House staff
                    would try that and then I would check it with Marvin Watson. Invariably, he
                    would tell me not to do anything about the request. The President and Watson
                    didn't want the White House staff doing that. The President felt that if his
                    staff called, it should have been at his behest, not theirs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In that connection, it is interesting to note that in a
                        book by Secretary Rusk, which has just been published, he said “I did
                        wrestle with the White House staff and occasionally President Kennedy over
                        Ambassadorial appointments. There were always 10% or 15% who were
                        old-fashioned political appointments. Among these, we would always pick a
                        few dogs”. Was that your experience with the Johnson people?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No. I would say that only one ambassadorial appointment was
                    controversial and that was the one in the episode I relayed earlier. As I said,
                    Johnson would often call to find out who was on the list or who were we
                    considering. But that is all I would hear. It never carried any further. The
                    Secretary or the Under Secretary would come to the ambassadorial panel meetings
                    and tell us that they had a very good candidate. That was a clear message. When
                    the choice would be made for some minor European post, there was never any
                    argument; we knew that who ever would be appointed, would be someone that the
                    President selected for his own purposes. But the Department accepted that and it
                    was never a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have contacts with the Secretary or the Under
                        Secretary on other management issues besides personnel?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Not with the Secretary; never with the Secretary. But I had a lot of
                    meetings with Under Secretary Katzenbach. He was followed by Elliot Richardson.
                    Katzenbach would be interested in a very broad brush way; if it was a more
                    specific issue, he would turn it over to ne of his assistants. These matters
                    were spot items that had arisen somewhere or that I had raised with the Under
                    Secretary. But I never discussed a general management issue either with the
                    Secretary or either of the Under Secretaries (Richardson or Katzenbach). I did
                    see Secretary Rogers several times, but he never got involved in broad
                    management questions. Richardson did; he liked to philosophize. He liked to talk
                    about where we should be going. He had some very smart staff—and they would join
                    the conversation. I don't think the Secretary's staff was nearly as well tuned
                    in as Richardson's. Richardson had a good, retentive mind. I got some guidance
                    from those conversations with the Under Secretary. I always felt that the
                    personnel process was in good shape. During my successor's—Bill Macomber—period,
                    the American Foreign Service Association took over the direction of the
                    personnel system to an extent I would not ever have tolerated. They tried to do
                    that while I was in the job and I just refused. One time I took Lannon Walker
                    aside and said: “You see that certificate on the wall signed by the President. I
                    think you will see my name on the top. Where in that certificate does it say
                    that I am to abdicate my responsibilities to the Foreign Service Association? It
                    doesn't and I don't intend to do it!”. So AFSA and I had an adversarial
                    relationship; very much so. I think they were wrong. I think the whole system is
                    now wrong; it is now so contrived that they think that the whole system can be
                    run without human hands touching it. They think it can be run by all these rules
                    and regulations. It doesn't work that way. People run things; organizations
                    don't run anything. Chairs, tables and charts can't run anything. It is people.
                    If you get the right people in the right jobs, you'll have a good operation.
                    Conversely, if you have the wrong people, no structure or organization chart
                    will help. It will not work. Today, the Department has a personnel system so
                    devised that rules and regulations will run it. It won't; it can't. Today's
                    system is terribly complicated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: If people make a good organization, as you have suggested,
                        how do you develop the right persons to fill the right positions at the
                        right time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: My experience has been that as an officer develops, you give him or her
                    increasing responsibilities. That will develop them. Take Larry Eagleburger. I
                    knew Larry when he was a young officer sitting at a desk writing letters. But he
                    was sharp, smart; a guy with a good intellect and a good feel for people when I
                    knew him in his youth. He may have changed now, but twenty years ago he had good
                    human relationships. You spotted him right away as a “comer”. You could also
                    spot younger officers whose life would never be long enough for them to reach
                    the senior ranks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's use Eagleburger as an illustration. Should the
                        personnel system devote time to developing an officer like him or would the
                        customary assignment process be sufficient to insure that he would rise to
                        the top?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In Eagleburger's case, he was in the Secretary's office; he was known
                    as a guy who would produce; when you gave him an assignment, it would be
                    completed in a most satisfactory manner on an expeditious basis. We got a call
                    one day that Kissinger was looking for some staff and the name Eagleburger had
                    come up. The question was whether the Department would make him available for
                    the NSC assignment. I said: “Hell, yes. If they want him, that is where we want
                    him!”. I later found out that my approval wasn't really being asked; the
                    decision had already been made and the phone call was pro forma. I had told my
                    people that such assignments were a good deal for the Department; when someone
                    like Larry, who knew the Department, could be assigned to the NSC, that would
                    rebound to our benefit. A lot of people might resent such an assignment. Larry
                    was in the right spot at the right time; he got to be known and he was selected
                    because he was known. You can go to any organization and find that nine-tenths
                    of the personnel selections are made because someone knows that a particular
                    individual can produce. That doesn't mean that every selection will be the right
                    one—the Peter Principle certainly will govern some of those selections. In
                    general, however, I think such a system is a far, far better one than the system
                    in existence today which is based on the assumption that you can eliminate that
                    personal factor in the assignment process.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Larry Eagleburger was one of your successors. When he was
                        appointed, he had not been well grounded in the management-administrative
                        operations of the Department. Did that give you any concern?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No, because the job of Under Secretary for Management was not the same
                    as that of Deputy Under Secretary for Administration. Macomber took the guts out
                    of the Deputy Under Secretary's job. He gave a lot of the functions to the Under
                    Secretary (later Deputy Secretary). Look at the organization chart of today and
                    compare it to the way it was twenty years ago; they are entirely different. The
                    Under Secretary today is responsible for the over-all management of the
                    Department, including the Foreign Service Institute. He has nothing to do with
                    the day-to-day operation of the Department, whereas in my days, I was
                    responsible for personnel, budget, security, general services and all the other
                    administrative functions of the Department. That isn't true today. So Larry's
                    job was different from the one I had. It was one for which he was well qualified
                    and would do well. He is a good thinker.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You attribute to Macomber this change in the
                        responsibilities of the Department's top management-administrative guy. What
                        is that Macomber did that changed the nature of the job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: He acquiesced in what the Foreign Service Association wanted. They had
                    had so much trouble with me and my predecessors that they wanted their issues
                    raised at the next higher level and Macomber allowed that to happen. All the
                    Deputy Under Secretary had left were the planning and management work. A lot of
                    the day-to-day decisions on administrative matters were in fact transferred to
                    the Under Secretary's office. Several years ago, I was in Washington at a lunch
                    with a number of Congressmen from the Foreign Relations and Budget Committees.
                    They wanted to know why in my days and in Crockett's days the discussions were
                    about the over-all business of State. After that, all the State officials wanted
                    to talk about was travel allowances, overtime, women getting paid. The only
                    subjects on Department's officials' minds were perks, nothing but perks. I said:
                    “That is the new Foreign Service!”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell us about your relationships with the Congress when
                        you were the Deputy Under Secretary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: My relationships with Congressmen were excellent. I spent time with
                    them. I spent a lot of time going to the Hill and dropping in on people like
                    Congressmen Fascell, Hayes, Rooney, Smith, etc. I would just stop by and tell
                    them that I was just passing by and was there anything I could do for them? They
                    liked that. They often gave me a cup of coffee and we would chat a little. A
                    month never went by that I didn't spend at least two days walking the halls of
                    Congress. I did the same thing with Senator McClellan and his staff. He had a
                    son who had been killed in war and we would commiserate about that. I didn't go
                    to see Senator Fulbright because Johnson hated him with a passion. I didn't want
                    it to be known that I had seen Fulbright.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At budget time, did you discuss at least the general
                        outlines of the Department's requests with Rooney and McClellan? Were these
                        mostly briefing sessions or did you also use them to find out what would be
                        approved and what wouldn't be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was essentially a matter of letting them feel that they were
                    involved and knowledgeable before the budget was actually sent to them. I would
                    ask if they had any problems with any part of it. They appreciated the briefing.
                    They liked to know the answers before they asked the questions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But Rooney would still berate you and other witnesses at
                        hearing time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. Rooney had a technique. It didn't take long to catch on to it.
                    Rooney would ask: “How many cars do you have in post X or Y or Z?”. He loved to
                    ask about cars. Or he would ask about housing, particularly about some
                    apartments that he had seen during one of his trips which he thought were too
                    plush. A lot of the questions had nothing to do with the budget—nothing. But the
                    budget would come through unscathed. But Rooney would have his fun; he would get
                    his digs at the Department in the newspapers. Frank Bow, who was the ranking
                    minority member on the appropriations subcommittee, was not that type. I saw him
                    as often as I saw John Rooney. He was very appreciative of my visits and my
                    briefings. I always got a big glass of bourbon out of Senator Young of North
                    Dakota, who was on the Senate Appropriations Committee. The members of Congress
                    are human too; they like to know that you know who they are and where they fit
                    in the system and that you are paying attention to them. I never had any
                    business with Fulbright; he dealt with the substantive side of the Department
                    and gave them all a fit. He was not interested in administrative matters.</p>
                <p>Sometimes, I would go to John Rooney's house—he didn't live too far away from us.
                    One time, a Congressman from Chicago was giving us a hard time, because he
                    thought that we hadn't treated one of his constituents correctly. So I went to
                    see Rooney and he told me he would take care of it. I never heard another word
                    about the matter. Most of the State Department staff didn't understand why it
                    was necessary to cultivate these Congressmen and Senators. They felt it was
                    demeaning. They never understood that they were important parts of the U.S.
                    Government and that someone from the Executive Branch had to liaison with
                    them—good, warm relationships. These Congressmen had to feel that they could
                    call me by my first name. I would address them as “Senator” or “Congressman”,
                    but they had to be able to call me “Idar”. Only with Rooney did I use his first
                    name. A lot of the State officials never understood the necessity for developing
                    a personal relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You did say that Rooney would, in general, approve the
                        funding requests that the Department would submit? His hearings therefore
                        were primarily for the record?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. He would see me after his presentations on the floor of the House
                    and say to me: “ What did you think of that? I got that one good, didn't I ?”.
                    We had a lot of supplemental budgets; he never touched them. He appropriated
                    exactly what we had asked for. Again, we would go to him before submitting the
                    budgets and tell him what the supplementals would contain. We would show them to
                    him. They used to go through on a consent calendar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your assessment of the Congressional views of the
                        Foreign Service during the late 60's?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Many thought the Foreign Service to be “cookie pushers”. Too prissy.
                    They would go to an Embassy and see our officers there with blue jackets, gray
                    pants and red ties standing properly. They didn't like that. The Congressmen
                    weren't farmers, but most were down-to-earth and didn't appreciate the “Ivy
                    League” look. I would say that the majority of Congress did not speak highly of
                    the working level staff of the Department and the Foreign Service. I never heard
                    them be derogatory; they didn't do that. But they didn't say anything nice; that
                    told you their views. But you could never accuse them of bad-mouthing the
                    Foreign Service; they didn't do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you escort Rooney on his trips?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: On lots of them. They were difficult because he never wanted to see the
                    Ambassador. He would if you forced him into it. He would have to see the DCM. He
                    had a set pattern. When he came to Paris, he wanted to see the garage. So we
                    took him to the garage which was a mess because we were in the middle of a move.
                    He would say: “Can't you guys do anything right? Can't you clean up this
                    thing?”. He would want to go out to Neuilly to see the apartments. Never came
                    into the Embassy. He was there three days and never came into the Embassy. He
                    would make extended trips—to Paris, to Rome, etc. I went with him to Rome and
                    didn't go into the Embassy there. He wanted to see the Pope and we got that
                    done, which was quite a deal. John Rooney said: “ I was entitled to that”
                    because he had helped pass an appropriation to rebuild Monte Cassino.</p>
                <p>But at every post, he had certain pet projects he wanted to see. You could count
                    on it that during some speech that he would give when our appropriations bill
                    was being considered, these things would come up—they were little, nit-picking
                    things. Rooney was difficult because he was so demanding in terms of late night
                    hours, restaurants and other personal requirements.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about President Johnson's and his White House staff's
                        view of the Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: He didn't trust the Foreign Service. He didn't; President Kennedy
                    obviously didn't. I don't know about Carter. Nixon obviously didn't. Presidents
                    don't like the Foreign Service because they don't understand it. They like the
                    people in the system whom they know, but as a Service, they didn't trust it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is the Foreign Service so different from other
                        bureaucracies?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: No, Departments like Commerce or Agriculture only have to deal with a
                    small number of members of Congress. Those Departments can focus on them. State,
                    on the other hand, needs to worry about all 535 members, all of whom become
                    foreign affairs experts when they travel. The Department must make extraordinary
                    efforts to cultivate all members. When a Foreign Service officer, who might be
                    from Iowa, returns from an overseas tour, he or she should go see his or her
                    Congressperson. They don't, but they should. They should develop that one-on-one
                    contact which makes friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let me ask you about your views of the role of
                        management-administration in the Department of State. You followed a Deputy
                        Under Secretary who had difficulties with the Foreign Service because of
                        some of the management systems he wanted to introduce into the Department.
                        What was the situation when you took over the job? How was the job viewed
                        and how were you viewed personally?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: The system was apprehensive. I never had a warm, friendly relationship
                    with Assistant Secretaries and Deputy Under Secretaries. They don't like
                    administration. They didn't like me because I was in administration. I was the
                    guy who would tell them what they couldn't do. Interestingly enough, I had
                    excellent working relationships with Llewellyn Thompson, Dick Davis, Chip Bohlen
                    and Bob McBride. These were fellows, who, when I was nominated for the position
                    of Deputy Under Secretary, gave me full support. Rusk called all of them and
                    they were apparently very laudatory. But the people with whom I had not served
                    were obviously apprehensive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you make any efforts to overcome that
                        apprehension?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I don't think I made enough. There were so many issues on my desk that
                    I couldn't spend enough time with them. I spent a disproportionate amount of
                    time working with Congress and the White House. I should have cut off some of
                    that and spent more time with my State colleagues. But I had lunch with a lot of
                    the Assistant Secretaries and Deputy Under Secretaries and others. But I also
                    think that from the time a junior officer joins the Service, he is told by his
                    elders to watch out for the administrative types—”they would do you no good”.
                    The consequences were that there was no support for administration at the junior
                    or mid-career levels. There wasn't a single member of the American Foreign
                    Service Association Board that had any sympathy to administration or its
                    problems. Not one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You raised the subject of time. This seems to be a
                        particularly difficult problem for people in the Deputy Under Secretary
                        position. What is the problem and what are possible solutions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I felt that there was not enough time to adequately focus on an issue
                    or problem. You had to pick and choose; I would berate myself for not having
                    been on the Hill recently. I just felt that I had to see the Congressmen who
                    were important to us. You couldn't only see them when a bill of interest to the
                    Department was about to be brought to the floor. That would have been too
                    obvious. You had to see them when there wasn't an issue before them just to
                    touch base with them. But I probably should have spent more time with Department
                    officials. But I had to make a choice and I felt that people outside the
                    Department were more important. I didn't really have much sympathy at the time
                    for the “cry babies”—the Departmental people who would be complaining about this
                    and that. There was always something that they wanted. When I suggested that
                    they go see their own Assistant Secretary, they would say that they couldn't get
                    by him. Maybe there is a problem in the whole system, but it certainly starts at
                    the junior levels when the new members of the Service are advised to watch out
                    for the administrative staffs. From the time they graduated from the Foreign
                    Service Institute and were given their first assignments, they had a mind set to
                    distrust administration and the people in it. They had already learned to resent
                    the administrative people for having so much authority. Officers who carry power
                    in the system and who moved up in the ranks, understood administration. Very
                    rarely did I find an Assistant Secretary or Deputy Assistant Secretary who
                    didn't understand my point of view. He may not have liked it, but he did
                    appreciate my problem and would try to be helpful. But below that level, it was
                    a real minefield.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In light of your comments, what is the answer to the
                        problem of spreading the then Deputy Under Secretary (now Under Secretary)
                        position too thin? Is there a solution to “over-load”?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: In order to function in that job, you had to know something about
                    personnel, security, budget, building, etc because the Deputy Under Secretary
                    was responsible for all those functions. My objection to today's system is that
                    the Department has taken those responsibilities away from the Under Secretary
                    for Management so that he has no feel for the day-to-day situation. None of
                    these administrative functions go through him. He really is divorced from
                    reality and works in the blue skies. In my days, I knew what was going on in
                    each of the administrative areas. I would come to work at seven in the morning
                    and rarely left before seven at night. I would go back to my conference room and
                    read and do the work I had to do uninterruptedly. I did a lot of business over
                    lunches and breakfasts with the staff. But when you are dealing with thousands
                    of people, you can only scratch the surface. But I did find that the people I
                    got to know in Moscow and in Paris and in Germany to some extent, all became
                    pretty good friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did the position of Assistant Secretary for
                        Administration get re-established?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: That was strictly a political move. When I became the Deputy Under
                    Secretary, there was no Assistant Secretary position—it having been abolished by
                    Bill Crockett at an earlier time.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>By April 1969, it was obvious to me that I was not in tune with the new Nixon
                    Administration and I decided to leave the position of Deputy Under Secretary. It
                    would have just become more painful if I had continued. Too many times I would
                    send memos to the Secretary or Under Secretary for decisions and they would be
                    passed on to some staff level person. So I went to Secretary Rogers and told him
                    that I thought it would be best for all concerned if I left. There was an
                    Ambassadorial opening in Geneva which would be available in the Fall and I told
                    him that I would like that post. He said he would get back to me. A couple of
                    weeks later, Rogers told me that I could go to Geneva, but that White House
                    clearance would be required which would be forthcoming sometime in the Summer. I
                    then briefed Frank Bow on the situation, because he had told me back in January
                    or February that Bill Macomber was trying very hard to become the Deputy Under
                    Secretary. He had been on the Hill mounting Congressional support. But all the
                    people he spoke to wanted to know what would happen to me—these people had
                    become friends of mine by that time. So I went to talk to Bow and he asked me
                    what would happen to Frank Meyer, who was working for me at that time. I told
                    him that I didn't know. Bow asked whether Frank could become an Assistant
                    Secretary. I responded that I hadn't thought of it, but anything was possible if
                    that were his desire. Bow said: “That is what I want”. I reported that
                    conversation to Rogers and Richardson and I expressed the view that Macomber
                    might have a difficult time being confirmed unless Meyer was made an Assistant
                    Secretary. I had operated as Deputy Under Secretary without an Assistant
                    Secretary, which may have been part of the reason for the very heavy workload
                    that fell on my position. I had taken the administrative structure as it was. If
                    I had had an Assistant Secretary, I would still have had Personnel report to me,
                    but as for budget, security and general housekeeping, that could have come under
                    the purview of the Assistant Secretary. But I would have had to keep Personnel,
                    the Bureau of Consular Affairs, the Foreign Service Institute and to some
                    extent, the budget operations, particularly in the final stages of formulation—I
                    had to be involved in that. The rest could have been supervised by an Assistant
                    Secretary and that would have eased my work-load considerably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That last comment suggests that you saw your
                        responsibilities to be primarily personnel and budget.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: That is correct. We had to have the money and we had to be sure that
                    the personnel system was working with efficiency—that the right people were
                    being assigned to the right jobs. Let's face it: an Assistant Secretary doesn't
                    necessarily have the right judgement on whom he is placing in jobs. I am
                    thinking particularly of Latin America which staffed with a lot of “old hands”
                    whom they assigned to jobs that just weren't appropriate for the officer. But
                    the Bureau would never publicly admit these misassignments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you know, the Department has been going back and forth
                        from the days it was founded about whom should be given responsibility for
                        assignments: a central office or each regional bureau. Every few years it
                        swings back from one system to the other. What are your views?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I think it should be the responsibility of a central Personnel office,
                    with a large input from the Bureaus. Bureaus have a tendency to have the “old
                    boy” syndrome because too many of the senior officers in a Bureau have buddies
                    whom they want to bring along with them. EUR especially suffered from this
                    syndrome. That is not good for the personnel system. Chip Bohlen had some people
                    that he took care of. He used to give me hell when I was in “O” because I
                    wouldn't follow his recommendations on some of his people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What does that syndrome say about the Foreign Service as
                        an institution? In the late 60s, what did you consider the strengths and
                        weaknesses of the Service to be?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: The Service includes some tremendously capable people. Given lead, it
                    does a very good job. But the Service suffers from its poor relationships with
                    the rest of the Government. Those parts do not understand the Foreign Service;
                    they don't understand its functions. It is a big void to them. The Service must
                    make a major effort to let the rest of the Government, and particularly
                    Congress, know what and how it does.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There is another continual debate in the Department and
                        that is whether the Service should be staffed with generalists or
                        specialists. What are your views?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I was a specialist who became a generalist. But it would have been a
                    big mistake to make me Ambassador to Italy. I think it is a big mistake to put
                    some of the political appointees in these very sensitive Ambassadorial positions
                    because they have not been nurtured in the political and economic environment
                    that you need in a lot of these jobs. There are of course a lot of posts where
                    the Ambassador has essentially a management job and where he or she is supported
                    by good technical people. In that kind of post, a manager can often do a far
                    superior job than a political officer who can't manage.</p>
                <p>The decision to assign one kind of person over another to certain ambassadorial
                    positions varies from year to year. If there is a country with political or
                    economic problems either internally or with the United States—such as India, for
                    example—it should be filled with someone well versed in the diplomatic problems
                    that exist between it and Pakistan and it and the U.S. That is not a job for a
                    manager. It is job for someone with international political and economic
                    experience. The same is true with a lot of the Third World countries. The
                    management of a large Embassy such as we have in New Delhi can be left to the
                    DCM. The political and economic problems that India has are so acute that a
                    mistake would be made if the Department assigned a manager to try to make sense
                    of and influence the situation.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So the major question for you is what are our
                        relationships with the country rather than what is the content of our
                        program?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: My question always was: “What are we looking at today?”. The answer to
                    that question changes periodically. In Thailand and in most of the smaller
                    European countries, you can get by with managers. There is no compelling reason
                    to put an economist or political officer in those jobs. All you need is someone
                    with fairly decent judgment. But you can't generalize even for the same post.
                    What is right for a post one year, may not be the following. Czechoslovakia
                    might be a good illustration. The right Ambassador before the revolution would
                    have been one person; following it, it probably should have been someone else.
                    After the revolution, I would have saved that post for a Czechoslovakian expert.
                    There are real problems coming up in that country and I am sure the Department
                    has sent a DCM and other officers well versed in Czechoslovakian matters to back
                    up Mrs. Black. She is a very nice person; she used to come to see me in the
                    Department, but she certainly is not a Czechoslovakian expert.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This discussion raises the question of developing managers
                        in the Foreign Service. What were your views on that subject?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I believed that a variety of experiences could develop managers,
                    starting with an assignment to a small post and moving on to larger ones. The
                    officer must have “hands-on” experience; you won't learn management of the
                    Foreign Service in school. It would be nice if the officer had a business
                    administration degree, but someone with that degree doesn't want to start at the
                    bottom; because of the education that person wants to start higher up. But if an
                    officer starts at a small post and gradually is moved up, then he or she will
                    have the right experience. Once you have been at a major post—it doesn't have to
                    be a big one—you will have seen all the problems. The management issues in The
                    Hague are no different than they are in Paris. The Paris embassy is just larger,
                    but the problems are the same.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather from your comments that you think that there
                        shouldn't be a debate about specialists and generalists, but that the
                        Department needs some of each?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Absolutely. The Department needs both. To say otherwise, shows an
                    ignorance of the system and the problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How should the system insure that there are cadre of
                        personnel in sufficient numbers to specialize in any one of the many areas
                        of expertise needed by the Department?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It should bring younger officers up in each of the areas, particularly
                    those that have difficult languages. You start them out as a third secretary,
                    then you bring him or her back as chief of the political section and later on as
                    the DCM. The main problem is that somewhere between 30% and 40% percent of
                    ambassadorial appointments are made from non-career ranks. When Johnson was
                    President, he wanted to keep the number under 40%. Even Kennedy, who was not
                    impressed by the Foreign Service, tried to keep it under 40%. These non-career
                    appointees don't want Central American posts or African posts; there are a lot
                    of posts that they don't want. So they get European posts. That is a fact of
                    life and the Service must accept it. Therefore, the system has to concentrate on
                    who the DCM will be, who will be the chiefs of the Political Section, Economic
                    or Administrative Sections. That is what the system must concentrate on. If the
                    President wants to fill certain jobs with non-career people, that is his
                    prerogative and he will do it. The Department keeps fighting about the
                    Ambassadorial job; it should think more about the number two jobs and the
                    Section chiefs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were Deputy Under Secretary, were these the kinds
                        of issues that came to you that kept your “plate full”?. Were most of the
                        issues you worried about in the personnel field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. Mostly about individuals. In the final analysis, people would talk
                    theory and then get down to one or two actual cases. By the time the lunch was
                    over, you got to the bottom line: the assignment of one or two officers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your experience, are individual assignments as
                        important in other institutions? Or would the discussions with some one at
                        your comparable level have been more system-oriented or philosophical?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I can tell you that in the ACDA, during the brief time I was there, it
                    was no different. There are many top-level people, like McCloy, who believed
                    that any system would work if it had good people. I believe that as well. That
                    of course can be carried too far. There may some systems that are so lousy that
                    no one can make it work, but give me any reasonable system and with good people
                    they will make it work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your views of your own staff when you were
                        Deputy Under Secretary?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was a mixed bag. Roberts in budget was good; he was not the fellow
                    that I would have picked, but did an acceptable job. He did not fare too well
                    with Congressional staffs; he had a tendency to talk down to them which they
                    didn't appreciate. The Chief of Personnel changed so often while I was there
                    that I don't have a clear answer to your question. The Director General—John
                    Steeves—was not very useful. On my first day on the job, he came to see me to
                    tell me that he should have had my job. Other than Steeves, it was a competent
                    staff. I did have a change in the Administrator of Consular Affairs when Barbara
                    Watson was appointed. She was a great person. Just great! Absolutely tops. She
                    had a legal background and was just the right appointment for that job. You
                    never had to worry about her. Never. She had good judgement. She was highly
                    respected by her staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In retrospect, would you have done things differently as
                        Deputy Under Secretary than you actually did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes, if I could do it over again. For example, I would put a much, much
                    greater emphasis on restructuring of our overseas representation. I would have
                    tried to cut down overseas staffing, particularly from other government
                    agencies, who, as I said earlier, could have performed as effectively if not
                    more so by sending their people from Washington for specific and short-term
                    assignments. That would have greatly reduced our large housekeeping functions
                    overseas, maintaining housing and schools and all that goes with overseas
                    staffing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Along the same lines, what were your views of Consulates
                        General and Consulates? Did we need all of them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: They are there primarily to “show the flag”. Many were not needed then
                    and are certainly not needed today. But I would have liked to give to Nice or
                    Marseille or Bordeaux, for example, as long as they were open, more consular
                    functions and kept them out of the Paris Embassy. Such a decentralization might
                    have justified keeping those posts open. If such decentralization were not
                    acceptable, I would have preferred to have Honorary Consul Generals in most of
                    the large cities in Europe. I would have given them enough money to have an
                    office, but I would not have paid them. That is very much what the Europeans do
                    in the United States. They have Honorary Consul Generals. Such a system would
                    have been a big help; it would have been good public relations and would have
                    met our needs adequately. You might have had to have an American in some of the
                    places to take care of the consular responsibilities. We made a mistake when we
                    just completely closed these posts. We didn't save that much money; we should
                    have kept a presence. We could have done that by providing just enough money for
                    an office and a secretary—$ 25,000 would have done that in most of these
                    cities.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You implied in one of your previous comments that the size
                        of the Department's administrative workload was just too large. It had to
                        support too many Americans overseas. Is that correct?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. We should have achieved that cutback by bringing back some of the
                    people stationed overseas. When I left Paris, there were about 750 Americans in
                    the Embassy. Two-thirds were not State Department. It was true that CIA was a
                    large presence at that time, but all had to be provided office space and
                    housing. I always wondered what all these people were doing. Why couldn't they
                    be stationed in Washington and fly to Paris when needed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your relationships with other agencies when you
                        were Deputy Under Secretary?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: I saw so little of them. Commerce knew that I didn't want the
                    commercial service to transfer from State to Commerce. But that was the only
                    agency with whom relationships were tense. I didn't see much of USIA or AID; we
                    had good working relationships. I had very good working relationships with CIA,
                    AEC. I supported the general concept of joint administrative services at
                    overseas posts, but since it varied so much from post to post, it could not be
                    discussed in the abstract. I supported joint services in the larger posts, as
                    long as State maintained the leadership role. In smaller posts, particularly
                    those where other agencies overwhelmed State, the top job probably had to be
                    filled by a State officer because the orders would come from the Ambassador and
                    it would have been difficult had it been a representative of another agency. It
                    might have worked if an Ambassador would have been willing to have the
                    administrative support provided by AID or any other agency. I think that case
                    would have been very rare. One problem was that other agency representation
                    varied so much from time to time. One year it would be large; a few years later
                    it might be non-existent. That would have made support by that agency very
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: While you were Deputy Under Secretary, there was a change
                        in administrations. What do you recall from that transition?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Except for myself, every senior officer in the Department left when the
                    new administration came into power. One of the great mysteries has always been
                    why I was kept on because I had no contacts with the Nixon people. Kissinger
                    spent a lot of time in State; Rogers was there often. Rogers brought in his own
                    team, more or less. That transition was not difficult because it was obvious
                    right from the beginning that Nixon would be his own Secretary of State. It was
                    clear that nothing would happen in the Department without Nixon's blessing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any particular responsibility for preparing
                        briefing papers for the new team?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>RIMESTAD: They didn't ask for any. They didn't have a transition team in
                    administration. And I don't think that they had one on the substantive side
                    either. It was obvious that foreign policy would be decided in the White House,
                    not in State. There was no transition team, as had been set up in the past. The
                    new team had a nice office on the first floor and had four or five people there,
                    but it was not a transition team in the usual sense of the word. The new team
                    showed no interest in the organization or management of the Department. The
                    emphasis was 100% on substantive issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When Rogers took over as Secretary of State, he left you
                        entirely alone?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Absolutely. Only Richardson, as I mentioned earlier, showed any
                    interest in management. That was true also for personnel appointments. If the
                    Secretary had any wishes, they would be transmitted to me through
                    Richardson.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the new appointees make any demands on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Nothing unusual. Some of them wanted to bring their own secretaries and
                    we agreed to that. Some of the new appointees were easy to get along; some were
                    more difficult. There was a guy by the name of Pederson, who was appointed as
                    Counselor, who for a time, I think, thought he was the Secretary of State. That
                    was the exception. There were a lot of ambassadorial appointments that became
                    problems, but not on my side of the house. There were mostly problems resulting
                    from the lack of White House checking with Congress on whether the nominations
                    would be approved. But I had no problems with the new team on ambassadorial
                    appointments. We followed established practice of using a small committee of
                    senior officials to make up the list of candidates. That list went from Rogers
                    to the White House and any problems were discussed between Rogers and the White
                    House. It was quite different from the practices during the Johnson
                    Administration. This change was primarily due to the fact that Nixon wouldn't
                    talk to anybody but his very senior officials. Johnson and Kennedy would go
                    directly to the officer who would have the most knowledge on a subject; Nixon
                    would not. Kissinger also never called me. Once in great while, Eagleburger
                    would call, but that was it.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>But as I said, after three months, I knew that I wasn't welcomed. I would put a
                    problem forward and either not get an answer or some staffer would call me. I
                    took that as an indication that my time was up. That was not the normal
                    operating procedure on the Seventh floor. Rogers dealt directly with other
                    Deputy Under Secretaries. I went to one lunch given by the Secretary; he used to
                    have such affairs about three times per week for his top staff. I was invited to
                    only one. That really told me that my days were numbered. That made me wonder
                    even more on why I had not been replaced. I still don't know what transpired. I
                    assume that someone talked to Nixon because the President had to approve the
                    re-appointment, but I don't know who it was or why it was done. But by the end
                    of the third month, I told my wife that we would be moving; I had been around
                    the Department long enough to know when things were going well and when they
                    weren't. And they weren't. In the Nixon Administration, all you had to say that
                    this was the way it was done in the Johnson Administration and that would be
                    sufficient cause to change it. Rogers was nice to me; Richardson was nice to me.
                    But obviously I was not their choice. I know that Richardson wanted Macomber; he
                    made no bones about it. I don't think that Macomber had any closer relationship
                    to the Secretary than I did; he probably didn't care one way or another.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lets' move on to your Geneva assignment. You arrived in
                        Geneva in December, 1969. What were the main responsibilities of the U.S.
                        Representative (Ambassador) to International Organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Management. The title had little meaning. You got the benefit of going
                    to all the National Day observances of each country represented in the UN
                    bodies. We had a small political and a small economic staff. The job was
                    basically to manage the logistics for all the conferences convened by the UN
                    specialized agencies headquartered in Geneva. I had very little to do with that;
                    I had a good staff that handled these matters. Some of the UN agencies, like WHO
                    (World Health Organization) did their own logistic work. All we needed to do was
                    to tell them the size of our delegation, they would take it from there. I never
                    gave a speech that I had written; all my speeches were written in Washington and
                    one better not have changed a word. I gave these speeches once in a while to one
                    or another of the UN specialized agencies when the Washington agency didn't send
                    a high level representative to Geneva. There is a lot of political mileage to be
                    obtained by taking an expert from Chicago and sending him to Geneva to give a
                    speech. He was very honored. Maybe that speech should have been delivered by the
                    US Ambassador, but no domestic political credit would have accrued. The US
                    Representative was an Ambassador in title only. You are useful in helping
                    Congressmen or other high-ranking officials. We had a very heavy visitors
                    workload. We did everything possible to make these VIPs comfortable during their
                    visits to Geneva. We would have dinner party for them. We had good relationships
                    with the other European representatives who had the same problems. I would
                    probably give a dozen large dinner parties every year.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>As with other US overseas representation, if we were still in the sailing ship
                    era, permanent personnel stationed in Geneva would have been useful. But today,
                    with modern transportation, it is much more effective to send people from
                    Washington to give the speeches and attend the conferences. Only rarely—if
                    someone would get sick for example—would the US representative have to stand
                    in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What did your political and economic staffs do?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: The economic officers would work primarily on GATT (The General
                    Agreement on Trade and Tariffs organization) which is headquartered in Geneva. I
                    would not have anything to do with GATT—I wouldn't touch that thing. That had
                    many people already involved. Washington watched those deliberations very
                    carefully. The economic officers worked for me, but it was understood that the
                    prudent approach was to leave them alone. I did a lot of work on the immigration
                    and disaster relief programs that Sadruddin Aga Khan ran for a long time. I gave
                    them a lot of checks and gave a lot of impromptu speeches.</p>
                <p>But the Ambassadorial job in Geneva was essentially a managerial one. You also
                    had to have a sense of when to step in and when to step out. You were dealing
                    with a lot of egos. At one time, there was a fellow by the name of Walsh who was
                    working with WHO. He was a friend of President Nixon; he ran Project “HOPE”.
                    When I met him, I told him that if he ever ran into a political problem that
                    might become testy, to let me know and I would see what I could do. In reply he
                    said: “What do I need some pipsqueak from State Department to tell me how to do
                    my job” and he walked out.</p>
                <p>Despite this episode and my other comments, I do believe that some resident US
                    representation in Geneva is required because there are a lot of formal
                    government notes to be delivered to the various international organizations and
                    that needs to be done by a senior official. I had to go to the ILO
                    (International Labor Organization) on many occasions; we had trouble with them.
                    I would carry the formal note over and explain it. That's when I became familiar
                    with that famous State Department record called the “Memorandum of
                    Conversation”. You would write it up before the meeting and then hand it to the
                    person with whom you would have the meeting. They appreciated it; everybody
                    appreciated that the staff work had been done ahead of time. This would preclude
                    any surprises. Sometime the other person would have done the same thing; we
                    would then sit down and make what modifications were necessary and come up with
                    an agreed document.</p>
                <p>It is important that we have some senior representation in Geneva. It is an
                    all-year job with little time for vacation because one or another of the
                    international organizations would be involved in a conference or some activity
                    that needed monitoring. December and January were the slow months; otherwise
                    there was always something going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you satisfied with the role that the U.S. played in
                        these international organizations while you were in Geneva?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: We had the big fight with the ILO, which they brought on themselves. I
                    knew the chairman—he was a Britisher. He had to make a choice of whether he
                    would offend us or the Soviets. He appointed a Russian to be his deputy. I told
                    him that we could never accept that. He said that he had to make a choice
                    between two unpalatable options. Finally Rooney, at George Meany's request, cut
                    off US financial support to ILO. And we pulled out.</p>
                <p>We were sufficiently involved in WHO; we were very forthcoming with WHO in terms
                    of financial support which is what they needed. We were very active in trying to
                    eradicate small pox, yellow fever, malaria and other major diseases. So I was
                    satisfied with US involvement with the international organizations headquartered
                    in Geneva.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You left Geneva in May or June of 1973 after almost four
                        years. Did you enjoy the assignment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: It was very pleasant, but at times not challenging.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then you decided to retire?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>RIMESTAD: Yes. I talked to Macomber about future assignments and he told me that
                    there was nothing at the moment. He said that there would be an opening in
                    Honduras and some other post, but that I would have to return to Washington and
                    wait for an opening. Macomber was telling me what I had told many Ambassadors
                    while I was Deputy Under Secretary of State. “We will bring you back and we will
                    see what we can do”. I could not nor would I walk the hallways. I asked him to
                    arrange for my retirement.</p>
                <p>Within the Senior Service, many officers had to be brought back without an onward
                    assignment. Some were very good officers; some had very little possibility for
                    an onward assignment. The one thing we did frequently when I was Deputy Under
                    Secretary was to use that section of the Foreign Service Act which permits the
                    Secretary to retire any returning Ambassador who did not receive another
                    assignment within three months. We did that frequently. An Ambassador would
                    return from an overseas tour and if no other assignment had been found within
                    the three months period, he would get a termination notice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Thank you very much, Idar. That was a very useful
                        contribution to the Oral History of the Foreign Service collection.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
