<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib001338">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Dr. Evelyn S. Colbert </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2007</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress</p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2007-11-05"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project</p>
                <p>DR. EVELYN COLBERT</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Charles Stuart Kennedy</p>
                <p>Initial interview date: September 20, 2004</p>
                <p>Copyright 2005 ADST</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is tape one side one with Dr. Evelyn Colbert. This is
                        being done on behalf of the Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training,
                        and I'm Charles Stuart Kennedy. Do you go by Evelyn?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When and where were you born and could you tell me
                        something about your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I was born in New York City on July 6, 1918. My grandparents and their
                    families were part of the massive flight of Jews from Russia during the pogroms
                    of the 1880s. At the time of their arrival in New York, my father was a baby, my
                    mother a toddler. I was a late child and did not know any of my
                    grandparents.</p>
                <p>My father ran his own business, an export-import company dealing largely with
                    Latin America. His involvement with Latin America had come about during the
                    Spanish-American war when he was a very young man. An outspoken pacifist, he was
                    fired from his job in the chemistry library at Columbia, his boss being a strong
                    supporter of the war. Through a friend, who had married into a prominent family
                    in Mexico City, he got a job in a mining company and quickly became fluent in
                    Spanish. After a number of years in Mexico, he moved to a mining company in
                    Honduras. Returning to New York, he organized the export department of one of
                    the major chemical companies of the time and then went into business on his own.
                    Because of my father's business connections, my family entertained many Latin
                    American visitors bur, called upon to do no more than pass the peanuts, this did
                    not particularly enlarge my horizons.</p>
                <p>My mother before her marriage had been what was then called a typewriter at a
                    company that published the leading women's magazines of that time. My
                    recollection is that she enjoyed her job. But she never worked thereafter.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>I have one sibling, a brother six years older. For a long time I was the brat kid
                    sister. But by the time I was twelve or so, we became good friends. It was he
                    who introduced me to the joys of browsing through the second-hand bookstores
                    that then lined Fourth Avenue, where all sorts of treasures could be found for
                    fifteen cents and a quarter. We have remained very good friends even though,
                    since college days we have never lived in the same place.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: New York was quite open wasn't it in those days? A small
                        child could mover around quite freely?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Absolutely. Those were the glory days for growing up in New York. As
                    soon as you could be counted on not to get lost, which in New York was an easy
                    stage to reach, you had the freedom of the city. Where I lived, Riverside Park,
                    Central Park, and the major museums were all within easy reach and the museums
                    were all free.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Politics, of course in New York City in that era, were
                        quite strong weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: They certainly were in my family. My father had become an active
                    Socialist at an early age and remained one. When I was growing up he was on the
                    board of directors of the Socialist weekly newspaper, The New Leader, and of the
                    Socialist-affiliated Ranel School. So international and national politics were
                    routinely part of family discussions and the subject of a number of the
                    periodicals that came into the housThe Nation, the American Mercury, and, of
                    course, The New York Times. Debates, sometimes rather heated, among family and
                    friends concerned not only general domestic and international issues but also
                    questions of particular interest in left-wing circles: the rights and wrongs of
                    Soviet policies, support for non-Socialist, reformist leaders, relations with
                    the Communists. One the last issue, my father was very much of the right-wing.
                    When the Socialist Party split in the late thirties because its then leader,
                    Norman Thomas, wanted to enter a united front with the Communists, my father was
                    part of the group that left the Socialist Party and set up the Social Democratic
                    Federation.</p>
                <p>As far as politics were concerned, my mother walked very much in my father's
                    footsteps. Pacifism was the one belief that she held very strongly. Otherwise
                    her real interests lay in art, the theatre, and music. However, she was a great
                    admirer of Franklin Delano Roosevelt and was very happy to be able to vote for
                    him when the Socialist Party supported him for a second term.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your parents' views rub off on you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I was very much influenced by both my parents. They were both very
                    strong-minded and articulate. My mother, in particular, had lots of time for me
                    and, before I did such things by myself or with friends, she took me to plays,
                    concerts, and galleries. My father not only stimulated my interest in politics
                    and international affairs but also encouraged an interest in science which,
                    however, did not outlast my high school years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you much of a reader?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Reading was something you did naturally, like breathing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about early on, what kinds of books?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: All kinds. Whatever was in the house was open for me to read and that
                    was a lot. And if I wanted to read the popular serials, that was okay too. We
                    had a very good local public library; beginning in eights grade I think it was,
                    you had access to the adult section. By the time I was twelve or so, I was
                    reading adult books, classic and contemporary, but still reading children's
                    books as well. My favorite authors at that time were Bernard Shaw, H.G. Wells,
                    E. Nesbit, and A.A. Milne.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go to school, let's start from your first
                        schooling?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My first school was a coeducational grade school. I went from there in
                    fifth grade to the all girls Joan of Arc Junior High School. It was very good
                    with the basics, but very conservative. Most of the teachers were all, in my
                    eyes, very elderly. Basics aside, I think I learned more from my parents, from
                    reading, and from outside activities, particularly Girl Scouts, than I did in
                    junior high school.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How Jewish was your school? Both schools?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My junior high school drew entirely from the neighborhood which was part
                    of the upper west side which was then very diverse but in a geographically
                    divided way. The apartment houses of Riverside Drive, West End Avenue, and
                    Central Part West were largely occupied by upper middle class business and
                    professional Jewish families, quite conservative socially and politically.
                    Amsterdam and Columbus Avenues and the side streets were mostly lower middle
                    class and working class, predominantly Irish and Italian. We all went to school
                    together but Jewish girls predominated in the fast-track classes.</p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>My high school, Lydia Wadleigh, was very different. Located on the fringes of
                    Harlem, it drew students of very varied backgrounds from all over the city.
                    About one-third of the students were black but I don't remember much real
                    contact between black and white students. Unlike my junior high school, Wadleigh
                    did not rank very high academically, but I found it much more stimulating. The
                    teachers were younger, more liberal, and imaginative in their approach. Some of
                    them were even married and not all of them were women.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of activities did you get involved in in high
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I was on the school newspaper and our combined yearbooliterary magazine.
                    Typically of the times, our senior yearbook was dedicated to peace. Most of my
                    activities took place outside school but in company with schoolmates. My circle
                    was very literary. We read a good deal of poetry, gave one another Edna St.
                    Vincent Millay's latest books as presents, fancied ourselves as bohemians, and
                    spent Saturdays in Greenwich Village.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where did you go during the summer?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In my very early childhood we summered at the Jersey shore. For a number
                    of years I attended a Girl Scout camp on a lake in the Hudson River valley. It
                    was very cheap and run on a shoestrinno tennis courts, horses, or other
                    expensive facilities. The emphasis was on taking advantage of the natural
                    surroundinghiking, woodcraft, nature study, water sports, canoeing,
                    folk-singing, and folk-dancing. I loved it but at fifteen I felt I had outgrown
                    it. Thereafter, I spent my summers as a camp counselor in arts and crafts and/or
                    dramatics in a number of different camps.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At high school, were they pushing the students towards
                        college?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My high school at least was very unlike those of today in this regard.
                    We had no guidance counselors or the equivalent. In my particular circle of
                    friends we all assumed we were going to college and where we applied was a
                    personal or family matter. Of course, in that era, there was nothing like the
                    tension over being admitted that there has been for so many years. You didn't
                    have to apply to six schools to be sure of being admitted to one. Perhaps it was
                    the depression. Or perhaps there were many fewer high school students going on
                    to college.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At the high school, were they pushing the students towards
                        college?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>COBLERT: I had always had Barnard in mind. I really didn't want to leave New
                    York. It was the place I did everything I was interested in. Nor did I have any
                    particular desire to live away from home since I did not feel at all restricted
                    in my activities and, from what I'd heard of it, dormitory life did not appeal
                    to me. Plus, a practical consideration, I had a four-year New York State
                    scholarship that could only be used at a college located in the state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about the depression? How did this affect things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Our depression began well before 1929. My father, having been quite
                    wealthy, had managed to lose a good deal of money some years before the crash.
                    So that the big difference was that, among the people we knew, everybody else
                    became as poor as we were. But this was not the poverty of breadlines,
                    unemployment, and other real depression era suffering. Instead, for us, being
                    poor meant living in a smaller apartment without a river view, having no maid,
                    not buying or doing expensive thingin short, living very frugally. But living
                    frugally was not all that bad. Lots of things were frelike the museumor very
                    cheap, like movie and second balcony theater tickets and neighborhood
                    restaurants, and you could lead quite a good life without much money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Then the New Deal came along. What was the impact of that
                        on your family?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Not much that I can recall on our economic circumstances, but
                    considerable impact otherwise. When Roosevelt ran the first time, the Socialist
                    position that there was no real difference between the two major parties
                    remained unchanged. But, with the New Deal under way, the Socialists supported
                    him for a second term, in line one might say with the principles of Fabianism
                    that were a strong influence on my father. Domestically, it was a hopeful period
                    in many waynot only the programs to correct social and economic ills but also
                    the ferment in the arts and literature. But there was a dark side as well. The
                    world outside was becoming increasingly disturbing and concern with the threat
                    of ware and fascism was very much part of the intellectual climate of the
                    thirties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went to Barnard? You were there from when to
                        when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: 1934-38.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was it like when you were there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I have to start out by saying that Virginia C. Gildersleeve was the dean
                    of Barnard in my day. Although she has gone down in history as a liberal, to us
                    she seemed very conservative both politically and socially and the school
                    reflected this. It was a much smaller school than it is now. I think we were
                    about 900 altogether. Academically, it was rigorous if you wanted it to be, but
                    it was also possible to get by without undue exertion if you chose the right
                    major. Socially it was great because, although it wasn't coeducational, we had
                    all those boys across the street at Columbia College and there were twice as
                    many of them as there were of us. I lived at home so I was not subject to all of
                    the dormitory rules.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In by 10 and all of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In by 10 and having to sign out where you were goina walk being the
                    favorite destination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know 10 years later, I used to date girls at Smith and
                        all, they all went to the library. Did you have to wear gloves and a hat on
                        certain occasions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: It wasn't a matter of regulation, one simple did. The activism on the
                    campus of the thirties, unlike that of the sixties, was not a life style
                    rebellion. Our casual dress for classes and on campus by today's standards was
                    very conservative, sweaters and skirts, or suits. There was only one dress rule;
                    no slacks or ski pants unless it was snowing and you commuted from the
                    suburbs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where the young ladies at Barnard from when you were
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The greatest number were from the New York area, Manhattan, the outer
                    boroughs, the near and distant suburbs in New York, New Jersey, and Connecticut.
                    There were quite a few from the South and others from elsewhere in the country.
                    There were a few foreign students but not very many.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you concentrated in any area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I was a history major and, as such, took history all four years. But the
                    history faculty, with the exception of the medieval history professor, was not
                    terribly stimulating. The government and economics departments were much
                    livelier. The titular head of the government department, Raymond Moley, was on
                    leave in Washington helping run the New Deal and the real mainstay of the
                    department was the quite young Thomas P. Peardon who had just made assistant
                    professor and who was an outstanding teacher and a very stimulating one. These
                    days, he probably wouldn't get tenure. He didn't do research or publish and was
                    always available for conversation with students. I took almost all of the
                    government courses available and two or three in economics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the events both in the Far East and in Europe concern
                        you? This is the high time of Hitler and weak government in France, and you
                        had Mussolini and then you had the Manchurian takeover. Things were really
                        happening.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: All that was very much part of our atmosphere. Events in Europe were of
                    particular concerit was, after all, the part of the world we were most familiar
                    with. Those of us concerned with such matters were anti-Japanese, pro-Chinese
                    and we tried to demonstrate our sympathies by wearing rayon stockings,
                    boycotting silk because it came from Japan. Otherwise, events in Asithe
                    activities of Mahatma Gandhi asiddidn't enter into our consciousness. These were
                    the days of a very active peace movement on campuses all over the country in
                    which even apolitical students participated at least to the extent of attending
                    rallies and demonstrations. And everyone took the Oxford Pledge. You remember
                    the Oxford Pledge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: “We will not fight for king or country.” It originated at
                        Oxford University. Most of the men ended fighting very well for king and
                        country, but during the thirties they all signed the pledge.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes. Of course, that was true also in this country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was the enormity of what was beginning to happen to the
                        Jews at this time in Germany emerge? I assume that a pretty steady flow of
                        refugees was coming out of Germany?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In the period we're talking about, I don't think the full enormity had
                    yet emerged. What was happening to the Jews of Germany had not yet assumed the
                    proportions of unprecedented horror. It seemed more like a replay, a deeply
                    disturbing one to be sure, of the persecutions familiar in the past. I don't
                    remember personally experiencing a vast flow of refugees. I encountered only a
                    very few: a small girl at one of the summer camps where I worked; a
                    distinguished professor of international law at the graduate school for whom I
                    worked as a student assistant; and a woman professional of some kind whom I
                    helped with her English. A refugee student was among my friends at the graduate
                    school but he was Czech, not Jewish.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Extracurricular, what sort of things were you involved
                        in?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: A great variety of things, well beyond the peace movement and the clubs
                    focused on politics and international relations. I was on the literary magazine,
                    becoming editor in chief in my senior year, and also on the editorial board of
                    our other two publications, our yearbook and newspaper. The latter was
                    particularly rewarding; I did movie reviews in my junior year and play reviews
                    as a senior. In those days, at least, the theatres which were far from filled,
                    found it worthwhile to provide free tickets in exchange for reviews in the
                    Barnard Bulletin. I was in something called Greek Gamea competition between the
                    freshman and sophomore classein dance, various athletic events, and poetry. I
                    directed the Junior Show, another long-lived institution. We had a very active
                    literary society devoted to filling a gap resulting from the fact that, until my
                    senior year, English literature teaching stopped before the modernists. We were
                    quite successful in getting contemporary poets to come for talks and readings.
                    William Carlos Williams among them. An added attraction was provided by our
                    joint meetings with the Columbia College literary society.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And boys, did you have time for boys?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Oh yes, indeed. In this regard, we were better off I think than many
                    other girls' schools. Being part of a university that included Columbia College
                    and being in a big city meant that our social life wasn't so focused on weekends
                    and formal dances although we had plenty of those. And those of us who lived at
                    home could entertain there; in this regard, I benefited from living near the
                    campus and having very hospitable parents.</p>
                <p>However, although our social life was coeducational, our academic life was
                    anything but. In my four years, I was in three coeducational classes. Two were
                    in my freshman year. One was a course in ancient history offered to both Barnard
                    and Columbia students because it was given by one of the foremost experts in the
                    field who was teaching at Columbia for just one academic year. The other was a
                    course in analytic geometry. I was assigned to this course rather than freshman
                    math because I had had four years of math in high school. The class included two
                    other Barnard freshmen, a couple of Columbia College students, and a couple of
                    graduate students. We all found it a miserable experience, our teacher a German
                    baroness and a very advanced mathematician indeed seemed quite unable to
                    understand that all of us — graduates and undergraduatefound her lectures
                    extraordinarily difficult to follow. In my senior year, my grade point average
                    permitted me to take one course in the graduate school. This was a course in
                    political theory with Robert MacIver, a distinguished political scientist and a
                    great teacher.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You moved from Barnard to graduate school at
                        Columbia?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes. I had been supposed to go to Oxford and had been admitted to
                    Somerville College. But this was 1938 and both my father and my faculty advisers
                    argued that Oxford would not be a good investment since war was likely to break
                    out within a year and I would be sent home lacking the degree for which a
                    two-year stay would be required. So in the fall of 1938 I entered what was then
                    the Public Law Department (later Political Science) with a major in
                    international relations and a minor in political theory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went all the way through at Columbia to get your Ph.D.
                        this was from 1938 to when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I completed my MA in June 1939 and in the next year completed my course
                    requirements for the Ph.D. and passed my doctors orals. (This was not unusually
                    fast in those days.) My next step involved selecting and justifying a
                    dissertation topic, a rather crucial task at that time since Columbia still had
                    a publishing requirement and, at least in theory, one's dissertation was
                    supposed to add something significant to the existing state of knowledge. In the
                    fall of 1940, not yet having a topic and therefore unable to apply for a
                    fellowship, I took a job as a teacher-in-training at a New York City high school
                    where I was a dogsbody for the chairman of the history department and taught two
                    classeone in modern European and one in American history. This gave me plenty of
                    time to spend in the library where, having selected a dissertation topic, I
                    concentrated on working up a prospectus that would support a fellowship
                    application. With a fellowship in hand, I returned to Columbia full-time for the
                    1941-42 academic year working on my dissertation. The Doctrine of Retaliation in
                    International Law under the supervision of Professor Philip C. Jessup. However,
                    in the summer of 1942, newly married, I moved to Washington and the next year
                    went to work for the Office of Strategic Services so I did not complete my
                    dissertation and get my degree until 1947. My dissertation was finally published
                    in 1948.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were at the graduate school at Columbia for four
                        years. Was it sort of a continuation of your four years at Barnard or very
                        different?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Very different. My academic life was now very coeducational but in an
                    unbalanced way since in the Public Law Department women were a very small
                    minority. There was only one way in which we suffered any discrimination and
                    this was in connection with something call the Wilsonian Club. Membership was by
                    invitation to the best students, but only to men. Since it was an honor to be
                    invited and the club met at professors' homes, I suppose we should have resented
                    the exclusion. But I don't think any of us did. Our consciousness had not been
                    sufficiently raised. I should add parenthetically that of my five classmates
                    who, like me, ended up in the State Department, three were womeKathleen Dougall
                    and Elizabeth Brown from the Public Law Department and Alberta Colclaser from
                    the Law School.</p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>My life in the graduate school was also significantly changed in other ways. In
                    college my activities and interests had been scattered over a wide area. At the
                    graduate school, they were much more focused on my major and minor subjects and
                    extracurricular activities consumed very little of my time. They were pretty
                    much confined to the Public Law Club, which included only students of our very
                    small department and was largely social, and to bull sessions over beer after
                    long hours at the library. I should add, I suppose, that I didn't spend all my
                    time on Morningside Heights. There were still the attractions of the city and a
                    social circle beyond my fellow students.</p>
                <p>The change in focus of our bull sessions was another marked difference, a
                    difference resulting from the changes in the world around us that culminated in
                    the outbreak of war in Europe. The issue was no longer simply peace or war; it
                    had become more complicated. Was military force the only feasible response to
                    Hitler's advance? Could one be against fascism and also against war? The Oxford
                    Pledge had already become irrelevant in Britain. Was it an appropriate position
                    for Americans? And, most of all, what should the Untied States do? Pearl Harbor,
                    of course, settled the debate between interventionists and isolationists. In due
                    course, most of my classmates went into government service, military or
                    civilian. I can remember only one conscientious objector in my circle;
                    eventually he opted out of his CD camp and joined the army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: By the time of Pearl Harbor had you had more exposure to
                        developments in Asia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My graduate work had involved somewhat more exposure to developments in
                    Asia and, of course, China was very much in the news. I took at least one course
                    with Professor Nathaniel Peffer, who before he came to Columbia had been for
                    many years a journalist in China and whose lectures focused on Japanese foreign
                    policy. And, in his seminar on Post-War Imperialism, of which I was a member for
                    two years, there was also some discussion of Asia. But Asia still remained on
                    the fringes of my consciousness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'd like to go just one step back. Could you tell me a
                        little bit about your husband. His background and how did you meet him?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I met him at Columbia where he had arrived in 1939 as a graduate fellow.
                    He was born and brought up in Victoria, British Columbia. After he graduated
                    from the University of British Columbia, he worked for a year or two for the
                    provincial government in Vancouver. Since he was in the Public Law Department as
                    a major in international law and relations we were in a number of classes
                    together and got to know one another fairly quickly. In due course, we became a
                    couple and were married in May 1942. Not long after that he was offered a job
                    with the British Raw Materials Mission and we moved to Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you went to work in OSS. How did that come
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: For a year or so after we moved to Washington, I continued to work on my
                    dissertation at the Library of Congress feeling free to fend off a couple of job
                    offers that came my way during this period. (Women with some training were a hot
                    commodity in those days.) But I was becoming aware that sending Jessup chapters
                    about private reprisals and retaliation during the Napoleonic Wars was putting
                    an unfair burden on a very conscientious man who was heavily involved in the war
                    effort. So I decided that the time had come to get a job. No sooner had I made
                    that decision when I got a call from Jessup inviting me to come to work for him
                    in the State Department in an office doing postwar planning. No sooner had I
                    filled out the State Department forms when I got a call from someone named
                    Burton Fahs who said, “Professor Peffer recommended you. I wonder if you would
                    be interested in working on Japan in the Office of Strategic Services. It then
                    turned out that State Department hiring had been frozen and Jessup encouraged me
                    to let OSS go ahead and clear me arguing that in the time that process would
                    take either State would open up again or, if not, I'd have an interesting job in
                    OSS. So, I went to see Fahs, confessed my total ignorance of Japan , was
                    interviewed by a number of people, a couple of whom I never saw again, and was
                    offered a job.</p>
                <p>I was told the clearance process would take three months which proved exactly
                    correct. I spent the time reading everything available on Japan at the Carnegie
                    Endowment library. To someone accustomed to doing research on the US and Europe,
                    it was pretty slim pickings. The books I remember as most useful were a study of
                    contemporary Japanese government and politics by Robert Reischauer (Edwin's
                    brother killed in 1937 in a Japanese air attack on Shanghai) and a history of
                    Japan's emergence as a modern state by the Canadian scholar, E. Herbert Norman.
                    Also useful were some books and articles by journalists covering recent events.
                    Two had memorable titles: Government by Assassination and Japan's Feet of Clay.
                    So, when I reported to work at OSS on December 13, 1945 I was at least better
                    informed. And, although I didn't know it, I was on the road to becoming an Asia
                    specialist at a time when Asia specialists were few and opportunities
                    correspondingly great. Had I been hired to suit my qualifications in the
                    European division, I would have been a gofer for a host of very eminent
                    scholarsome of them the top men in their fields. In the Far East division, I was
                    given interesting and challenging work from the start.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wasn't the OSS a predecessor of both CIA and the State
                        Department's INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, after the war. When I joined the Research and Analysis Branch (the
                    predecessor of INR), OSS was only about six months old. Earlier, it had been
                    part of an organization called the Coordinator of Information (COI) established
                    in July 1941 and, a year later, divided into OSS and the Office of War
                    Information. OSS came under the jurisdiction of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                    itself newly created.</p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did it feel to be working in an intelligence
                        organization at a time when this was something really new?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: When I joined there was still a pioneering atmosphere. This, together
                    with the unaccustomed secrecy in which we were supposed to be operating was
                    quite exhilarating. Research analysts in Washington were not involved in the
                    deeds of derring-do overseas for which OSS became famous. But we did hear about
                    some of them from the R&amp;A units stationed overseas. And, as secret servants,
                    we wore badges which we were supposed to conceal when we left the building.
                    Likewise, when we were asked, we were supposed to say only that we worked for
                    the US government. So that was very exciting. At the same time, it was not
                    wholly unlike the university most of us had only recently left behind. In terms
                    of age and experience we fell into three categories: students, junior faculty,
                    and senior faculty (fewer of the latter in the Far East division than in
                    others.) And those of us who had recently been graduate students, instead of
                    paying fees, were now being paid for doing much the same kind work we had been
                    doing at university.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where was your office located?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In an old eight-story apartment building on the corner of 23 and E
                    Street NW. It was known as War Annex I. It was crowded and uncomfortable. No
                    air-conditioning, of course, but if you were on the top floor, as we were most
                    of the time, it was hotter still because the roof was not well-insulated. In the
                    winter, because the windows did not fit well, it could be very cold indeed,
                    despite out efforts at weather-stripping. We did have an escape, a new,
                    air-conditioned annex of the Library of Congress where R&amp;A had a large
                    reading room. It was very popular in the summer time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did your office fit into the overall
                        organization?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The Research and Analysis Branch, with some administrative and
                    functional exceptions, was organized regionally. The Far East Division had three
                    subdivisionpolitical, economic, and geographic. The Japan section was one of
                    three sections in the political subdivision, the others being China and Southern
                    Areas which included both India and Southeast Asia. Some members of the staff
                    were genuine country specialists but many were, like myself, quite new to Asia,
                    others had Asia connections that came from residence as missionary, military, or
                    foreign service children.</p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>Our chiefs were all very young, mid or late thirties. Charles Burton Fahs, the
                    Division Chief, was one of a very small group of young American academics who
                    had specialized in Japanese language and history before the war. Cora DuBois,
                    chief of the Political Subdivision, an anthropologist, had done her doctoral
                    dissertation on the people of a small island in the Indonesian archipelago. When
                    she was assigned overseas she was replaced by C. Martin Wilber, a Columbia
                    University China specialist. Edward A. Kracke, chief of the Japan section had
                    only recently been transferred from work on China. He was a Sung dynasty
                    specialist. In December 1943, I became the second of two analysts working under
                    Ed Kracke. The other, Jane Alden, like me, had no real Asian background. But she
                    was more knowledgeable, having taken a couple of courses in modern Japanese
                    politics and government. She was also a relative old-timer having started out in
                    COI. For the first few months of my tenure, however, she was on leave in New
                    York waiting for her navy husband's ship to be commissioned. In the following
                    years our professional staff grew somewhat in size although not significantly in
                    expertise. Our staff also came to include several Nisei enlisted men who worked
                    at our Library of Congress annex. They were intended to provide us with a
                    translation capability but they were uneducated and unable to handle written
                    material of any complexity.</p>
                <p>Our numbers were also intermittently augmented by a variety of consultants. Two
                    of these were former missionaries and I do not remember that they made any
                    specific contributions to our work. Two others were political scientists with
                    more relevant expertise. One of these, Kenneth Colegrove of Northwestern
                    University, was not a Japan specialist but, in collaboration with a Japanese
                    American assistant, whose name I have forgotten, had produced a number of very
                    useful journal articles on Japanese government. The other, Chitoshi Yanaga of
                    Yale, came to us late in the war and was an invaluable guide. We were also able
                    to draw on the expertise of one of Margaret Mead's husbands, I forget which. He
                    would drop in from time to time and tell us about the impact of toilet training
                    on Japanese behavior.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved with Joseph Grew at all or was he too
                        exalted?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Much too exalted. The two young men who had served one after another as
                    his private secretary in Tokyo before Pearl HarboMarshall Green and Robert
                    Fearewere both in Washington. Marshall in the Navy and Bob in the State
                    Department. But I have no contact with either of them or with anyone working on
                    Japan in the State Department until after the war. Of the two academic Japan
                    specialists then in WashingtoHugh Borton in State and Ed Reischauer in the armI
                    knew only the latter. This was essentially a social relationship resulting from
                    a Reischauer-Kracke friendship dating from Harvard days and from my friendship
                    with Bob Reischauer's widow, Jean, an OSS colleague.</p>
                <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                <p>Also in Washington at the time were a number of missionary families who had been
                    repatriated from Japan after Pearl Harbor. I was assigned to interview them but,
                    although I found them interesting to talk to and I'm sure they contributed to my
                    understanding of Japan and the Japanese, the problems of government structure
                    and functioning that were so much part of my work were not ones on which they
                    could be of very much help.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you arrived at your job, were you given any
                        preliminary training or indoctrination?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: None on Japan. Some on OSS which I remember as not very illuminating and
                    sometimes rather baffling. For example, whenever I was summoned for a briefing,
                    I was almost always also shown a short film on the bombing of Wewak. It was only
                    years later that I discovered that Wewak was in New Guinea and I never did find
                    out why I was shown the film or what I was supposed to learn from it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You have said you were concerned with Japanese government
                        structure. Was this the major part of your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In its various aspects it certainly constituted a large part of it. I
                    had come on the job just as a program under the army's Civil Affairs Division
                    had gotten under way. In anticipation of the post-war occupation of Germany,
                    Italy, and Japan, it was intended to provide information on all aspects of
                    administration for which the occupying forces might become responsible. The job
                    of producing these civil affairs handbooks was assigned to various agencies
                    according to their competence. I wrote the ones on national government, local
                    government, and the police and judicial systems; sections dealing with the
                    economy were prepared in our economic subdivision. The handbooks were to be
                    followed by guidehow-to advice depending, in Japan's case, on three different
                    assumptions: surrender before an attack on the home islands; surrender after
                    invasion and brief hostilities; surrender after prolonged hostilities. I had
                    been embarked upon one of these having to do with local government when the war
                    ended, relieving me of a task I was sensible enough to realize was far beyond my
                    experience and capabilities.</p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>Another military sponsored program in which we were involved was the Joint Army
                    Navy Intelligence Survey, the JANIS. These studies were intended for the use of
                    forces invading enemy-occupied territories and were largely concerned with such
                    subjects as coasts and landing beaches. But they also had brief sections on
                    political and social characteristics. The two areas involved for which the Japan
                    section was responsible were Formosa and Korea for which we had no corresponding
                    expertise. I remember heavy reliance on the Encyclopedia Britannica and, for
                    Korea, lengthy conversations over the phone with George McClure, a Korea-born
                    specialist, who had left OSS for State, and his wife Evelyn, also Korea-born.
                    For Formosa, we relied on a classmate of Ed Kracke's at the Pentagon, who had
                    spent time there before the war and on a prewar series of dispatches from John
                    Emmerson, a Japanese language officer, presumable there in a consular
                    capacity.</p>
                <p>I was also able to participate in the other major part of our worthe effort to
                    keep up with and report on what was going on in Japan in contributions to our
                    division Situation Report, a weekly produced by each of R&amp;A's regional
                    divisions. We were also from time to time called upon to provide briefings
                    mostly for the military. I remember one in particular on Japanese air-raid
                    precautions. It was memorable only because when the colonel I briefed later
                    thanked my boss for sending me, having forgotten my name, he referred to me as
                    “that cute little girl with glasses”. Times have changed!</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you get much useful information from reports from the
                        field?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: If there was any clandestine reporting from Japan on political subjects,
                    I never knew of it. We did get classified summaries, rather like out Situation
                    Reports, produced by the British in India but, as I remember them, their
                    Japan-related material dealt with the occupied territories, not with Japan
                    itself. I remember only one example of American reporting from the field that
                    was useful in our work on Japan. This was a series of reports from John Emmerson
                    who, rather late in the war, joined the Dixie Mission in Yenathe U.S. team
                    assigned to Chinese Communist headquarters. Until John arrived, Dixie Mission
                    reporting had focused on China and local activities. As a Japanese speaker, John
                    was able to take advantage of the presence in Yenan of one Sanzo Nosaka, a major
                    prewar Japanese Communist Party leader, interviewing him at length on Communist
                    plans and objectives for post-war Japan, where, for a time, the party was to be
                    an important political force. For me, these reports were particularly valuable
                    because we had recently initiated a study of pre-war Japanese political parties
                    in anticipation of their post-war revival. With her academic background in
                    prewar Japanese politics, Jane Alden was assigned the two parties that had
                    dominated Japan's parliamentary period; the Socialists and Communists, of very
                    little importance in this period, fell to me.</p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>Translation of various kinds also came to us from the fielmostly soldiers'
                    diaries and POW interrogations. These were interesting for what they revealed of
                    Japanese attitudes and behavior, but they did not contribute to our work. We did
                    make some use of an annual official directory the Shokuin Roku that listed all
                    the elements of the government structure down to the lowest level, helping us
                    track the changes as the war progressed and make some guesses about their
                    significance. The edition held by government agencies in Washington was quite
                    out of date. When it was discovered that the Navy had concealed its acquisition
                    of a more recent one, it was quite a scandal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your major sources of information?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: For the most part, we were dependent on unclassified sources, sources
                    that have only now been dignified with an unlovely acronym of their own, OSINT,
                    open source intelligence. Most important for purposes of current analysis was
                    the Daily Report produced by the Foreign Broadcasting Information Service
                    (FBIS), an invaluable source then and thereafter. Providing daily translations
                    of government and other Japanese broadcasts, it was a principal tool in our
                    efforts to track political and related developments in Japan and to gain some
                    sense of the changing atmosphere as the war progressed.</p>
                <p>More dated but still useful were the Library of Congress files of prewar Japanese
                    English-language periodicals; the Japan Times in particular. I was also able to
                    find in the Library of Congress some specialized studies in English of Japanese
                    legal and administrative institutionone particularly useful one for Civil
                    Affairs handbook purposes was a study of Japanese law by a German scholar whose
                    name I have forgotten. Another was an account of the government of Tokyo by the
                    eminent American historian, Charles A. Beard, who had been commissioned by the
                    Japanese government to analyze proposals for its reorganization.</p>
                <p>In connection with the Civil Affairs program, it is ironical that while I was
                    struggling with these limited sources on subjects of which, even in the American
                    context, I had no real experience, R&amp;A had in its ranks someone who would
                    been able to do a really expert job. This was Thomas L. Blakemore, an American
                    law school graduate, who, before the war, had taken a law degree at Tokyo
                    Imperial University and had become proficient in the Japanese language. He,
                    however, was in China in the OSS unit dong target work for the 14th Air Force.
                    Although at the time, I chafed at the obstacles to enlisting his help in any
                    serious way, I have to admit in retrospect that what he was doing in China was
                    of much more consequence than what he might have done in the Civil Affairs
                    program had he been in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your work on Japan bringing any changes in your
                        attitudes toward the Japanese?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I don't really think so. I came to my job with what were pretty much the
                    standard attitudes developed during earlier Japanese aggression in ChinJapan was
                    a military dictatorship supported by an economic oligarchy, sustained by an
                    elaborate mythology revolving around the Emperor system, and reinforced by
                    severe police controls; and behaving with the utmost brutality to the people who
                    came under its rule. I did not, however, share in those stereotypes that painted
                    the Japanese as either less than human or especially mysterious in their
                    behavior or as incapable of more enlightened or democratic government. Nor did
                    anyone with whom I was associated.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At time went on, did you begin to see changes taking place
                        in Japan in reaction to the fact that the war was going against them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: We did look at changes in the government and Japanese propaganda for
                    clues as to how the government was responding, how it was coping. But I don't
                    think we developed any significant insights. Our confidence that we were now
                    winning the war, that the end might be coming nearer really came from the
                    actions on our side, not from anything we read into Japanese behavior. We were
                    certainly aware that in Washington the terms of Japanese surrender and in
                    postwar treatment were being discussed more intensively at higher policy levels,
                    for example in the State War Navy Coordinating Committee (SWNCC) which was
                    established at the end of 1944.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your office have any role in the SWNCC
                        discussions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Not any that affected activities at my level. It is possible that Hugh
                    Borton, who did have a role, may have engaged Burton Fahs, in such discussions.
                    The answer might be found in Borton's memoir which I have not read. But Borton
                    did gather some of us together for after-hours discussions of peace terms at
                    Jean Reischauer's conveniently located apartment. What I recall from these
                    discussions is the focus on the fate of the Emperor. This, of course, was being
                    rather widely debated at the time, some arguing that he should be treated as a
                    war criminal and the emperor system abolished, others that he was not a
                    principal decision-maker and that his retention would be important in promoting
                    peaceful acceptance of post-surrender allied occupation. Most of us supported
                    the latter course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any inklings of the atomic bomb?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>COLBERT: None whatever. But I do remember a question that was put to us toward
                    the end of the war that, in retrospect, it seems to me might have been connected
                    to the discussion of its use. We were not told who made the request or why. We
                    were merely told to respond briefly and quickly to the question of how the
                    Japanese would respond to an invasion. Would they surrender quickly or would
                    there be a prolonged and bitter resistance? Me recollection is that we opted for
                    the latter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this before or after we invaded Okinawa?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I don't remember but it seems likely that it was at least during or
                    after Iwo Jima.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We move on now to a new period. The war is over. The
                        wartime agencies are being terminated. What is happening to your part of
                        OSS?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In the months between Japan's surrender and October 1945, our future
                    seemed very uncertain. For some of us this was of no great conceracademics
                    returning to their universities, young women whose husbands were returning from
                    overseas, resuming their prewar lives. But some of us were prepared to remain if
                    this should prove possible. I was one. My husband had already moved to the
                    Washington headquarters of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation
                    Administration (UNRRA) so it was clear that we would be remaining in Washington.
                    At this time, I had no real commitment to a future in Asian affairs and my brush
                    with studying Japanese had convinced me that I would never have the language
                    capability for real scholarship. On the other hand, I enjoyed my work and my
                    colleagues so I was happy to stay on when R&amp;A was transferred to the State
                    Department in October. The other part of OSS became the nucleus of the Central
                    Intelligence Agency.</p>
                <p>It took some time for our place within the Department to become fixed. Initially,
                    under the influence of senior Department officers who had opposed the transfer,
                    R&amp;A was broken up and its regional divisions attached to their respective
                    policy offices. In January 1947 this decision was reversed and R&amp;A was
                    reunited first as the R area under a Special Assistant for Research and
                    Intelligence and then as the Office of Intelligence Research (OIR). At some
                    point thereafter, OIR became INR, its present title. My office became the
                    Division of Research for Far East (DRF) subdivided into three brancheChina,
                    Southeast Asia, and Northeast Asia. The latter consisted of a Korea section and,
                    on Japan, a political section where I worked and two economic sections, one
                    covering industry and trade, the other labor, finance, and agriculture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How was your job affected by the transition?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                <p>COLBERT: In this respect, we in DRF, especially those of us working on Japan,
                    were very fortunate. We were really not affected by the hostility many old-line
                    FSOs felt toward the inclusion of a large number of OSS outsiders. At that time,
                    the senior staff of what was then known as FE was far from exclusively foreign
                    service. This was especially the case with respect to Japan which, in fact, had
                    become at least the partial responsibility of the Office for Occupied Areas
                    under Major General John H. Hilldring as Assistant Secretary. The principal
                    officers on the political side in its Japan-Korea secretariat were Ed Reischauer
                    and Hugh Borton, both academics and old friends of Burton Fahs; the economic
                    side was run by Edwin M. Martin who had joined the civil service in the
                    mid-thirties and, in 1944, had come to our OSS office as chief of the economic
                    subdivision.</p>
                <p>Of our principal counterparts at the working level, Alice Dunning (later Hsieh)
                    and Robert Fearey were both civil servants at that time. Marshall Green, who was
                    to join them after a first foreign service assignment in New Zealand, was only
                    too happy to cooperate with anyone prepared to cooperate with him.</p>
                <p>Perhaps even more important, we were able to be of particular service to the
                    policy desk because of circumstances arising from the organization of the
                    occupation of Japan under General Douglas MacArthur, Supreme Commander of the
                    Allied Powers (SCAP). MacArthur was indeed supreme, operating under general
                    directives that had originated in Washington but acknowledging no responsibility
                    either to Washington or our allies in implementing them. The latter were
                    represented in Washington by the Far Eastern Commission which, although
                    officially a policy-making body in fact played no such role. The Commission's
                    members, the ambassadors of the eleven member countries, were nevertheless
                    intent on asserting their right to be informed. If only for diplomatic reasons,
                    it was important to comply with their demands for information and, to do so, was
                    State's responsibility. But our equivalent of an embassy in Tokyo was the Office
                    of the Political Adviser, merely a SCAP section with no reporting authority.</p>
                <p>In this regard, we in DRF were able to fill the gap thanks to a SCAP provided
                    service, the work of its Allied Translation and Interrogation Section (ATIS).
                    Everyday we received from ATIS a legal size volume of translations of Japanese
                    newspapers and other publications. SCAP censorship was devoted largely to
                    preventing any criticism of the U.S. and the Occupation or support for
                    militarism and the old regime. Otherwise the press was free to report on
                    developments in Japan and did so in detail. Exploiting this large mass of data,
                    we were able to follow on a timely basis Occupation activities, the new ferment
                    othe social and political scene, and the continuing problems of the Japanese
                    economy. For the Japan desk, our ability to put this material together and
                    provide it in written or oral form freed its officers from the demands on their
                    time and attention that mining for themselves this vast flow of data would have
                    entailed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk a little more bout the content of the work
                        of your office during this period?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Since, for some time, our FE counterparts were still in old State, we
                    were on the phone more than we might have been otherwise. This was particularly
                    the case with what might be called our number crunching responsibilities:
                    keeping track of the purge, the removal from office of those regarded as
                    responsible for Japanese aggression, and of the number of members of the armed
                    forces repatriated from overseas.</p>
                <p>Analytical papers, however, remained at the center of our work. Some of these
                    were prepared in response to requests, mostly from FE. Some were in response to
                    immediate needs with very short deadlines. One of these that I particularly
                    remember was stimulated by the publication in the New York Times early in the
                    occupation of the full text of the SCAP drafted constitution that was to replace
                    the Meiji constitution. This development, wholly unanticipated in Washington,
                    preceded by not very much time a scheduled meeting of the Far East Commission.
                    It could be anticipated that the members, irate at this disregard of their
                    prerogatives, would have many questions about the draft. Since I had already
                    prepared a rather detailed study of the Meiji constitution and had been
                    reporting on Japanese revision proposals, I was able to respond to FE's request
                    for a detailed analysis of the SCAP draft within the close deadline imposed by
                    the imminent FEC meeting.</p>
                <p>Other studies were less constrained by short deadlines. Among these was a series,
                    originally requested by Hugh Borton, that analyzed progress toward
                    democratization in various fieldeducation, the press, the police system, public
                    administration, and so forth. The pace of change as restrictions on political
                    activity were lifted also made us almost weekly contributors to the Situation
                    Report (of which I became division editor right after the war). Writing for the
                    Situation Report enabled us to be up to the minute since the papers published
                    there did not go through the sometimes slow process of OIR review.</p>
                <p>While the Situation Report by its nature encouraged brevity, even there and even
                    more in our other written output, we continued to reflect our academic origins.
                    We tended to write at length; our papers were footnoted; and, although summaries
                    were provided, format was not a consideration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you feel about the changes that were being imposed
                        on Japan?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I don't remember that any of us had any quarrel with the basic policy
                    and objectives. Where we were critical was with the way these policies were
                    being implemented; the way in which SCAP officials, with no previous exposure to
                    Japan, seemed to be transferring their experience as federal or state government
                    officials to the programs they were now implementing. On specifics, I saw the
                    decentralization of the police system as a futile exercise, unlikely to survive
                    the end of the occupation as indeed it did not. I was also dubious about the
                    emphasis on protecting the civil service from political influence along American
                    lines since my own studies, limited as they were, had convinced me that, far
                    from needing protection, the Japanese bureaucracy needed to have its power
                    curbed. I was concerned also that in an independent Japan there might be a
                    strong reaction against some of the provisions of a constitution imposed from
                    without, notably those concerning the Emperor and the renunciation of war.
                    Although the debate in the Diet's upper house during the ratification process
                    lent some support to this view, the passage of time has proved me wrong. It is
                    only now, more than half a century later, that the revision of Article IX has
                    become a real possibility while today's big issue concerning the Emperor relates
                    to female succession.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your analyses provoke any reaction from SCAP? Was
                        there any point at which you were criticized or told to stop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: No. The first point is that we were not in the business of criticizing
                    policy or policy-making. To the extent that our misgivings entered into our
                    product at all, they would have been reflected only very indirectly in our
                    discussions of Japanese reactions. Secondly, I'm not sure that anyone in SCAP's
                    higher levels was even aware of our existence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you able to get to Japan during the occupation
                        period?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In the early post-war days, the only way to get to Japan was to sign up
                    with the occupation for a full term — I think it was two years. Later, I don't
                    remember when, it became possible for DRF analysts to spend a month or so in
                    Japan in connection with some particular project. At least two analysts in the
                    Japan political section were able to take advantage of this opportunity, but I
                    was already the mother of a small child and accordingly in no position to do
                    so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Coming to the later yearby 1948, the Cold War was really
                        underwawhat with the Communist coup in Czechoslovakia and the Berlin
                        blockade. Did this bring about any change in your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Cold War compulsions certainly brought about a change in U.S. policy
                    toward Japan. This was the year of the so-called “changed course” when U.S.
                    emphasis on Japan's democratization was replaced by emphasis on its economic
                    recovery, hither to defined as outside American responsibility,. Earlier
                    policies aimed at purging “ultranationalists and militarists” and dissolving the
                    economic monopolies were softened. The trade union movement, which had become
                    increasingly Communist-influenced, militant, and strike-prone, became the target
                    of laws curbing its activities. Nerestrictions were imposed on the Communist
                    Party, a major beneficiary of occupation-endowed political liberties, which had
                    become significantly more radical in the wake of Cominform criticisms of its
                    earlier “lovable party tactics”. New efforts to conclude a peace treaty were
                    also encouraged by expectations that an independent Japan would become an
                    American ally.</p>
                <p>DRF's role remained unchanged: analyzing events as they occurred, examining new
                    trends, and, in general, responding to the requirements of our mostly State
                    Department customers as they expressed them or as we anticipated them. To be
                    sure, we had views about policy that entered into our conversations if not our
                    papers. I remember, for example, discussing with Marshall Green the pros and
                    cons of what seemed a likely SCAP decision to ban the Communist Party. I don't
                    remember whether he put our thoughts on paper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned the peace treaty. Was your office involved
                        in that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Sometime in 1947, steps toward convening a peace conference were
                    abandoned, it having become evident that U.S.-Soviet agreement over its
                    composition and treaty provisions was impossible. Nevertheless, a committee
                    chaired by Hugh Borton continued to discuss peace treaty provisions. My then
                    branch chief and I were both members and our office prepared a number of papers
                    dealing with peace treaty issues. I do not recall that this committee survived
                    Borton's return to Columbia in 1948 and the appointment of John Foster Dulles
                    assigned to negotiate a treaty through bilateral agreements with each of the
                    countries involved. My office played only one small part in that process,
                    memorable only to me. At some time when I was in the last stages of pregnancy
                    and on leave, Dulles asked for a briefing on the Japanese Communist Party and I
                    was called in to provide it. Feeling I had done a reasonably good job, I was
                    somewhat taken aback when, showing no indication of recognizing that I was
                    enormously pregnant and good wishes might be in order, Dulles offered no more
                    than the most perfunctory thanks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any relationship with George Kennan and the
                        Planning Staff?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>COLBERT: With Kennan only once when, just before he left the Department, he
                    called together all of us who were working on one aspect or another of the
                    Communist movement. Presumably he felt it important to convey some parting
                    thoughts. But, if so, I don't remember what they were. Our relations with
                    Planning Staff members concerned with East Asia were quite close and active. In
                    one joint paper that I particularly remember we tried to predict the situation
                    in Asia ten years hence. Exactly ten years later, Joseph Yager, then on the
                    Planning Staff, was given a similar task. I suggested that he take a look at our
                    earlier paper to see whether we had been right about anything and where we went
                    wrong. But the paper was nowhere to be found.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you asked during this period to take a long-term look
                        at where Japan itself might be going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT:Normally this would have been regarded as a regular part of our work. Our
                    China-watcher colleagues, for example, were called upon to participate in
                    long-range estimates, one at least looking ahead 35 years. I suppose that, as
                    long as we were occupying Japan, it might have seemed inappropriate to speculate
                    about the survival of SCAP reforms.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: During most of this period, McCarthy was riding high on
                        the Washington scene. How did this affect the atmosphere in which you
                        worked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I suspect the depression pervading the Department was felt most acutely
                    by those of us concerned with Asia. It was, after all, the China-watchers who
                    were principal targetJohn Service and John Davies among them. Some of our DRF
                    staff were subjected to intense interrogations and there were some resignations.
                    We were all constantly being interviewed by investigators who seemed both crude
                    and ignorant. I remember, in that age of innocence, being very much embarrassed
                    when I was asked whether I thought one of my colleagues was a normal male. I had
                    the wit to reply “you should ask his wife” but I'm sure I blushed. My own
                    distinctly minor problem resulted from the publication in 1952 by the Institute
                    of Pacific Relations of a declassified version of my INR study of left-wing
                    politics in Japan. Some time later with others in INR I was invited to an NSA
                    briefing. Just before the visit I was disinvited I was told because my book had
                    been published by a suspect organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was Korea part of your orbit?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                <p>COLBERT: No, it came under a separate section. I don't remember that it got very
                    much attention before the North Korean invasion. I do remember my last
                    conversation with George McCune before his death. He was deeply concerned about
                    the decision at the end of the war to cut Korea in two with U.S. forces taking
                    the Japanese surrender in the south and Soviet forces in the north. He feared
                    that this division would become permanent with disastrous consequences for the
                    Koreans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Korean War, does this change anything for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Only in providing the one occasion in this period when I was at all
                    involved in Korea. Responding to the Secretary's request for an INR estimate of
                    reactions worldwide to possible U.S. responses, I wrote the estimate on Japan
                    after branch-wide discussion. We concluded that Japan would be deeply disturbed
                    by the invasion and fearful of the future and that, if we failed to respond
                    vigorously, the Japanese would lose faith in our commitment to their defense and
                    move toward neutralism.</p>
                <p>That was my last involvement in issues having to do with the Korean War because,
                    several months later, I made a decision that was to govern my career for the
                    next ten years. I was very happy in my job. I liked and respected the people I
                    worked for and with. I had been promoted as rapidly as civil service procedures
                    permitted. My commitment to an East Asian focus had been strengthened and,
                    through my role as Situation Report editor, I had become more familiar with
                    China and Southeast Asia. But, I was expecting a second child, and,
                    fortuitously, one of my colleagues in a similar situation had discovered that it
                    was possible to work in the Department on a part-time basis. Equally
                    fortuitously, there was a relatively new position opethat of Coordinator of the
                    DRF contribution to the National Intelligence Survewhich no one in DRF of the
                    appropriate grade wanted and which it seemed to me could be adequately handled
                    on a part-time basis. So the deal was I'll take the NIS job but only if I can
                    work part-time.</p>
                <p>In the interval between this agreement and my departure on maternity leave, I
                    found myself acting chief of the China branch for three months. A series of
                    rather rapid personnel changes had created this vacancy and, although someone
                    had been chosen to fill it, his transfer from the Pentagon was moving very
                    slowly. My responsibilities involved me for the most part in making sure that
                    things kept moving, that papers got produced, and that they were literate and
                    sensible. But I did get involved for the first time in the estimative process.
                    The question to be addressed was one that is still with uwill the PRC invade
                    Taiwan? Our relatively new division chief, Sabin Chase, who had briefly headed
                    the China branch, was a true China expert. But he was very diffident and without
                    intelligence experience. So he asked me to come along. What we concluded I do
                    not remember, although I daresay the answer was hedged with all the customary
                    qualifications. What I do remember even now is that the discussion was
                    interrupted for some time by a heated debate between the navy and air force
                    representatives over whether it was possible to sink a junk from the air.</p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lets move on to September 1951 when you came back from
                        maternity leave as DRFs NIS coordinator. Perhaps you could start by
                        describing the program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The program was well-intentioned but unrealistic. It aimed to provide
                    the government for its guidance in peace and war with a set of encyclopedias,
                    one for every country in the world including the most insignificant. The program
                    was organized, funded, and supervised by CIA. Each country study contained nine
                    chapters, each covering one or another significant activity. The chapters, in
                    turn, were divided into sectionthe basic unit of productiosometimes as many as
                    ten. INR was responsible for the economic, political, and sociological chapters
                    and for a biographic appendix. A very detailed standard outline was provided for
                    each section to be adhered to religiously. Each INR division had an annual quota
                    of sections to be produced. CIA's budgetary support was based on calculations
                    about the time and manpower, professional and secretarial, required to fill the
                    quota.</p>
                <p>The requirement to follow a one size fits all outline was one source of analyst
                    frustration. An even greater one was the labyrinthine three-level review
                    process. Division review was intended to apply the coordinator's presumed
                    expertise to substance, analytic quality, and the like; copy editing was
                    provided by a division editor. Having survived this exercise, which frequently
                    entailed a good deal of revision and additional work, the analyst was then
                    subjected to two more reviews, first by INR's NIS staff and then by the CIS's
                    NIS office. Although first priority in these reviews was ensuring fidelity to
                    the outline and house rules governing capitalization etc., the reviewers felt
                    free also to deal with substance, however limited their expertise. At both
                    levels, but particularly at CIA, the reviewers, secure in not very onerous jobs
                    no one else wanted, tended to be of rather mediocre quality and often difficult
                    to deal with. The retired colonel who headed the CIA office epitomized the level
                    of competence; he had graduated last in his class at West Point. The senior CIA
                    reviewer barred any use of the word organ because of its sexual connotations.
                    Analyst frustration with this process, a frustration I shared as the author of a
                    number of NIS sections myself, was compounded for many by the remoteness of the
                    program from what they saw as INR's real and much more exciting mission in
                    support of State's policy-making responsibilities.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the program had its compensations for both analysts and the office.
                    DRF, like the rest of INR, milked the program shamelessly. Among the thirty or
                    so analysts being paid by CIA, the best were constantly diverted from NIS work
                    to participate in the regular program. Because of the INR-wide practice, State
                    came remotely close to meeting its annual quota only by a major production drive
                    in the last quarter of the fiscal year. Both the analysts and the office as a
                    whole gained from the accrual of expertise that resulted from delving deeper
                    into history, politics, economics, and society. Travel money was generoustudy
                    trips for as long as three months could not possibly have been financed from
                    INR's own budget.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>Fro me, being able to work part-time was the major compensation. I started at
                    about eighteen hours a week, increasing over time to about twenty fur. The
                    experience made me a strong advocate of part-time work as a solution to the
                    problems entailed in combining family satisfactions with professional ones. And
                    there were professional compensations also. Ten years of reviewing, revising and
                    writing NIS sections added immeasurably to my education, particularly on
                    Southeast Asia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say that the NIS analysts were frequently diverted to
                        DRF's other work. Was this the case with you also or were your hours too
                        limited?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Being part-time certainly limited the number of hours I could devote to
                    non-NIS work. But the lulls in production did give me time to do other things.
                    As had been the case earlier, I was called on from time to time to put together
                    papers involving some East Asia wide issue or development. One such project gave
                    me the welcome opportunity to spend a number of days in Paris. This stemmed from
                    a NATO decision in the early sixties to provide its ministerial meetings with
                    so-called Experts Papers on regions outside NATO's jurisdiction but important to
                    its members. NATO countries were free to submit their own drafts for
                    consideration by representatives charged with producing an agreed text at their
                    discussions in Paris. At least in my day, the U.S. paper normally became the one
                    around which discussions were conducted. DRF was responsible for preparing the
                    U.S. draft, but attendance at the meeting tended to be alternated between FE and
                    DRF. Indochina was almost always the most difficult subject on which to get
                    agreement. When I attended the second meeting, U.S. charges that North
                    Vietnamese troops were operating in Laos was the most contentious issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Working on the NIS for so long, did you get any evidence,
                        then or later, that it was being used?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The only use I ever heard about was by FSOs en route to countries they
                    knew nothing about. And the only comment I can remember from a reader was from
                    someone going to Laos who pointed out that a flag, shown flying over a building
                    identified as a Lao government office was, in fact, the flag of Cambodia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before leaving this period, what impact did the
                        Wristonization program of the mid-fifties have on your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Fortunately, it was a gradual process. We did not have a sudden mass
                    departure of civil servants opting to become FSOs or resigning. Nor did we have
                    a mass influx of FSOs. Over time, however, the process was transforming. Since
                    the end of the war, DRF had been predominantly staffed by long-timers, many with
                    their roots in OSS. As the result of Wristonization, the personnel mix began to
                    change. Many of the long-timers, including a goodly number of star performers,
                    opted for the foreign service. Others, both competent and ambitious, expecting
                    to become second-class citizens in a foreign services dominated organization,
                    moved to other agencies. This was especially the case among our economists.
                    Married women with children were least affected, facing no obstacles to
                    remaining.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You now move to another period beginning in the middle of
                        1961?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes. I moved to the Office of United Nations Political Affairs (UNP) in
                    the Bureau of International Affairs (IO). This resulted from changes that
                    affected both my job and INR as a whole. Roger Hilsman, who had come in with the
                    Kennedy administration as Director of INR, had been instructed by Secretary of
                    State Dean Rusk to give the NIS program back to CIA. Rusk regarded the program
                    not only as irrelevant to the State Department but also as an obstacle to INR's
                    proper function of policy-oriented research. Ending the NIS program meant that
                    INR lost a very large number of positions. Many of the analysts in these
                    positions moved with the program to CIA. Others found jobs elsewhere. But this
                    process moved very slowly and a reduction in force loomed on the horizon. In
                    these circumstances, I was advised to come back to work full-time since my long
                    tenure would protect me in the event of a RIF. This seemed sensible advice. My
                    children were now very involved with school and after school activities and I
                    had a full-time housekeeper who loved the children who in turn loved her. But I
                    would also be full-time in a now disappearing job and, while I could be
                    reasonably confident that a job would be found for me, did I want to stay in
                    INR? After all, it was the opportunity to work part-time that had kept me in INR
                    in a rather frustrating job for so many years. And INR was now in a rather
                    chaotic state.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're talking about 1960-61?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, the beginning of the Kennedy administration. Hilsman, I think, was
                    unaware that INR had been doing policy-oriented research before he came and
                    seemed to have in mind a major reorientation without, as yet, having any
                    coherent plans for bringing this about. And my own office was also under rather
                    uncertain direction. All in all, the reasons for leaving seemed a good deal
                    better than those for staying. So I began to look around and, in due course, was
                    offered a job by Joseph Sisco who had just become Director of UNP. I knew Joe. I
                    liked him and respected him and I knew that, under his direction, UNP would be
                    active and influential. Joe was also willing to accept two conditions. One was
                    that I was not to be put in charge of what we used to call Chirep, the annual
                    effort at the General Assembly to keep Taiwan in the Untied Nations and China
                    out. This was a policy with which many of us had no particular sympathy. We
                    regarded it as having an unfortunate impact on our relations with some of our
                    allies and as doomed to eventual failure. The other condition was that my
                    responsibilities as far as possible would be limited to areas where I would be
                    unlikely to have to put in a lot of overtime, especially unanticipated overtime.
                    This was a condition for which Joe had real empathy since his wife had an
                    executive job at Woodward and Lothrops and she too was limited in what she was
                    prepared to do by the fact that the Sisco's had two children somewhat but not
                    much younger than mine.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Within these restrictions, what were your principal
                        functions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>COLBERT: My principal responsibilities were for our activities and policies in
                    two international organizations dealing with nuclear activities and issues. The
                    more important of these, although less important than it is today, was the
                    International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). The other, less known, was the United
                    Nations Subcommittee to study the effects of Atomic Radiation (UNSCEAR). Our
                    membership in the IAEA generated a good deal of activity, most of it fairly
                    routine. When I came on the scene the selection of the Director General was
                    underway and this, of course, involved seeking the support of member governments
                    for the candidate favored by the United States. The Agency's annual meeting and
                    the meetings every quarter of its Board of Governors generated the customary
                    requirements for position papers many of which required consultations with
                    colleagues in the Atomic Energy Commission and the Weather Bureau, the latter
                    involved because the big issue of that time was not proliferation but
                    atmospheric testing. The position paper process was enlivened by the presence in
                    Washington of our ambassador to the IAEA, Harry Smythe. An eminent physicist,
                    Smythe had been one of those involved in making the bomb and had written, I
                    believe, the first unclassified history of the Manhattan Project, the Smythe
                    Report. Although ambassadors to the IAEA were normally resident in Vienna,
                    Smythe lived in Princeton, where he was on the university faculty, coming to
                    Washington for consultations before going to Vienna for the IAEA meetings.
                    Smythe was not unconscious of his own importance, but he had a good sense of
                    humor and was clearly amused by my own role as a completely inexpert young
                    woman. I remember his saying on one occasion, “Ah, I know how it will be. I will
                    get to Vienna. I will have a brilliant idea about what we should do. I will send
                    a telegram to the Department. And the response will be that the Department
                    considers that this is a very good idea to think about but it would be somewhat
                    premature to raise it at this time. And who would the Department be? Why, Evelyn
                    Colbert.”</p>
                <p>UNSCEAR normally required very little attention. Wholly non-political, its annual
                    meetings were devoted entirely to technical issues discussed by highly-qualified
                    scientists. However, in 1963 Canada's Minister of External Affairs had become
                    intent on making a proposal that would have involved UNSCEAR politically, an
                    outcome the U.S. opposed. Since until this time, UNSCEAR activities had been
                    largely unnoticed, a good deal of explaining of its role and functions was
                    necessary before a decision was reached on how to deal with the problem, which
                    in the end was disposed of by the skillful diplomacy of our representative, Dr.
                    Shields Warren, a physician of great eminence in the nuclear world.</p>
                <p>I was also responsible for arranging the meetings of IO's advisory panel of
                    nuclear scientists. This was largely a housekeeping matter. Taking the minutes,
                    however, was something of a problem as I was not always sure what the experts
                    were talking about. I do remember great preoccupation with when widespread
                    commercial resort to nuclear power would become economically feasible. Nor do I
                    remember, in this connection, any concern with waste disposal or, for that
                    matter, with proliferation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved at all in Asian issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I was not involved in either of the two major Asian issues in which UNP
                    played a part. On Chirep, Sisco largely honored his commitment. The other issue
                    was the disposition of West Irian contested between the Netherlands and
                    Indonesia. Disturbed by the possibility of armed encounters and hopeful that
                    satisfying Indonesia would cause President Sukarno to become more friendly to
                    the United States and the West, the Kennedy administration persuaded the parties
                    to join in negotiations under the auspices of Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker. These
                    negotiations were underway when I arrived and were already staffed by two
                    Department officers, one from UNP and one from EA. So, on this issue, I was
                    merely an interested audience for whatever reports our representative was able
                    to provide.</p>
                <p>When I arrived in UNP, IO's role in another high-visibility developmenthe Geneva
                    Conference on Laowas merely that of an interested spectator, but a spectator
                    hoping to become involved. Accordingly, as UNP's resident Asian, I was expected
                    to keep abreast of developments in Laos and at the conference and to provide
                    Harlan Cleveland, I'O's Assistant Secretary, with briefings from time to time.
                    Cleveland had already made one attempt to involve the UN, and hence himself, in
                    the conference, but his bid had been rejected by Governor Averill Harriman,
                    leader of the U.S. delegation. I was now charged to develop a new proposal, one
                    that would provide for UN involvement in post-conference relief and
                    rehabilitation. Even though I had little faith that the effort would succeed, I
                    found the exercise an interesting one, giving me an excuse to learn more about
                    the Lao economy and its almost non-existent infrastructure. But I do not recall
                    that the proposal I drafted with EA's help ever went anywhere. The conference
                    ended and among the many parties involved in Laos thereafter the UN was not
                    one.</p>
                <p>I was also concerned with Korea as an item appearing annually on the General
                    Assembly [GA] agenda, South Korea having been defended under UN auspices and the
                    juridical status of the two Koreas remaining unsettled. However, the Cold War
                    atmosphere made it inevitable that any discussion in the GA would produce no
                    more than heated debate. It had therefore become the U.S. objective to ensure
                    that the question of Korea would “fall off the agenda”. Most of the work
                    involved was performed by our mission in New York (USUN) in their daily contacts
                    with other delegates. But UNP was responsible for getting out circular telegrams
                    coordinated with EA seeking support for our tactics. It was a pretty routine job
                    and only briefly time-consuming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You seem to have liked your job? What made you decide to
                        go back to INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Its true, I was enjoying my job very much indeed. I was learning new
                    procedures. I was involved in interesting new subjects and with new people. And,
                    in some ways, it was less strenuous than working in INR: more talking, less
                    writing; a more hectic pace, but less concentration and more variety.
                    Nevertheless, I had two compelling reasons for leaving, one personal, the other
                    having to do with changes in INR.On the personal side, although my children wee
                    becoming teen-agers and very busy with their own activities, it was still
                    important to me to have a reasonably predictable schedule, to be home before the
                    dinner hour and on weekends. And even though, if I was intermittently involved
                    in suddenly hot subjects, it was only briefly, the way in which we functioned
                    often, frequently unpredictable, made it impossible to count on leaving the
                    office at the end of the regular working day. Since our “embassy”, USUN, was in
                    New York, much of our business with our counterparts there was conducted over
                    the telephone. They in turn usually spent a good deal of the working day
                    carrying on their business at UN headquarters, not returning to their offices
                    until late in the day. So they were rarely available to talk business with
                    Washington colleagues until at least 5 pm, frequently later, by which time they
                    were likely to have more than one call to deal with.</p>
                <p>Cleveland's working habits also often made it difficult to predict when one was
                    going to be able to leave the office. Cleveland was not only a very ambitious
                    man, he also found it very difficult to delegate. His deputies rarely signed off
                    on our outgoing messages. He did. And when he was signing off toward the end of
                    the day, he naturally turned first to the messages that he regarded as most
                    important, as of great interest to him and on which he was going to spend
                    perhaps quite a bit of time. Those of us responsible for less important matters
                    would frequently face long periods in the outer office awaiting our turn. So the
                    job, much as I enjoyed it, was really not wholly consistent with my
                    responsibilities as a wife and mother.</p>
                <p>At a point when I was feeling these misgivings particularly strongly, I was
                    invited to return to my old INR office by its new chief, Allen Whiting, a China
                    specialist from RAND. I had not met Whiting; he had been given my name by Robert
                    Barnett, then a deputy assistant secretary in EA. But I knew of his excellent
                    academic reputation and his ground-breaking study of China's role in the Korean
                    War. China Crosses the Yalu. And those who knew him agreed that he was very
                    energetic, very policy-oriented, very ambitious which, in my eyes, made him a
                    good man to work for. INR as a whole looked a lot better to me. It had settled
                    down; its basic analytical strength had survived the loss of NIS money and
                    positions; continuing to do policy-oriented research did not, after all, require
                    some drastic rethinking of INR's mission and structure; and its position in the
                    Department and the Intelligence Community was bolstered by Hilsman's relations
                    with President Kennedy who was known to read INR's papers.</p>
                <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                <p>The advantages seemed decisive and in September 1962 I returned to INR as chief
                    of REA's Southeast Asia Division. I remained in INR for twelve years becoming
                    REA's deputy director in 1968. From February 1972 until May 1973, I was on leave
                    as a Federal Executive Fellow at the Brookings Institution. I should perhaps
                    mention here a change in INR's status. Sometime in the fifties INR became a
                    bureau headed by a Director. Its former divisions became offices and their
                    branches divisions. DRF became RFE and then REA as the term Far East went out of
                    use Department-wide.</p>
                <p>Allen had offered me a choicNortheast Asia or Southeast Asia. Simply in terms of
                    my experience, it seemed an even choice. I had developed an earlier
                    specialization in Japan. But I now had acquired quite a bit of background on
                    Southeast Asia through my work on the Situation Report and even more on the NIS.
                    From the point of view of an intelligence analyst, however, the advantage seemed
                    to lie with Southeast Asia. Japan was under very stable conservative control.
                    The alliance was in good shape. The country was doing well economically.
                    Southeast Asia was the opposite. Practically every country in the region faced a
                    Communist or ethnic insurgency or both. Governments were unstable, coups or coup
                    attempts common. And we were already well on the road to very deep involvement
                    in Indochina.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were in INR for twelve yearan unusually long tour in
                        State Department terms. You must have seen a lot of changes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: A great many. During this period, INR had four directors, all of them
                    from outside State. Roger Hilsman left in March 1963 and was succeeded by Thomas
                    Hughes, his former deputy who had come to INR in1961 from the staff of the
                    Senate Foreign Relations Committee. In 1968, when the administration changed,
                    Hughes was replaced by Ray Cline and he in turn by William Hyland, both from
                    CIA. In the same period, we had four office directors. Allen Whiting was
                    followed by another academic, Fred Greene, a political scientist from Williams
                    College who, until then, had served the office as a consultant continuing to do
                    so after he returned to Williams. Four foreign service officers followed: John
                    Holdridge, William Gleysteen, and Paul Popple, all China oriented, and William
                    Hamilton, primarily Southeast Asia. I became deputy director in 1968, replacing
                    John Holdridge in that job.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>It is hard to say at this distance in time how much difference these changes made
                    beyond requiring the usual adjustments to new people with differing backgrounds,
                    temperaments, and working habits. At the Bureau level, Tom Hughes long-tenure
                    was a source of order while his searching intellect disciplined our minds. In
                    addition his tenure on the Senate Foreign Relations committee had given him, and
                    through him INR, access to the ranks of the powerful outside the Department. Ray
                    Cline, I think, was less well-received in the Department, being regarded, justly
                    or otherwise, as too much of an advocate for CIA-proposed covert activities
                    abroad. Under Cline's auspices, the bureau levepreviously quite leabecame
                    distinctly top-heavy, multiplying bureaucratic procedures and, worse still,
                    reducing the number of parking permits available for the hoi polloi. I left INR
                    too soon after Hyland's arrival to know what impact he had. But the fact that he
                    was Kissinger's prot�g� must have had some effect on his relations within the
                    Department. At the office level, each of our directors brought strength of his
                    own to our work. We benefited in particular from Averill Harriman's reliance on
                    Allen's briefings on Vietnam carried over from when the Governor had been
                    assistant secretary for East Asia. Fred had unusually good contracts at the
                    Pentagon, especially useful in our work on Vietnam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you retuned to INR, did you find that Secretary
                        Rusk's injunction that the bureau become more integrated into the Department
                        had in fact been carried out?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In this respect, it's very hard for me to compare INR as I left it with
                    the INR to which I returned. My NIS job, although permitting me to do some
                    non-NIS work from time to time, left me bureaucratically outside the main
                    stream, largely unaware of how INR was functioning inside the Department, what
                    its relations were with the policy bureaus, the Departments principals, and so
                    on. So I can only talk about what I found when I returned and experienced
                    thereafter. On this basis, I can answer your question in the affirmative. But
                    how much, if at all, this differed from the INR I had left two years earlier, I
                    really can't say.</p>
                <p>Looking back, it seems to me that INR's briefing system was an important factor
                    in integrating INR into the Department. At the top, INR's director, having
                    himself been briefed earlier by analysts from the various offices, regularly
                    briefed the Secretary and the other principals. Office directors briefed
                    regional bureau assistant secretaries, usually daily, and attended their staff
                    meetings; deputy office directors briefed deputy assistant secretaries. Division
                    chiefs participated in the staff meetings of their counterpart country
                    directorates. Beyond these regularly scheduled responsibilities, we were also
                    called upon on occasion to provide one-time briefings, for example, for
                    newly-appointed ambassadors en route to post. A crisis of some kind might
                    require us to provide daily briefings over a period of time.</p>
                <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                <p>One such series was particularly memorable. It took place during the so-called
                    incursion into Laos in 1971 when South Vietnamese troops, supported by U.S. air,
                    invaded Laos seeking to cut off North Vietnamese access to their principal
                    supply route into the south, the Ho Chi Minh trail. The incursion was an
                    operation of major importance. If successful it would be a heavy loss for the
                    Communists. With Vietnamization already underway, it was also a test of the
                    ability of South Vietnamese troops to operate without U.S. support on the
                    ground. Because of the importance the Secretary and the seventh floor principals
                    were to be briefed daily with Bill Gleysteen and I alternating as briefers.
                    Unlike CIA and the military we were entirely lacking in impressive visual aids.
                    But we did have a talented analyst who was able to decorate a large white board
                    map with pictorial explosions showing the location of the day's military
                    encounters. Our major problem was Secretary Rogers himself, nothing in his
                    background as a very successful lawyer having prepared him to deal with the
                    peculiarities of the Ho Chi Minh trail. The fact that he was also being briefed
                    by the military compounded the problem. In the morning, his military briefer
                    would tell him how successfully the operations of the day before had cut the
                    road. At noon we would tell him that there was no road only a web of trails and
                    when one strand of the web was cut the supplies would simply move down another.
                    At one point we thought we had the problem solved, importing a briefer from
                    another part of the community who brought with him a table size three
                    dimensional model of the border between Laos and Vietnam and the mountainous
                    terrain through which the supplies moved. He did an excellent job winding up in
                    customary military style, “This ends the briefing sir. Do you have any
                    questions?” To which the Secretary replied “Which way did you say Vietnam
                    was?”</p>
                <p>But back to our integration in the Department, there were other factors that
                    contributed. Among them was Wristonization. Another, harder to define, which
                    perhaps I over-rate, involved overcoming some of our OSS-inherited habits. Well
                    before I returned to INR, the problems Wristonization had initially createthe
                    loss of experienced personnel who joined the foreign service or left the
                    Department, the resistance to INR assignments of ambitious FSOhad been pretty
                    much overcome. Desk officers and INR analysts, having frequently served together
                    elsewhere, could more easily see one another as colleagues than was always the
                    case when there was a foreign service / civil service, Washington / overseas
                    divide. On Indochina, in particular, the experience and insights of officers
                    coming to us from the field made a very valuable contribution to our work. As to
                    our OSS-inherited habits, what I am talking about is the influence on our
                    product of the fact that in OSS our senior people tended to be academics and
                    many of the rest of us recent graduate school products. Brevity was not really
                    one of our values. Lengthy and detailed accounts evinced gravity of thought and
                    depth of research. Footnotes were a matter of course. It took a while to alter
                    institutional values, to rank brevity high, to accept that devising eye catching
                    forms of presentation was not to succumb to the forces of mindlessness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about relations with the rest of the Intelligence
                        Community? Was this important to your work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                <p>COLBERT: In a sense it was part of our work since the frequent requirements for
                    National Intelligence Estimates (NIEs) brought us all together and the product
                    both reflected consensus where it existed and defined differences where it did
                    not. But, for day to day purposes our principal relations were with CIA. CIA was
                    responsible not only for producing the now famous President's Daily Brief (PDB)
                    in which we had no part but also a version (containing many of the same items)
                    for lesser mortals with appropriate security clearances. Items published in this
                    version required INR clearance and, since developments in Southeast Asia were of
                    high consumer interest, REA Southeast Asian analysts and CIA analysts were
                    frequently in almost daily communication over the secure phone. There was in
                    addition a good deal of information exchange. CIA with its very large staff was
                    able to follow subjects at a level of detail far beyond our reach while we were
                    more likely to be aware of what was going on at the policy level. And we could
                    also look to CIA number-crunchers for data on subjects requiring their
                    particular skillfor example the number of infiltrators from North Vietnam into
                    the South. Outside the estimative process or other interagency projects,
                    contacts with DIA analysts were minimal. This was even more the case with NSA.
                    We received their materials but a separate INR office was responsible for any
                    necessary dealings with the Agency.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you go back to the NIEs? How they were prepared and
                        what part you played in their production?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: This is a subject I'd like to talk about in even more detail than you
                    might think is necessary. This is because both in the press and in CIA's
                    unclassified histories of its various activities, the impression is given that
                    NIEs are a CIA product. And, having worked very hard in this vineyard for more
                    that a few years, I find that annoying.</p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>To begin at the beginning, or rather at the end, NIEs were issued by the Director
                    of Central Intelligence after they had been approved by the United States
                    Intelligence Board (USIB) composed of the heads of all the intelligence agencies
                    (including Army, Navy, and Air Force) each of whom was entitled to take a
                    footnote to any statement with which he disagreed. An Estimate might be
                    initiated by CIA's Office of National Estimates (ONE) or requested by the
                    Secretary of State or Defense or other high official. Such a request then put in
                    train a rather elaborate process. ONE's staff, composed of senior analysts would
                    first prepare a draft. After the draft was reviewed by ONE's board and perhaps
                    elsewhere in CIA, it was circulated for comment and consideration to the other
                    members of the community. We in REA took this task very seriously considering
                    not only content but also organization and wording. Our proposed changes, more
                    often than not quite extensive, were usually incorporated in new line-in, line
                    out drafts. These, if possible, were circulated in advance of the meetings of
                    representatives of all of the intelligence agencies, or they were brought to the
                    meeting by the INR representatives. These so-called reps meetings usually went
                    on for several days and were quite large. Each agency decided for itself the
                    number of representatives. We usually had two, rarely more. CIA representatives
                    were more numerouthe ONE drafters of course but also analysts from the
                    Intelligence Directorate and others, not identified but easily recognized from
                    the Operations Directorate. The meetings were chaired by a member of the board
                    who were, without exception, outstanding intellects and formidable in the chair.
                    Chief among them was Sherman Kent, mentor of us all.</p>
                <p>Reps meetings were long and frequently contentious. The draft was reviewed
                    sentence by sentence and revised as we went along. It was advantageous to be
                    able to rewrite on your feet and we and CIA were better at this than DIA. In
                    this process we often departed quite radically from the original draft. Where
                    one agency's representative disagreed with what was otherwise the consensus, he
                    would take a footnote but did not need at this point, to provide a text.</p>
                <p>The draft produced after these frequently long debates would then be circulated
                    for clearance. How this worked in the other agencies I don't know. In State, the
                    process was simple. Copies were circulated to the Desk or Desks involved but
                    their comments were in no way binding. Briefing the Director for the USIB
                    meeting on the draft was the key task that, at least in Tom Hughes day,
                    subjected us to a very strenuous cross-examination. He would need to know what
                    problems other agencies had; who was taking footnotes and why. And, under
                    cross-examination, it would often dawn on us that what we were explaining was
                    not the meaning of a sentence but how a compromise was worked out among
                    differing proposals to get a sentence everyone could accept. The resulthe fuzzy
                    language for which Estimates are often criticized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you in touch at all with foreign embassies?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>COLBERT: In terms of exchange of information, our contacts were pretty much
                    limited to the embassies of Australia, New Zealand, and the United Kingdom with
                    which the U.S. had intelligence exchange agreements. Our contacts with
                    Australians were mostly with members of their intelligence service. Those with
                    New Zealanders, in contrast, were with regular members of their foreign service
                    assigned to the embassy to perform the intelligence liaison as well as other
                    functions. This was a much sought-after job awarded to the best and brightest.
                    All of those who served in my time became ambassadors. We saw a good deal of
                    them and became good friends. In 1980, when I retired, all of them sent
                    telegrams and it was only then that I learned they had become known as Evelyn's
                    boys.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Lets go back to September 1962 when you became chief of
                        the Southeast Asia Division. What were things like for you as division
                        chief?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The first thing to say is that the Southeast Asia Division was then very
                    small although it got bigger later. South Vietnam and Laos had one analyst each,
                    the other countries doubled up, and one analyst covered all the economics of the
                    region. The one analyst on North Vietnam belonged to the China Division, a
                    heritage from a brief period when all the Communist countries were grouped on
                    one INR office. But this posed no problem as we worked closely together. The
                    analysts were roughly half foreign service, half civil service.</p>
                <p>As you can imagine, we were spread pretty thin to cover a great many developments
                    in which U.S. interests were involved all taking place within the same short
                    period. The neutralization of Laos, established at Geneva in July 1962, had
                    begun to disintegrate almost immediately thereafter. The survival of Malaysia,
                    amalgamating Malaya, Singapore, Sabah, and Sarawak, was being threatened by
                    Sukarno's militant opposition, Philippine territorial claims, and friction
                    between Kuala Lumpur and Singapore. In South Vietnam earlier signs of progress
                    in 1962 were fading in the wake of the 1963 Buddhist crisis and the
                    assassination of Ngo Dinh Diem. Cambodia under Prince Sihanouk was constantly at
                    odds with our Thai and South Vietnamese allies, vociferously critical of the
                    U.S., and seemingly moving ever closer to the PRC.</p>
                <p>All of these developments we needed to follow closely, analyze, and write about.
                    In discussing our work, I'd like to begin with Indonesia for two reasons. First,
                    because, as a major preoccupation, Indonesia came and went, whereas Indochina
                    remained one long after my time. And second, because in the period preceding the
                    October 1965 coup attempt our policy was being increasingly questioned within
                    U.S. government ranks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Why was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>COLBERT: The Kennedy administration, attributing much greater importance to
                    Indonesia than had its predecessor, had based its policy on getting along with
                    Sukarno as the only way in which we could hope to influence Indonesia's policy.
                    Thus, in the West Irian dispute, the U.S., in effect, supported Indonesia
                    against the Dutch, hoping that once Indonesia's nationalist aspirations were
                    satisfied Sukarno would abandon his destabilizing policies and, with the added
                    incentive of U.S. aid, turn toward the West. Instead, the reverse proved to be
                    the case. Sukarno's attacks on the United States and western imperialism became
                    even stronger. “To hell with your aid,” he told us and, beyond words, were
                    government-inspired riots and attacks on U.S. facilities. Internally, more and
                    more he was favoring the Indonesian Communist Party, the PKI, at the expense of
                    the other parties and the military. Externally he was moving closer to the
                    Communist powers, proclaiming Indonesia a member of what he called the
                    Jakarta-Beijing-Hanoi-Pyongyang axis. And he was receiving military assistance
                    from the USSR including a much publicized battleship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was a cruiser, the Smirnoff class, very old and
                        decaying?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Right, and also unsuitable for tropical waters. In this atmosphere,
                    understandably a good deal of our work, including our participation in the
                    estimative process, was focused on Communist advances, not only the successes of
                    the PKI itself but also on its domestic alliances especially with elements of
                    the military. Concerns about the direction of Indonesian-Soviet relations were
                    heightened by a RAND analyst's report that Sukarno had agreed to the
                    establishment of a Soviet missile base on Indonesian soil. Coming in the wake of
                    the Cuban missile crisis from a long-time and very persuasive Indonesia-watcher
                    known for his close relations with a number of Indonesian generals, the report
                    attracted a good deal of apprehensive attention and became the subject of an
                    NIE. Without dissent, the Estimate found little or no prospect that Sukarno
                    would take a step, among other negative factors, so antithetical to Indonesian
                    nationalism. Nor were there any other indications that such a move was in the
                    offing. The problem evaporated as quickly as it had arisen leaving in its wake
                    only some resentment over the time it had consumed.</p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>While Sukarno's policy toward the PKI and the Communist powers boded ill for the
                    future, his Konfrontasi policy was an immediate threat to a constructive
                    decolonization process and was complicating our relations with our Commonwealth
                    allies. In promoting the establishment of Malaysia, the British had sought to
                    divest themselves of their colonial responsibilities while leaving behind a
                    single state rather than four vulnerable small ones. Sukarno, however, chose to
                    denounce the new state as a neocolonial creation, a threat on Indonesia's
                    borders. Like the West Irian campaign, Konfrontasi involved a good deal of
                    heated propaganda, and demonstrations, and attacks on British installations, the
                    destruction of the British Embassy included. But unlike West Irian, it also
                    included military actiocross border attacks and support for guerilla activity in
                    North Borneo and troop landings and air drops in Singapore and peninsula
                    Malaymilitary action that was being met by British and other Commonwealth
                    forces. As the British saw it, our policy was only encouraging Sukarno's
                    extremism and there was an added complication, the possibility that Australia
                    might invoke the mutual defense provisions of the ANZUS pact. By early 1975 the
                    question of how we should respond had become an issue in particular between our
                    ambassador in Jakarta and his staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was Ambassador Howard Jones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, Ambassador Jones, a strong supporter of Kennedy administration
                    policy, felt that he understood Sukarno and the Sukarno was his friend. I
                    remember one telegram in which he reported that, after having said something
                    particularly offensive about the U.S., Sukarno patted him on the knee and
                    smiled. He knew, wrote Jones, that I knew what he really meant. Increasingly,
                    however, among the embassy staff the conviction was growing that, by putting so
                    much emphasis on keeping on good terms with Sukarno, we were only encouraging
                    him to stay on course.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you in INR aware of these differences?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Oh yes. These things seep out. And, in any case, Jones did not interfere
                    with the flow of information from Jakarta that enabled us to form our own
                    judgments. In addition to embassy and CIA reporting, the FBIS reports printed
                    Sukarno's speeches in full as well as those of PKI leaders and also covered the
                    Indonesian press. Western journalists were also giving some attention to
                    developments in Indonesia. Before Jones, who had long wanted to retire, was
                    replaced by Marshall Green in July 1965, there had been some changes or at least
                    adjustments, in our policy. Avoiding a break with Sukarno remained central. But
                    we were now putting some distance into the relationship. Reducing our exposure
                    to mob attack, USIS and AID operations were terminated, our libraries were
                    closed, the Peace Corps was withdrawn, and the official American presence was
                    otherwise reduced. Marshall's arrival produced no change in Indonesian behavior,
                    but Marshall was adept in maintaining the prescribed American distance while
                    avoiding falling into traps that would have provided Sukarno with occasions for
                    further attacks. An incident described in Marshall's own account of his service
                    in Indonesia well illustrates his technique. He is at a diplomatic reception.
                    Sukarno is saying vile things about the U.S. He should walk out but he knows
                    this will only add fuel to the fire. There is a woman present, a government
                    minister who is reputed to have had a romantic relationship with Sukarno.
                    Marshall turns to her any says, “Madam Supeni, I was so distracted by how
                    beautiful you look in that beautiful dress that I really didn't hear what the
                    President said. Could you repeat it for me?”</p>
                <p>Marshall's dexterity, notwithstanding, no improvement seemed to be in sight.
                    However, on October 1, 1965 the scene was decisively changed by an attempted
                    coup involving both the PKI and some military elements and during which six
                    generals were murdered. The coup attempt was suppressed by General Suharto but
                    Sukarno's position, although weakened, remained uncertain for some time
                    thereafter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did we have any advance indication of the coup?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: No. It was a complete surprise. I have to admit that quite a bit
                    earlier, I had completely discounted the possibility. I had been asked to
                    consider two questions raised, as I recall, by Roger Hilsman: Was a Communist
                    coup attempt likely? And, if one were to take place, would the Indonesian
                    military require U.S. help to put it down? This was one of those occasions when
                    one is asked to provide a paper without involving anyone else. I suppose its
                    sensitivity arose from the suggestion that we were considering adding Indonesia
                    to our military responsibilities in Southeast Asia. I responded that the
                    Communists seemed highly unlikely to mount a coup since they were doing so very
                    well under Sukarno's patronage. But if they did mount a coup, I concluded, their
                    seeming enormous mass support would melt away and the army would be quite
                    capable of putting it down without any help from us. So, I was half right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've had a long interview with Bob Martens, who had come
                        from Moscow to Jakarta and applied his Kremlinologist techniques there. How
                        did you view his work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I don't think we attributed embassy reporting on the PKI to anyone in
                    particular, nor do I recall how valuable embassy reporting on this subject was
                    as compared with other sources. But one aspect of Martens' work has become well
                    known. This was a list of PKI members he compiled by combing through newspapers
                    and other publications, a list he turned over to the army after the coup
                    attempt. His action became the source of allegations that the Embassy had
                    fingered Communists and accordingly was complicit in the blood bath that
                    followed the coup attempt and accompanied the army's suppression of the PKI.
                    This charge has had a life of its own. It was repeated in 2005 in the obituaries
                    of two Indonesian generals who played a conspicuous part in post-coup events.
                    There is no question that Martens kept a list and turned it over. But it is hard
                    to see how anyone knowing anything about the Indonesian military would think
                    that, without the list they would have been unable to identify PKI members.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Talking about the blood bath, Martens reported being asked
                        at a staff meeting how many people he thought had been killed. He responded
                        that, although it was only a guess, he thought maybe 35,000. And that this
                        figure subsequently became holy writ.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Marshall has a somewhat different account, to the effect that he put the
                    question to the staff as a whole and the answers averaged out to 35,000. But
                    memory is fallible. As to holy wriI don't think we ever took an official
                    position on the numbers. The embassy was certainly in no position to do so. The
                    killings took place in areas where there was no American presence or access,
                    some of it in remote villages where it seemed to be grass roots reactions to
                    Communist expropriation campaigns and affronts to Islam.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Again I go back to my interview with Bob Martens who
                        believed that Sukarno was getting closer to declaring himself the supreme
                        leader of the region's Communists so that, in our dealings with him, time
                        was not on our side.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Whatever may have been in Sukarno's minand I should add that Bob was
                    convinced that Sukarno had been a card-carrying Communist from earliest daythe
                    idea is really quite implausible. One would have to imagine that the North
                    Vietnamese, the North Koreans, the Chinese Communists would accept Sukarno as
                    their self-proclaimed leader. Or that even in Southeast Asia alone, the most
                    significant Communist insurgent movements of the mid-sixties, those in Thailand
                    and Malaysia, mostly ethnic Chinese in composition, would have put themselves
                    under Indonesian leadership.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Another report, as I understand it, about the U.S. role,
                        was put out by a number of Indonesian specialists, academics from
                        Cornell.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Roughly speaking, with nothing to correct my memory, their contention
                    was that the coup attempt was organized by the military to provide them with an
                    excuse to destroy the PKI and that perhaps the U.S. was in some way complicit.
                    This didn't make them very popular with the State Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before this, had they been among your sources and did the
                        report affect the Department's relations with Cornell?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: The Indonesian Program at Cornell under George Kahin had pioneered
                    Indonesian studies in the U.S. after World War II and its publications were read
                    by anyone with a serious interest in the country. In my office, our only direct
                    contact with a Cornell Indonesian scholar before the coup was with Ruth McVey
                    than a leading expert on the PKI. She spent a good deal of time in Indonesia and
                    had extended conversations with Communist leaders. Her expertise made her a
                    welcome visitor in REA and elsewhere in Washington. In the post-coup era, of
                    course, the PKI ceased to be a subject of current interest and McVey herself
                    moved on to other topics. As far as I am aware, the Department's official
                    contacts with Cornell involved only sending FSOs there for language and area
                    training and this program was not interrupted by the coup attempt and its
                    aftermath.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After the coup attempt was put down, where did it seem to
                        you that Indonesia was going?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: There was considerable uncertainty about this. Although Sukarno's
                    presence at Halim Air Force base, the coup center, and other factors as well
                    seemed to implicate him in the coup, General Suharto, now in command of the
                    armed forces, took no immediate action against him. Sukarno remained president
                    and there was great concern over his possible return to power. I experienced the
                    continued preoccupation of the diplomatic community with Sukarno when in Jakarta
                    in, I think, January 1967 I attended one of the periodic luncheons where the
                    DCMs of friendly embassies exchanged news and views. One of them had just
                    attended one of Sukarno's receptions and everyone else was full of questionHow
                    did he look? Were his feet swollen? Whom had he talked to? What did he say?
                    Suharto's slow pace was a source of anxiety and we were kept busy reading the
                    tea leaves. But in March 1967, after what had seemed to be a long period of
                    uncertainty, the suspense came to an end. Responding to an ultimatum from the
                    military, Sukarno signed a statement making Suharto acting president with full
                    authority to take any steps necessary to ensure peace and stability. The New
                    Order was now unquestionably under way with Suharto clearly in charge and, from
                    Washington's perspective, moving in the right direction.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did this affect U.S. policy and REA work in
                        particular?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Of course, we continued to do the usual analysis of developments that
                    seemed importanthe Indonesian political scene remained fairly lively. However, a
                    major task we were assigned at this time had to do with Indonesia's economic
                    recovery. Sukarno's policies had driven the economy into the ground; his
                    approach was epitomized when he announced that neckties were more important than
                    trousers. But Suharto's New Order seemed to be genuinely committed to recovery
                    and development along lines recommended by a group of U.S.-trained Indonesian
                    economistthe so-called Berkeley mafia. Supporting Indonesia's economic recovery
                    in cooperation with other foreign donors became central to U.S. policy. In this
                    connection, we were asked to study Indonesia's capacity to utilize large-scale
                    economic assistance. This was a difficult task. Our database could not have been
                    more inadequate. Earlier economic reporting on Sukarno's disastrous policies
                    could not now be of much help. Attempting to weigh the factors involved we took
                    into account Suharto's good intentions, his reliance on the Berkeley mafia,
                    Indonesia's rich resources, and its large population. But we weighed against
                    these factors the total degradation of the economy, the prevalence of corruption
                    inside and outside the government, the inefficiency and labyrinthine procedures
                    of an antiquated government service, and the domination of the entrepreneurial
                    class by the disesteemed overseas Chinese. The resulting paper took a gloomy
                    view. I don't remember it in any detail but, from today's perspective, I suspect
                    that it was probably much too pessimistic.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There have been some claims that, if we hadn't already
                        been heavily involved in Indochina in 1965, the Indonesian army would not
                        have had the courage to turn against Sukarno.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Bill Bundy, when he was assistant secretary, made this claim very
                    publicly. The Indonesians were furious and they were right. They did it
                    themselves. Marshall was very aware of Indonesian sensitivities. During the
                    anxious transition period, he never let it be seen that the U.S. was 100 percent
                    behind Suharto and trying to help him.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is certainly the view of the people I've talked to
                        who were serving in the embassy at the time. But you mentioned corruption as
                        a problem. Of course, the Suharto regime became terribly corrupt and this
                        was a factor in bringing it down. Did you see this corruption
                        developing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: What we saw was that corruption played an important role under Suharto
                    as it had under Sukarnperhaps more of one since there was more of an economy to
                    exploit. And, over time, Suharto's wife and children became foremost among the
                    corrupt. So the question for us as analysts was not whether there was
                    corruption, it was the extent to which corruption was having a negative impact
                    on economic performance and to what extent it was arousing politically potent
                    criticism and opposition.</p>
                <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                <p>As a negative factor in U.S. relations with Indonesia, it was certainly
                    outweighed by the positive ones. Not the least of these, was the stimulus the
                    New Order provided to the establishment of the Association of Southeast Asian
                    Nations (ASEAN) relations with which were to become an important component of
                    U.S. East Asian policy. Moves toward regional organization in the past had been
                    obstructed by a number of factors among which Sukarno's policies had been one of
                    the more important. This obstacle was now overcome and Indonesia's foreign
                    minister had become a prime mover in ASEAN's establishment with Indonesian's
                    role thereafter an important factor in the organization's success.</p>
                <p>We in the Intelligence Community failed to recognize the potential importance of
                    this new regional organization. We focused on the negative factors: the wide
                    differences in ethnicity and religion; long-standing bilateral antagonisms and
                    border disputes; insufficient trained personnel to staff a new organization. We
                    failed to recognize important psychological factors. One of these of great
                    importance was ASEAN's role in developing contacts, indeed intimacy, among
                    leaders who previously had had minimal contact with one another, had not even
                    visited one another's countries. The long tenures most of these leaders enjoyed
                    contributed to and reinforced the ties that developed among them. We failed also
                    to recognize the importance of the fact that ASEAN had been created and its
                    functions determined by Southeast Asians themselves, unlike SEATO devised and
                    its terms of reference determined by the U.S. One of the obstacles we had cited,
                    the difficulty of establishing a regional bureaucracy turned out to be an
                    advantage avoiding the problems of the Brussels model, the gap between the
                    decisions of technocrats and political reality.</p>
                <p>Another case where we as estimators failed to give adequate credit to
                    psychological factors involved Singapore's expulsion from Malaysia by Prime
                    Minister Tunku Abdul Rahman. We were quite aware of the problems Singapore's Lee
                    Kuan Yew's policies were posing for the Tunku and his Malay constituents. But we
                    concluded only days, as I recall, before the expulsion, that other factors,
                    economic interdependence in particular, would preserve the relationship. We
                    failed to give adequate weight to the Tunku's deep dislike of Lee going back to
                    their Cambridge days when the Tunku had been the playboy prince and Lee the
                    striving Chinese, hard-working, brilliant, and making himself felt as a coming
                    man. Nor did we give sufficient weight to Malay fears that Lee's proposed
                    substitution of multiculturalism for the traditional division of powepolitical
                    for the Malays, economic for the Chineswas merely a device through which the
                    Chinese would achieve political as well as economic domination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: We seem to have reached 1967. Perhaps now we should go
                        back a few years. In 1962, when you took over the Southeast Asia Division,
                        how did Indochina look to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Essentially as a single problem with three inter-related problems: Laos,
                    still the center of immediate attention; Cambodia, a problem but a peripheral
                    one; and Vietnam where our basic interests were at stake.</p>
                <p>In Laos, neutralization was already becoming a fiction but a useful one,
                    providing a fa�ade behind which outside powerthe United States and Thailand,
                    North Vietnam, the PRK, and the USSR supported their respective Lao
                    clientneutralists, rightists, and Communists. For analysts two questions
                    constantly recurred. Could the neutral facade for which Prime Minister Souvanna
                    Phouma was the indispensable element survive factional conflicts? Would the
                    Communist forces carry their attacks into the Mekong lowlands, thereby
                    destroying the Geneva fa�ade? Our own courses of action also carried this danger
                    and I remember at least one occasion when we were asked to produce an Estimate
                    concerning U.S. policy choices. Requested by Secretary Rusk, the Estimate was to
                    consider the possible consequences of sending U.S. troops into Laos to cut the
                    Ho Chi Minh trail. We foretold dire consequences on the ground with the
                    possibility of a Chinese and Soviet role of some kind and, as well, negative
                    reactions elsewhere in the international community. We suspected, at the time,
                    that the Secretary had anticipated our conclusions when re requested the
                    Estimate.</p>
                <p>Cambodia was not yet involved in the Indochina war. Nevertheless, Sihanouk's
                    policiehis relations with is neighbors, his efforts to manipulate Cold War
                    rivalries to Cambodia's advantagmade for problems that required attention and
                    analysis.</p>
                <p>Vietnam, of course, was the big show, a theatre in which in 1962 the U.S. was
                    implementing new policies devised by the Kennedy administration. The
                    administration came into office believing as strongly as its predecessor in the
                    domino theory and the importance to the U.S. of preventing a Communist takeover
                    in South Vietnam. Facing Communist advances in the countryside, they saw this
                    and other problems as arising less from anything having to do with Vietnam
                    itself than from what we were doing ourselves or what we were telling the
                    Vietnamese to do. Their new approach was embodied in the concepts of
                    counter-insurgency and nation-building. We would continue to support President
                    Ngo Dinh Diem, as we had been doing since 1954, and the South Vietnamese army
                    (ARVN). But Diem was to be encouraged to seek greater contact with and
                    popularity among the people. ARVN, hitherto organized and trained to face a
                    Communist assault across the DMZ, was instead to turn Communist tactics against
                    the VC providing security to the countryside by emphasizing mobility and small
                    unit actions and winning peasant support through significantly improved
                    behavior. Programs implementing increased U.S. aid were to be more consciously
                    directed by U.S. advisors to nation building and winning hearts and minds.
                    Measuring progress was thus an important part of our work as well as tracing
                    developments on the Communist side.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>Thus, we had a great many things to keep track of and a very small staff with
                    which to do so. To be sure, over time our staff increased and its expertise was
                    significantly reinforced by the assignment of FSOs fresh from the field and with
                    area and language training. And we could turn to our China Division when the PRC
                    role was involved. But at no time did we have more than eight analysts on all of
                    Indochina as compared with the platoons at CIA and DIA which enjoyed the luxury
                    of assigning analysts to individual pieces of the problem.</p>
                <p>However, our small size had a number of advantages. Our analysts were more likely
                    than those in CIA, and certainly DIA, to see the big picture. Perhaps because we
                    did not have multitudes of people to supervise and a many-layered bureaucratic
                    structure, from our office directors on down, we regarded ourselves not as
                    managers but as senior analysts. We contributed to what was written and what was
                    briefed as much as we supervised it. And we were fortunate, or clever, or maybe
                    some of both, in the people who were recruited as our staff got larger. We had a
                    really outstanding crew.</p>
                <p>To be sure, our small size made it impossible for us to cover some subjects
                    adequatellargely subjects requiring manipulation of lots of numbers. These
                    included subjects in considerable dispute: the size of the infiltration flow and
                    of the Communist armed forces; the impact of our bombing in Laos on the flow of
                    supplies to the Communists in the South. In the debates on these issues our
                    major resource was common sense and we tended to support CIA estimates, unlike
                    DIA's, untainted by political pressures. But both agencies in arriving at their
                    estimates relied on what they called methodologies that were uncertain at
                    best.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, the thing is, having been on the ground, I know
                        so many of those figures are fake. Hamlet evaluations and all of that. Bunch
                        of nonsense.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Early in Ray Cline's tenure, because of some meeting he had to attend,
                    he wanted to know something about how bomb damage assessments were being
                    calculated. I called the CIA analyst in charge of these calculations whom I
                    trusted to give me a straight answer. First, he described DIA's methodology. And
                    I said, “That doesn't make much sense does it?” And he said, “no.” Then I said,
                    “How do you do it.” And when he told me I said, “That doesn't make much sense
                    either, does it?” And he said, “No, it doesn't.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find the quantity and quality of other kinds
                        of information available to you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: In quantity, very large indeed. It varied in quality, of course, but we
                    had enough from enough sources to give us some confidence in our ability to sift
                    the good from the bad.</p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>Embassy reporting was voluminous as was CIA's. FSOs assigned to the provincial
                    reporting program reported on local developments. A very large group of talented
                    journalists aggressively supplemented the official flow. Opportunities to
                    interview returning FSOs, military officers, journalists, and miscellaneous
                    visitors were numerous. Our access to the Communist-side, leadership decisions
                    and divisions, was of course very limited. The only independent reporting I can
                    recall from Hanoi was provided by a British representative, a remarkable woman
                    later the subject of a New Yorker profile. I believe her responsibilities were
                    consular and she had no access to the regime. Her reports were confined to what
                    she could observe. Within the restrictions imposed on her movements and her
                    contacts, her reports provided insights into such subjects as economic activity,
                    corruption, and morale. Even within the limits imposed by a Communist regime,
                    there was much material from which we could learn. Speeches by Communist
                    leaderto which they were much givewere carried in full by FBIS. Captured
                    documents were useful in our analysis of Communist objectives and strategy and
                    the themes they were using to gain support and to indoctrinate their cadres. The
                    work of RAND corporation analysts in the field was also very useful, the results
                    of their POW interrogations in particular which cast a good deal of light on
                    Viet Cong discipline and morale and on the relations between the cadres who had
                    remained in the South after 1954 and those who had later been infiltrated from
                    the North. For some subjects, for example, the presence and movements in the
                    South of units of the North Vietnamese army (PAVN, later NVA), technical means
                    provided most of such information as we had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What you say certainly seems to contradict Robert
                        McNamara's claims that we didn't understand, didn't know what was going
                        on.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: McNamara, it seems to me, attributes his mistakes to other people's
                    ignorance. It is true that, when the U.S. became involved in Southeast Asia
                    after World War II, few Americans knew very much about the region in general,
                    Indochina in particular. But even then, we already knew enough in DRF to
                    understand the contribution of nationalism to the Communist cause. And by the
                    60s, much had been accomplished both in academia and by government-supported
                    programs providing language and area training. I'm not arguing that we in the
                    Intelligence Community and others as well, who were mining the data available to
                    us, were always right. But we were right I think on most of the basic issues and
                    trends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Didn't McNamara rely mostly on numberbody counts and so
                        forth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: He was certainly big on numbers and he had a number-crunching office of
                    his own. They did something called systems analysis which was gong to tell us
                    everything we needed to know. They may have told McNamara, but I don't remember
                    that they made any contribution to the Vietnam debate.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As you kept on working the problem were there times when
                        you were optimistic, other times when you concluded we just aren't going to
                        make this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I don't think there was any period in which we didn't see significant
                    failures in performance. The first NIE in which I was involved late in 1962 took
                    a pretty bleak view of the situation, particularly ARVN's performance. But, as I
                    recall, it also stressed the opportunities for progress better implementation of
                    counter-insurgency strategies would provide. It was also in 1962 and 1963 that
                    the Buddhist crisis and other events led us to put greater emphasis on the
                    obstacles to progress stemming from the practices and policies of Ngo Dinh Diem
                    and his family. But we anticipated that, if Diem refused to change, there were
                    others who could replace him and perform more effectively. The aftermath of
                    Diem's assassination in November 1963 soon began to call this optimism into
                    question. In 1964, for example, seven governments came and went in the course of
                    the year. Thereafter, government change by coup, continuing Buddhist-military
                    conflict, poor ARVN performance, and other such factors induced pessimism
                    always, however, qualified by attention to new developments that seemed to
                    promise better performance and by optimism that, if so and so properly
                    implemented U.S.-supported programs, the situation would improve. But, at least
                    by the mid-sixties we had begun to lose faith in the possibility of improvements
                    on our side that, more than delaying a Communist victory, would actually prevent
                    it. In 1967 when General Nguyen Van Thieu became president, remaining in office
                    until the fall of Saigon in 1975, the political scene seemingly became more
                    stable. But we saw Thieu's ability to remain in power not as moving us closer to
                    our nation-building objectives but as owing to his coercive capabilities and his
                    skill in manipulating army factions. Nor did the increasing deployment of U.S.
                    military power appear to us to improve ARVN performance. The introduction of
                    U.S. ground troops, it had been anticipated, would relieve ARVN of some of its
                    major combat role to the benefit of its counter-insurgency mission. This hope
                    was not fulfilled and Saigon's power structure, civil and military, as we saw it
                    continued to be dominated by self-interest, factionalism, and corruption.</p>
                <p>If we were pessimistic about Saigon's will and capacity to resist, we were
                    equally pessimistic about the impact of our policies on Hanoi's pursuit of its
                    objectives and its capabilities for achieving them. We saw it as unlikely that
                    Hanoi could be forced by bombing or induced by bombing halts to abandon its
                    determination to reunify Vietnam under Communist auspices whatever cost and
                    damage North Vietnam might incur in the process. And we cited Soviet and Chinese
                    interest in Hanoi's success, as well as their own growing competition, as
                    guaranteeing that they would continue to fulfill Hanoi's requirements for
                    military equipment and assistance in repairing bomb damage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your pessimism shared by other members of the
                        Intelligence Community or were there deep differences?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Pessimism about the situation as a whole was fairly general. But there
                    were significant differences over the elements of the problem at any given time
                    to cause us to spend days in smoke-filled rooms seeking to reach an agreed NIE
                    text. The deepest differences, as I recall, had to do with the effects of our
                    efforts to cut off Communist supplies, the size of the Communist fighting
                    forces, and the possibility of Chinese military intervention. On the impact of
                    the bombing, I referred earlier to the rather dubious calculations involved. We
                    tended to support CIA in estimates on the low side; DIA and air force
                    intelligence took a more positive view. On communist military manpower, the
                    debate was largely over what elements of the Communist force structure,
                    conventional and otherwise, should be included in the order of battle. Here CIA
                    and INR took the more inclusive view. The dispute was settled in a meeting in
                    Saigon attended by representatives of the Washington agencies, including REA,
                    and of MACV. More than anything else, horse-trading dominated the outcome.</p>
                <p>On Chinese intervention, until 1967, INR rated the possibility somewhat higher
                    than other members of the community. We were all agreed that Chinese military
                    intervention in some form was likely if the regime in Hanoi seemed on the verge
                    of collapse or if US/ARVN forces were to invade the North. But REA also saw the
                    possibility of PRC intervention in the air as raised by some of Beijing's
                    statements and new deployments of Chinese air assets. Seeing a greater
                    likelihood than others that China might introduce ground forces, we argued that
                    Hanoi's fear of Chinese domination would be outweighed if it perceived a vital
                    need for Chinese assistance. But we also argued that, even under such
                    circumstances, Hanoi would continue to control its own strategy. However,
                    China's failure to respond to the bombing of the Hanoi-Haiphong area and the
                    disorder accompanying the Cultural Revolution led us to join the rest of the
                    community in restricting the likelihood of Chinese intervention to the invasion
                    of the North or the imminent collapse of the regime.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could you talk about the Tet Offensive and its effecthis
                        is in January 1968.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>COLBERT: In the military sense this was certainly not a success for the
                    Communists. They took a lot of casualties. They lost a major part of their South
                    Vietnamese infrastructure. They had to retreat from the cities they had
                    occupied. And if they really expected the general uprising they told their
                    cadres would, at some point, accompany their military campaigns, they were
                    certainly disappointed. But the fact that it was a military success on our part
                    and a military failure on theirs was not necessarily the point. The
                    psychological effects in South Vietnam and the U.S. were what really counted. Up
                    until Tet, the hostilities had impinged mainly on the countryside. People in the
                    cities and big towns lived more or less normal lives, many benefiting
                    economically from the U.S. presence. Now Tet had brought home to the urban
                    population the reality of Communist power, the likelihood that the Communists
                    would win, and, therefore, the advisability of not seeming to take sides with
                    the government and the U.S. In the U.S., until Tet, Washington had told the
                    country that we were winning, that the light was at the end of the tunnel, and
                    that the Communists were being driven into the ground. So inevitably the
                    question arosif you have been telling the truth, how is it that the Communists
                    were able to attack 100 cities and towns all over the South, even attack the
                    American Embassy. Opposition to the war began to spread much more widely and
                    into more politically potent circles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you find the unhappiness of the American people
                        seeping into your evaluation?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Not directly but certainly in our analysis of how estimates of our
                    staying power affected Communist strategy and what tactics they were adopting
                    less for their military value than for their hoped-for impact on American
                    attitudes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you at any time put under pressure from outside INR
                        to bring your analysis into greater conformity with official positions?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My feeling most of the time was that we were saying, “The Emperor has no
                    clothes on.” and our masters were saying, “Yes, but doesn't he look beautiful
                    that way?” In general, we were left to do our own thing, perhaps because as is
                    so well argued in Gelb and Betts, The System Worked, our pursuit of the war was
                    less determined by how it was going than by potent political compulsions. And,
                    except for Daniel Ellsberg, we didn't leak.</p>
                <p>There were a few instances of pressure but not enough to cause us to change our
                    ways. The very pessimistic tone of the first Estimate in which I was involved
                    was greeted by protests from DOD and MACV which caused USIB to send it back to
                    us for reconsideration. In the process, we were lectured by a number of generals
                    about how and why we were so wrong. In its final form the Estimate remained
                    pessimistic but somewhat less so.</p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>On another occasion in 1963 DOD took exception to one of our papers the title of
                    which is lost to memory, but which is known as RFE 90. It was a short and simple
                    paper which, using MACV statistics, demonstrated that the Communists were taking
                    the offensive against ARVN and doing well. This evoked a memo from McNamara to
                    Rusk asserting that military statistics were DOD's affair not State's and
                    demanding that INR be instructed to observe this distinction. In due course the
                    Secretary sent back a rather vaguely worked memo while the complaint had no
                    impact on our work nor, despite much later accounts, on the fate of its author
                    who was twice promoted thereafter, reaching the highest grade then available in
                    the civil service.</p>
                <p>The only other such incident I can remember took place after the Paris Peace
                    Accords involving a paper detailing the way in which they were being violated by
                    both North and South Vietnamese as each side sought to strengthen its position.
                    The attribution of violations to the South Vietnamese so aroused the ire of
                    Graham Martin, our ambassador in Saigon, that he sent a letter to one of INR's
                    deputy directors denouncing the author in what could only be described as
                    McCarthyite terms. Our deputy director had earlier worked for Martin in Rome and
                    was very disturbed by the letter but it was not too difficult to convince him
                    that the analysis was sound and we heard no more.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: At any point, were you called upon to brief Dean Rusk or
                        any of the other seventh floor principals?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: This of course was Tom Hughes' job and that of course, was the way that
                    REA's views could be brought to higher levels. Sometimes, however, we were asked
                    to write memos to an unidentified consumer from an unidentified author which we
                    suspected meant that someone important was being addressed outside regular
                    channels. One such request called for an estimate of the consequences of
                    introducing U.S. ground forces not too long before the decision to do so. We
                    contested the argument that this would cause the North Vietnamese troops, now in
                    the South in large numbers, to stand and fight thereby subjecting themselves to
                    our massive firepower. We expected instead that they would encounter U.S. forces
                    only at times of their own choosing and in circumstances that would make them
                    reasonably confident of success.</p>
                <p>Another such unsourced, unaddressed tasks came in the wake of one of those
                    missions to Hanoi code named Daffodil and the like and entrusted to foreign
                    nationals to solicit Communist views on a peace treaty. I remember reading the
                    account of their conversations in a remote little room with the door shut and
                    finding that nothing these emissaries had learned conflicted with our view that
                    the Communists would settle for nothing less than a political arrangement that
                    would open their path to power in Saigon.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In the spring of 1970 there was an incursion into Cambodia
                        that caused a number of FSOs to reign and many more to sign a document
                        protesting the move. Did this have any reverberations within INR?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Oh yes, indeed! We all thought it was madness, anticipating that any
                    damage to North Vietnamese capabilities would be temporary and that Cambodia
                    woulbe drawn into a wider war to the benefit of the Communists. In this we were
                    right but earlier we had been wrong in significantly underestimating the volume
                    of supplies the Communists had stockpiled in the Cambodian border area en route
                    to South Vietnam. In earlier consideration of the desirability of some sort of
                    incursion into Cambodia, proponents had argued that cutting off the supply route
                    would inflict major damage on the Communists. Contesting this view, strongly
                    held in Saigon, INR and CIA argued that the Cambodia supply route was not
                    indispensable, and that the damage to the Communists would be only temporary. As
                    the incursion demonstrated, we had significantly underestimated the Communist
                    stockpiles in the Cambodian border area but we were right that no lasting damage
                    would be inflicted, while the incursion and the events that followed provided a
                    springboard for the eventual Khmer Rouge takeover.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Cambodia aside, did the advent of the Nixon administration
                        bring about any change in INR's role?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Not really. Changes in personnel and style certainly but neither in
                    mission or influence. To the extent that we had had access to the seats of
                    power, it had been through Tom Hughes; I don't think Ray Cline had any similar
                    access. At some point when I was already at Brookings there was some slight
                    reason to think that Henry Kissinger was actually interested in the views of the
                    Intelligence Community since he had asked for answers to a very large number of
                    questions, somewhere in the vicinity of 100. But the cynical view soon emerged
                    that he was just trying to keep us busy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned your absence at the Brookings Institutions
                        for a year. How did that come about?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I had something called a Federal Executive Fellowship under which, while
                    the government continued to pay your salary, you could spend a year at Brookings
                    just reading or writing or both. I had heard about the program not from
                    Personnel oanybody else in the Department but from a college classmate who had
                    been nominated by the National Science Foundation. For some time, I had seen the
                    absence of a diplomatic history of post-war Southeast Asia as a gap that needed
                    to be filled. Fred Greene, from his academic vantage point, confirmed my
                    impression that no such study existed. Henry Owen, formerly head of the Planning
                    Staff and now Brookings' director of studies, assured me that, if I were
                    nominated by the State Department, Brookings would be glad to have me. Ray Cline
                    agreed in principle but insisted that I could not leave until a suitable
                    replacement had been found for Bill Gleysteen, who was about to become DCM in
                    Taipei. Until Bill's replacement had been found and settled in, I was needed to
                    run the office. It was quite a while before Paul Popple arrived, persuaded Mort
                    Abramowitz to replace me for a year, and settled in. A process that I had
                    initiated sometime in the spring of 1971 took me to Brookings in February
                    1972.</p>
                <p>The contrast with my life in the Department could not have been greater.
                    Brookings, unlike the Carnegie Endowment where I spent some time after I
                    retired, was anything but collegial. People arrived in the morning, closed their
                    door, and went to work. Events designed for fellows as a group were few and far
                    between. Office space, secretarial assistance, and, for my purposes, library
                    resources were minimal. So I spent most of my time working at home or at the
                    State Department or other libraries around town. Liberated from interruptions
                    and distractions, and given a three-month extension, I managed to produce a
                    finished manuscript covering the period from World War II to 1956. This was at
                    least a logical breaking point, although not as far as I would have liked to go.
                    I say finished but only in the sense that I had a complete manuscript. It took
                    quite a bit of revision, reorganization, and general improvement, not to mention
                    dealing with the editorial process once it had been accepted by the Cornell
                    University Press, before it was finally published in 1976.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you went back to INR in May 1973 and remained there
                        until when?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: A little less than a year, leaving for CIA in March 1974. By the time I
                    returned the Paris peace settlement was in effect, the last American troops had
                    left Vietnam in March, and the U.S.-China rapprochement was well under way. So,
                    while there was still much to cover in Indochina, the pace was somewhat less
                    intense even though it still kept us quite busy. Meanwhile, looking back at our
                    other preoccupations, it seems to me that this short period in East Asia was
                    marked by an unusual number of events that were harbingers of things to come.
                    These included not only developments in the PRC but also, in South Korea, the
                    emergence of Kim Dae Jung as a significant opposition figure, in Thailand, the
                    1973 student revolution, and, in the Philippines, Marcos' suspension of the
                    constitution, the imposition of martial law, and the beginnings of the Moro
                    insurgency.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you moved to CIA in March 1974. How did that come
                        about?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: It was not a decision I moved to quickly. I was very comfortable where I
                    was. I knew all the people I needed to know; they knew me; and we seemed to be
                    happy together. I knew what doors to knock on and what buttons to push. But, on
                    the other hand, I would not just be going from State to the Agency. I would be
                    becoming part of a new structure with new functions in the Agency and the
                    Community. So this seemed to offer a new challenge and perhaps this was
                    something I needed. I knew Bill Colby. I knew his deputy for the new NIO system,
                    George Carver, very well having worked with him on Vietnam and other Estimates
                    since 1962. And this was true of a lot of other people in the Agency. So in the
                    end I decided that for the two years I would be detailed it was worth a try.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just what was this new system and how was it
                        organized?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: As conceived by Bill Colby, then DCI, the National Intelligence
                    Officers, each an expert in his particular region or function, were to serve as
                    his senior substantive staff, assume the responsibilities of the now-abolished
                    Office of National Estimates, and play a coordinating role both in CIA and the
                    Intelligence Community. In line with Colby's hopes to bring about greater
                    interchange between the Community and other related agencies, State in
                    particular, and with academics and think tank people, the NIOs were not to be
                    drawn exclusively from CIA ranks. Each regional and functional area of
                    significance to U.S. policy was to have an NIO. (At this time there was no NIO
                    for South Asia or for Africa.) Uniquely there were to be three NIOs for East
                    Asia: one on Indochina and Thailand, still a full time responsibility, best
                    filled by a CIA officer to ensure the cooperation of the Operations Directorate;
                    and two to be filled from State, one on China and one, identified as Japan and
                    Pacific Asia, to cover everything not included in the other two. This was to be
                    my job. China, however, proved to be more difficult to fill from State
                    Department ranks. FSOs of appropriate rank and expertise aspiring to eventual
                    ambassadorial nominations were unwilling to risk a CIA assignment that might
                    later unfavorably affect the agr�ment process. In the end, the China slot was
                    not filled until George Bush became DCI and brought with him Jim Lilly who had
                    been his station chief in Beijing.</p>
                <p>Other than myself, of the original group of NIOs, only two came from outside the
                    Agency, an academic from RAND as the NIO for economics and, from DOD, an admiral
                    who covered conventional forces. The deputies, one for each NIO, were all from
                    the Agency. After the fall of Saigon, the NIO for Indochina became NIO for South
                    Asia and I inherited his earlier responsibilities. China also eventually became
                    part of East Asia but I don't know when that happened.</p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>The NIO system at that time had very little structure. We were collegial to the
                    extent that we shared office suites and that we met together with Colby to
                    report to him on developments in our areas and to hear from him whatever he
                    wanted to tell us. We also met from time to time under George Carver's
                    chairmanship mostly to hear from him information or instructions that affected
                    us all. Otherwise, however, we performed our substantive roles as individuals
                    responsible to the DCI, joining forces with one or another of our NIO colleagues
                    when our substantive responsibilities overlapped.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How were the NIO's functions defined at that time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Some quite specifically, others more amorphously. The most clear cut had
                    to do with the production of National Intelligence Estimateoutlining the terms
                    of reference, establishing requirements, reviewing original drafts, presiding
                    over representative meetings, and presenting the final draft to the DCI.
                    Although we inherited the board's responsibilities, we did not inherit the staff
                    that had been responsible for producing the initial text. Colby had hoped that
                    this responsibility could be shared with other elements of the community called
                    upon to produce drafts on subjects for which their responsibilities best suited
                    them. This never really worked out and, at least in my area, drafts were
                    normally the result of NIO/DI collaboration.</p>
                <p>NIOs were also expected to coordinate any intelligence contribution required for
                    various types of policy papers the most important of which were the PRMs of the
                    Carter administration and the NSSMs of the Nixon administration. These sometimes
                    required written contributions, at other times participation in working group
                    meetings.We were also expected to keep the DCI informed of important and
                    prospective developments in our fields of responsibility. This of course was a
                    function which, in fact, we shared with other, sometimes highly competitive
                    colleagues. We were also expected to involve ourselves in the rather elaborate
                    machinery that had developed to define intelligence collection and goals. Except
                    in the case of Korea, where it became possible to move the machinery in the
                    direction of better collection on the North, I found this a pretty pro-forma
                    process.</p>
                <p>NIOs were supposed to be active in promoting Colby's interest in encouraging
                    greater Agency interchange with policy makers and outside specialists. The
                    individual NIO was expected not only to maintain active contact with State,
                    Defense, and NSC counterparts but also to encourage DI analysts to do the same.
                    Also, in the interests of greater communication with the academic world, we were
                    encouraged to bring scholars in for conferences. Attendance at meetings of
                    learned societies was supported for NIOs and DI analysts in general and we were
                    to identify ourselves there as working for CIA. Attending a meeting of the
                    American Historical Association where I had been asked to read a paper based on
                    an article I had written for Foreign Affairs during my Brookings interlude, I
                    found myself in a crowded elevator standing next to an elderly priest. Studying
                    my badge, he asked, “What's a nice lady like you doing working for an outfit
                    like that?”</p>
                <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could have said, “Just lucky, I guess.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes. Or if I'd been a little quicker on the draw, I could have rejoined,
                    “What's a nice man like you working for the Pope?” But I'm not very good at that
                    sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've described a pretty ambitious agenda. How did it
                        work in practice?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Certainly not to the extent that Colby must have hoped. But well enough
                    to survive down to the present, now in a somewhat more structured form as the
                    National Intelligence Council and, most recently, to be attached to John
                    Negroponte's office.</p>
                <p>From the outset DOD reacted suspiciously and defensively, suspecting that the
                    system's object was to give the DCI real authority over the overwhelmingly large
                    proportion of the intelligence budget allocated to the Defense Department and
                    perhaps even to replace the DOD in authority over the important intelligence
                    organizations falling under its jurisdiction. Sometime later, I don't remember
                    when, DIA set up its own system of Defense Intelligence Officers (DIO).
                    Presumably this was intended to prevent NIOs from engaging in direct tasking or
                    other overly close involvement with DIA offices. In fact it proved to be a
                    blessing providing a much needed central contact for dealing with DIA. My DIO
                    was a pleasure to work witbright, helpful, experienced and well-versed in
                    Pentagon ins and outs.</p>
                <p>For other parts of the Agency, the new system insofar as its functions and
                    authority extended beyond those of the Board of National Estimates could be seen
                    as threatening established prerogatives. And Colby was in no position to sweep
                    all before him. The DCI is no exception to the rule that an agency heads
                    strength is affected by the strength of his political backing. And Colby was
                    just an old CIA hand, a very distinguished one to be sure, but he wasn't the
                    president's man or anyone else's man. And he had aroused some resentment in the
                    DO because of his willingness to cooperate with the Congressional investigations
                    of the period and even the press. But the proof of the pudding is, after all, in
                    the eating. The system has survived for over thirty years while many other
                    innovations have fallen by the wayside.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After all of your years in the Department, how did the
                        transition to the Agency affect you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: My immediate transition was vastly eased by my first deputy, a GS-15
                    Agency veteran who, in addition to his many other talents, was a magnificent
                    guide to CIA's ins and outs.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>On the whole, the move turned out well. There was no lack of interesting work to
                    do. Being staff not line was in many ways a pleasant change. Without line
                    authority over the DI, I had no responsibility over the work of its analysts. I
                    didn't give them their assignments. I didn't write their performance ratings. I
                    didn't adjudicate their turf fights. But I could rely on their cooperation in
                    the projects for which I was responsible and, over time, I found I could suggest
                    topics and offer comments on some of the things they were doing.</p>
                <p>I was under no illusions that my coordinating responsibilities extended to the DO
                    and I needed to move carefully to secure DO cooperation when it was necessary.
                    But I had no serious problems and I got a little extra credit among the
                    remaining OSS veterans for having been one of them. It didn't hurt either that,
                    as compared to life in INR, NIOs lived high on the homore attractive offices,
                    much better services, much more money for travel, cars available more or less on
                    call, top secretaries.</p>
                <p>The things to which I reacted less favorably had more to do with the Agency
                    itself than with my own job. Perhaps because it was so much bigger than State,
                    it was much more bureaucratithis, I would think to myself, is what the
                    Department of Agriculture must be like. And, perhaps, partly because of its
                    immunity at that time from political appointments below the top, it was very
                    much an age pyramid. The closest thing to a Dick Holbrooke, assistant secretary
                    at age 35, was George Carver, and he was in his mid-forties.</p>
                <p>I was also surprised to find that the very high quality of the CIA people I had
                    worked with over the years largely in the estimative process was not full
                    representative of Agency analytic personnel as a whole. As I suppose is
                    frequently the case, areas in constant crisis or of great strategic importance
                    to the United States tend somehow to draw the brightest, the most energetic, the
                    most ambitious. In other areas where the challenge was less great, there were, I
                    found, quite a few analysts who were happy to lead a quiet life, enjoy trips to
                    the field, and produce papers but who, when the need arose, were not always
                    useful performers. Even among the really good analysts, many seemed to live in a
                    cocoon. The rest of the world, the State Department included, was downtown. You
                    didn't go there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Perhaps you could talk now about the more important
                        policy-related problems that you dealt with as NIO.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: From that point of view, it was a pretty lively three years, involving
                    the production of quite a few Estimates and participation after 1976 in the
                    policy papers a new administration initiates. Most of the Estimates passed
                    through the USIB process with no particular difficulty; two did not, one on
                    international reactions to the fall of Saigon, the other on the military balance
                    on the Korean peninsula. I'll save these to talk about more extensively and deal
                    with the others first.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>Some of the Estimates in which I was involved during this period were of the
                    temperature taking variety, a look at the situation and prospects, unrelated to
                    a policy decision or a particular crisis. Estimates on Indonesia and the
                    Philippines reached similar conclusions: both faced serious problems and
                    opposition but in both the regime was firmly in control. In Malaysia, the
                    Communists had become more active and there were indications that they might
                    soon engage in urban warfare but we concluded that the situation was manageable.
                    Probably stimulated by one of North Korea's periodic threatening actions, we
                    took another look at the possibility of a military assault on the South but
                    found no reason to depart from the conclusion that as long as U.S. troops were
                    in the DMZ, North Korea would not attack the South.</p>
                <p>New concern with Soviet activities in the South Pacific as most of the island
                    countries were becoming independent was aroused by reports of Soviet discussions
                    of a naval base with the King of Tonga coupled with the buildup of the
                    previously neglected Soviet Pacific fleet. The questions of Soviet intentions
                    was thus ripe for estimative treatment especially since an ANZUS Council meeting
                    was imminent and the subject was as interesting to our ANZUS partners as to
                    ourselves. Although we were dealing primarily with Soviet intentions and it was
                    Soviet specialists who were doing most of the work, I was designated to chair
                    the Estimate meetings. Part of the answer to the questions Soviet activities had
                    raised was reassuring and caused no dissension around the table. It had to do
                    with fish. With the Russian diet heavily dependent on fish for protein, the
                    Soviets were beginning to run into supply problems. Some of their traditional
                    fishing grounds were becoming exhausted; others were being closed to them for
                    political reasons. Hence a search for new sources of supply was bringing them
                    into waters where they had never fished before, waters very rich in tuna. This
                    left the questiowhy the new Soviet Pacific fleet buildup and here I failed in an
                    effort to substitute clear disagreement for fudge. I no longer remember the
                    substance of several paragraphs in the draft to which only the Navy objected.
                    Pressed to take a footnote they refused to do so for reasons that seemed
                    somewhat mysterious to us but important to them. Accordingly, to get the
                    Estimate out we agreed to fudge in return for a Navy commitment to provide a
                    separate Estimate on the fleet issue which, at least in my time, they never did.
                    A subject now, of course, of interest only to historians.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you involved in the tree-cutting incident on the DMZ?
                        I was consul general in Seoul and it was a very scary time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                <p>COLBERT: You're right, it was. On the day the news came in that North Korean
                    troops had attacked American troops cutting down a tree in the DMZ and beaten
                    two officers to death, Kissinger and a number of the other principals were in
                    Kansas City attending the Republican nominating convention. Accordingly an NSC
                    meeting could not be held until early the following morning, around 6 a.m. or
                    so. Immediately, however, a working group had been established under Phil Habib,
                    then Assistant Secretary of State for East Asia, and, as the Intelligence
                    Community member, I was asked to remain at the State Department for an all night
                    session at the Operations Center. Meanwhile, my deputy spent the night at
                    Langley putting together relevant data from CIA and the other intelligence
                    agencies to use in preparing Bush to brief the NSC. Putting together
                    graphicphotos, maps and so forth was relatively easy. Answering the obvious
                    questions was not: had this been only the first step in what was to be a series
                    of provocations? Had it been ordered from Pyongyang or was it some locally
                    concerned adventure? Well before the NSC meeting we met Bush at his home to
                    provide him with the intelligence briefing and let him know what had been going
                    on on the policy side in the course of the night. At the door, as we were about
                    to leave, Bush turned, gathered up the coffee cups, and washed them, saying
                    “Barbara doesn't like me to leave dirty dishes around.” I really liked that.</p>
                <p>The NSC meeting was primarily concerned not with the whys and wherefores but with
                    how to respond in ways that would convince the North Koreans to abandon any
                    further moves they might have in mind while avoiding the possibility of
                    escalation. I don't remember what part Bush played in this debate. I, of course,
                    was one of the people who sat against the wall and spoke only when spoken to.
                    Kissinger did ask me one question. I don't remember what it was, but it was
                    clear to me that he was not satisfied with my answer. This was confirmed after
                    the meeting when Phil growled at me, “You don't know how to answer Kissinger.”
                    But then he added, “You never have anything to do with him, how should you?”</p>
                <p>I have since thought that if this had been a war game, the players would have
                    regarded the point of departure as far-fetched. But, that said, everybody played
                    very well. We went into high alert, put on an impressive display of naval and
                    air might, and sent another team out to cut down the tree, this time with air
                    support. But we used no force against North Korea. The Japanese did not object
                    to our deploying from our bases on their soil. The Chinese, in effect, told Kim
                    Il Sung, “You're on your own.” And Kim expressed his regrets.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Our ambassador, Dick Sneider, was on leave and our DCM was
                        Tom Stern. There we were the country team trying to figure it out. My main
                        contribution when they said they were going in to cut down the tree was to
                        say, “Well for God's sake make sure the chainsaws work. Test them before you
                        go.”</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                <p>COLBERT: They seem to have taken your advice. Earlier we had had another Korean
                    problem, this one created by the South which, in 1974, had embarked on a secret
                    nuclear weapons program. We were charged with analyzing Seoul's capabilities in
                    this regard and the Agency's Scientific and Technology Directorate was assigned
                    the principal responsibility. It became quite evident that, on a subject that
                    had not previously concerned us, we were simply incapable of answering the
                    question in any useful way. Fortunately, there was no need to rely on our
                    uncertain answers. Diplomatic pressures on President Park Chung Hee and
                    potential foreign suppliers brought the program to an end.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I gather you became involved in Vietnam once again. When
                        did this happen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Early in 1975 I had had a detached retina operation which didn't keep me
                    out of the office for very long but which left me for some time with
                    significantly impaired vision. So I couldn't do the amount of reading and
                    writing the job usually entailed. In order to make sure I kept busy and earned
                    my salary, I was sent to meetingmany the kind to which you send someone just to
                    demonstrate your right to be present. But during this period also the North
                    Vietnamese military offensive that was to result in the fall of Saigon was well
                    under way. Almost daily meetings were being held to track developments and
                    examine prospects. Given my background and, since I could hear and speak if not
                    read, I was invited to participate.</p>
                <p>As the end approached, USIB called for an Estimate on world reactions to the fall
                    of Saigon which had indeed fallen by the time the Estimate got under way. I was
                    put in charge of what was a rather unusual procedure. Community representatives
                    for each world region met in separate panels under my chairmanship to produce
                    regional drafts. Then, also under my chairmanship, representatives of each panel
                    met to put the pieces together. There was little disagreement on the substance.
                    The countries of East Asithose of Southeast Asia in particulawould be
                    apprehensive, not so much over the Communist victory which most of them had
                    anticipated for some time, but over its impact on U.S. policy. Would the United
                    States, as some politically prominent Americans were urging, leave Southeast
                    Asia altogether, reduce its role in East Asia as a whole? Without over-stepping
                    our intelligence role, we were able to comment that the U.S. had it within its
                    powers to allay these fears. For the rest of the world, it was agreed the
                    reaction would be relief. With the end of our war-generated problems and
                    domestic divisions, the United States would now be able to pay adequate
                    attention to what other countries saw as the really important problems.</p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>These conclusions, however, proved unacceptable to most of the USIB members.
                    Obviously, it was difficult for the military members to accept the conclusion
                    that, in most of the world, the failure of an effort to which they had devoted
                    so much was of so little consequence. Bill Hyland, whose INR analysts had
                    earlier joined in the Community consensus, seemingly found it more important to
                    defend Kissinger's credibility thesis than to maintain INR's well established
                    tradition of independence from political pressures. Only Bill Colby and George
                    Carver, who had as much emotional involvement in the war as any of their
                    military colleagues, stood up for the integrity of the analysis. The Estimate
                    accordingly was remanded to reps, a term of art, sometimes meaning go back and
                    do better, but in this case, go away don't bother us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In a way, the Estimate as it emerged on paper is not the
                        real point is it? The work that goes on the discussions, don't these mean
                        that the conclusions become pretty well known among people dealing with the
                        subject even if the Estimate is not published?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: It seems to me that that would depend on the subject. But certainly, in
                    this case, I wouldn't argue that the failure to publish the Estimate had
                    consequences beyond the frustration felt by the people involved in its
                    production. However, the USIB response to the fall of Saigon proved to be
                    consequential for our work on Korea over the next years. Our experience with the
                    deficiencies of the South Vietnamese army now raised a question not earlier
                    considered. Were our over 30,000 troops in South Korea likely at some point to
                    be facing the enemy with military partners no better than the South Vietnamese.
                    I was tasked with two responsibilities: setting in motion more energetic
                    collection efforts on Korea; and taking a preliminary look in Washington and
                    Seoul at the South Korean army through reviewing the reporting and interviewing
                    the knowledgeable. The results of the latter effort were reassuring. It seemed
                    safe to conclude that the ROK army did not suffer from the weaknesses that had
                    plagued its South Vietnamese counterpart. Meanwhile, it was becoming evident
                    that we had been asking the wrong question; it was the capabilities of the North
                    Korean military that we should be examining.</p>
                <pb facs="0062" n="Page0062"/>
                <p>With your own Korean experience, you will probably remember the Nixon
                    administration decision to withdraw one of the two divisions we then had in
                    South Korea. The study preceding this decision had concluded that the military
                    forces of North and South were in more or less equal balance. In subsequent
                    examinations of the military balance, the North Korean total was arrived at by
                    calculations of growth based on the 1970 figures. Since the South Korean armed
                    forces were also growing, the assumption of a North/South military balance
                    remained firmly embedded. Estimates on the North Korean threat, since they
                    invariably cited the U.S. presence as a convincing deterrent, did not require
                    detailed attention to North Korean capabilities. Nor had we been collecting
                    intelligence that seemed to challenge the North/South balance assumption. In
                    fact, the collection and analysis of intelligence on North Korea had not been
                    accorded very high priority. Vietnam had absorbed both people and resources. In
                    CIA, for example, work on the North Korean economy had been assigned to the
                    office covering China, becoming a subject analysts dealt with when they had
                    nothing more important to do. Political analysts tended to absorb themselves in
                    a form of Kremlinology with inconsequential results.</p>
                <p>Even before the USIB injunction to strengthen the intelligence effort had borne
                    fruit in significant improvements, particularly better photographic coverage,
                    new attention was being paid to intelligence already collected. Garmy
                    intelligencdissatisfied with DIA's work on the North Korean military had
                    assigned an analyst of their own, one John Armstrong, to spend every minute of
                    his working time going over already accumulated material, photography,
                    intercepts, and whatever else applied. Late in 1975 he had already found that
                    North Korean tank forces were much larger than had been thought with one whole
                    tank regiment near the DMZ that had never before been identified. At more or
                    less the same time, CIA economists had done a study of North Korean iron and
                    cement production on which they had pretty good data and which left unanswered
                    an important question. Where was it all going? With the consumption figures far
                    below the production ones, the obvious suspicion was that a good deal was being
                    used for concealed military purposes, which indeed proved to be the case.</p>
                <p>By the end of the Ford administration, military and CIA analysts had come to the
                    conclusion that North Korean military policies, beginning in 1970 or
                    thereabouts, had significantly altered the military balance in favor of the
                    North. But we had not yet found very much interest in this conclusion in the
                    policy community. Some of my best friends said, “You intelligence analysts
                    always see the enemy as ten feet tall.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Hadn't Jimmy Carter already announced is plan to remove
                        U.S. ground troops from South Korea?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0063" n="Page0063"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, during his campaign for the Democratic nomination. And, over time,
                    this did increase interest in our findings. Whatever other reasons Carter may
                    have had, this must have looked to him like a politically popular move. The
                    opposition to committing U.S. forces to wars in Asia generated by Vietnam was
                    still potent while both on the Hill and among elements of the general public.
                    President Park's human rights excesses and Koreagate revelations had brought
                    South Korea into great disfavor.</p>
                <p>Immediately after Carter's nomination, when he became entitled to CIA briefings,
                    it seemed possible that his mind was not entirely closed. Asked by Bush to
                    express his interests, Carter asked particularly to be told about things he
                    didn't know about so that he could avoid making statements as a candidate he
                    would regret as president. Thereafter the weekly list of possible briefing
                    topics invariably included Korea and the military balance. And invariably it was
                    ignored. We were, of course, deeply discouraged by our inability to call the
                    attention of a potential new administration to our findings. Mort Abramowitz,
                    then a deputy assistant secretary at DOD/ISA suggested a half-way step, a
                    DIA/CIA memo to Brent Scowcroft at the NSC outlining the data and our
                    conclusions. This would at least go into the files and perhaps come to the
                    attention of the transition team at the NSC. Useful as the memo was in putting
                    together our agreed summary of the existing intelligence and providing a basis
                    for future elaboration, it had no other impact.</p>
                <p>Late in January when a rather vaguely worded Presidential Review Memorandum (PRM)
                    13 called for a review of Korea policy, including a reduction in U.S.
                    conventional force levels, it seemed possible that the Korea PRM, like the one
                    on the Philippine bases, could include some consideration of the pros and cons.
                    When the working group convened, however, it was instructed that the PRM was to
                    include no such consideration. Instead it was to be confined to examining ways
                    in which the troop withdrawal might be carried out. This was devastating news to
                    a group most of whom, like our embassy in Seoul and the military in the field,
                    believed that the troop withdrawal policy was unwise. Now it appeared that the
                    only way in which the PRM could have any sort of useful influence was by setting
                    forth phases and procedures that might minimize the damage. And perhaps an NIE
                    laying out the North Korean data and the military vulnerabilities of the South
                    might have a helpful impact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I was in Korea at the time and we were absolutely
                        horrified. It seemed to be to uncork the bottle and make the situation much
                        more problematic, one where anything could happen. I remember talking to
                        Lieutenant General Chaplain. I went up to visit him during one of their war
                        games based on the assumption of U.S. withdrawal on the ground. He said just
                        when Seoul is about to fall we'll have to call in massive air force strikes
                        which we're not sure we'll be able to do in time. The feeling as I recall
                        was that we could probably beat the North Koreans but not until horrific
                        damage had been done and Seoul had been overrun.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0064" n="Page0064"/>
                <p>COLBERT: In the Washington bureaucracy, supporters as I recall, were pretty much
                    confined to the Bureau of the Budget and DOD's budget people who, in the period
                    I'm talking about, were not convinced by the military balance arguments and saw
                    some prospective savings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well actually I thought that keeping the divisions in
                        South Korea was a money saver because the Koreans were paying the upkeep
                        and, if it were brought back to what I think was its headquarters in the
                        State of Washington, there wasn't any room and it would cost money.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: We raised that but they had the idea they could disband the division
                    altogether. But, of course, for the Intelligence Community the main task was
                    producing the NIE. This was made somewhat more difficult by what seemed to be
                    constantly shifting deadlines. I don't remember the reason for these changes.
                    But I do remember that the analysts responded cheerfully, worked terribly hard,
                    and never really complained even when called on Sunday morning to come in Sunday
                    afternoon. I should add that my relatively new deputy (his predecessor had left
                    for an overseas assignment) was a source of tremendous strength. A Special
                    Forces colonel, he more than compensated for my own lack of a military
                    background.</p>
                <p>With the arrival of Bush's successor as DCI, Admiral Stansfield Turner, a new
                    complication entered into our efforts. When Carter attended a USIB meetinthe
                    first time to my knowledge that a president had done shis purpose really seemed
                    to be to make it clear that Turner was his man, reinforcing the DCI's already
                    substantial ego. When, in response, the general then heading DIno shrinking
                    violet himselasserted what he regarded as DIA's prerogatives, the President
                    struck him down in no uncertain terms.</p>
                <p>By the time Turner appeared on the scene, we had completed a first draft of the
                    Estimate and promptly sent it up to him for comment. The draft came back to us
                    with numerous objections scrawled in the margins all phrased in intemperate and
                    insulting language far beyond anything I had ever experienced in my long years
                    in government. The attacks continued in much the same vein, but never to the
                    point of taking issue with the conclusions in ways that could be construed as an
                    attempt to bring the Estimate into conformity with policy. Instead the assault
                    was always on individual elements of the argument, for example, the degree to
                    which North Korean MIG 17s would contribute to enemy fire power in the event of
                    a surprise attack. Even so, by April, we thought we had a text which, while
                    retaining the basic thrust, had met all of Turner's objections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What were your conclusions at this point?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="Page0065"/>
                <p>COLBERT: The conclusion that in terms of military capabilities North Korea had a
                    distinct advantage was already pretty clear cut. Beyond superior fire power the
                    Estimate pointed to other significant assets: their capacity for surprise owing
                    to the concentration of their troops close to the DMZ, their terrific
                    communications security, and the location of their capital far up North whereas
                    Seoul, the hub of South Korean economic and political life, was very close to
                    the DMZ. Absent U.S. ground troops as trip wire or as part of the defense, North
                    Korean forces might well reach Seoul before the U.S. could bring its air and
                    naval forces fully to bear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Admiral Turner seemed to accept the basic thrust?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, or we would not have been able to submit the text to USIB. But
                    Turner then threw the USIB meeting into confusion, announcing that he was going
                    to take a footnote to some paragraphs drafted by the Navy which, as I recall, he
                    attacked as exaggerating North Korean capabilities at sea. Consternation ensued.
                    How could the DCI, in whose name Estimates were issues, take a footnote? Faced
                    with this anomaly, DIA and ONI succumbed, agreeing that Turner could substitute
                    his text and they would take a footnote. The footnote having been provided,
                    there seemed to be no further obstacle in the way of issuing the Estimate. But
                    Turner had other ideas. He would not give the text the authority of an Estimate.
                    It would merely be an intelligence annex to the PRM.</p>
                <p>I suppose this could have been regarded as a distraction without a difference.
                    Nevertheless, for me it was the last straw. For the DCI to disavow the dedicated
                    efforts of a host of analysts and the views of his USIB colleagues was the final
                    manifestation of a kind of behavior I felt I couldn't live with anymore. Unlike
                    some of my equally horrified colleagues, I had a place to go. In principle, I
                    had a right to return to the Department. I had been detailed to CIA for two
                    years. I had served three. But I had to find a job for myself. Here luck was
                    with me. I had some contact with EA's new assistant secretary Dick Holbrooke
                    whom I had briefed on Vietnam when he was a staff assistant to the
                    Undersecretary and we had attended a number of the same meetings after he
                    resigned from the foreign service and became editor of Foreign Policy. I had
                    much closer connections with his senior deputy Bill Gleysteen whose deputy I had
                    been in INR and with whom I had been working on the PRM. So, in the event, on
                    May 5, 1977, I entered on duty in EA.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your return to State end your involvement in the
                        military balance issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0066" n="Page0066"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I remained involved but much less so. When I first arrived in EA, Dick
                    was uneasy about letting me get anywhere near Korea, the word having got around
                    a bit that I had left CIA because of my resistance to Turner's efforts to
                    distort intelligence to support Carter's policy. This was a charge you couldn't
                    pin on him; his demands for change were always directed toward individual
                    aspects of the analysis. And in any case, as I have said, this is not why I
                    left. Dick's uneasiness passed very quickly, however, and, with my friends at
                    Langley keeping me informed of the results of the continuing intelligence
                    effort, I was involved from time to time in EA's work on the subject. In the
                    end, of course, the policy was suspended in February 1979 without any
                    significant withdrawals having been made.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Back to your arrival in EA in May 1977. What was your
                        job?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: First of all, it was outside the regular table of organizatiothe kind of
                    slot political appointees are entitled to fill in the early days of a new
                    administration. So, a title had to be invented and this was Policy Planning
                    Coordinator. Policy was certainly involved, planning in a fairly short-term
                    sense, and coordination most of all; drafting and putting together contributions
                    to departmental and inter-agency policy papers; reviewing policy papers
                    involving East Asia drafted in the NSC and DOD; and drafting speechea new
                    enterprise for me and one that kept me a lot busier than I had anticipated.</p>
                <p>Because I was supposed to be planning, I also became EA's liaison with the
                    Planning Staff. Attending Planning Staff staff meetings produced little of EA
                    interest since, under Tony Lake, the preoccupation was largely with Africa. More
                    closely connected to my interests and EA's was the opportunity to attend the
                    regular meetings between members of the Planning Staff and their Japanese
                    counterparts and other Gaimusho officials. These were held alternately in
                    Japausually at some very attractive resort hoteand in Washington. Discussions at
                    the meetings were always interesting and stimulating and I was able to take
                    advantage of the trip to do other business in Tokyo.</p>
                <p>Also outside EA, I had some responsibility for keeping an eye on the East-West
                    Center in Honolulu, partially financed by USIA, which Holbrooke regarded as part
                    of his parish. This involved little more than occasional discussions with USIA
                    people and visits to the Center when I was stopping in Honolulu en route to
                    Asia.</p>
                <p>And, in the simplest terms, it often came down to doing whatever Holbrooke or one
                    of the deputies wanted me to do at any given moment.</p>
                <pb facs="0067" n="Page0067"/>
                <p>It must be evident that this was a job full of pitfalls and dangers. Almost
                    anything I was called upon to do might be something a Country Director or some
                    other officer might feel was treading on his toes. But I think I had certain
                    assets that made the job less difficult than it might have been. First of all,
                    I'd been around for a long time. I wasn't somebody brought in from outside
                    thinking “now is my time to make the brains run on time.” And also, because I'd
                    been around for a long time, I knew most of the people and they knew me. Some of
                    them had even worked for me in INR. Plus, I was getting close to retirement so I
                    wasn't seen, I think, as a competitor, somebody out to get someone else's job or
                    to the get the job somebody wanted to get after he left the job he had. So I
                    think it worked out pretty well in terms of sometimes getting into other
                    people's business without getting them upset.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you find working under Dick Holbrooke?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Terrific. I get along very well with Dick who could be difficult.
                    Partly, I'd known him a long time. Partly, I think, again, because I was not
                    competitive, I was, in his eyes, much older almost ancient, in a way a link with
                    history. And it turned out that the kinds of things he wanted me to do, I was
                    able to do. And I could get away with saying things to him other people
                    couldn't. When Dick would shout at me, as he would at other people, I could say,
                    “Dick, you shouldn't talk to me that way. Remember, I'm three years older than
                    your mother!” and, as Dick had a strong sense of humor, it worked. He was
                    brilliant, absolutely brilliant. I think I learned more about operating in the
                    real world in the three years I was working with Dick than I had in my entire
                    earlier career.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Most people who have worked closely with him have
                        tremendous respect for him. He might be a shouter and a yeller, but the
                        dominant reflex is one of admiration. The man was very good. He was an
                        operator, but it's healthy to work for an operator.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: He also did things that were not in and of themselves of great
                    importance but were valuable in terms of advancing EA's interests. For example,
                    he would invite people from the Hill or otherwise politically prominent to EA
                    staff meetings. They appreciated the attention and it gave EA greater
                    entr�e.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm told he could carry on a policy discussion, be on the
                        telephone, and watch television all at the same time.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0068" n="Page0068"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes that's true, but it was not always useful. For some people, visitors
                    especially, this meant that they weren't getting the attention they deserved.
                    But, more significant in policy terms, Dick was both imaginative and creative
                    with a strong sense of what was about to be important. And this was very much
                    needed in what were still the early days of the Carter administration. The war
                    in Vietnam was not far behind us, leaving Southeast Asians concerned about our
                    future course and American seeing Southeast Asia as a disturbed and dangerous
                    place. Under Nixon, the Guam doctrine and the opening to China had eaten away at
                    the two philosophic pillars supporting an active role in Southeast Asithe domino
                    theory and the Chinese Communist threat. So while we were already on a new
                    course in China and the major elements of our alliances with Japan, Australia,
                    and New Zealand remained intact, future policy toward Southeast Asia remained in
                    doubt. As yet the Carter administration had made clear only its desire to
                    normalize relations with Hanoi while important Democrats were talking about
                    abandoning the Philippine bases and ending our commitments to Thailand.</p>
                <p>In this vacuum, certain of our policies elsewhere seemed positively threatening
                    to our Asian audienctroop withdrawal from South Korea, approaches to the Soviet
                    Union about mutual withdrawal of the Indian Ocean, preoccupation with human
                    rights which seemed to overlook the PRC and the DRV while focusing on our
                    friends. Nor were fears of American abandonment of Southeast Asia confined to
                    Southeast Asians. They were felt also by our East Asian allies, Japan in
                    particular.</p>
                <p>When Secretary of State Cyrus Vance was invited to address the Asia Society an
                    opportunity was provided to assuage these fears, to convey to Asians America's
                    determination to remain a major actor in Asia and to demonstrate to Americans
                    that East Asia was no longer an area of fearsome enemies and economic and
                    political disorder but instead was politically stable, economically flourishing,
                    and a valuable trading partner. Drafting this speech, to be delivered at the end
                    of June was to be my first responsibility in my new job. But this meant merely
                    that I was the one person at the bottom of an inverted pyramid required to be
                    responsible to any number of people in EA, in Public Affairs, in the Planning
                    Staff, in the Secretary's staff, others I no longer remember, and finally the
                    Secretary himself, who, the night before the speech, did some rewriting of his
                    own. Finding the balance between not inadvertently seeming to abandon policies
                    we wished to preserve by failing to repeat old platitudes and seeming to
                    enunciate new and dynamic policies was not easy. One comment I particularly
                    remember came from Tony Lake. “What is the headline”, he asked as a group of us
                    were going over an early draft. “Vance goes to New York” he answered himself. It
                    was not a fun job and I wound up with half a safe drawer full of drafts. But the
                    speech, although in many ways little different from Ford administration
                    post-Vietnam speeches proclaiming “the Untied States is and will remain a
                    Pacific power”, did emphasize Southeast Asia and especially ASEAN, with which we
                    had not yet had any kind of relation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was the problem? Was there some concern somewhere
                        that ASEAN was a bad thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0069" n="Page0069"/>
                <p>COLBERT: No, the absence of a relationship was largely ASEAN's doing although it
                    also resulted from less American attention than might have been useful. When
                    ASEAN began to establish relations outside the organizatiothe so-called dialogue
                    relationshipit didn't wish to be seen as moving into the arms of the United
                    States. This was still the time when the USSR and the PRC were attacking ASEAN
                    as another SEATO while ASEAN characterized itself as independent and neutral. So
                    establishing dialogue relationships was a very slow and cautious process,
                    starting small with Australia and New Zealand, later moving on to Japan and the
                    EC.</p>
                <p>The new emphasis on ASEAN continued and was strengthened in Dick's speeches (a
                    much more satisfying occupation for me since only he, I, and others in EA were
                    involved). But beyond speeches, other developments were to make our relations
                    with ASEAN much more substantial. Our first dialogue meeting was rather a
                    let-down from the AEAN point of view. While the ASEAN countries were represented
                    by their foreign ministers, we were represented by the undersecretary. At the
                    second meeting in Washington in 1978, however, the secretary attended as did a
                    number of other Cabinet members and every effort was made to lend importance to
                    the occasion. In the same year, the completion of the Philippine base
                    negotiations confirmed our continuing interest and presence in Southeast Asia as
                    did Vice President Mondale's confirmation, during his ASEAN trip, of the U.S.
                    security commitment to Thailand, in doubt since the dissolution of SEATO during
                    the previous administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any objections elsewhere in the Department to
                        our getting closer to ASEAN?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: There were some concerns in the economic bureau that we might go too far
                    in responding to ASEAN's third-world type economic proposals. But otherwise, the
                    East Asia Bureau had a relatively free hand in developing Southeast Asia policy.
                    As is well known, China policy was a battleground in which State was ultimately
                    defeated by the NSC. Japan policy, then concerned largely with trade issues,
                    involved a host of other players, State's own economic bureaus as well as
                    Commerce, the U.S. Trade Representative, and others.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And on the other hand, the ASEAN states became much more
                        comfortable with the United States?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, and, although we were not able to satisfy ASEAN's third world type
                    economic demands, our bilateral economic relationships became increasingly
                    active and healthy. We also demonstrated our friendships in tangible ways.
                    During the Vietnamese refugee crisithe flight of the boat peoplwe relieved the
                    ASEAN countries of heavy burdens through our leadership in and participation
                    with others in refugee resettlement and financial support. And, in response to
                    the Vietnamese invasion of Cambodia, we were loyal supporters of ASEAN's
                    leadership in the effort to bring about Vietnamese withdrawal.</p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="Page0070"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your principal preoccupation during this perio1977,
                        197with ASEAN or did you get involved in other issues?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Oh yes. I've talked so much about ASEAN, I suppose, because it continued
                    to be one of my major interests after I retired from the Department. But I've
                    already talked about my continued involvement in matters relating to the Korean
                    military balance. And my miscellany of functionspeech writing, reviewing,
                    coordinating, filling gapinvolved me also with most of the rest of East
                    Asia.</p>
                <p>I was once even admitted into the sacred precincts of China policy. Vance's first
                    trip to China in August 1977 called forth the usual flock of briefing papers,
                    including a numbecovering what were known as global issues. In the past, these
                    were written by the China desk and not even cleared with other concerned desks.
                    Now things were to change. Under my guidance, the other bureaus were to prepare
                    their own briefings which I was then to review. To enable me to do my job, I was
                    given access to one part of the China files which were usually closed to
                    outsiders. This was very exciting. Or so I thought until I went through the
                    files and discovered that all the things the Chinese were saying to us on these
                    global subjects, they were also saying to all sorts of other visitors, officials
                    and otherwise. More interesting were the comments Kissinger had scrawled on the
                    margins of some of the telegrams. I was particularly gratified to see on one of
                    them “X is a horse's ass” my opinion exactly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you run across the Human Rights Bureau and Pat Derian
                        at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Pat was inescapable. EA was very much in her sights since three of our
                    countrieSouth Korea, the Philippines, and Indonesiall important to the U.S. in
                    one way or another, were undeniably serious human rights offenders. I think we
                    came out pretty well in arguing that we needed to maintain a sensible balance
                    among our various interests and that quiet diplomacy could be a useful tool.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can we move on now to April 1978 when you entered a new
                        job as Deputy Assistant Secretary?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="Page0071"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Not so much a new job but, as I'll explain, an additional one. But the
                    first thing to be said is that my elevation had nothing to do either with the
                    needs of the Bureau or my own sterling qualities. You may remember that at this
                    time Vance had ordered each of the regional bureaus to appoint a woman to the
                    front office. This may have been easier for EA than for some of the other
                    bureaus. I was already part of the landscape and, even more important, no one
                    had to be displaced to make room for me because it turned out that we had an
                    empty DAS slot, one that had not been lost when the Vietnam Working Group was
                    dissolved, merely put in storage.</p>
                <p>From Dick's perspective, I could just go on doing what I had been doing under a
                    new title. But others, and I became one of them, believed I should have a
                    regional responsibility. Turning Australia, New Zealand, and the Pacific Islands
                    over to me was easy enough since neither the Northeast Asia nor the Southeast
                    Asia deputy had any possessive feelings about the South Pacific. For the
                    resourceful Holbrooke, this became an opportunity to portray the appointment of
                    a senior officer to this new position as the administration's recognition of the
                    importance of the countries concerned. There was no question, however, that I
                    would also continue to carry on many of my old responsibilities. In one sense
                    indeed my availability was extended. When for some reason, deputy assistant
                    secretary rank was needed to do some job and the appropriate officer was out of
                    the country or otherwise unavailable, the job often became mine. Thus I found
                    myself having to bone up on the evidence that the Lao government was using
                    poison gas (Yellow Rain) against its opponents (evidence I did not find wholly
                    persuasive) in order to testify before the House Foreign Relations
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>In continuing to carry on my old responsibilities while taking on new ones, I was
                    singularly fortunate in my two country directors, Frank Bennett for Australia
                    and New Zealand, Bill Bodde for the Pacific Islands. They were both very
                    experienced foreign service officers, very intelligent, very self-starting and
                    more than capable of compensating for any failure of attention on my part. The
                    cordial relationship between Vance and the foreign ministers of Australia,
                    Andrew Peacock, and New Zealand, Brian Talboys also helped while Peacock and
                    Holbrooke were kindred souls.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you took over, what was the state of U.S. relations
                        in your area?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0072" n="Page0072"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Australia and New Zealand, of course, had long been our allies in the
                    ANZUS pact. We had fought together. We were joined by common traditions and
                    language. Although the relationship was not without problems, these were largely
                    trade related. However, at the time I took over, the atmosphere between the
                    Carter administration and the Australian government was not very good. Carter
                    had somehow learned that when he first took office Prime Minister Fraser had
                    referred to him dismissively as just a peanut farmer. Then, when Vice President
                    Mondale visited Australia, he and Fraser had a very contentious debate over meat
                    exports. Strong words were exchanged and all this was leaked to the press.
                    However, an opportunity to improve the atmosphere arose when it became necessary
                    to send a delegation to the funeral of former Prime Minister Robert Menzies who
                    had also been something of an international figure. With Prince Charles
                    representing the Queen and at least one former British prime minister in
                    attendance it was important that the head of the American delegation be someone
                    of distinction. Fortunately, Governor Harriman was willing to represent the
                    United States. A private dinner with only the Frasers and the Harrimans went
                    extremely well and the cloud over the relationship evaporated.</p>
                <p>My life in the intelligence business had never required me to travel as an escort
                    to some very important person, but I knew from my foreign service friends how
                    difficult such an assignment could be. I was extremely fortunate that my first
                    experience can only be described as a delightful one. Harriman was totally
                    attentive to duty, read his briefing book carefully, and was interested enough
                    to ask very good questions. He was equally attentive to his next assignment, a
                    disarmament conference immediately following the funeral. For this, he had with
                    him two fat briefing books full of obscure initials. He was completely
                    understanding that I was well out of my field when I was unable to translate
                    some of them.</p>
                <p>Although I had had some contact with the Governor when he was EA's assistant
                    secretary, I had never met Pamela Harriman. In her relations with those of us
                    traveling with her, she was far from the bitchy type pictured in the gossip that
                    emerged from her own social circle. She was totally helpful, cooperative, and
                    charming. She was also, of course, very astute politically. In talking about
                    Malcolm Fraser and his resemblance to General de Gaulle, she made very vivid the
                    Downing Street atmosphere during World War II.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I've gotten some extremely complementary comments about
                        her from people I've interviewed who served with her when she was ambassador
                        to France. They all describe her as a very effective representative.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: I think she had what was perhaps a distinctively aristocratic British
                    view of how you treat your staff, how you deal with the people who are working
                    for you and with you as opposed to the way you relate to your social
                    competitors.</p>
                <pb facs="0073" n="Page0073"/>
                <p>Not long after the Harriman trip, Prime Minister Fraser's visit to Washington
                    opened the way to another gesture catering to his sense of his own importance.
                    We were in a meeting in the cabinet room and Fraser was being very gracious and
                    complimentary indeed. Mondale, who was sitting next to Dick, passed him a note
                    and he passed it to me. It read simply, “Do I know this man?” A point came when
                    Fraser was clearly about to invite the President to visit Australia.
                    Intercepting him, Carter asked, “How would you like me to send my most senior
                    ambassador, Mike Mansfield, to talk with you and your people about the situation
                    in Asia and the world?” Well, what could Fraser saoh yes, indeed. So in due
                    course we went to Australia and New Zealand in November 1978 where Mansfield had
                    very good conversations with Fraser and Prime Minister Muldoon of New Zealand
                    and other officials in both countries. Like the Harrimans, although very
                    different in personality, the Mansfields were great to travel with.</p>
                <p>By the end of the Carter administration, relations with Australia were so good
                    that Fraser offered us home porting in Perth for an American warship. For EA,
                    this was an intriguing idea, a way of cementing the security aspects of the
                    ANZUS relationship and as a possible fall back for the Philippines. But the
                    Navy, concerned only with steaming time to the Near East, would have none of
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about New Zealand? Didn't we have a nuclear problem
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: It was one that came upon us full force later on, but that we could
                    already anticipate. Anti-nuclear sentiment was very strong among the New Zealand
                    public and in the Labour Party which was widely expected to succeed the
                    conservative Muldoon in office. Visits by nuclear powered or nuclear armed
                    warships were the particular targets in our case and this meant any U.S.
                    warships since our policy was “neither confirm nor deny.” Accordingly, in my
                    several visits to New Zealand during this period, I did a good deal of talking
                    to Labour Party leaders, some of them with very strong anti-nuclear views,
                    others less fixed in their own positions but very conscious of the views of
                    their constituents. I was not very persuasive but my ego was fed by a headline
                    in one of the leading New Zealand newspapers, “Colbert fails to change Labour
                    Party policy.” Only in New Zealand could Colbert make the headlines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the Pacific Islandwhat kinds of problems arose
                        there?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0074" n="Page0074"/>
                <p>COLBERT: Probably the first problem was that this was an area about which I knew
                    absolutely nothing. In Australia and New Zealand many of the people I was to
                    deal with in my new job, I already knew from my years in the intelligence
                    business. I had traveled in both countries and was reasonably well acquainted
                    with their history, politics, and their relations with each other. On the
                    Pacific Islands it was difficult even to educate myself. Before independence, as
                    dependencies of France, Britain, Australia, and New Zealand subject to some
                    degree of UN oversight, State Department responsibility such as it was had
                    rested largely with the International Organization bureau. So there were few
                    records of earlier dealings on which to draw. There was also little in the way
                    of outside literature; most of what was then available having been the work of
                    anthropologists. It wasn't until well after my retirement when I was asked to do
                    a small book by the Asia Society, that I learned many things it would have been
                    useful to know in 1978.</p>
                <p>That said, however, it is also fair to say that the problems that arose in my day
                    in our dealings with the Pacific Islands were largely of post-independence
                    origin or had to do with negotiations with our own Trust Territory of which
                    there was already a long and painful history. We were, of course, anxious to
                    demonstrate a constructive interest in all these newly-independent islands, to
                    show them that we were their friends. However, there were two obstacles in our
                    patone relating to fisheries the other to territorial claims. Neither of these
                    problems was resolved during my tenure. Nor were we able to conclude our
                    negotiations over the future status of the Trust Territory. On all three
                    problems, I came in the middle and left in the middle.</p>
                <p>The territorial problem arose from formal U.S. claims, dating from a much earlier
                    period, to sovereignty over a number of small islands that were now within the
                    boundaries of four newly-independent states. These claims were not easily
                    renounced since to do so required congressional approval. Defense considerations
                    also complicated the negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was this the strategic denial doctrine intended to keep
                        the Soviets from establishing bases there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes. And, since concern with this possibility was deeply rooted in
                    Defense Department and congressional thinking, nothing was to be gained by
                    arguing its unlikelihood. To satisfy these concerns, we needed to obtain from
                    the island states commitments that foreign countries would not be permitted to
                    bring warships into their territorial waters or harbors without U.S. consent.
                    From the point of view of the countries concerned and their island neighbors
                    this was an infringement on their sovereignty. From the point of view of New
                    Zealand, which regarded itself as part of the island world, the United States
                    was introducing the Cold War into an area where, hitherto, it had been absent.
                    Once we succeeded in negotiating a treaty, congressional action did not follow
                    quickly. The first of the four was not signed until 1991, a year after I
                    retired.</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="Page0075"/>
                <p>The tuna issue was much more important and of much wider concern to the island
                    countries. For most of them, tuna was their one commercially important resource
                    and now, under the Law of the Sea Treaty, they had their first chances to profit
                    from it. Under the treaty in their economic zone (200 miles from shore) they
                    could now regulate the fishermonopolized by distant water fisherlicensing,
                    setting fees, quotas and other conditions. This, however, was unacceptable to
                    the United States because under American legislation we could not recognize
                    coastal state sovereignty over highly migratory species and tuna was nothing if
                    not highly migratory. Not only were we precluded from recognizing the right of
                    coastal states to regulate the tuna fishery, but also, if any American vessel
                    were confiscated or fined for violating coastal state regulations, the U.S.
                    government was required both to compensate the owner and boycott fish exports
                    from the offending state. However, the legislation also seemed to offer a
                    solution. It also provided that we could recognize the regulatory rights of the
                    island states if they and we were part of a regional organization that issued
                    licenses and otherwise regulated the catch. Indeed such an organization was
                    already in being for the eastern Pacific tuna fishery. Now we sought to persuade
                    the Pacific island countries, already organized in the Pacific Forum, to engage
                    in a regional fishing organization of which the United States would be a member.
                    But we were not successful. The island states resented our policy as an affront
                    to their sovereignty and regarded American tuna fishers as little better than
                    pirates. They were concerned that we would dominate to our own interest any
                    organization of which the United States was a member. And finally not all of the
                    island countries really wanted a regulatory agency that would assign quotas;
                    some countries, like Papua New Guinea, were very rich in tuna, well aware that
                    in the waters of some of the Polynesian countries there were no tuna at all, and
                    not enthusiastic about sharing with less endowed neighbors. So, when the Forum
                    Fisheries Agency was organized in 1978, the outcome from Washington's point of
                    view, was totally non-productive. Membership was confined to the Pacific Forum
                    itself of which only Australia and New Zealand were non-island members. It had
                    no regulatory functions being limited to research-type activities. U.S. efforts
                    to alter the situation were not successful until 1988, long after I had
                    disappeared from the scene.</p>
                <p>The other major problem in which I was involved had to do with the future status
                    of the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands (TTPI) former Japanese colonies
                    placed under U.S. administration at the end of World War II. When I came on the
                    scene, negotiations, under way since the Nixon administration, had made it
                    evident that, if the various island groups making up the territory were united
                    in anything, it was in the desire that future relations with the United States
                    should involve semi-sovereignty but continued economic support. The principal
                    issues at the time revolved around the extent of such support, the degree to
                    which its utilization would be subject to federal government review, and the
                    extent and modalities of U.S. military use of Micronesian territory.</p>
                <pb facs="0076" n="Page0076"/>
                <p>The negotiating process, agonizingly slow and cumbersome, had beaten any number
                    of people into the ground by the time I came along. We were no longer
                    negotiating with a single Micronesian team but with three separate ones
                    representing three regions, each with somewhat different interests and each
                    represented by highly-paid American lawyers from big U.S. law firms. On the U.S.
                    side, the actors were even more numerous. In State, the overall responsibility
                    was vested in the Counselor, then Rozanne Ridgway, negotiating responsibility in
                    EA, but IO was also involved because any agreements would have to be approved by
                    the Security Council and, in the expectation of a Soviet veto, this was gong to
                    be difficult. And, while the Counselor was our leader, she wasn't anybody else's
                    leader. There was the equally involved and very possessive Department of the
                    Interior, the administering authority. And, of course, the Defense Department,
                    not to mention other cabinet departments with programs of one kind or another in
                    the islands. Hoping to provide leadership and cohesion, the Carter
                    administration had established the Office of Micronesian States Negotiations
                    headed by a special representative of the President with ambassadorial rank. I
                    may have contributed something useful to the process but, if I did, I certainly
                    don't remember what it was.</p>
                <p>Despite these frustrations, my Pacific Islands assignment had its rewards, not
                    the least of them a visit to Fiji and Papua New Guinea as escort to Andrew
                    Young, then our ambassador to the United Nations. It began as simply a trip to
                    Australia, the Australia-America Association having put Young at the top of its
                    list of desired speakers for Australian America week, formerly a one-day
                    commemoration of the battle of the Coral Sea but now a weeklong celebration with
                    events in a number of cities.</p>
                <pb facs="0077" n="Page0077"/>
                <p>Initially Andy was reluctant to accept the invitation. On crutches after a leg
                    operation, he was not enthusiastic about a long trip to Australia to be followed
                    by air travel from one end of the continent to the other. I was pretty
                    unenthusiastic myself. In New York, Andy's spontaneous and not always diplomatic
                    responses to press interrogations had been widely reported. I knew Australian
                    journalists to be aggressive and adept at laying traps for the unwary and, of
                    course, I would be responsible for any mishaps. Fortunately, Andy abandoned his
                    reservations when it was decided to put an air force plane at his disposal.
                    This, however, introduced new complications. To send Andy Young alone in a whole
                    plane only to Australia seemed wasteful of manpower and equipment. EA added Fiji
                    and Papua New Guinea. The bureau responsible for U.S. representation at the
                    Manila meeting of the United Nations Commission for Trade and Economic
                    Development (UNCTAD) made Andy the nominal leader of the U.S. delegation. This
                    aroused Pat Derian who objected that Andy's presence would seem to lend U.S.
                    sanction to the egregious human rights abuse of the Marcos regime. She was
                    mollified, however, by arrangements for Andy to meet in Manila with
                    representatives of the Philippine opposition. By the time we took off we had a
                    plane load: Andy, his wife, his New Yorkentouragthree or four people who had
                    been with him through the civil rights struggle and two security officers; a
                    number of people from various parts of the Department and AID with an interest
                    in one or another aspect of the trip; and some five deserving Democrats whose
                    turn it was to represent the United States on some pleasant occasion in a nice
                    place. However, it proved to be a congenial group with no prima donnas.</p>
                <p>My misgivings about the Australian leg of the trip were quickly dispelled.
                    Australian journalists were so completely preoccupied with the slowly-emerging
                    results of a hotly contested election in Victoria that they had no time for
                    provocative questions. My fears of disasters arising from Andy's refusal to read
                    his briefing books were also dispelled. His Australian audiences were more
                    interested in his views on the decolonization of Rhodesia process in which Prime
                    Minister Fraser had also been involvethan on anything covered by his briefs.
                    Since the UN had also been important in the transition from Rhodesia to
                    Zimbabwe, Andy was on home ground. Ironically, all I can remember of what he
                    said was his endorsement of Mugabe and his colleagues as well-educated,
                    intelligent, fully equipped to run a modern, progressive state. But the unhappy
                    outcome was far in the future. Meanwhile, Andy was enthusiastically received at
                    every event at which he appeared, all of them over-booked, one of the
                    expectations, I was told, that had led this quite conservative organization to
                    seek him as their speaker.</p>
                <p>His encounter with representatives of the Australian aborigines was quite
                    different. There he was audience rather than speaker in a dimly-lit, soon
                    smoke-filled hall in Perth. A succession of tribal leaders stood up to speak,
                    each repeating more or less what the others had said. Andy's people in
                    particular were completely dismissive: these people are totally tribal; they
                    have no notion of organization; they will never amount to anything.</p>
                <pb facs="0078" n="Page0078"/>
                <p>Another aborigine encounter took place on our return to Canberra. There one of
                    the few aborigines who had risen to a role in national politics asked for an
                    appointment. This was arranged for early in the afternoon and, when he asked for
                    a postponement until later in the day, this too was arranged but he was warned
                    than Andy might be a little late as, on doctor's orders, he would have to fit in
                    a swim after his previous appointment. This man, whose name I have forgotten,
                    had recently published a biography titled I am a Son of a Bitch. And so he was.
                    When he arrived in a room in the residence known as the library, he made it very
                    evident that he was annoyed that Andy was not yet there and that only his public
                    affairs officer, a tall an imposing woman, and I were there to greet him. Having
                    complained about Andy's absence, he remarked sarcastically on the not very
                    well-filled bookcases and then, in a more ingratiating tone, said to Andy's PAO,
                    “I know your people, I've been to Harlem.” Drawing herself to her full height
                    (he was a very little man) she replied coldly, “I was born and brought up in
                    Chicago.” If he had anything significant so say to Andy, it has escaped my
                    memory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You went on from Australia to Fiji and Papua New
                        Guinea?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Yes, and Andy was greeted even more enthusiastically there than in
                    Australia. Even before he arrived, he had a lot going for him. He was a black
                    like them who had won great prestige and high public office in a very powerful
                    country and he was, in addition, an ordained minister. This fact, which had
                    passed unnoticed in Australia, was of great importance in the islands which had
                    been very successfully Christianized by nineteenth century missionaries and
                    where clergy were important in politics and other fields outside the church. The
                    importance of religious observance, in fact, brought about a change in plans for
                    a welcoming ceremony in Fiji. Originally arriving on Saturday, we were to be
                    greeted at a village outside Suva with a traditional ceremony featuring native
                    dress, kava, and customary ritual. But when our arrival was changed to Sunday, a
                    church service was substituted and the traditional ceremony postponed until
                    Monday. So, in the biggest Protestant church in Suva, Andy preached the sermon,
                    his theme “we are all children of God.” With the hymns booming out of those huge
                    Fijian chests, it was a truly tremendous experience. And the reception was the
                    same wherever he spoke especially in the universities, one in Suva and one in
                    Port Moresby, where the audience was literally hanging from the rafters. It was
                    all quite astonishing. Meetings with the prime minister of both countries and
                    other high officials were of less note. Andy had been extensively briefed on the
                    fisheries problem in hopes that he would press our case but it was not something
                    he had any enthusiasm for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did things go in Manila?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0079" n="Page0079"/>
                <p>COLBERT: I would say, very curiously, very curiously indeed. Protocol events
                    aside, Andy had only two missions in Manila. One was as titular head of the U.S.
                    UNCTAD delegation. This required him only to deliver the U.S. opening statement.
                    The other was to meet with opposition activists, they having decided for reasons
                    of their own that there should be two meetings, one with a lay group, the other
                    with clerics.</p>
                <p>The meeting with the oppositionists was something of a surprise to me. There was
                    a really evident absence of sympathy on both sides. On the Filipino side, I
                    seemed to see a trace of resentment at having to deal with someone they seemed
                    to see as of lower social status, ambassador or not, certainly no apparent sense
                    that they were fellow freedom fighters. And, on the side of Andy and his people,
                    almost contempwhat's the matter with these people? They keep complaining about
                    what the United States should do. Don't they realize they've got to do it
                    themselves?</p>
                <p>Of Andy's other calls, the only one I remember was a one on one with President
                    Marcos. Here were these two very important men sitting in very important chairs
                    in a huge room otherwise inhabited only by more important chairs and me. There
                    they sat exchanging highly elevated thoughts on very big subjects but, for the
                    note taker, nothing that needed to be preserved. And, all the while, Imelda kept
                    marching through with small groups of people in tow for all the world like a
                    tour guide.</p>
                <p>Then she had her own turn, with very little notice inviting us all to lunch at
                    the Blue HousAndy's own delegation and the rather large UNCTAD group in which
                    African Americans were also well represented. We sat at any number of small
                    tables being served innumerable courses and entertained by singers and dancers
                    after each. One dance, billed as a southern Philippine tradition was performed
                    in blackface. In another performance, a bevy of young Filipinas in their
                    beautiful traditional dress arrived swaying and singing. And what were they
                    singing? Dixie! Every verse known to man. I could see Ambassador Murphy at the
                    head table stiffening with embarrassment. Our black colleagues, however, took it
                    all in stride. What they loved about the event was that it ended up with disco
                    dancing; all through the trip we had been searching in vain for a place to go
                    disco dancing.</p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="Page0080"/>
                <p>The irony of it all was that Andy unimpressed by the opposition came away very
                    impressed with Marcos. In his goings back and forth, he had frequently passed
                    through the Manila business district which was full of big, modern high rise
                    buildingbanks, hotels, and the headquarters of various enterprises. He found
                    this reminiscent of Atlanta where he attributed the success of integration to
                    the great rise in employment that came about because he, as mayor, had been able
                    to attract big business, banks, and hotels to the city. Sometime after the trip
                    he had drafted a telegram to Manila arguing for the need to understand the good
                    features of the Marcos administration, all it was doing in the way of economic
                    development. He had come by one day to show the draft to Holbrooke. But Dick as
                    usual was on two telephones so, to pass the time, Andy had wandered into my
                    office and asked my opinion. Well, I said, this might be okay with Dick but you
                    better show it to Pat. What happened after that, I have no idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was after the trip? Was Manila the last stop?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: For Andy yes. He had planned to go on to Tokyo which he had enjoyed
                    visiting earlier. But by Manila he was very tired and had decided to go home.
                    But I went on to Tokyo where I had appointments in the Gaimusho with officials
                    concerned with Japanese-South Pacific relations and others. From Tokyo I went on
                    to Seoul to touch base with Bill Gleysteenow our ambassadoand the embassy. At
                    this time, May 1979, some of the strain in U.S.-ROK relations had been eased by
                    the suspension of troop withdrawals in February and the announcement in April of
                    plans for a Carter-Park summit in the summer. In October, however, South Korea
                    was thrown into turmoil when President Park was assassinated by the head of his
                    intelligence agency and his security chief. Were you still there then?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, I had already left.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: Well, you may have been interested enough to follow events there and to
                    remember the turmoil that followed and the difficult problems we faced in a time
                    of rapidly moving and often confusing developments that ultimately eventuated in
                    the absolutist government of General Chun Doo Hwan. I needn't detail these
                    developments or our responses here. They are amply covered in Bill Gleysteen's
                    published account. Suffice it for me to say here that these events alternated
                    between extreme repression and total abandonment of constitutional institutions
                    on the one hand, and, less frequently, signs that a transition to civilian,
                    constitutional government might be possible. And that there were grave
                    difficulties in the way of determining appropriate and effective responses not
                    the least of which was that our strongest lever, the security relationship, was
                    clearly out of bounds.</p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="Page0081"/>
                <p>Here I would just like to touch on the policy-making process itself because it
                    was both unique and effective. Early in his term as assistant secretary,
                    Holbrooke had invented a device called the EA Informal. This brought together,
                    usually once a week, Dick, his deputies and representatives at the assistant
                    secretary or deputy assistant secretary level of DOD, CIA and the NSC. It had
                    been utilized to good effect on a number of occasionbut it was in connection
                    with the Korean crisis, when it included the Korea country director, that it
                    really proved its worth. Cutting through the bureaucratic maze, it brought into
                    continuous contact the senior action officers of the agencies concerned in
                    continuous review of developments on the ground and embassy comments and
                    recommendations and in debates over the alternatives. These could be heated but,
                    for all involved, the object was to arrive at recommendations that could be
                    passed up to superiors as having been agreed upon by their representatives. This
                    very collegial approach was very fortunately mirrored in Seoul where the
                    ambassador, the station chief, and the commander of U.S. forces enjoyed a
                    cooperative relationship that had not always prevailed in the past. My own role
                    in a process, not really completed until the Reagan administration, ended with
                    my retirement shortly after a brief trip to Seoul in June, together with the
                    Korea Country Director, just to go over the ground with Bill and his staff to
                    make sure that no gaps existed between the views of Washington and Seoul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it was at the end of June 1980 that you retired?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>COLBERT: From the Department, yes. But not from an active professional interest
                    in East Asia maintained for the next twenty years through teaching at the FSI
                    and SAIS, lecturing elsewhere, writing, working at the Carnegie Endowment, and
                    participating in a variety of other professional activities.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
