<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mfdipbib000023">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="interview">Interview with Anne Legendre Armstrong </title>
                <title type="series">The Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection of the Association
                    for Diplomatic Studies and Training</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Selected and converted.</resp>
                    <name>American Memory, Library of Congress</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Washington, D.C., 2006</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p type="lccn"/>
                <p type="sourcecol">Manuscript Division, Library of Congress </p>
                <p type="copyright">Copyright status not determined; refer to accompanying
                    matter.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Library of Congress makes digitized historical materials available for
                    education and scholarship.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This transcription is intended to have an accuracy rate of 99.95 percent or
                    greater.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change type="encoding" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2006-02-01"/>
                <change type="rev" when="2017-02-07" who="WicentowskiJC@state.gov">Migrate from
                    AMMEM2.DTD to basic TEI P5</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb facs="0001" n="Page0001"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Association for Diplomatic Studies and Training Foreign Affairs Oral History
                    Project Women Ambassadors Series</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR ANNE LEGENDRE ARMSTRONG</p>
                <p>Interviewed by: Ann Miller Morin </p>
                <p>Initial interview date: October 7, 1987</p>
                <p>Copyright Ann Miller Morin (used with permission)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Could we begin with your place of birth? You were born in
                        New Orleans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: In New Orleans, in 1927.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you tell me a little about your parents'
                        backgrounds?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. My father was from an old Louisiana family. Some of the earliest
                    settlers had been sugar planters on the Mississippi River and moved to New
                    Orleans in the 1800s. His father was a lawyer, James Legendre. My paternal
                    grandmother was English, Cora Jennings, with strong English ties. So it was a
                    mixture of the Gaelic and the English.</p>
                <p>My father grew up in New Orleans, was educated there, except for going away to
                    Princeton. They used to go to Maine in the summer. For the first time this
                    summer I went to Camden, where they used to go, and it's just lovely. The
                    better-off people in New Orleans, to get away from the summers, often used to go
                    to the Carolinas, or to Maine in this particular family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a long way.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's a long way. I gather they had long summers, too, like three
                    months or something. So my father was a coffee importer. In World War II, he
                    went into the Naval Reserve, returned, had emotional problems, unfortunately,
                    was very miserable and upset for years, and committed suicide.</p>
                <p>My mother was from Texas, and so I had early Texas ties. She was from San
                    Antonio; her name was Olive Martindale. She grew up in the little town of
                    Martindale, Texas, which is west of San Antonio—a tiny little town. When she was
                    in her early teens, her family moved to San Antonio, the big city, and her
                    father was in the mortgage business. She went away to a school that doesn't
                    exist anymore in Pennsylvania—Ogontz.</p>
                <pb facs="0002" n="Page0002"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How do you spell that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: O-G-O-N-T-Z. Ogontz had a summer camp in the White Mountains; she went
                    there. I would say that was her experience of being away from home from Texas
                    when she was young. She met my father at a Princeton weekend, I think, and they
                    were married—I think it was about 1923 or '24—in San Antonio. Mother had never
                    had a career. She did a little writing after she was married, but, you know,
                    free-lance for the Junior League or some travel magazine or something. She was
                    interested in politics. It was the era of Huey Long. It is the political era I
                    remember. She was a member of the women who wanted a clean sweep. But really my
                    family was not very political.</p>
                <p>As you remarked, in college and in my teens, I was a Democrat. I was quite
                    liberal; I studied in the Marxist study group in Vassar. I wrote a little bit
                    for the papers at Vassar. My major, first, was drama, and then I decided that
                    wasn't for me, so I changed to an English major. I went away to boarding school
                    in Virginia, at Foxcroft, which was a very social kind of boarding school but,
                    luckily, gave a terrific education, I think. I never thought I'd have a career;
                    didn't plan on it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Traditional?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Very traditional.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever write for your school paper?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I wrote a lot. I wrote at summer camp, I wrote at school. My jobs
                    in New Orleans—my paying jobs—were as a reporter for the New Orleans
                    Times-Picayune for a couple of summers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then you also were an editor for Harper's Bazaar?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, no. That's lifting me up. I had been offered the assistant to the
                    literary editor of Harper's Bazaar, beginning in January of 1950, and that was
                    when I got married.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you didn't take that job?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0003" n="Page0003"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I didn't take that job. No, Carmel Snow, who was the editor in those
                    days of Harper's Bazaar, had known me, and offered me this job on the literary
                    end of Harper's Bazaar, which in those days was very good. They published good
                    stuff then.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you met your husband . . .</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I had met my husband earlier, in 19—oh, approximately 1942. I visited
                    a schoolmate, Helenita Kleberg, she was then. Her father was the head of the
                    King ranch, Bob Kleberg. I went to visit Helenita at the King ranch, in
                    Kingsville, Texas, and Tobin was there. The Armstrong ranch borders on the King
                    ranch. He was visiting, too, but at that point, four years was a big difference,
                    because he was in college and I was in high school. So I noticed him, but he
                    didn't take too much notice of me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From all I've heard, he is a very attractive man.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He is, indeed. Then he went away to war; he was a fighter pilot in
                    World War II. When he came back, he'd made a list of people he was going to ask
                    on a weekend in Texas, and I was, I think, about three-quarters down that list,
                    but the rest had been turn-downs. So I went on that weekend with him, not having
                    seen him in a couple years, and it was a whirlwind courtship. He asked me to
                    marry him right away; told me if I went and took this New York job, forget it,
                    that he wasn't about to afford to court me in New York. And so we were married
                    about five months later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was shortly after you graduated?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I went to Europe the summer of '49, saw Tobin again in November
                    of '49, and we were married in April of '50.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He knew what he wanted! Then is this correct? You had five
                        children in five years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. First child was born in '51, and then we had twins in that five
                    years, which partly explains it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They must have been a bit of a shocker since they were the
                        last.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0004" n="Page0004"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Well, if they'd been the first, it would have been a worse shock,
                    I guess. By then I was an old hand, and it turned out to be great; not that I
                    was happy at the time. But living in a remote place on a ranch, it turned out to
                    be the best thing that could have happened—having them all so close.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes. They must be—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Very, very close. I've never been so tired in my life. Anything after
                    that seemed easy. They lived right there on the ranch and were educated there,
                    in a one-room schoolhouse. I taught for a year, but I was a flop, so we got the
                    county to let us put in a schoolhouse, a school for the ranch children,
                    including all the ranch hands and our kids. It turned out to be a very fine
                    education. The children did well.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The older ones probably helped the younger ones?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was a one-room schoolhouse?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: One-room schoolhouse, and one teacher. It averaged about fourteen
                    kids.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you didn't send your children away to boarding
                        school?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I did when they were very young. Generally, when they were in the
                    seventh or eighth grade, we sent them to San Antonio, which had two good
                    schools—one for boys and one for girls. And unlike most boarding schools, there
                    were a lot of young children in those schools and quite a few from Mexico, which
                    was good. Our children are bilingual.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is this because of ranch life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, it's only eighty miles from the border.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's to get the children to be with other children,
                        perhaps; is this why so many young ones go to boarding school?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0005" n="Page0005"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, I would say a lot of it's because of the proximity of Mexico;
                    people from Mexico want their children to come up and learn English and get an
                    American education, so there are a lot of children from Mexico. Then a lot of
                    ranches—that's changing in Texas, but in those years, there were many more
                    children living on ranches than do now. Increasingly, ranchers live in town and
                    commute to the ranches.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but there can't be many ranches the size of
                        yours?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, well, I guess in Texas more than any state, but still,
                    percentage-wise, that's small. In our county, for instance, the average holding
                    is 50,000 acres. We have a half-a-million-acre ranch next to us, and the King
                    ranch is a million acres.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A half-a-million acres. Imagine!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, that's the neighboring ranch. The King ranch is a million. Our
                    ranch is 50,000. Our ranch is a family partnership. My husband is now the
                    majority shareholder; for years he wasn't, but he's worked. He decided he wanted
                    to be a rancher, and he's been on the ranch ever since he came back from World
                    War II.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Has he really? I wondered if I could go back just a little
                        bit to when you were a young girl. I want to ask you a couple of things
                        about your growing up. Did you have any brothers and sisters?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, a sister, who lives in Houston, and a brother, who's dead.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you tell me what position in the family you
                        are?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I was the oldest. A sister, eighteen months younger, and a brother,
                    ten years younger. Really, I think I was fortunate being the first born in that
                    my father always treated me and my sister as if we could do anything—more as if
                    we were boys in those very traditional times in a well-off, traditional
                    family.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Not having a son, you mean, for ten years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, not for ten years.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0006" n="Page0006"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. That's very interesting.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We even played football. My father was a football hero, and he'd take
                    my sister and me out to the park and play football with us on the weekends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You enjoyed this, of course?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kinds of games did you like?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I liked dodge-ball; I liked high jumping; then, later on, I played
                    field hockey. I loved sports—tennis, basketball.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Team sports?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I liked both—individual and team. I liked track.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Would you categorize yourself as having been a
                        tomboy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned that your brother died. Was this when he was
                        young?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. He died. He, too, committed suicide—tried to, failed; jumped off
                    the same bridge that my father did. He was in poor health after that, and he
                    died of a heart attack. Goodness, it's been about ten years now. He never was
                    well after that horrible thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, no. When you were growing up, was he a sickly
                        child?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not a bit, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your sister wasn't either? You were all healthy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: All of us were very healthy.</p>
                <pb facs="0007" n="Page0007"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No illnesses?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No illnesses.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You weren't kept out of school for any bad accidents?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, no illnesses whatsoever. One operation for a cyst when I was about
                    six, and that's the only thing I ever remembered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, well, good. You have a lot of energy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Always did have?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I've never much thought of it till I got older and people would
                    remark on it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That is something you have in common with all of your
                        sister ambassadors.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Really? That's interesting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is; it's very interesting. I'm sort of stumbling upon
                        these things as we go along.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, it must be fun to see some patterns coming.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of reader were you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Excellent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And early?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Early.</p>
                <pb facs="0008" n="Page0008"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Any special books you remember when you were little? The
                        kind of thing you liked?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, the Oz books, the Bobbsey Twins, Nancy Drew, Kipling, simple
                    poetry; later on, Stevenson. I adored Robin Hood. Later on, I guess about eleven
                    or twelve, Gene Stratton Porter, who you never hear about now: Girl of the
                    Limber Lost. Then I remember I read Gone With the Wind, because my mother had it
                    when I was about ten, I guess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You mentioned Gene Stratton Porter. Did you read the Anne
                        books, the Anne of Green Gables books?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, loved them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You loved those, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. The Secret Garden, that was Frances Hodgson Burnett.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Obviously, these must have made a big impression on your
                        imagination?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, I did love to read. I read a great deal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you wrote for your school, too. That is a very
                        early indicator, apparently. You can see why that would be very
                        important.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I loved school, except math. I got to like math later. I think it
                    was I had a scary teacher. But English has always been my favorite.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about languages? Did you study languages?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I took French. New Orleans is heavily slanted that way, and
                    luckily, the school I went to taught it at a young age. Then at Foxcroft, I took
                    a year of Spanish, which, of course, turned out to be very helpful later on.
                    I've always liked languages.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And do you speak Spanish?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0009" n="Page0009"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. The French is rusty; the Spanish is good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were a good student?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You graduated Phi Beta Kappa, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I always led my class. I think I must have been competitive, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have any influential teachers who became role
                        models for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I think the most influential teacher was an English teacher I had
                    at Foxcroft, an Irish woman, who taught us to see good writing in all sorts of
                    things. She'd take the shopping portion of the New Yorker magazine and make us
                    understand why that was marvelous writing, and she introduced me to the modern
                    poets—modern for that time—T.S. Eliot and Pound. So I guess she was the most
                    influential. I had a splendid chemistry teacher on the other hand, at Foxcroft,
                    who was more by the numbers, and made me see the joy of thinking in different
                    ways. I'd never thought in the way that science demands, and I loved it and went
                    on to take physics and biology and some other science, which I didn't naturally
                    star at, but I worked very hard at, and liked thinking that different way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very interesting that you are aware you were
                        learning to think in different ways.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Even at the time; that's not a retrospective thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, that's what's so unusual. What about World War II? Did
                        that impact much on your life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, my father left and my mother was very upset that he left. So I'd
                    say it was first awareness of family battles and unhappiness—and young men that
                    I went out with. But there was no terrible tragedy that impacted on my life from
                    that; nobody close to me killed. I was quite isolated—off in a boarding school
                    forty miles west of Washington, never went into town except to go to the
                    dentist, and so it was like being in a cocoon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So, of course, you couldn't do any war work?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0010" n="Page0010"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We did at the school. The head of the school was a remarkable woman
                    who did have an impact on me, Charlotte Noland—quite an activist, a traditional
                    Virginia lady in many ways, but a fearless woman and full of zest. Whether it
                    was fox hunting or—she's unusual; she turned out decisive girls if she had an
                    impact on them. She respected learning. She wasn't an intellectual by any matter
                    of means, so she helped me in non-intellectual ways. She made everything fun.
                    Whether it was a school game, she always would have the pizzazz and the fun and
                    the team spirit and the tradition. And she made you decisive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's an interesting point. I gather she was a definite
                        role model for you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Very much. Also, she never married. I think that was good for us
                    girls, that we saw a very attractive woman unmarried. She had white hair, but
                    the men obviously liked her; she had premature white hair. So you began to
                    think, “Well, there is life after spinsterhood.” [Laughter] “You don't need to
                    get married to be a wonderful woman.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In other words, you can be a whole person?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: You can be a whole person and a great woman and not be married.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Still, you conformed to the mold?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I was still very much a traditionalist, but she taught me some of the
                    first inkling that a woman can have a marvelous life and be just herself, and
                    not somebody's wife.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And that is something that one doesn't see too often.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, very rare, very rare. And yet she had all the graces that made her
                    acceptable to your parents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about your first interest in foreign affairs? Can you
                        recall when you became interested in the world beyond the U.S.?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, yes. Time did a good thing; at least I thought so. They gave a
                    prize in the high schools for the best essay on foreign affairs, and I won that.
                    My history teacher made me think about it, I would say, other than just personal
                    feelings, emotional feelings of people in the war; that really this was the
                    first analytical thinking about foreign affairs I'd ever done. That would have
                    been second or third year of high school.</p>
                <pb facs="0011" n="Page0011"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you would have been around fifteen?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: About fifteen. I don't think I'd had many serious thoughts. I'd always
                    liked the papers and the weekly magazines, say, since thirteen or fourteen. My
                    family was well read to that extent; was not an intellectual family. They were
                    interested in current affairs. Q: You were home until you went to Foxcroft?</p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I was home until I was twelve, at two different schools, both
                    private; one a rather progressive school, Metairie Park Country Day School. It
                    was more follow your interests. If you don't like multiplication tables, play
                    checkers or chess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Montessori?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, more. I didn't know what Montessori was then. Maybe a little bit
                    of John Dewey; and I loved it. But my father decided I wasn't being taught my
                    basics well enough, so he changed me to Newman, which had been a school for the
                    children in the Jewish orphanage, and had about half Jewish children, I'd say,
                    and highly motivated children. They were a lot of poor orphans, and education
                    was the way to a better life. It was a very, very fine education, less
                    imaginative by the numbers than the first school, probably a good
                    combination.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good combination. Did it bother you boarding out at
                        that young age?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, I didn't board. These were day schools, these two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But at the age of twelve, then you did?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I wanted to go away.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You wanted to go away?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. My mother, I would say, was the pushy one in my life, both for
                    education and what she felt was social advantage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That brings me to the point of asking you, were you close
                        to one parent more than the other, or did you feel close to both?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0012" n="Page0012"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I had more fun with my father. I think I was closer to my mother.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You looked up to both of them?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Both of them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your mother a role model? Or was your father a role
                        model?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I think they both were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They sound like positive people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, they were. They were both positive, bright, attractive, very
                    loving. I had a very good early family. Then after the war, it went to pieces.
                    It didn't hurt me so much because I was married, but I think it was very hard on
                    my sister and brother, because they ended up getting divorced before my father
                    committed suicide.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they? Which did not really have any impact on
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not much on me. I was over in Texas. Though it made me very unhappy
                    and I traveled back home a lot, trying to fix things, but it didn't take the
                    toll on me. I was grown and had my own life.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say they were both positive people. Were they
                        domineering at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not too. I think they had a very good balance between discipline and
                    giving you your head.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But they expected certain things of you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, they did. They cared a lot. I mean, you knew they were watching
                    you, and caring, and measuring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you compared to your siblings at all? Were the others
                        made to live up to Anne?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0013" n="Page0013"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I think it probably would have been tougher on my sister. My brother
                    was out of it as far as being so much younger, and the boy, versus two girls. My
                    sister, not being good in school, but being prettier and maybe more appealing, I
                    think things were—you know, they evened out. They were careful to do that
                    because I always had it so easy in school. But I think they were fair. My
                    sister, I don't think, thinks they were.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You wouldn't categorize either one of them as
                        authoritarian?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. We were corporally punished, we were spanked, but I don't think
                    ever unfairly.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That by your father or your mother?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Father.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You made the comment that things evened out because your
                        sister was prettier.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was your mother the kind of woman whose goal for her
                        daughters was that they should marry well?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And therefore being pretty was very important?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which was at that age—I mean—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That age, yes. She's much more that way than I am, but on the other
                    hand, I don't think it ended up hurting me. When I got married, she would have
                    much preferred I married somebody richer, but, you know, it didn't make me
                    unhappy, and she didn't try to change things.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0014" n="Page0014"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: She was a product of that Victorian idea, “Daughters marry
                        well”?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Daughters marry well, that's right. And never thought I would be doing
                    anything on my own, so your avenue to success in life is through your male
                    choice.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: After you were married and off on your own, did your
                        mother have any influence on you at all? Did you turn to her for—?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: In a helpful way, she would—when I was having the twins, for instance,
                    I had to live in the city in a hotel for a month because they threatened to come
                    early, and she came and stayed with me. I would say I was definitely never a
                    mama's girl, though.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you Daddy's girl?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, not in later life, because he was, you know, all messed up. I
                    don't think particularly in young life; maybe more. I'd say my mother was more
                    exacting than my father. Like so many fathers, you'd see your father at the fun
                    times. Your mother was all day long, and having to do the tough things as well
                    as the nice things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's true. I'm getting a feeling of a very lively family
                        and a caring family, and one where the children were encouraged.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Until I was in college, I would say it was just an ideal situation; it
                    was wonderful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were encouraged to use your abilities?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Very much so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Spread your wings?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: To stretch and try things, and work in the summers. There was a good
                    work ethic, though we were well off.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What sort of work did you do in the summers?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0015" n="Page0015"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Let's see. During the war, I remember, I worked in Touro Hospital as a
                    nurse's—well, it wasn't really a nurse's aide; I was too young for that, but I
                    remember it was the burn ward. It wasn't pleasant.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, no.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: And then two summers, when I was a junior and senior in high school, I
                    worked as a reporter. It was hard work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That was on the Picayune?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were in that field even before you graduated from
                        Vassar?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Now, wait a minute, wait a minute. I'm giving you wrong times.
                    No, no, no. The Picayune was—let me think. It was in college. I'm wrong. It was
                    my first two years in college. My third year, I went to Tulane and took courses
                    in the summer, which made me appreciate Vassar.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not very demanding. There again, my mother pushed me into the jobs and
                    paved the way. She knew the editor, George Healy. I was never made to feel—I
                    didn't feel badly that Mother had used her influence. I learned later that she
                    had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you didn't know it at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I didn't know it at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You married. You were very busy with your family and
                        everything. Did you have help in the home, I hope?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0016" n="Page0016"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, a lot of help where we live, and still have a lot of help. Here
                    it's mundane, but it's one of the reasons I can do what I do. I don't know how
                    anybody does it without it. Mexican-Americans are particularly lovely with
                    children, so I had a full-time nurse and a full-time cook.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This was the beginning of your interest in
                        Hispanic-Americans, was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I had no interest before, really.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When did you first become interested in Europe, that is,
                        visiting there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Let me think. I guess it was just when I went myself, really, summer
                    of '49.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Tell me about that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I tried to get a job there and I couldn't. It would have been a typing
                    job, and I wasn't good enough.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Where were you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: In Paris. I stayed over—I was supposed to come home in September;
                    stayed over an extra month trying to get the job, failed, and came home after a
                    summer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you remember going back and forth on a ship?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Don't you wish those days would return?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, it was wonderful and it was smooth; didn't get seasick; had a
                    heavenly time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you recall which ship you went on?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I can't.</p>
                <pb facs="0017" n="Page0017"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I just wondered if it were American or one of the great
                        French—?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We were in steerage, and I went with some college friends and my
                    sister. We had a ball.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'll bet you did. This was just to go visiting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, it was my graduation present.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, wonderful! And you used your French?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I went to Italy and England and France and Switzerland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The next thing I have on your write-up in Who's Who is
                        that you then became trustee of the Kennedy County, Texas, school
                        board.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. That isn't much of a job; it's an elected job. But in our county
                    there are a total of 600 people in our entire county. It's got trustees of this
                    school board, but it's a small job.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's an elected job, though?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It shows you how to run, I suppose. In between that and
                        the—you were busy with children, but at the same time, you were interested
                        in politics, weren't you, because these were the Eisenhower years?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I got mildly interested in the Eisenhower years and did a little
                    bit of political work in one of the towns near us, Raymondville, poll-watched
                    there. I would say my big interest didn't come until the sixties, though. I kept
                    the ranch books. Tobin and I really were at the ranch 99 percent of the time for
                    the first ten or twelve years that we were married and the children were growing
                    up. Then as they went off to school when they were about twelve, well, I began
                    to have more time. Tobin got a secretary instead of me, and so in the sixties I
                    began to be interested on the state level.</p>
                <pb facs="0018" n="Page0018"/>
                <p>The Republican party was very small then, so it was an ideal time to make strides
                    in politics. They really needed everybody they could get, and it was a very good
                    group of people, too, a bright group of people. I've seen since then that the
                    norm of politicians is not that good, but at that point, the people that were
                    getting the Republican party of Texas started were exceptionally able and bright
                    and of high integrity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They were all very idealistic, were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. They were effective in little increments. Idealistic, yes, they
                    were idealistic. They were also practical. John Tower was elected the first
                    Republican senator of a Southern state in years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, I remember when he was elected.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I rose through the state Republican party, became state vice chairman.
                    Started off as precinct chairman, which, again, was scarcely anything to do
                    because there were about five Republicans in our precinct. Became a district
                    committeewoman; that means congressional district committeewoman representing
                    the congressional district on the State Republican Executive Committee (SREC).
                    And then became state vice chairman, then became Republican national
                    committeewoman for Texas. That took me to the national scene for the first time.
                    You are then the state's female representative on the national committee. The
                    state has two—a male and a female.</p>
                <p>I liked it, and so when—then it was called vice chairman of the Republican
                    party—when that became vacant, I said to Tobin, “I would like to go for this.”
                    He was not happy about it, but he agreed. So I came up to Washington and I
                    called on Bob Dole, who was going to be the chairman. We knew in advance; Nixon
                    had given his blessing. Of course, I didn't realize then how much influence a
                    sitting president has on the party. I mean, it would have been Nixon's call; I
                    didn't realize that. Dole agreed to take me as co-chairman, and then it was made
                    an elective office. Before that it had been appointed, which was a tiny
                    plus.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Am I right in thinking that the name has changed from vice
                        chairman to co-chairman?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, it changed to co-chairman with Dole, and was elective for the
                    first time. I asked for that and got it. Because before then, the woman had just
                    been the “critter” of the chairman. The male chairman appointed the woman he
                    wanted. This time they agreed to let the committee vote on the vice chairman,
                    too, and make it elective.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0019" n="Page0019"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. How many members on the committee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, well, it was about 100 then. Well, how many states did we have
                    back then? It's two from each state, whatever the number of states was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I don't know whether perhaps there were extras from—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I don't believe so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the Washington group or whatever?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, they had observers from the Women's Federation and the Young
                    Republicans and the College Republicans, but they weren't—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What about Puerto Rico or the District of Columbia?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, not voting members.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Voting members are just from states. When you first
                        started out in politics, what did you hope to accomplish? Because it's a lot
                        of work.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right. By that time, I'd say my philosophy had solidified, and
                    I had come to the conclusion that, in general, government interference was not
                    healthy, that the more things that could be decided by the individual and the
                    county and the state level, rather than the federal level, the better. I had
                    also begun to believe in a strong national defense. I had become highly
                    skeptical of communist intentions. I'd become a conservative, in shorthand. What
                    I hoped to do was to put forward more of these ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. And this was when you first started. You weren't
                        interested in paving roads in Texas or that sort of thing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Local things did not interest me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's what I wanted to know. You were looking at the big
                        picture right from the beginning.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="Page0020"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, there were certain things that were highly personal, and I don't
                    think this is very good because it's kind of selfish. But the school, for
                    instance, interested me; our children were there and the ranch kids were there.
                    But in general, it was national and, increasingly, international issues that
                    interested me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your rise has been nothing short of meteoric.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It was possible, because I used to kid Sissy Farenthal, who was a
                    Vassar friend of mine, and she was a very liberal Democrat and was nominated
                    for—I guess it was president by the Democrats—Sissy and I used to kid, because
                    Sissy had to go through a big entrenched bureaucracy of the Democratic party of
                    Texas with many males in place who weren't about to want her to rise. I didn't
                    face that. I was in a highly fluid situation where there was opportunity for
                    rapid rise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very similar to what Eugenia Anderson encountered.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Did she?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Of course, it was the opposite party.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: You could get leadership opportunities quickly, rapidly, and you had
                    challenges just thrown at you, you know, as fast as you could handle them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you balance this with your family life?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I'd say I didn't notice any problems, because these were my—just
                    about—only time-consuming activities. I didn't do the things that I might have
                    done as a wife in a big city; I didn't do symphony this day, USO another,
                    Disadvantaged Children another. I had two big things I was doing—my family and
                    politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your husband have to fill in for you at home?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He did?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="Page0021"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He liked that. Having lived on the ranch since he was a little boy, he
                    adores it. It's everything, from his family tradition and the way of life he
                    loves, to being the only person who knows where the plumbing pipes are. I mean,
                    I didn't fix anything. If a cook had to be hired, he was used to hiring the
                    cooks. He was in charge. That is his family's ranch and had been for
                    generations. It wasn't so much my home as with most wives; it was his family's
                    place.</p>
                <p>And he's a wonderful father; that's the other thing. Besides feeling this is his
                    home, it's just—he's just a terrific father in every aspect of his kids'
                    lives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And nurturing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Nurturing. Very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very important. Well, let me ask you, when you
                        moved to the ranch, was it difficult for you to get used to that kind of
                        life? You had come from a big city.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I've often thought that that's one reason I got so interested in
                    politics; there would not be enough there to interest me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You're not yourself a ranching-type woman?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. I think if it were my responsibility, I could do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You could do it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But my husband wouldn't welcome my getting in the way, and I wouldn't
                    want to. I mean, it's his job. And he hasn't chosen—I mean, we talk about the
                    ranch and things. No, there isn't enough for me to do on the ranch.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is he interested in what you're doing?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, he's interested in politics.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And shares your convictions?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0022" n="Page0022"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. He's more conservative than I am. We have some arguments, but not
                    major ones; it's a difference of degree.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I see. Sounds like a marvelous marriage.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, it is. I mean, I couldn't have done what I've done if I'd had
                    another kind of husband. And also, if Tobin had been the one to be away a lot or
                    to aspire to things other than what he has, there might not have been time for
                    me to, or desire on my part, to do these other things.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Everything came together; you were the member of the
                        National Committee from Texas, you were co-chairman with Dole. Would you
                        mind, for the record, telling me a little of the things you did in that
                        position?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Traditionally, of course, you had the women to organize. It was
                    the only ticklish thing, that there was a thing called the National Federation
                    of Republican Women, which is a pretty autonomous organization made up only of
                    women, unlike the Republican party. You needed to get along with them because
                    they, too, were organizing the women for campaigns, for the long pull, for
                    teaching the women. It was a very interesting time for women, of course. My
                    predecessor had been an activist woman; Ellie Peterson was her name.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Ellie was terrific. When she went out, she spent a lot of time helping
                    me. It was the time of the Equal Rights Amendment; it was a time of great flux
                    for women, and that was of interest to me. It was disruptive to the Republican
                    party; I mean, it was an old split way back then between the more activist women
                    and the traditionalist women, who didn't want the Equal Rights Amendment. We had
                    huge battles over that. But in those days, pretty much my direct
                    responsibilities were with women's affairs. Now, in both parties, but even more
                    so in the Republican party then, women were welcome, mainly because we did so
                    much work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0023" n="Page0023"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: So our views on high matters of policy may have been hard to put
                    across, but as far as the nitty-gritty of politics, I'd say 80 to 90 percent of
                    that work was done by women. It was in an era when many fewer women were
                    working. It was the old era of volunteerism of middle-class and upper-class
                    women, so they had plenty of time to spend on politics. We did every aspect of
                    politics. I was not given, at that point, any particular responsibility for
                    Hispanics; I took a little bit, but that wasn't official. I liked working with
                    the Young Republicans and the College Republicans. I did that, and nobody
                    objected to it. Bob Dole was a very good chairman. He gave you a lot of autonomy
                    and flexibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In that campaign, the young were really getting out in
                        droves, weren't they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And the college students.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: They had the most ferocious politics of any part of the Republican
                    party; it's really interesting. The College Republicans are always—well, of
                    course, they like to be extreme; it's fun to be extreme when you're young. So
                    the battles were really bitter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you have to travel a great deal?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, traveled a lot. I got to know the United States in a way few
                    people ever have a chance to. That was one of the greatest things about that
                    job; I loved it. Went all over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you travel with the president?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Very rarely. In the campaign, somewhat, but it would mainly be
                    ceremonial when I was with him, when the party was showing unity, etc., etc. In
                    campaigns, usually, you disperse your assets to cover as many bases as you can.
                    So Dole would go one place, I'd go another, the president would go another.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You've been a delegate every time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0024" n="Page0024"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Except when you were ambassador. That must be very
                        exciting—a national convention—isn't it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It is, it is. I always think, “Next time I'm not going to do this; I'm
                    tired of this.” And then you get revved up and it is—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it just round-the-clock work, work, work?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, it is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you emerge exhausted and—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, now I've learned to pace myself a little better. As you get
                    older, of course, you don't have the same intensity. You get more mellowness and
                    balance. So I can't say I've been exhausted by the last couple of ones, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Do you do a lot of lobbying of delegates?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. It hasn't been necessary, except on platform, in recent ones,
                    because our candidate was pretty well known at the last go-round, to say the
                    least.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were the first woman co-chair of the Republican
                        National Committee?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you were the first woman keynote speaker—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In 1972. Would you tell me about that? How were you
                        selected, and so forth, to give that address.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0025" n="Page0025"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I don't really know, but a sitting president always calls those shots.
                    So who else was—Goldwater was one, I was one, and who was the third? Was it
                    Lugar? Maybe Lugar, Dick Lugar, who was then mayor of Indianapolis. I would have
                    to say they were touching different bases; they had three keynoters, which is
                    unusual. So Goldwater, I'm presuming, was the conservative wing; Lugar was the
                    bright, young face—the president's favorite mayor, he was known as—and here's
                    Armstrong, as a woman and the party leader. I don't really know how I was
                    chosen, but if I were analyzing it, I'd say that's what it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you think it was Nixon—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Nixon loved politics. So I'm sure—he was the kind of president that
                    okayed every detail, and he was very conscious of television. He was ahead of
                    his time in realizing the importance of that, so he picked it not only for the
                    politics, the party, but also how are these people going to be on television,
                    too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I must say, he certainly picked three winners.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He did. I remember he called me afterwards. Nixon was not a very
                    personable type person. He called me afterwards because he was impressed that it
                    had gone well on television. He was very objective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You got good reviews at the time. I remember watching it
                        and then reading about it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Right. Well, it was rare; I think most people were pleased it was a
                    woman. I was fairly young at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How did you decide what to say? Was there input from, say,
                        Bob Dole?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, there was input from the White House. And, too, besides being a
                    woman, I was chosen to speak for the South. I guess I have a little bit of a
                    Southern accent, not much, and so I spoke for the South in saying McGovern was
                    antithetical to things that most Southerners believed in; of course, the South
                    being much more conservative than the North and McGovern not being typical of
                    his party, which the presidential candidates of the Democrats have not been. The
                    party itself is more conservative than their presidential process allows.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that curious?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="Page0026"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Well, it stems from the McGovern era. When they put in primary
                    rules of representation—so many blacks, so many Hispanics, so many women, a
                    quota system—that heavily leverages it toward the liberals. That's why they're
                    having trouble getting presidential nominees who reflect the thinking of the
                    country. I can't say Carter was that much more liberal, but they're going to
                    have a hard time winning general elections.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I think that's become pretty evident to them,
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, but they've still got—they've changed some of those rules and
                    they've softened them. Bob Strauss and others, the more conservative elements,
                    have worked on it, but they've still got a very strange primary system.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How long did that speech run?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I don't know. It was short; I'd say certainly not over fifteen
                    minutes, probably ten minutes. I don't know, though. I don't even have a copy of
                    it, I don't believe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really? That must be on file somewhere.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, yes. The Republican National Committee keeps archives of those
                    things. Whether they put that on tape in those days, I don't know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were you frightened?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, but so were Goldwater and Lugar (I think was the other man). I
                    guess it was one of the more nervous times in my life, but once I started to
                    speak, I wasn't. I was shocked, because I didn't realize, having been in the
                    noisy audience before, that the poor speaker—your heart goes to your feet,
                    because I had not analyzed that nobody's going to listen to you on that floor. I
                    could look down and see all these people lobbying and gesticulating, and it
                    hadn't occurred to me before that the floor wasn't interested that I was
                    speaking to the TV audience. So I thought I'd been a flop.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: [Laughter] Did you practice first?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. They had a trailer house, I remember, and some nice pros, and so
                    I practiced three or four times with the little monitor so you could see
                    yourself. I'd never been on national TV, but I'd done a lot of TV in my years as
                    the co-chairman.</p>
                <pb facs="0027" n="Page0027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had not actually spoken in that huge a hall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, never had spoken in a huge hall, and had never done the easy thing
                    of putting myself in the shoes of the person up there seeing all this commotion
                    on the floor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, my word! That must have been quite something. You
                        could hear your own voice though, I hope, through all of the rattling—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, yes, yes. You could. That's hard. The mike was thoroughly normal.
                    That wasn't the upsetting thing. It was just seeing everybody scurrying
                    around.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you read it or did you have the little cue cards?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I had a teleprompter, which is a very effective thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Is it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. I had never used a teleprompter, so I had the speech, too, just
                    in case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would like, if you don't mind, to discuss how you came
                        to be chosen to be first woman ambassador to the Court of St. James, which
                        is a very big job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: You've asked me about one of the few mysteries as far as my jobs go in
                    my career, because almost every other job I've had, I've wanted and I've tried
                    for. Certainly that was true of being co-chairman of the Republican National
                    Committee; I asked for it. It was true of being a counselor for the president; I
                    certainly hinted broadly to the president that I would like it. And President
                    Ford knew I wanted to stay on after Nixon. This one is, really—I don't know,
                    because I had been out of public life. I thought I owed it to my family to go
                    back and be a wife and mother again. I was living that kind of a life in
                    Armstrong, Texas, when I got a very surprising phone call in December from
                    President Ford, asking me to be ambassador to Great Britain.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What was your immediate reaction?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0028" n="Page0028"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I was totally thrilled and totally surprised. I knew I wanted very
                    much to do it, but it took quite a while. I couldn't have done it, or wouldn't
                    have done it, if my husband hadn't agreed that he would go, and that meant then
                    we had to find somebody to run the ranch in his absence, because it's a family
                    ranch and we had to find someone that the rest of the family would be happy
                    with. That took about three weeks to get all those things settled.</p>
                <p>We had our eldest son working on a ranch in Venezuela, and he had just started
                    the job a few months before; adored it, but agreed to come back, and that was
                    hard for him. My husband was so upset by the idea that he literally got sick and
                    lost weight beforehand—in the months before we went over. But the happy end to
                    that story is that although he said that he would try to be there for all the
                    most important times that I needed him, he would have to go back every month to
                    help our son with the ranch and other business interests. The way it turned out,
                    he went back once from England to Texas and never went back again except when we
                    both went on vacation. He was very happy, very busy; made the friends that truly
                    are our best friends now. He agrees with me that was, if not the best time in
                    his life, one of the best times.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was there any initial reaction on his part? “No, this is
                        out of the question. We can't do this.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: There may have been, but he didn't say so to me. He listened to all my
                    arguments. We talked to lots of people we both respected. We both talked to our
                    son and the rest of our family, and he finally agreed, and agreed
                    wholeheartedly, as far as what he intended to do. But it did make him very
                    unhappy. When I was doing these jobs in Washington, he didn't have to be here. I
                    mean, he rarely came up. I would go home on weekends. But for this job, he'd
                    have to leave the ranch and be there. And there's no doubt that most males don't
                    like the idea of being three steps behind.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I know it. I can imagine, especially in such a visible job
                        as that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but he did do it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: And in a new milieu. I mean, neither one of us knew very much about
                    England; had very few friends there. It would be strange territory.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You say it's just a mystery; you don't know why—</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0029" n="Page0029"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It is a mystery. I don't know. I think President Ford genuinely wanted
                    to appoint more women, and he had worked with me for a number of years. And
                    then, of course, most recently I was his counselor in the White House. I think
                    he thought I could do the job, and he really was reaching out to find women to
                    give them top jobs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had left that job in the White House for personal
                        reasons, hadn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I had really wanted to leave earlier than that, but then Watergate
                    came. That was a horrible experience. And President Ford asked me to stay on,
                    really to help get the White House and him through that period; plus, in a way,
                    I wanted to sort of cleanse myself, as it were, so I stayed a few months with
                    him. It was just a wonderful experience in every way. He was marvelous to work
                    for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: From the tone of the letters in your correspondence at his
                        library, you seem to know him very well.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I do, and I have the highest regard and friendship for him. I see
                    him, oh, almost every month; we're both on a board together. And I adore Mrs.
                    Ford, so I feel close to them personally. He's really a very fine man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And she's a very courageous—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Really. I'm just so proud. She's always been a lovable person and a
                    dear, fine person, but what she's accomplished in recent years is extraordinary
                    and commendable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's remarkable. Well, you had the backing of many people,
                        which you didn't even seem to be aware of, for this job.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I didn't know anything about any campaign; and, in fact, if there was
                    a campaign, this is the first I've known it. Maybe I should have shown more
                    curiosity, but I never have known there was a campaign. In fact, it was
                    embarrassing, because a fellow Texan, for one, and probably some other people
                    that I don't even remember, but one man that I thought was a very good
                    candidate, had enlisted my aid, and I had written several people in his behalf.
                    But I never heard a word that anybody was backing me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, when you appeared before the committee—can you
                        remember about the Senate committee? Can you remember anything about
                        that?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0030" n="Page0030"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I remember that they were very reasonable and that I was asked very
                    fair questions. I thought it was a good experience. I had been warned that not
                    many would be there, so that wasn't a shock. I think most ambassador nominees
                    think everybody's there; all are going to be turning out with great curiosity.
                    The State Department had prepared me very well. I think they have a good program
                    for their nominees, for the administration nominees. I felt well prepared and at
                    ease.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Very good. At the State Department, at that point, they
                        did not yet have the program that they now have. I believe you yourself ran
                        it for a while, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I participated in one with Ambassador Dean Brown.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, I was not given that. They didn't have that preparation then,
                    which I think is a marvelous idea. No, but they had a very good person, a
                    woman—I can't remember her name—who was in charge of shepherding through the
                    nominees, and I felt that was very well handled.</p>
                <p>But, true, it would have been even better had I known more about what was going
                    to be expected of me later as an ambassador. I knew everything that—I mean,
                    enough to know what was expected at the hearing, but at that point, no, there
                    wasn't any cram school for what an ambassador should know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which they have now, and which Shirley Temple
                        [Black]—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Fine addition.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is good.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: And it's good for the State Department, too, and for the former
                    ambassadors. The one time I participated, I learned things. I was able to keep
                    up with what's going on in the embassies. Also, you find out what's going on in
                    the outside world through these nominees.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Can you recall who was on your Senate committee at the
                        time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0031" n="Page0031"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. I'd have to check that. I had known Mike Mansfield very well
                    through a Commission on Foreign Policy in the Reorganization of the Government
                    for the Conduct of Foreign Policy—what a name! I remember he was helpful. But I
                    don't remember who was there at the hearing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, the next thing then, you were getting ready—I
                        suppose you also went up to New York?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Went to New York on that program.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, this kept you very, very busy—running from one thing
                        to another. I understand it's a very frantic time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, but I think it's invaluable. I didn't feel that it was too
                    hectic.</p>
                <p>Going back to the program—the cram course—I've forgotten the proper name for
                    it—that the State Department gives now. That would have been—or certainly part
                    of it—very good to have given me before all these meetings at the CIA or with
                    the New York business group, etc., took place, because you could have
                    assimilated a great deal more. A lot of it hit you so fresh and strange that you
                    really didn't take it in as well as you might have.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It would have given you a framework?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It would have given me a framework.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you were running that course, was that under
                        President Carter?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Let me think. Yes, when I participated, it was under Carter; and there
                    were two of us. The main ones were Dean Brown, who was a true pro, of course,
                    and then myself. Later, Shirley took it over, and I thought, it's good to have a
                    mix of a political appointee and a career person. I think then everybody can
                    relate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And it was Brown and Black for a good long time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Does Shirley do it by herself now?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0032" n="Page0032"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, she doesn't do it alone now. I don't know whom she's
                        doing it with right now. She was doing it with Tony [Motley].</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, that's good.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: One of the ones that she was doing it with is now the head
                        of the Foreign Service Institute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's not George Vest?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No, Charlie Bray. George Vest is still the Director
                        General.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. A splendid man.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Your swearing-in ceremony seems to have been rather a
                        formal occasion.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It was much higher-profile than those things usually are. And, again,
                    probably several dimensions to this—I was close to the President and Mrs. Ford,
                    and it did highlight a high role for a woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. There was a great deal of press coverage at the time,
                        wasn't there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was very unusual.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: For such a, you know, big post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And our biggest ally. Other than Clare Boothe Luce, you
                        were the only woman who had ever been to one.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: To a major post.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: To a major post of that caliber.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right.</p>
                <pb facs="0033" n="Page0033"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And still are. Kenya has been elevated to a [class] one
                        [post], but we don't think of Kenya in the same [light], as far as being
                        allies, and so forth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's see, it was in the Cabinet Room. Now, where is the
                        Cabinet Room?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: The Cabinet Room is actually right next to the president's office—to
                    the Oval Office. It's in the west wing of the White House; it looks out on the
                    gardens. It's a beautiful room.</p>
                <p>Lewis Powell of the Supreme Court swore me in. He was a personal friend; somebody
                    that I'd got to know up here and liked very much.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, really? Who held the Bible?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: My husband.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This would have been in February '76. The time was 2:00
                        p.m. Here is a schedule routing memo. How many people were present, can you
                        recall?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, quite a lot of people. Do these ring any bells?
                        These people all got notices. Did they attend?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Cheney would have; he was chief of staff. Marsh, Dr. Connor, Dr.
                    Hoops, Mrs. Yates—that's interesting. I can't remember who Dr. Connor, Dr. Hoops
                    or Mr. Jones were. The White House staff, I presume.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Must have been, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. These are not people who were my invitees, necessarily. Scowcroft
                    would have been; Cheney would have been, etc., but I think this is just the
                    routing slip. It seems that Orbin—he's the one that wrote jokes, isn't he?</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0034" n="Page0034"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, he is.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: So he might have been in the speech writing. [Laughter] I don't
                    remember that I had a good joke.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You gave a little speech, did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right; just a thank you, a short—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was prepared for you, was it?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, it was just a thank you. I think I probably—as I remember, I said
                    something about this opportunity for women. It was an acknowledgment rather than
                    a speech.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Apparently, Secretary Kissinger was there, [Brent]
                        Scowcroft, Arthur Hartman. Here you are—this is what was supposed to take
                        place. They prepare this so the president will know exactly what he's to do,
                        and so forth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, right. Well, but it doesn't say that I said anything
                    particularly. I think anything I said would have been in one minute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, your counterpart from Great Britain was
                        present.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Peter Ramsbottam, yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Peter Ramsbottam was present, yes, whom you already knew.
                        Before you left, did you go again to the White House?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, not that I remember.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you had photographs taken at that time, didn't
                        you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="Page0035"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Signed by Ford at the time?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: This is something that not all ambassadors have.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. I realized at the time, novice that I was, that this was quite
                    rare. I asked the president to do it, and he agreed to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The swearing-in, you mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And then the pictures.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, the pictures are rare, too?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The pictures are rare, too—actually to have them with the
                        president. Now, not under President Reagan—he's very good at ceremonial
                        things—but under some of the others. They don't always—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's a pity, because think what that means on the ambassador's wall.
                    Oh, that little symbol can just do—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Exactly.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, we ought to see to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A lot of them will send pictures of themselves and sign
                        it, but it won't be with the ambassador.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, that's so important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It is, ceremonially.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0036" n="Page0036"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Surely. Oh, I understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And Reagan, of course, has a very good grasp of what this
                        means. But Carter never did it.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. What a pity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was difficult for some of his people not to have that,
                        because other countries always do it, I guess.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Now, you didn't have to worry about language training. [Laughter] And did you
                    stop over? No, you would go directly.</p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I went directly. We went directly; flew in, arrived at night, and Ron
                    Spiers and the chief counselors met us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your children come to the swearing-in, by the
                        way?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: They were all occupied at the time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, had you read much about the reaction of the British
                        to your appointment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Let me think. Well, there was some—I'd say slightly unfavorable—at
                    first, that I remember. The only really bad one—but it was so funny that it was
                    all right—it was Punch. Punch did a devastating thing on—it was a takeoff on
                    High Noon. I was the ambassador, and my husband was really the chief protagonist
                    in this piece as the shoot-'em-up Texan. But if there was any other problem in
                    the British press, I wasn't aware of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, good. Well, after all, they have a queen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. And once I got there, I'd say the press—because then I did see
                    it—was very favorable; I mean, unusually favorable, more so than I expected or
                    probably deserved. They sort of thought it was a romantic thing—mainly the
                    woman, and then I think the Texan, too, rather intrigued them. Texas was riding
                    high then, you know.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's very true; it was. When you went there as
                        ambassador, which is, as you said, an overwhelming idea, what did you hope
                        to accomplish as ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="Page0037"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, it is our closest ally, or certainly one of the top two or
                    three. I hoped to further cement those relationships. I realized there'd be some
                    economic problems over there. At that point, I really didn't know what my role
                    was, but England was in the depths then, as you'll remember; had to get an IMF
                    loan, which just seems unbelievable today. As far as the issues, I didn't know
                    that Croatian terrorists overhead in a plane, hijackers, would be an issue. That
                    never occurred to me. I knew Northern Ireland would. It was not clear to me when
                    I went what, if anything, an American ambassador could do. I saw England, too,
                    with London as a hub of many of our activities—military, economic, NATO,
                    otherwise—so I hoped to be able to be useful in areas that weren't even strictly
                    London, as it were.</p>
                <p>And I guess, drawing on my own past, I thought I'd probably be pretty good—and
                    then this turned out to be maybe the thing I was strongest as—was portraying the
                    United States through the ambassador to your host country. I'd had a lot of
                    experience doing that. I had not had a lot of experience in negotiations or
                    running an embassy. I had been able to run volunteers—thousands of them—but that
                    was my limited managerial experience.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did the job sort of frighten you at first?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It did, although I had had some of my fears assuaged even before I
                    went by people assuring me of the caliber of people who'd be working for me. And
                    that, of course, turned out to be exactly what it was. And no matter what job
                    I'd had—and I guess the most demanding in a management sense had been
                    co-chairman of the Republican National Committee—you certainly can't do it all,
                    even when you know a field as I knew U.S. politics. So, as it turned out, that's
                    what was there. Ron Spiers couldn't have been a better complement to me; I mean,
                    the consummate pro. Poor Ron, he'd already trained Walter Annenberg, Elliot
                    Richardson. As you know Ron, there's nothing put-on about him. He wasn't too
                    happy about this job, but he gave it his all; he would never hold back. And
                    although it wasn't the challenge he was looking for at the moment—and he told me
                    so—I couldn't have asked for a finer DCM. At first, I thought he was awfully
                    prickly, and I didn't particularly take to it. But as the weeks went on, I did
                    appreciate him, and I wouldn't have changed him. At first I thought, “Oh-oh, I
                    don't think that this flint and steel or oil and water is going to mix at all.”
                    But it did. And our counselors, with one exception, were very strong, and
                    therefore that makes the ambassador strong. And they were not only
                    professionally most able, but also the chemistry was right in these instances.
                    It was just a top-flight embassy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I guess London gets the best people anyway.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="Page0038"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, it's a plum assignment. People yearn to go there at some point
                    in their career. And so we really had fantastic people. I mean, I was made a
                    believer in the Foreign Service in no time flat. And their loyalty, too: the
                    professionalism of being able to serve, to the utmost of their abilities, the
                    person who's in place. It really is inspiring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: The problems we would have were, I'd say—I've heard from other
                    ambassadors—often happen in big posts, of course. Treasury and your economic
                    ministers don't often get along. And there was some of that problem. The Henry
                    Kissinger syndrome of conducting diplomacy behind the ambassador's back. And
                    Henry kids me; he still hasn't got the story straight. We had a big blowup once.
                    I picked him up at Claridge's, and I'd found out he was having some meetings
                    with the foreign minister that I was not privy to, so I blew my top and told
                    him, “That better not happen again.” And Henry tells the story and claims I
                    cried. Well, the last thing I was going to do was cry then. I might have bitten
                    him, but I wasn't going to cry. So after that, that went better. But these were
                    things that happen to ambassadors in many, many posts. In London, they're often
                    glamorous because they involve a Henry Kissinger or a Bill Simon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did Bill Simon come over, too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, often. And he had an able person in Treasury there at the
                    mission. He was extraordinarily able, and Treasury was the tail wagging the dog,
                    as far as the economic section of the embassy proper.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It was hard to quarrel with, because it was a pretty able combination.
                    But we had problems of them trying to send cables behind even the DCM's
                    back.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Treasury and Econ, you mean?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Treasury, straight to Treasury in Washington. I quickly learned that
                    that's a common ailment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And so the econ officer got all upset?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0039" n="Page0039"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: The econ officer and Spiers got pretty upset. Simon was not exactly
                    the most malleable soul. But no harm done. It all worked out well. In other
                    cases, harm can be done. I don't think in these instances it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have to call people in and dress them down?
                        Or did you leave Ron to do that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Dressing down is not usually what I do, no matter what. Correction,
                    yes, in some instances. Mainly, Ron handled things so well that very little had
                    to come to my attention. It would usually be such things as Cabinet heads or
                    heads of committees that I'd have to handle. Ron would have been willing to try,
                    but in many instances I was just the one to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You would have to be the one to do it, of course. They
                        wouldn't take it from him.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But he's so able that very little had to percolate up and cause
                    scenes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I'm sure of that. Yes, he certainly is able, isn't
                        he?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, and he's very straightforward. I mean, Ron calls a spade a spade.
                    He would not have hesitated to say, “You do this,” or, “You'll be no good with
                    that.” He did it. I mean, he's very honest with me, which I, once I got over my
                    hurt feelings—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You said you had a rough settling-in period there. Did you
                        ever have words, the two of you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, not words. I think I'm generally pretty controlled, but I
                    certainly had misgivings. But I got over that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I understand that you had collegial staff meetings.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. It was a splendid spirit in that mission. I really enjoyed the
                    work. It was something you looked forward to every day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, tell me, had you any idea that you would have to do
                        so much entertaining and be involved in so many things?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="Page0040"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. That was probably one of the few things that wasn't surprising,
                    because not just ambassadors, but especially females are supposed [to be], you
                    know, “easy on the head and hard on the feet.” So really, it was not as
                    demanding, particularly in a post like London. London is so sophisticated that
                    the demands on the ambassador, as far as the formal calls, et cetera, are less
                    than they would be in a smaller post. The other ambassadors have plenty to do,
                    and they really care very little if the U.S. ambassador calls on them. Whereas
                    in another post, you know, it's a very important matter. So the entertaining was
                    not a surprise, and I didn't feel it was out of line. I didn't get
                    exhausted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course, you were always used to entertaining a great
                        deal anyway. You must have had a good staff running the residence?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Excellent staff. Just as in the chancery, the residence was splendid.
                    I didn't run the best residence in London. You know, it's funny. Maybe it's
                    because you're so sensitive that you'd spend too much time on getting the right
                    chef because you're a woman that you don't do enough. I didn't get a good enough
                    chef. I had able help with the guest lists and the entertainment, and the
                    entertainment was fun. It was not as elegant nearly, say, as I am sure
                    Evangeline Bruce did or Lenore Annenberg, and so I could have done better
                    there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, but you had a full-time job to do.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I know, but your full-time job is also to set one of the best tables
                    in London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, I suppose that's true.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: And that's management, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did your husband take on any of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He's not particularly good at that kind of thing. Now, he was splendid
                    at thinking up groups of people or who would be exciting in that group of people
                    or who'd leaven the loaf in that one, but as far as menus and chefs, that's not
                    his bag.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Some husbands have done that.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="Page0041"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, I realize that. But Tobin just—he'd have a good idea for a theme
                    for a party or he'd hear somebody from the United States was coming, in politics
                    or culture, and he helped a lot that way, and was a marvelous host. He was one
                    of the reasons people had a good time and an interesting time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, so I have heard, that he was an excellent host. In
                        fact, there were even newspaper clippings that I've got about him at the
                        post.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Really? Good. Well, he deserved the praise.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. And I imagine this was so different from being on the
                        ranch that it must have—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But as I said, within about a month's time, he had fallen in love.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Isn't that wonderful? And you say you met some very good
                        friends over there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We did make wonderful friends. And we go back—Tobin isn't as
                    interested in politics as I am by a long shot, so we don't keep up with the
                    political friends that were more the ones I made. We keep up more with the
                    social friends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now, did you go grouse hunting?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Tobin loves to shoot. I do, too, but I didn't shoot over there
                    for several reasons, mainly because it is tough shooting. And since it's their
                    livelihood, they sell the grouse or the pheasant or the partridge, whatever it
                    is, and so when you miss, that's money flying out of the bank. So they're
                    magnificent shots, and I'm not that good a shot to stand in a line. Plus, I
                    never had a chance to be with the women except on the weekends, and so this was
                    a chance to meet and get to know the women, the wives or their friends or
                    whatever. So that was just fine by me. I shot a couple of times over there, and
                    we would go on weekends when there was no shooting, just for country life or
                    going to the American museum or doing this or doing that, sightseeing. We were
                    gone many, many weekends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, I gathered the reason you were so popular and you
                        were extremely popular, because most ambassadors—there are so many of them
                        and they're so blas�.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, they're men and they wear gray suits, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0042" n="Page0042"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And they wear gray suits. But also they're so used to it
                        that you were a novelty and were very popular. But I understand one of the
                        reasons is that you met a great cross- section of the British.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That was Ron Spiers' idea. I remember sort of your traditional, number
                    one speech is the Pilgrims [Society] over there. And I remember him saying,
                    “Now, you must say that you want to get all around this country and meet all
                    kinds of people.” Well, I did, but I wasn't necessarily going to say that. He
                    made a point of pointing out to me that I'd probably do well at that. And I did,
                    and I guess the people sensed that I was enthusiastic and thoroughly enjoyed
                    that. So we did; we traveled a lot and met all sorts of people.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You enjoyed the ceremonial parts of the job.
                        Representational, I should say, not ceremonial.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, I loved that. True, the most boring would be the cocktail parties
                    in town. That's boring for most people. But at least when you're an ambassador,
                    you have a mission usually to see a couple or three, or a dozen people, and ask
                    this or that, so you're often there for a purpose.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You and Ron would work out your little scenarios, would
                        you, before you'd go to these?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That makes it too precise. I'd have an idea from him at our almost
                    daily staff meetings, counselors' meetings, of what was on the agenda for the
                    embassy and what I could be useful in trying to pick up or plant, to get some
                    ideas around, et cetera. But, no, Ron and I did not put our heads together
                    before each party and say, “Now, I'll do 1-2-3, and you do 4-5-6.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But would you ever do that when you were working on a
                        specific issue?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Maybe on a couple of occasions it would get down that precisely to
                    that night what you did, but not generally; not every night of the week.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It was more spontaneous than that the way you ran
                        things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Or let's say it wasn't each party; it was occasional parties where
                    you'd have an agenda that was pretty clear in everybody's minds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you were quite definite in wanting to get around to see
                        everybody?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0043" n="Page0043"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: As many as you could, because I understand that can be a
                        trap in these Old World capitals, that you will only see the aristocracy.
                        You were quite aware of this, I think.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. But again, you know, I think having been in politics in the U.S.
                    was a big help. I mean, you wouldn't think of representing the Republican Party
                    by going to see Madam La-De-Da and her pals, and quitting and thinking that was
                    Chicago or Peoria or whatever. You'd know you wouldn't know a place or what was
                    on people's minds if you were limiting it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But you know as well as I do, Ambassador, that many
                        ambassadors go over there with the idea that they're just going to have a
                        nice social time.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Well, that's when, one, they've either picked the wrong person
                    for ambassador, or two, the ambassador hasn't been enlightened on what's
                    expected of him. And if they go over there and don't change, well, that's a
                    disaster. That's a waste of everybody's time and money.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, indeed, it is. The principal problems at the time
                        were economic, were they not?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: They were. And NATO, of course, you're always working on—the military
                    aspects. But it was economic above all. We had Rhodesia going on then, and
                    that's one reason Kissinger was in town so often.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, after you got through scolding him, he didn't do
                        that anymore? (Laughter)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not that I've ever learned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, that seems to have been his way of operating.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, it was. And I'm not sure—he seemed so surprised, I'm not sure it
                    was even deliberate. I think he'd just gotten in the habit.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0044" n="Page0044"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Were there any special humanitarian events that took place
                        at that time? I mean, things that you had to help with. Were there any
                        floods or any—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Disasters, no. The only disasters were slow—like drought in the summer
                    of '76. There was a bad drought, and the farmers suffered badly and there was
                    water rationing and gardens died. But it was not a quick disaster.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So it didn't have to call for U.S. help?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. There were just the humanitarian things, just things that are not
                    of nature but—oh, I would go to things like for handicapped children or that
                    sort of thing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You cut a lot of ribbons, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Cut a lot of ribbons; did a lot of the ceremonial, did a lot of the
                    trade shows, which some ambassadors don't like to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Was promoting U.S. trade one of your pursuits?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That was one. I gathered from the embassy talk that a lot of
                    ambassadors are averse to that. I'm not at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You saw yourself as representing the whole of the United
                        States, didn't you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is, of course, what you are doing, but,
                        unfortunately, not all ambassadors realize this.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: One reason I think, too, and I think you're right and I think I was a
                    popular ambassador, was the Bicentennial. And so America was on everybody's
                    minds, and here was the American lady.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now tell us about the Bicentennial. What did you do
                        over there before you came with the queen over to America?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="Page0045"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: To me, the most moving and impressive thing I did was at Westminster
                    Abbey. They had me read the Thanksgiving service, and they had the service in
                    honor of America. That was an absolutely magnificent ceremony.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you read the—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I read the, oh, whose is it—Governor Bradford's. It's the famous
                    description of the first winter of the pilgrims. I read that and I read a
                    lesson, too. I read lessons all over England and Scotland and Wales. They liked
                    ambassadors to do that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes. Well, I don't think we ever got into that the last
                        time. We didn't get into religion. Are you a—</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I'm an Episcopalian.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Episcopalian. Oh, well then, that's perfect.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: So that fits; but the Presbyterians had me in Scotland, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did they really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. And I was interested in that. Prince Phillip would often read
                    lessons. Prince Charles would. I don't think the queen would. That was a very
                    pleasant ceremonial way, too—of combining the Church and the representation.
                    And, of course, their beautiful church services. I just love them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, did you have a particular kind of entertaining? Was
                        there some particular type of function you liked to give that you felt
                        really served the purpose better and made good use of the money?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, yes. It would have to be the good ol' drinks party, because
                    really what people want to do is see that beautiful house. And that would not
                    serve the purpose of making warm friends or conducting negotiations in a
                    conducive social venue. It served getting a lot of people to say, “I met the
                    ambassador and her husband and their children, and we saw that gorgeous house,”
                    et cetera. So we did more of that than anything, and that served that purpose of
                    the huge numbers of Americans in London, of the congressmen that want their
                    constituents entertained.</p>
                <pb facs="0046" n="Page0046"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You had to do all of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We did a lot of that. It was only abused once, and he was very key to
                    the State Department budget, so we didn't say anything, but there was one real
                    problem. But those occasions, obviously, are not where the ambassador learns a
                    lot or where the ambassador teaches other people very much about what's on
                    America's mind. Then, the dinners are better. I did very few lunches, mainly
                    because we did quite nicely at the chancery, and it was just easier for the
                    counselors, rather than having to stop work and go—because it took a good
                    fifteen, often twenty minutes with traffic back to Winfield House. We had many
                    lunches at the chancery.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you had lunches at the chancery, Ron [Spiers] would
                        sort of stand in for your husband? Or would he come over and join you,
                        too?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: My husband hardly ever joined us. No, he was sensitive to that and I
                    was, too. That wouldn't have been right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Just at the home, he was your host?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: The only time he had anything to do with embassy business was with
                    agriculture, which he's thoroughly competent in. And Butz, who was then
                    Secretary of Agriculture, had given him a commission to try to promote U.S.
                    exports, which was wonderful of Earl Butz and useful to the country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: And he wasn't paid, but he did it well. And he did it in England, and
                    he went to Poland, some Iron Curtain countries, Greece. I think those were the
                    main countries. And he would work occasionally, maybe a couple of days a month,
                    with the agricultural attach�; he'd try to go to the agricultural shows. It was
                    a part-time job that maybe took a day a week. But otherwise, he did not have
                    anything to do with embassy business, and would not have wanted to; he knew
                    better than that. That was never a problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A very delicate sense of what is fitting, obviously, you
                        both have. When you had these drinks parties for all these hordes of people,
                        did you also have British people at the same time?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0047" n="Page0047"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, definitely. I could count on one hand, I think, the times we would
                    have just Americans, and then it would not have been a big party. No, I think
                    that's a key function of an ambassador's entertainment, unless there's a very
                    good reason—you know, if you're having a caucus of congressmen who want to talk
                    privately. But unless there's a good reason to have only Americans, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Now, I understand that Elliot Richardson was given—, the
                        Senate voted him special allowances when he was there. Did you also have the
                        benefit of that?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I never had to dig into my pocket, unless I wanted to do something
                    exceptional, which was hardly ever. I mean, if I wanted to have a better
                    champagne than we paid for, which was quite adequate, then I did that on a
                    couple of occasions. It never occurred to me that was something special voted by
                    the Senate. I don't know whether it was or not in my case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: In your case, I don't know, either.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Remember Larry Eagleburger?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He'd know. And, of course, our excellent administrative counselor,
                    Mike Conlin, who would say, “Now, we've got this much,” and da da da. “Here's
                    where you are in the budget.” But I thought, “Well, isn't this a splendid
                    thing?” because I asked before I went. Because my husband and I are well off,
                    and had we been there for a short time, which we were, we could have handled
                    several thousand dollars extra. Had we been there longer, it would have been
                    hard.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Of course.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But they told me I was not going to have to unless I wanted to have,
                    you know, yellow roses or champagne that was beyond the norm. So I did not have
                    to dig into my pocket for anything over a couple of thousand—$3,000, something
                    like that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's a very good point. I don't know whether or not you
                        were given the special allowance. I know Elliot Richardson was.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="Page0048"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. We ought to find that out. I'd like to know, too. I'm going to
                    make a note of that, because it never even occurred to me. I just thought that
                    that was a general situation, and I thought, “How healthy; at last they fixed it
                    so you don't have to be rich.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I think Richardson said, “I just can't afford to take the
                        job otherwise.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, I never said that, so—I would be very happy if it was not
                    special, because I can tell you, it's enough to do it very nicely. You'd never
                    be criticized. We had California wines, but they were very good wines. And I was
                    happy to do that anyway—the things American. We had a wonderful American art
                    that year for the Bicentennial. I had a friend—you've heard of the famous Bass
                    brothers? Well, they weren't that famous then. But Perry Bass, the father, was a
                    friend of ours and lent us their marvelous Remington &amp; Reynolds collection
                    of bronzes and pictures, which for Texans, too, was just—and I always had a
                    little trepidation: how will these things look in that Georgian house? They were
                    absolutely stupendous. And in that foyer, those bronzes—it was sensational. And
                    we got help from Art in Embassies; they were very useful, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you select them yourself?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. So we had American art.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, now Annenberg had just redone the house not too long
                        ago?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It was in the most beautiful shape. Yes, Elliot and Anne had been
                    there since, and there was just scarcely a thing to do. I remember saying before
                    I went, “Well, of course, I'll put my touch here and there.” It would have been
                    a mistake.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really, really.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Upstairs we painted the library, and that was a little worn. That was
                    the only thing we did. Put some music in and changed the pictures, because the
                    walls were bare. But Wildenstein's pitched in. A friend who's a decorator, Betty
                    Sherrill of MacMillan, which is with a very fine firm in New York, went over
                    with us. The only disappointing thing was, all the walls were not only bare, but
                    the alarms—because Annenberg had had that fantastic art, so the pictures were
                    alarmed—so here were all these dreadful gadgets hanging out of the walls. But
                    within a couple of days, Wildenstein's had lent us enough. We gave a dinner
                    party within two nights, I think it was.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="Page0049"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Wildenstein's is an art gallery?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It's an art dealer who's been, evidently, good to Americans around the
                    world at times, and they were certainly good to us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: A London firm?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: London firm. Well, they're in Paris, New York. And through our
                    decorator friend, Betty Sherrill, who was doing this for nothing, they came up
                    with magnificent art until we got pictures. Some of them weren't replaced for
                    months, until everything came over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And you featured American art.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. That would have been much easier for us, anyway; and being the
                    Bicentennial, it was appropriate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Let's talk about the queen. You came over to the United
                        States with the queen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We did not actually come with her in the yacht, the Britannia, and
                    really for a very homespun reason: my husband gets violently seasick. And as it
                    turned out, they did have a horrible storm while they were—I think they were
                    laying off Bermuda and got caught in the storm. We met them in Philadelphia and
                    had a marvelous tour. We did ride the Britannia on inland waterways, across to
                    Manhattan. I'm trying to think. I think maybe we then—did we go up to Boston,
                    too, on the Britannia? I can't remember. Or maybe Connecticut and then to
                    Boston. Anyway, we were on the Britannia, which was fun in calm waters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And did you spend all of your time with her during the
                        day?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0050" n="Page0050"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right. We would go wherever—accompanied her everywhere, from
                    the University of Virginia, Wall Street. We landed—she landed in Philadelphia.
                    It was really interesting. It was so interesting to see the different ways the
                    cities would manage it. And Philadelphia amused her. It horrified me. Rizzo was
                    mayor, and Rizzo's idea of a proper greeting for the monarch was to have more
                    policemen than I have ever seen in my life, arms akimbo like this, from the dock
                    to downtown Philadelphia, with their backs to the Queen, facing the crowd, as if
                    there were imminent danger of a riot any minute. It was really something. And,
                    of course, nothing happened. They were happy crowds. The Northern Ireland
                    problems did not cause much of a disturbance. And Boston did it magnificently. I
                    think Dukakis was governor then. They had their police people—they weren't
                    police people, but they were from the local towns, and probably sheriffs or
                    other sorts of law enforcement people—done in Colonial costume. So it was
                    attractive, rather than a downer. Everywhere, I was very proud of America. Other
                    than the Rizzo meeting, I think everything was just perfect. [Laughter] And she
                    was amused by that, so that wasn't bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose that your husbands got along well, did
                        they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, very well. They had known each other in England.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: They're both outdoorsmen.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Both outdoorsmen, both horsemen.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you actually see the Queen very often as
                        Ambassador?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No. Mostly at ceremonial occasions. She would always be gracious, of
                    course, to the Ambassador of the United States and always have some words to
                    say. But we did see her at Sandringham. I guess that was the most personal visit
                    we had with her.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You stayed at Sandringham, did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0051" n="Page0051"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, we went to visit. We spent the day at Sandringham. We were with
                    some friends nearby, and evidently her people called and asked us over. We were
                    really sort of surprised, which was even more fun. And the Queen was there, the
                    Prince, or what is he—King Constantine of Greece, the cousin, very attractive.
                    Princess Margaret was there, the Queen Mother, Prince Phillip, and the Queen,
                    and I guess that was it. We had a very informal, delightful time—luncheon. And
                    then she puts on her bandanna and her low shoes and takes me out to the
                    landrover, and off we go to see the horses and the corgies are piled all over.
                    And we had just a delightful family time that time—Tobin and I and some friends,
                    another couple who knew them very well indeed—that's the other ones that we were
                    staying with.</p>
                <p>A very different picture of the Queen, when we were close, was on board the
                    Britannia, when she had President Ford and Henry Kissinger in conversation after
                    a party. And for the first time, I realized how knowledgeable she is in foreign
                    affairs; it really was an eye-opener. They were talking about the complexities
                    of Cypriot politics, which, of course, is Byzantine; all sorts of subjects, and
                    the Queen was an expert on all those subjects. She was terrific and, you know,
                    couldn't have had sharper colleagues than the President and Henry Kissinger.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I should say not. Now, this was right after the
                        Fourth?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That's right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You were not in New York for the Fourth with the tall
                        ships?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, we missed them. We came on the sixth. We were not there on the
                    Fourth; we stayed in London and then flew over, saw some friends for the
                    weekend, and then, as I remember, the tour started during the week. I'm not
                    precise on that. But we missed the tall ships, unfortunately, which is
                    interesting. I was the liaison for Presidents Nixon and Ford to the
                    Bicentennial, and we were desperately trying to get a central theme for that
                    Bicentennial. Would each state do a kind of a festival? Or would each state
                    dedicate a new Bicentennial park? Something that would tie the country together.
                    We never could come up with anything that the states would all accept, and I
                    wouldn't have dreamed that probably the most popular thing was the tall ships. I
                    mean, we were all in on the planning for that; it sounded like a nice thing. But
                    it's interesting how it came in.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, indeed it was. Well, I suppose it was felt it might
                        be a bit of a gaffe to have the Queen of England at our Fourth of July
                        party. [Laughter]</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="Page0052"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: That would ask a little much of her—although some of her talks were
                    very interesting and quite direct. She opened in Philadelphia by saying, “I
                    stand before you, the great, great, great, great, great granddaughter of George
                    III.” And she just lit right into the Revolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Yes, fascinating. When you visited her at Sandringham, the
                        people you were with, were they Americans?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, they were British.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I would have thought she wouldn't have close American
                        friends.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, they were two of our closest friends, Bryan and Carey Bassett is
                    their name. They're a couple, ten or fifteen years younger than Tobin and I, who
                    are, I guess, our closest personal friends over there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, really. And is the Queen Mother as delightful as
                        everyone says?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Every time—, in fact, every year, I think—we've given a luncheon or a
                    dinner for her in London, and we are very pleased to say we're close to her.
                    She's astounding, just the warmest and very quick, very quick. Doesn't miss
                    anything. And, of course, beloved by all. Tremendous energy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Has the Queen that sort of energy?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, but she's not effervescent like her mother. The Queen is far more
                    composed. And it's interesting to me, the English people seem to like that just
                    as well. Their public persona is so different. The Queen, when you're alone—but
                    it takes a very small group—has a delightful and much more outgoing personality.
                    In public, you notice she rarely smiles; the wave is a little half gesture.
                    Whereas, the Queen Mother just effervesces and is ebullient and smiling all the
                    time. And the English people seem to respond to both approaches to public life.
                    They're quite different. It makes a nice balance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: The Queen has to be the queen, as well as the
                        consort.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: She does. She has to be more serious, and she's got a long way to
                    go.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0053" n="Page0053"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Which is just what you had to do. You had to be the
                        ambassador and the ambassador's consort, didn't you? Or was your husband
                        able to, in his own way, be the consort?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Somewhat. I don't know that I could judge that to what extent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did he ever go to the lengths that Henry Luce did, of
                        sitting with the women while you sat with the men after a dinner?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, we didn't do that. We didn't separate the sexes. Now, I had to
                    make up my mind whether I was going to take a stand on that in other people's
                    houses. I did not. The only women's issue you'd say I took a stand on was at a
                    club; I wish I could remember the name of it. They had a separate entrance for
                    the women, and I did take a stand there. I said, “If I'm coming to speak here,
                    we're all going in the same entrance.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Good for you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But as far as separating after dinner, if we were in somebody's house
                    and did it, I did not squawk.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It's a little bit tricky, isn't it? You have to pick your
                        issues.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, you know, each woman has her own way of doing things. And I have
                    not been as confrontational as some women I respect very much who get things
                    done by making more noise. So it takes all kinds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I have a lot of questions I want to ask you, but today I
                        wanted to concentrate on your time in England.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Mrs. Thatcher, maybe?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Mrs. Thatcher, indeed.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0054" n="Page0054"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: She was the head of shadow government. She commanded my respect then,
                    and I think I knew her well enough not to be at all surprised at what she's
                    accomplished. A most commanding woman that makes an instant impression of power
                    and authority. The first time I met her, she'd invited me to her quarter. She
                    was just back from a trip to Israel, which had been a big success, and
                    tremendously impressive with her grasp of the issues, of her analysis of the
                    personalities, and she was very pleased. She had accomplished what she went for.
                    Then we got to know her after that.</p>
                <p>Since then, I have a better insight into here as a wife, because it was hard to
                    get her. We had a very hard time. Ron and I tried and tried to get her to come
                    for dinner to Winfield House, and she was slow to accept. Finally, we got her,
                    and it tickled me so afterwards. You know how the English are very polite about
                    seeing you literally to your car when you're their guests? So Tobin and I, as
                    hosts that night, after dinner at Winfield House took Mr. Thatcher and Mrs.
                    Thatcher to their car. Mr. Thatcher gets in behind the driver's seat and drives,
                    and Mrs. Thatcher gets in the back seat and he drives her. I thought Tobin would
                    die, because he liked her so much. But this was quite a blow to him.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, isn't that wonderful.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But she probably had some papers back there that she was going to
                    attend to. And since then, we have learned that Dennis is a very happy husband,
                    that she is a wife very dependent on him, that they're a marvelous pair. But
                    that was kind of a blow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, that's priceless. I can't imagine your husband doing
                        that.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, no.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I could see him behind the wheel, but you would sit up
                        front.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I'd sit up front; that's quite right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When you traveled around, speaking of cars—traveled around
                        England—did you go by car mostly?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0055" n="Page0055"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, we did. Very rarely by plane. It just doesn't make sense,
                    usually. We went by plane to Northern Ireland. I did; Tobin did not go then. But
                    we'd travel, and, of course, that was one of the delights. The English
                    countryside has to be one of the most gorgeous things in the world to drive
                    through. We shipped over a car of ours, a big car, and we had children over
                    there at various times, so we were able to make some family trips.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, wonderful, not all official trips.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not all official.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I suppose you took the embassy car for those. What was
                        your idea on when you should and when you shouldn't fly the flag on the
                        car?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: In those days, there was not the problem of terrorism. Yes, there were
                    still sandbags around some buildings in England because there'd been a bad rash
                    of bombings several months before we got there. And as I was leaving—well,
                    actually several months before I left—they changed the curtains in our offices
                    in the chancery to those mesh curtains that catch glass.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Oh, yes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: So there were a few steps taken, anti-terrorist steps. But there was
                    not the fear for the ambassador that there has been in recent years. So as far
                    as flying the flag, any time I was on official business, there was no problem
                    with drawing attention to the American ambassador; it was a good thing to do. So
                    only when I was on personal business would I not fly it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you ever have any health problems over there?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, I can't think . . . Well, I did lose my voice for a week or two.
                    Our daughter was there, and she took over some of my speaking engagements. I
                    can't remember any other health problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And your husband regained his lost weight?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes, he did. He would say, “Unfortunately.” It didn't take long.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0056" n="Page0056"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did you do all your traveling around the British Isles or
                        did you take vacations on the Continent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: We went to Mons, to Belgium, twice; to Germany once on a NATO tour;
                    down to Cadiz, Spain—the naval base, once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: These were all official things?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: These were official. That was it . . . and Northern Ireland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That must be a sad place.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Terribly sad; it's like an armed camp. It's just awful. The amazing
                    part is how normal life is.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Really?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I don't know whether—I guess they're just inured; just go on.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, you had your husband with you, so you didn't have
                        the problem of being lonely as Chief of Mission.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Not a bit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But were you able to have a private life at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Yes. Maybe it's partly because of the big, beautiful house and the
                    upstairs rooms. I never felt put-upon as far as lack of privacy. And those
                    gorgeous grounds; you could take a walk. You've got several acres there to walk
                    around. Regents Park. So I never felt hemmed in. And, of course, the British
                    people are such civil, wonderful people. They'll leave you alone, usually. Or if
                    they bother you, it's in a nice way.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: There's no culture clash at all?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="Page0057"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: There's no culture clash, and, of course, their politeness is famous,
                    and justly so. So if you were walking down Stratford-on-Avon and you were
                    sightseeing, if they had anything to say, it would be something complimentary
                    about your country or, “We're so glad to have a lady ambassador,” or something
                    like that. It would never be hurtful or intrusive.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No. And even the ones who are on the left are not
                        fanatical.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, no. In fact, of course, there was a left government, a Labor
                    government, in [power] the entire time I was there, and here I am a Republican
                    on the conservative end of Republicans. Wilson was a P.M. just a few weeks while
                    I was there. Maybe I told you the last time my distress when it came over the
                    wire that he had resigned, and I thought I was the only ambassador in London who
                    hadn't known. Of course, it turned out nobody'd known. But that was a very bleak
                    time. Callaghan was a very fair and good man. I feel we had a good
                    relationship.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: It does make a difference—all of those things. You, then,
                        never had any personal danger?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No personal danger that I was aware of at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: No death threats?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No death threats, no. We had guard dogs that ran around Winfield House
                    at night, but it was really quite relaxed and amateurish compared to what people
                    have to do now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: What kind of guard dogs were they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: This was a German shepherd.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Provided by the government?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: (Laughter) Yes. It bit. Obviously, didn't bite too hard, but our son
                    was returning late with a poor friend from a night on the town and the friend
                    had got bit. Thank goodness the friend didn't want to sue the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I should say. Did you have any major honors that you were
                        given by the British?</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="Page0058"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, yes. I've got a bookcase full of them—all sorts of things; a
                    couple of honorary degrees, and then various associations, everything from
                    Ladies of the Press to the this to the that would honor you.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: How about decorations?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No decorations. I was delighted Cap Weinberger got one recently. He's
                    a great Anglophile. There are not many things that you can do to please Cap that
                    way, but that really did it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, is there anything that you think being a woman
                        contributed to your great success? Do you think that was a large part of
                        your success?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: It certainly contributed to being well known and being a novelty, and
                    so you certainly got your foot in the door as far as getting people's attention.
                    You were noticed the minute you arrived. Ambassadors can do good jobs in so many
                    different ways, I've learned. One of my strengths was knowing how to deal with
                    the public and enjoying it, and this was the kind of a post where that could be
                    useful. In many countries, you wouldn't think of doing that—to be out and about
                    often. I think it helped to be a woman.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: You didn't do the actual, the nitty-gritty, day-to-day
                        work on IMF and things like that, did you?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Only on the most important parts. I mean, Ron would go over cables
                    with me when he thought I needed to know. Had I been there longer—I would say it
                    was an ambassadorship in stages, because had Ford been re-elected, you know it's
                    reasonably certain he would have asked me to stay on. When he wasn't, obviously
                    I was going to go, although they were very civil to me. Cy Vance, Bob Strauss
                    knew me, and they said, “Do stay on. Take your time.” Mr. Vance said he was busy
                    reorganizing the State Department. So it couldn't have been more nicely handled
                    that way.</p>
                <p>I tell you, the only truly unpleasant thing that happened the whole time I was
                    over there—other than this one congressman, who was a problem not just for me,
                    but for the whole embassy—was at the very end. After Carter was elected, even
                    though Vance had been marvelous, we get a phone call that I am to leave the
                    country because Mondale is coming. I said, “What? I'm ambassador for the vice
                    president-elect, and I'm ambassador for all the Americans.”</p>
                <p>“No. You get out of the country.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0059" n="Page0059"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: When was this?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: This was about in January.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Before the Inauguration?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: I think it was before the Inauguration, it was possibly after. It was
                    certainly close, one way or the other. And then I found out—oh, I know. Ken Rush
                    was ambassador to France, and he called and said he was getting out of France,
                    and could he come stay with me?</p>
                <p>I said, “Well, I've just gotten a phone call that I'm supposed to vacate.”</p>
                <p>And so I said to Ron, “Ron, you tell them I want to see a cable to that effect.
                    Put it in writing.” And it never came, and so I stayed.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister came out to meet Mondale and said very nice things about me
                    as I was standing there. On purpose, because I'm sure the British were privy to
                    this. And, you know, that isn't the way diplomacy works. I bet Mondale—I doubt,
                    from the way he talked, I don't even think he knew about it. Somebody had done
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: He probably didn't. Somebody down the line. What a
                        gaffe!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: But then there was an interesting thing that happened. There was an
                    unfortunate set of statements by one of Mondale's people after a party that the
                    prime minister gave them, and he had served them some famous old brandy or
                    famous old wine. Anyway, the next day the press person said, “Well, the Vice
                    President never would have been elected if he spent that kind of money on an
                    obscene party.” Well, poor Mondale by that time, was in Tokyo. That was the
                    other ambassador who didn't leave, the ambassador to Japan; he stayed put,
                    too.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: But Rush left?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Rush left. All the others left. There were some others involved. And
                    so Mondale called me and said could I explain to the Prime Minister that, of
                    course, those weren't his sentiments and that he was terribly embarrassed about
                    this statement. They had not invited me to that party and had said it was a stag
                    party. I found out later there were women there. But anyway, I called the Prime
                    Minister and said, “The Vice President—this is certainly not the way he feels.
                    It was a beautiful party. He's so upset that he's called from Tokyo to make sure
                    that you understand this.”</p>
                <p>
                    <pb facs="0060" n="Page0060"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: So you had to clean up after the mess made by those
                        people.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, that was the only mess.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: That's too bad, though, that you had to. It's a shame that
                        you didn't get to stay longer.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: No, but they couldn't have. I want to reiterate. I quickly saw that,
                    really, it didn't work either way. I could have stayed longer as far as Cy Vance
                    was concerned, but since I was so political, it wasn't right. There'd be issues
                    and people where it was slightly awkward for them and awkward for me. So it
                    wasn't the best. Whereas, for 90 percent of the ambassadors, it would have
                    worked. But I had been highly politicized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: And too highly visible. You were such a well-known figure,
                        too.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, that's true too. That was another thing. But it was beautifully
                    handled, with the utmost tact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: I guess Mr. Vance is very nice.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: He was completely fine about it. And all the State Department people
                    were. It just couldn't have been easier for all concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Did all of this—and this will be my last question
                        today—did all of this change your opinion, or any opinions you may have had,
                        about this Foreign Service?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Oh, most definitely! I had a preconception of the dilettantes, the
                    cookie pushers, the not-so-hard workers. It changed me completely, what I think
                    of the Foreign Service. I became a great admirer. I've never known a corps of
                    people who were—I figured they'd be intelligent. That, I knew, and that
                    certainly proved true: the most intelligent group of government people I've ever
                    worked with. But also I think I've cited the other characteristics—very hard
                    working, very loyal, without ever being two-faced, the ability to put all their
                    efforts behind whoever is deserving of it at that point. I am a great admirer of
                    the Foreign Service.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Q: Well, that's delightful to hear, I must say, and they
                        reciprocate. You have a good corridor reputation, indeed. Thank you very
                        much.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0061" n="Page0061"/>
                <p>ARMSTRONG: Well, thank you.</p>
                <p>End of interview</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
